Psalms 132

1 A Song of the Ascents. Remember, Jehovah, for David, all his afflictions.

2 Who hath sworn to Jehovah. He hath vowed to the Mighty One of Jacob:

3 `If I enter into the tent of my house, If I go up on the couch of my bed,

4 If I give sleep to mine eyes, To mine eyelids--slumber,

5 Till I do find a place for Jehovah, Tabernacles for the Mighty One of Jacob.

6 `Lo, we have heard it in Ephratah, We have found it in the fields of the forest.

7 We come in to His tabernacles, We bow ourselves at His footstool.

8 Arise, O Jehovah, to Thy rest, Thou, and the ark of Thy strength,

9 Thy priests do put on righteousness, And Thy pious ones cry aloud.

10 For the sake of David Thy servant, Turn not back the face of Thine anointed.

11 Jehovah hath sworn truth to David, He turneth not back from it: Of the fruit of thy body, I set on the throne for thee.

12 If thy sons keep My covenant, And My testimonies that I teach them, Their sons also for ever and ever, Do sit on the throne for thee.

13 For Jehovah hath fixed on Zion, He hath desired [it] for a seat to Himself,

14 This [is] My rest for ever and ever, Here do I sit, for I have desired it.

15 Her provision I greatly bless, Her needy ones I satisfy [with] bread,

16 And her priests I clothe [with] salvation, And her pious ones do sing aloud.

17 There I cause to spring up a horn for David, I have arranged a lamp for Mine anointed.

18 His enemies I do clothe [with] shame, And upon him doth his crown flourish!

Psalms 135

1 Praise ye Jah! Praise ye the name of Jehovah, Praise, ye servants of Jehovah,

2 Who are standing in the house of Jehovah, In the courts of the house of our God.

3 Praise ye Jah! for Jehovah [is] good, Sing praise to His name, for [it is] pleasant.

4 For Jacob hath Jah chosen for Himself, Israel for His peculiar treasure.

5 For I have known that great [is] Jehovah, Yea, our Lord [is] above all gods.

6 All that Jehovah pleased He hath done, In the heavens and in earth, In the seas and all deep places,

7 Causing vapours to ascend from the end of the earth, Lightnings for the rain He hath made, Bringing forth wind from His treasures.

8 Who smote the first-born of Egypt, From man unto beast.

9 He sent tokens and wonders into thy midst, O Egypt, On Pharaoh and on all his servants.

10 Who smote many nations, and slew strong kings,

11 Even Sihon king of the Amorite, And Og king of Bashan, And all kingdoms of Canaan.

12 And He gave their land an inheritance, An inheritance to Israel His people,

13 O Jehovah, Thy name [is] to the age, O Jehovah, Thy memorial to all generations.

14 For Jehovah doth judge His people, And for His servants comforteth Himself.

15 The idols of the nations [are] silver and gold, Work of the hands of man.

16 A mouth they have, and they speak not, Eyes they have, and they see not,

17 Ears they have, and they give not ear, Nose--there is no breath in their mouth!

18 Like them are their makers, Every one who is trusting in them.

19 O house of Israel, bless ye Jehovah, O house of Aaron, bless ye Jehovah,

20 O house of Levi, bless ye Jehovah, Those fearing Jehovah, bless ye Jehovah.

21 Blessed [is] Jehovah from Zion, Inhabiting Jerusalem--praise ye Jah!

Psalms 136

1 Give ye thanks to Jehovah, For good, for to the age [is] His kindness.

2 Give ye thanks to the God of gods, For to the age [is] His kindness.

3 Give ye thanks to the Lord of lords, For to the age [is] His kindness.

4 To Him doing great wonders by Himself alone, For to the age [is] His kindness.

5 To Him making the heavens by understanding, For to the age [is] His kindness.

6 To Him spreading the earth over the waters, For to the age [is] His kindness.

7 To Him making great lights, For to the age [is] His kindness.

8 The sun to rule by day, For to the age [is] His kindness.

9 The moon and stars to rule by night, For to the age [is] His kindness.

10 To Him smiting Egypt in their first-born, For to the age [is] His kindness.

11 And bringing forth Israel from their midst, For to the age [is] His kindness.

12 By a strong hand, and a stretched-out-arm, For to the age [is] His kindness.

13 To Him cutting the sea of Suph into parts, For to the age [is] His kindness,

14 And caused Israel to pass through its midst, For to the age [is] His kindness,

15 And shook out Pharaoh and his force in the sea of Suph, For to the age [is] His kindness.

16 To Him leading His people in a wilderness, For to the age [is] His kindness.

17 To Him smiting great kings, For to the age [is] His kindness.

18 Yea, He doth slay honourable kings, For to the age [is] His kindness.

19 Even Sihon king of the Amorite, For to the age [is] His kindness.

20 And Og king of Bashan, For to the age [is] His kindness.

21 And He gave their land for inheritance, For to the age [is] His kindness.

22 An inheritance to Israel His servant, For to the age [is] His kindness.

23 Who in our lowliness hath remembered us, For to the age [is] His kindness.

24 And He delivereth us from our adversaries, For to the age [is] His kindness.

25 Giving food to all flesh, For to the age [is] His kindness.

26 Give ye thanks to the God of the heavens, For to the age [is] His kindness!

Psalms 139

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm by David. Jehovah, Thou hast searched me, and knowest.

2 Thou--Thou hast known my sitting down, And my rising up, Thou hast attended to my thoughts from afar.

3 My path and my couch Thou hast fanned, And [with] all my ways hast been acquainted.

4 For there is not a word in my tongue, Lo, O Jehovah, Thou hast known it all!

5 Behind and before Thou hast besieged me, And Thou dost place on me Thy hand.

6 Knowledge too wonderful for me, It hath been set on high, I am not able for it.

7 Whither do I go from Thy Spirit? And whither from Thy face do I flee?

8 If I ascend the heavens--there Thou [art], And spread out a couch in Sheol, lo, Thee!

9 I take the wings of morning, I dwell in the uttermost part of the sea,

10 Also there Thy hand doth lead me, And Thy right hand doth hold me.

11 And I say, `Surely darkness bruiseth me, Then night [is] light to me.

12 Also darkness hideth not from Thee, And night as day shineth, as [is] darkness so [is] light.

13 For Thou--Thou hast possessed my reins, Thou dost cover me in my mother's belly.

14 I confess Thee, because that [with] wonders I have been distinguished. Wonderful [are] Thy works, And my soul is knowing [it] well.

15 My substance was not hid from Thee, When I was made in secret, Curiously wrought in the lower part of earth.

16 Mine unformed substance Thine eyes saw, And on Thy book all of them are written, The days they were formed--And not one among them.

17 And to me how precious have been Thy thoughts, O God, how great hath been their sum!

18 I recount them! than the sand they are more, I have waked, and I am still with Thee.

19 Dost Thou slay, O God, the wicked? Then, men of blood, turn aside from me!

20 Who exchange Thee for wickedness, Lifted up to vanity [are] Thine enemies.

21 Do not I hate, Jehovah, those hating Thee? And with Thy withstanders grieve myself?

22 [With] perfect hatred I have hated them, Enemies they have become to me.

23 Search me, O God, and know my heart, Try me, and know my thoughts,

24 And see if a grievous way be in me, And lead me in a way age-during!

Psalms 140

1 To the Overseer. --A Psalm of David. Deliver me, O Jehovah, from an evil man, From one of violence Thou keepest me.

2 Who have devised evils in the heart, All the day they assemble [for] wars.

3 They sharpened their tongue as a serpent, Poison of an adder [is] under their lips. Selah.

4 Preserve me, Jehovah, from the hands of the wicked, From one of violence Thou keepest me, Who have devised to overthrow my steps.

5 The proud hid a snare for me--and cords, They spread a net by the side of the path, Snares they have set for me. Selah.

6 I have said to Jehovah, `My God [art] Thou, Hear, Jehovah, the voice of my supplications.'

7 O Jehovah, my Lord, strength of my salvation, Thou hast covered my head in the day of armour.

8 Grant not, O Jehovah, the desires of the wicked, His wicked device bring not forth, They are high. Selah.

9 The chief of my surrounders, The perverseness of their lips covereth them.

10 They cause to fall on themselves burning coals, Into fire He doth cast them, Into deep pits--they arise not.

11 A talkative man is not established in the earth, One of violence--evil hunteth to overflowing.

12 I have known that Jehovah doth execute The judgment of the afflicted, The judgment of the needy.

13 Only--the righteous give thanks to Thy name, The upright do dwell with Thy presence!

Psalms 143

1 A Psalm of David. O Jehovah, hear my prayer, Give ear unto my supplications, In Thy faithfulness answer me--in Thy righteousness.

2 And enter not into judgment with Thy servant, For no one living is justified before Thee.

3 For an enemy hath pursued my soul, He hath bruised to the earth my life, He hath caused me to dwell in dark places, As the dead of old.

4 And my spirit in me is become feeble, Within me is my heart become desolate.

5 I have remembered days of old, I have meditated on all Thine acts, On the work of Thy hand I muse.

6 I have spread forth my hands unto Thee, My soul [is] as a weary land for Thee. Selah.

7 Haste, answer me, O Jehovah, My spirit hath been consumed, Hide not Thou Thy face from me, Or I have been compared with those going down [to] the pit.

8 Cause me to hear in the morning Thy kindness, For in Thee I have trusted, Cause me to know the way that I go, For unto Thee I have lifted up my soul.

9 Deliver me from mine enemies, O Jehovah, Near Thee I am covered.

10 Teach me to do Thy good pleasure, For Thou [art] my God--Thy Spirit [is] good, Lead me into a land of uprightness.

11 For Thy name's sake O Jehovah, Thou dost quicken me, In Thy righteousness, Thou bringest out from distress my soul,

12 And in Thy kindness cuttest off mine enemies, And hast destroyed all the adversaries of my soul, For I [am] Thy servant!

Psalms 144

1 By David. Blessed [is] Jehovah my rock, who is teaching My hands for war, my fingers for battle.

2 My kind one, and my bulwark, My tower, and my deliverer, My shield, and in whom I have trusted, Who is subduing my people under me!

3 Jehovah, what [is] man that Thou knowest him? Son of man, that Thou esteemest him?

4 Man to vanity hath been like, His days [are] as a shadow passing by.

5 Jehovah, incline Thy heavens and come down, Strike against mountains, and they smoke.

6 Send forth lightning, and scatter them, Send forth Thine arrows, and trouble them,

7 Send forth Thy hand from on high, Free me, and deliver me from many waters, From the hand of sons of a stranger,

8 Because their mouth hath spoken vanity, And their right hand [is] a right hand of falsehood.

9 O God, a new song I sing to Thee, On a psaltery of ten strings I sing praise to Thee.

10 Who is giving deliverance to kings, Who is freeing David His servant from the sword of evil.

11 Free me, and deliver me From the hand of sons of a stranger, Because their mouth hath spoken vanity, And their right hand [is] a right hand of falsehood,

12 Because our sons [are] as plants, Becoming great in their youth, Our daughters as hewn stones, Polished--the likeness of a palace,

13 Our garners [are] full, bringing out from kind to kind, Our flocks are bringing forth thousands, Ten thousands in our out-places,

14 Our oxen are carrying, there is no breach, And there is no outgoing, And there is no crying in our broad places.

15 O the happiness of the people that is thus, O the happiness of the people whose God [is] Jehovah!

Psalms 145

1 Praise by David. I exalt Thee, my God, O king, And bless Thy name to the age and for ever.

2 Every day do I bless Thee, And praise Thy name to the age and for ever.

3 Great [is] Jehovah, and praised greatly, And of His greatness there is no searching.

4 Generation to generation praiseth Thy works, And Thy mighty acts they declare.

5 The honour--the glory of Thy majesty, And the matters of Thy wonders I declare.

6 And the strength of Thy fearful acts they tell, And Thy greatness I recount.

7 The memorial of the abundance of Thy goodness they send forth. And Thy righteousness they sing.

8 Gracious and merciful [is] Jehovah, Slow to anger, and great in kindness.

9 Good [is] Jehovah to all, And His mercies [are] over all His works.

10 Confess Thee O Jehovah, do all Thy works, And Thy saints do bless Thee.

11 The honour of Thy kingdom they tell, And [of] Thy might they speak,

12 To make known to sons of men His mighty acts, The honour of the majesty of His kingdom.

13 Thy kingdom [is] a kingdom of all ages, And Thy dominion [is] in all generations.

14 Jehovah is supporting all who are falling, And raising up all who are bowed down.

15 The eyes of all unto Thee do look, And Thou art giving to them their food in its season,

16 Opening Thy hand, and satisfying The desire of every living thing.

17 Righteous [is] Jehovah in all His ways, And kind in all His works.

18 Near [is] Jehovah to all those calling Him, To all who call Him in truth.

19 The desire of those fearing Him He doth, And their cry He heareth, and saveth them.

20 Jehovah preserveth all those loving Him, And all the wicked He destroyeth.

21 The praise of Jehovah my mouth speaketh, And all flesh doth bless His holy name, To the age and for ever!

Psalms 147

1 Praise ye Jah! For [it is] good to praise our God, For pleasant--comely [is] praise.

2 Building Jerusalem [is] Jehovah, The driven away of Israel He gathereth.

3 Who is giving healing to the broken of heart, And is binding up their griefs.

4 Appointing the number of the stars, To all them He giveth names.

5 Great [is] our Lord, and abundant in power, Of His understanding there is no narration.

6 Jehovah is causing the meek to stand, Making low the wicked unto the earth.

7 Answer ye to Jehovah with thanksgiving, Sing ye to our God with a harp.

8 Who is covering the heavens with clouds, Who is preparing for the earth rain, Who is causing grass to spring up [on] mountains,

9 Giving to the beast its food, To the young of the ravens that call.

10 Not in the might of the horse doth He delight, Not in the legs of a man is He pleased.

11 Jehovah is pleased with those fearing Him, With those waiting for His kindness.

12 Glorify, O Jerusalem, Jehovah, Praise thy God, O Zion.

13 For He did strengthen the bars of thy gates, He hath blessed thy sons in thy midst.

14 Who is making thy border peace, [With] the fat of wheat He satisfieth Thee.

15 Who is sending forth His saying [on] earth, Very speedily doth His word run.

16 Who is giving snow like wool, Hoar-frost as ashes He scattereth.

17 Casting forth His ice like morsels, Before His cold who doth stand?

18 He sendeth forth His word and melteth them, He causeth His wind to blow--the waters flow.

19 Declaring His words to Jacob, His statutes and His judgments to Israel.

20 He hath not done so to any nation, As to judgments, they have not known them. Praise ye Jah!

Psalms 148

1 Praise ye Jah! Praise ye Jehovah from the heavens, Praise ye Him in high places.

2 Praise ye Him, all His messengers, Praise ye Him, all His hosts.

3 Praise ye Him, sun and moon, Praise ye Him, all stars of light.

4 Praise ye Him, heavens of heavens, And ye waters that are above the heavens.

5 They do praise the name of Jehovah, For He commanded, and they were created.

6 And He establisheth them for ever to the age, A statute He gave, and they pass not over.

7 Praise ye Jehovah from the earth, Dragons and all deeps,

8 Fire and hail, snow and vapour, Whirlwind doing His word;

9 The mountains and all heights, Fruit tree, and all cedars,

10 The wild beast, and all cattle, Creeping thing, and winged bird,

11 Kings of earth, and all peoples, Chiefs, and all judges of earth,

12 Young men, and also maidens, Aged men, with youths,

13 They praise the name of Jehovah, For His name alone hath been set on high, His honour [is] above earth and heavens.

14 And He exalteth the horn of His people, The praise of all His saints, Of the sons of Israel, a people near Him. Praise ye Jah!

Proverbs 1

1 Proverbs of Solomon, son of David, king of Israel:

2 For knowing wisdom and instruction, For understanding sayings of intelligence,

3 For receiving the instruction of wisdom, Righteousness, judgment, and uprightness,

4 For giving to simple ones--prudence, To a youth--knowledge and discretion.

5 (The wise doth hear and increaseth learning, And the intelligent doth obtain counsels.)

6 For understanding a proverb and its sweetness, Words of the wise and their acute sayings.

7 Fear of Jehovah [is] a beginning of knowledge, Wisdom and instruction fools have despised!

8 Hear, my son, the instruction of thy father, And leave not the law of thy mother,

9 For a graceful wreath [are] they to thy head, And chains to thy neck.

10 My son, if sinners entice thee be not willing.

11 If they say, `Come with us, we lay wait for blood, We watch secretly for the innocent without cause,

12 We swallow them as Sheol--alive, And whole--as those going down [to] the pit,

13 Every precious substance we find, We fill our houses [with] spoil,

14 Thy lot thou dost cast among us, One purse is--to all of us.'

15 My son! go not in the way with them, Withhold thy foot from their path,

16 For their feet to evil do run, And they haste to shed blood.

17 Surely in vain is the net spread out before the eyes of any bird.

18 And they for their own blood lay wait, They watch secretly for their own lives.

19 So [are] the paths of every gainer of dishonest gain, The life of its owners it taketh.

20 Wisdom in an out-place crieth aloud, In broad places she giveth forth her voice,

21 At the head of the multitudes she calleth, In the openings of the gates, In the city her sayings she saith:

22 `Till when, ye simple, do ye love simplicity? And have scorners their scorning desired? And do fools hate knowledge?

23 Turn back at my reproof, lo, I pour forth to you my spirit, I make known my words with you.

24 Because I have called, and ye refuse, I stretched out my hand, and none is attending,

25 And ye slight all my counsel, And my reproof ye have not desired.

26 I also in your calamity do laugh, I deride when your fear cometh,

27 When your fear cometh as destruction, And your calamity as a hurricane doth come, When on you come adversity and distress.

28 Then they call me, and I do not answer, They seek me earnestly, and find me not.

29 Because that they have hated knowledge, And the fear of Jehovah have not chosen.

30 They have not consented to my counsel, They have despised all my reproof,

31 And they eat of the fruit of their way, And from their own counsels they are filled.

32 For the turning of the simple slayeth them, And the security of the foolish destroyeth them.

33 And whoso is hearkening to me dwelleth confidently, And [is] quiet from fear of evil!'

Proverbs 2

1 My son, if thou dost accept my sayings, And my commands dost lay up with thee,

2 To cause thine ear to attend to wisdom, Thou inclinest thy heart to understanding,

3 For, if for intelligence thou callest, For understanding givest forth thy voice,

4 If thou dost seek her as silver, And as hid treasures searchest for her,

5 Then understandest thou fear of Jehovah, And knowledge of God thou findest.

6 For Jehovah giveth wisdom, From His mouth knowledge and understanding.

7 Even to lay up for the upright substance, A shield for those walking uprightly.

8 To keep the paths of judgment, And the way of His saints He preserveth.

9 Then understandest thou righteousness, And judgment, and uprightness--every good path.

10 For wisdom cometh into thy heart, And knowledge to thy soul is pleasant,

11 Thoughtfulness doth watch over thee, Understanding doth keep thee,

12 To deliver thee from an evil way, From any speaking froward things,

13 Who are forsaking paths of uprightness, To walk in ways of darkness,

14 Who are rejoicing to do evil, They delight in frowardness of the wicked,

15 Whose paths [are] crooked, Yea, they are perverted in their ways.

16 To deliver thee from the strange woman, From the stranger who hath made smooth her sayings,

17 Who is forsaking the guide of her youth, And the covenant of her God hath forgotten.

18 For her house hath inclined unto death, And unto Rephaim her paths.

19 None going in unto her turn back, Nor do they reach the paths of life.

20 That thou dost go in the way of the good, And the paths of the righteous dost keep.

21 For the upright do inhabit the earth, And the perfect are left in it,

22 And the wicked from the earth are cut off, And treacherous dealers plucked out of it!

Proverbs 3

1 My son! my law forget not, And my commands let thy heart keep,

2 For length of days and years, Life and peace they do add to thee.

3 Let not kindness and truth forsake thee, Bind them on thy neck, Write them on the tablet of thy heart,

4 And find grace and good understanding In the eyes of God and man.

5 Trust unto Jehovah with all thy heart, And unto thine own understanding lean not.

6 In all thy ways know thou Him, And He doth make straight thy paths.

7 Be not wise in thine own eyes, Fear Jehovah, and turn aside from evil.

8 Healing it is to thy navel, And moistening to thy bones.

9 Honour Jehovah from thy substance, And from the beginning of all thine increase;

10 And filled are thy barns [with] plenty, And [with] new wine thy presses break forth.

11 Chastisement of Jehovah, my son, despise not, And be not vexed with His reproof,

12 For whom Jehovah loveth He reproveth, Even as a father the son He is pleased with.

13 O the happiness of a man [who] hath found wisdom, And of a man [who] bringeth forth understanding.

14 For better [is] her merchandise Than the merchandise of silver, And than gold--her increase.

15 Precious she [is] above rubies, And all thy pleasures are not comparable to her.

16 Length of days [is] in her right hand, In her left [are] wealth and honour.

17 Her ways [are] ways of pleasantness, And all her paths [are] peace.

18 A tree of life she [is] to those laying hold on her, And whoso is retaining her [is] happy.

19 Jehovah by wisdom did found the earth, He prepared the heavens by understanding.

20 By His knowledge depths have been rent, And clouds do drop dew.

21 My son! let them not turn from thine eyes, Keep thou wisdom and thoughtfulness,

22 And they are life to thy soul, and grace to thy neck.

23 Then thou goest thy way confidently, And thy foot doth not stumble.

24 If thou liest down, thou art not afraid, Yea, thou hast lain down, And sweet hath been thy sleep.

25 Be not afraid of sudden fear, And of the desolation of the wicked when it cometh.

26 For Jehovah is at thy side, And He hath kept thy foot from capture.

27 Withhold not good from its owners, When thy hand [is] toward God to do [it].

28 Say not thou to thy friend, `Go, and return, and to-morrow I give,' And substance with thee.

29 Devise not against thy neighbour evil, And he sitting confidently with thee.

30 Strive not with a man without cause, If he have not done thee evil.

31 Be not envious of a man of violence, Nor fix thou on any of his ways.

32 For an abomination to Jehovah [is] the perverted, And with the upright [is] His secret counsel.

33 The curse of Jehovah [is] in the house of the wicked. And the habitation of the righteous He blesseth.

34 If the scorners He doth scorn, Yet to the humble He doth give grace.

35 Honour do the wise inherit, And fools are bearing away shame!

Proverbs 4

1 Hear, ye sons, the instruction of a father, And give attention to know understanding.

2 For good learning I have given to you, My law forsake not.

3 For, a son I have been to my father--tender, And an only one before my mother.

4 And he directeth me, and he saith to me: `Let thy heart retain my words, Keep my commands, and live.

5 Get wisdom, get understanding, Do not forget, nor turn away From the sayings of my mouth.

6 Forsake her not, and she doth preserve thee, Love her, and she doth keep thee.

7 The first thing [is] wisdom--get wisdom, And with all thy getting get understanding.

8 Exalt her, and she doth lift thee up, She honoureth thee, when thou dost embrace her.

9 She giveth to thy head a wreath of grace, A crown of beauty she doth give thee freely.

10 Hear, my son, and receive my sayings, And years of life [are] multiplied to thee.

11 In a way of wisdom I have directed thee, I have caused thee to tread in paths of uprightness.

12 In thy walking thy step is not straitened, And if thou runnest, thou stumblest not.

13 Lay hold on instruction, do not desist, Keep her, for she [is] thy life.

14 Into the path of the wicked enter not, And be not happy in a way of evil doers.

15 Avoid it, pass not over into it, Turn aside from it, and pass on.

16 For they sleep not if they do not evil, And their sleep hath been taken violently away, If they cause not [some] to stumble.

17 For they have eaten bread of wickedness, And wine of violence they drink.

18 And the path of the righteous [is] as a shining light, Going and brightening till the day is established,

19 The way of the wicked [is] as darkness, They have not known at what they stumble.

20 My son, to my words give attention, To my sayings incline thine ear,

21 Let them not turn aside from thine eyes, Preserve them in the midst of thy heart.

22 For life they [are] to those finding them, And to all their flesh healing.

23 Above every charge keep thy heart, For out of it [are] the outgoings of life.

24 Turn aside from thee a froward mouth, And perverse lips put far from thee,

25 Thine eyes do look straightforward, And thine eyelids look straight before thee.

26 Ponder thou the path of thy feet, And all thy ways [are] established.

27 Incline not [to] the right or to the left, Turn aside thy foot from evil!

Proverbs 5

1 My son! to my wisdom give attention, To mine understanding incline thine ear,

2 To observe thoughtfulness, And knowledge do thy lips keep.

3 For the lips of a strange woman drop honey, And smoother than oil [is] her mouth,

4 And her latter end [is] bitter as wormwood, Sharp as a sword [with] mouths.

5 Her feet are going down to death, Sheol do her steps take hold of.

6 The path of life--lest thou ponder, Moved have her paths--thou knowest not.

7 And now, ye sons, hearken to me, And turn not from sayings of my mouth.

8 Keep far from off her thy way, And come not near unto the opening of her house,

9 Lest thou give to others thy honour, And thy years to the fierce,

10 Lest strangers be filled [with] thy power, And thy labours in the house of a stranger,

11 And thou hast howled in thy latter end, In the consumption of thy flesh and thy food,

12 And hast said, `How have I hated instruction, And reproof hath my heart despised,

13 And I have not hearkened to the voice of my directors, And to my teachers have not inclined mine ear.

14 As a little thing I have been all evil, In the midst of an assembly and a company.

15 Drink waters out of thine own cistern, Even flowing ones out of thine own well.

16 Let thy fountains be scattered abroad, In broad places rivulets of waters.

17 Let them be to thee for thyself, And not to strangers with thee.

18 Let thy fountain be blessed, And rejoice because of the wife of thy youth,

19 A hind of loves, and a roe of grace! Let her loves satisfy thee at all times, In her love magnify thyself continually.

20 And why dost thou magnify thyself, My son, with a stranger? And embrace the bosom of a strange woman?

21 For over-against the eyes of Jehovah are the ways of each, And all his paths He is pondering.

22 His own iniquities do capture the wicked, And with the ropes of his sin he is holden.

23 He dieth without instruction, And in the abundance of his folly magnifieth himself!

Proverbs 6

1 My son! if thou hast been surety for thy friend, Hast stricken for a stranger thy hand,

2 Hast been snared with sayings of thy mouth, Hast been captured with sayings of thy mouth,

3 Do this now, my son, and be delivered, For thou hast come into the hand of thy friend. Go, trample on thyself, and strengthen thy friend,

4 Give not sleep to thine eyes, And slumber to thine eyelids,

5 Be delivered as a roe from the hand, And as a bird from the hand of a fowler.

6 Go unto the ant, O slothful one, See her ways and be wise;

7 Which hath not captain, overseer, and ruler,

8 She doth prepare in summer her bread, She hath gathered in harvest her food.

9 Till when, O slothful one, dost thou lie? When dost thou arise from thy sleep?

10 A little sleep, a little slumber, A little clasping of the hands to rest,

11 And thy poverty hath come as a traveller, And thy want as an armed man.

12 A man of worthlessness, a man of iniquity, Walking [with] perverseness of mouth,

13 Winking with his eyes, speaking with his feet, Directing with his fingers,

14 Frowardness [is] in his heart, devising evil at all times, Contentions he sendeth forth.

15 Therefore suddenly cometh his calamity, Instantly he is broken--and no healing.

16 These six hath Jehovah hated, Yea, seven [are] abominations to His soul.

17 Eyes high--tongues false--And hands shedding innocent blood--

18 A heart devising thoughts of vanity--Feet hasting to run to evil--

19 A false witness [who] doth breathe out lies--And one sending forth contentions between brethren.

20 Keep, my son, the command of thy father, And leave not the law of thy mother.

21 Bind them on thy heart continually, Tie them on thy neck.

22 In thy going up and down, it leadeth thee, In thy lying down, it watcheth over thee, And thou hast awaked--it talketh [with] thee.

23 For a lamp [is] the command, And the law a light, And a way of life [are] reproofs of instruction,

24 To preserve thee from an evil woman, From the flattery of the tongue of a strange woman.

25 Desire not her beauty in thy heart, And let her not take thee with her eyelids.

26 For a harlot consumeth unto a cake of bread, And an adulteress the precious soul hunteth.

27 Doth a man take fire into his bosom, And are his garments not burnt?

28 Doth a man walk on the hot coals, And are his feet not scorched?

29 So [is] he who hath gone in unto the wife of his neighbour, None who doth touch her is innocent.

30 They do not despise the thief, When he stealeth to fill his soul when he is hungry,

31 And being found he repayeth sevenfold, All the substance of his house he giveth.

32 He who committeth adultery [with] a woman lacketh heart, He is destroying his soul who doth it.

33 A stroke and shame he doth find, And his reproach is not wiped away,

34 For jealousy [is] the fury of a man, And he doth not spare in a day of vengeance.

35 He accepteth not the appearance of any atonement, Yea, he doth not consent, Though thou dost multiply bribes!

Proverbs 7

1 My son! keep my sayings, And my commands lay up with thee.

2 Keep my commands, and live, And my law as the pupil of thine eye.

3 Bind them on thy fingers, Write them on the tablet of thy heart.

4 Say to wisdom, `My sister Thou [art].' And cry to understanding, `Kinswoman!'

5 To preserve thee from a strange woman, From a stranger who hath made smooth her sayings.

6 For, at a window of my house, Through my casement I have looked out,

7 And I do see among the simple ones, I discern among the sons, A young man lacking understanding,

8 Passing on in the street, near her corner, And the way [to] her house he doth step,

9 In the twilight--in the evening of day, In the darkness of night and blackness.

10 And, lo, a woman to meet him--(A harlot's dress, and watchful of heart,

11 Noisy she [is], and stubborn, In her house her feet rest not.

12 Now in an out-place, now in broad places, And near every corner she lieth in wait) - -

13 And she laid hold on him, and kissed him, She hath hardened her face, and saith to him,

14 `Sacrifices of peace-offerings [are] by me, To-day I have completed my vows.

15 Therefore I have come forth to meet thee, To seek earnestly thy face, and I find thee.

16 [With] ornamental coverings I decked my couch, Carved works--cotton of Egypt.

17 I sprinkled my bed--myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.

18 Come, we are filled [with] loves till the morning, We delight ourselves in loves.

19 For the man is not in his house, He hath gone on a long journey.

20 A bag of money he hath taken in his hand, At the day of the new moon he cometh to his house.'

21 She turneth him aside with the abundance of her speech, With the flattery of her lips she forceth him.

22 He is going after her straightway, As an ox unto the slaughter he cometh, And as a fetter unto the chastisement of a fool,

23 Till an arrow doth split his liver, As a bird hath hastened unto a snare, And hath not known that it [is] for its life.

24 And now, ye sons, hearken to me, And give attention to sayings of my mouth.

25 Let not thy heart turn unto her ways, Do not wander in her paths,

26 For many [are] the wounded she caused to fall, And mighty [are] all her slain ones.

27 The ways of Sheol--her house, Going down unto inner chambers of death!

Proverbs 8

1 Doth not wisdom call? And understanding give forth her voice?

2 At the head of high places by the way, Between the paths she hath stood,

3 At the side of the gates, at the mouth of the city, The entrance of the openings, she crieth aloud,

4 `Unto you, O men, I call, And my voice [is] unto the sons of men.

5 Understand, ye simple ones, prudence, And ye fools, understand the heart,

6 Hearken, for noble things I speak, And the opening of my lips [is] uprightness.

7 For truth doth my mouth utter, And an abomination to my lips [is] wickedness.

8 In righteousness [are] all the sayings of my mouth, Nothing in them is froward and perverse.

9 All of them [are] plain to the intelligent, And upright to those finding knowledge.

10 Receive my instruction, and not silver, And knowledge rather than choice gold.

11 For better [is] wisdom than rubies, Yea, all delights are not comparable with it.

12 I, wisdom, have dwelt with prudence, And a knowledge of devices I find out.

13 The fear of Jehovah [is] to hate evil; Pride, and arrogance, and an evil way, And a froward mouth, I have hated.

14 Mine [is] counsel and substance, I [am] understanding, I have might.

15 By me kings reign, and princes decree righteousness,

16 By me do chiefs rule, and nobles, All judges of the earth.

17 I love those loving me, And those seeking me earnestly do find me.

18 Wealth and honour [are] with me, Lasting substance and righteousness.

19 Better [is] my fruit than gold, even fine gold, And mine increase than choice silver.

20 In a path of righteousness I cause to walk, In midst of paths of judgment,

21 To cause my lovers to inherit substance, Yea, their treasures I fill.

22 Jehovah possessed me--the beginning of His way, Before His works since then.

23 From the age I was anointed, from the first, From former states of the earth.

24 In there being no depths, I was brought forth, In there being no fountains heavy [with] waters,

25 Before mountains were sunk, Before heights, I was brought forth.

26 While He had not made the earth, and out-places, And the top of the dusts of the world.

27 In His preparing the heavens I [am] there, In His decreeing a circle on the face of the deep,

28 In His strengthening clouds above, In His making strong fountains of the deep,

29 In His setting for the sea its limit, And the waters transgress not His command, In His decreeing the foundations of earth,

30 Then I am near Him, a workman, And I am a delight--day by day. Rejoicing before Him at all times,

31 Rejoicing in the habitable part of His earth, And my delights [are] with the sons of men.

32 And now, ye sons, hearken to me, Yea, happy are they who keep my ways.

33 Hear instruction, and be wise, and slight not.

34 O the happiness of the man hearkening to me, To watch at my doors day by day, To watch at the door-posts of my entrance.

35 For whoso is finding me, hath found life, And bringeth out good-will from Jehovah.

36 And whoso is missing me, is wronging his soul, All hating me have loved death!

Proverbs 9

1 Wisdom hath builded her house, She hath hewn out her pillars--seven.

2 She hath slaughtered her slaughter, She hath mingled her wine, Yea, she hath arranged her table.

3 She hath sent forth her damsels, She crieth on the tops of the high places of the city:

4 `Who [is] simple? let him turn aside hither.' Whoso lacketh heart: she hath said to him,

5 `Come, eat of my bread, And drink of the wine I have mingled.

6 Forsake ye, the simple, and live, And be happy in the way of understanding.

7 The instructor of a scorner Is receiving for it--shame, And a reprover of the wicked-- his blemish.

8 Reprove not a scorner, lest he hate thee, Give reproof to the wise, and he loveth thee.

9 Give to the wise, and he is wiser still, Make known to the righteous, And he increaseth learning.

10 The commencement of wisdom [is] the fear of Jehovah, And a knowledge of the Holy Ones [is] understanding.

11 For by me do thy days multiply, And added to thee are years of life.

12 If thou hast been wise, thou hast been wise for thyself, And thou hast scorned-- thyself bearest [it].

13 A foolish woman [is] noisy, Simple, and hath not known what.

14 And she hath sat at the opening of her house, On a throne--the high places of the city,

15 To call to those passing by the way, Who are going straight [on] their paths.

16 `Who [is] simple? let him turn aside hither.' And whoso lacketh heart--she said to him,

17 `Stolen waters are sweet, And hidden bread is pleasant.'

18 And he hath not known that Rephaim [are] there, In deep places of Sheol her invited ones!

Proverbs 10

1 Proverbs of Solomon. A wise son causeth a father to rejoice, And a foolish son [is] an affliction to his mother.

2 Treasures of wickedness profit not, And righteousness delivereth from death.

3 Jehovah causeth not the soul of the righteous to hunger, And the desire of the wicked He thrusteth away.

4 Poor [is] he who is working--a slothful hand, And the hand of the diligent maketh rich.

5 Whoso is gathering in summer [is] a wise son, Whoso is sleeping in harvest [is] a son causing shame.

6 Blessings [are] for the head of the righteous, And the mouth of the wicked cover doth violence.

7 The remembrance of the righteous [is] for a blessing, And the name of the wicked doth rot.

8 The wise in heart accepteth commands, And a talkative fool kicketh.

9 Whoso is walking in integrity walketh confidently, And whoso is perverting his ways is known.

10 Whoso is winking the eye giveth grief, And a talkative fool kicketh.

11 A fountain of life [is] the mouth of the righteous, And the mouth of the wicked cover doth violence.

12 Hatred awaketh contentions, And over all transgressions love covereth.

13 In the lips of the intelligent is wisdom found, And a rod [is] for the back of him who is lacking understanding.

14 The wise lay up knowledge, and the mouth of a fool [is] near ruin.

15 The wealth of the rich [is] his strong city, The ruin of the poor [is] their poverty.

16 The wage of the righteous [is] for life, The increase of the wicked for sin.

17 A traveller to life [is] he who is keeping instruction, And whoso is forsaking rebuke is erring.

18 Whoso is covering hatred with lying lips, And whoso is bringing out an evil report is a fool.

19 In the abundance of words transgression ceaseth not, And whoso is restraining his lips [is] wise.

20 The tongue of the righteous [is] chosen silver, The heart of the wicked--as a little thing.

21 The lips of the righteous delight many, And fools for lack of heart die.

22 The blessing of Jehovah--it maketh rich, And He addeth no grief with it.

23 To execute inventions [is] as play to a fool, And wisdom to a man of understanding.

24 The feared thing of the wicked it meeteth him, And the desire of the righteous is given.

25 As the passing by of a hurricane, So the wicked is not, And the righteous is a foundation age-during.

26 As vinegar to the teeth, And as smoke to the eyes, So [is] the slothful to those sending him.

27 The fear of Jehovah addeth days, And the years of the wicked are shortened.

28 The hope of the righteous [is] joyful, And the expectation of the wicked perisheth.

29 The way of Jehovah [is] strength to the perfect, And ruin to workers of iniquity.

30 The righteous to the age is not moved, And the wicked inhabit not the earth.

31 The mouth of the righteous uttereth wisdom, And the tongue of frowardness is cut out.

32 The lips of the righteous know a pleasing thing, And the mouth of the wicked perverseness!

Proverbs 11

1 Balances of deceit [are] an abomination to Jehovah, And a perfect weight [is] His delight.

2 Pride hath come, and shame cometh, And with the lowly [is] wisdom.

3 The integrity of the upright leadeth them, And the perverseness of the treacherous destroyeth them.

4 Wealth profiteth not in a day of wrath, And righteousness delivereth from death.

5 The righteousness of the perfect maketh right his way, And by his wickedness doth the wicked fall.

6 The righteousness of the upright delivereth them, And in mischief the treacherous are captured.

7 In the death of a wicked man, hope perisheth, And the expectation of the iniquitous hath been lost.

8 The righteous from distress is drawn out, And the wicked goeth in instead of him.

9 With the mouth a hypocrite corrupteth his friend, And by knowledge the righteous are drawn out.

10 In the good of the righteous a city exulteth, And in the destruction of the wicked [is] singing.

11 By the blessing of the upright is a city exalted, And by the mouth of the wicked thrown down.

12 Whoso is despising his neighbour lacketh heart, And a man of understanding keepeth silence.

13 A busybody is revealing secret counsel, And the faithful of spirit is covering the matter.

14 Without counsels do a people fall, And deliverance [is] in a multitude of counsellors.

15 Evil [one] suffereth when he hath been surety [for] a stranger, And whoso is hating suretyship is confident.

16 A gracious woman retaineth honour, And terrible [men] retain riches.

17 A kind man is rewarding his own soul, And the fierce is troubling his own flesh.

18 The wicked is getting a lying wage, And whoso is sowing righteousness--a true reward.

19 Rightly [is] righteousness for life, And whoso is pursuing evil--for his own death.

20 An abomination to Jehovah [are] the perverse of heart, And the perfect of the way [are] His delight.

21 Hand to hand, the wicked is not acquitted, And the seed of the righteous hath escaped.

22 A ring of gold in the nose of a sow--A fair woman and stubborn of behaviour.

23 The desire of the righteous [is] only good, The hope of the wicked [is] transgression.

24 There is who is scattering, and yet is increased, And who is keeping back from uprightness, only to want.

25 A liberal soul is made fat, And whoso is watering, he also is watered.

26 Whoso is withholding corn, the people execrate him, And a blessing [is] for the head of him who is selling.

27 Whoso is earnestly seeking good Seeketh a pleasing thing, And whoso is seeking evil--it meeteth him.

28 Whoso is confident in his wealth he falleth, And as a leaf, the righteous flourish.

29 Whoso is troubling his own house inheriteth wind, And a servant [is] the fool to the wise of heart.

30 The fruit of the righteous [is] a tree of life, And whoso is taking souls [is] wise.

31 Lo, the righteous in the earth is recompensed, Surely also the wicked and the sinner!

Proverbs 12

1 Whoso is loving instruction, is loving knowledge, And whoso is hating reproof [is] brutish.

2 The good bringeth forth favour from Jehovah, And the man of wicked devices He condemneth.

3 A man is not established by wickedness, And the root of the righteous is not moved.

4 A virtuous woman [is] a crown to her husband, And as rottenness in his bones [is] one causing shame.

5 The thoughts of the righteous [are] justice, The counsels of the wicked--deceit.

6 The words of the wicked [are]: `Lay wait for blood,' And the mouth of the upright delivereth them.

7 Overthrow the wicked, and they are not, And the house of the righteous standeth.

8 According to his wisdom is a man praised, And the perverted of heart becometh despised.

9 Better [is] the lightly esteemed who hath a servant, Than the self-honoured who lacketh bread.

10 The righteous knoweth the life of his beast, And the mercies of the wicked [are] cruel.

11 Whoso is tilling the ground is satisfied [with] bread, And whoso is pursuing vanities is lacking heart,

12 The wicked hath desired the net of evil doers, And the root of the righteous giveth.

13 In transgression of the lips [is] the snare of the wicked, And the righteous goeth out from distress.

14 From the fruit of the mouth [is] one satisfied [with] good, And the deed of man's hands returneth to him.

15 The way of a fool [is] right in his own eyes, And whoso is hearkening to counsel [is] wise.

16 The fool--in a day is his anger known, And the prudent is covering shame.

17 Whoso uttereth faithfulness declareth righteousness, And a false witness--deceit.

18 A rash speaker is like piercings of a sword, And the tongue of the wise is healing.

19 The lip of truth is established for ever, And for a moment--a tongue of falsehood.

20 Deceit [is] in the heart of those devising evil, And to those counselling peace [is] joy.

21 No iniquity is desired by the righteous, And the wicked have been full of evil.

22 An abomination to Jehovah [are] lying lips, And stedfast doers [are] his delight.

23 A prudent man is concealing knowledge, And the heart of fools proclaimeth folly.

24 The hand of the diligent ruleth, And slothfulness becometh tributary.

25 Sorrow in the heart of a man boweth down, And a good word maketh him glad.

26 The righteous searcheth his companion, And the way of the wicked causeth them to err.

27 The slothful roasteth not his hunting, And the wealth of a diligent man is precious.

28 In the path of righteousness [is] life, And in the way of [that] path [is] no death!

Proverbs 13

1 A wise son--the instruction of a father, And a scorner--he hath not heard rebuke.

2 From the fruit of the mouth a man eateth good, And the soul of the treacherous-- violence.

3 Whoso is keeping his mouth, is keeping his soul, Whoso is opening wide his lips-- ruin to him!

4 The soul of the slothful is desiring, and hath not. And the soul of the diligent is made fat.

5 A false word the righteous hateth, And the wicked causeth abhorrence, and is confounded.

6 Righteousness keepeth him who is perfect in the way, And wickedness overthroweth a sin offering.

7 There is who is making himself rich, and hath nothing, Who is making himself poor, and wealth [is] abundant.

8 The ransom of a man's life [are] his riches, And the poor hath not heard rebuke.

9 The light of the righteous rejoiceth, And the lamp of the wicked is extinguished.

10 A vain man through pride causeth debate, And with the counselled [is] wisdom.

11 Wealth from vanity becometh little, And whoso is gathering by the hand becometh great.

12 Hope prolonged is making the heart sick, And a tree of life [is] the coming desire.

13 Whoso is despising the Word is destroyed for it, And whoso is fearing the Command is repayed.

14 The law of the wise [is] a fountain of life, To turn aside from snares of death.

15 Good understanding giveth grace, And the way of the treacherous [is] hard.

16 Every prudent one dealeth with knowledge, And a fool spreadeth out folly.

17 A wicked messenger falleth into evil, And a faithful ambassador is healing.

18 Whoso is refusing instruction--poverty and shame, And whoso is observing reproof is honoured.

19 A desire accomplished is sweet to the soul, And an abomination to fools [is]: Turn from evil.

20 Whoso is walking with wise men is wise, And a companion of fools suffereth evil.

21 Evil pursueth sinners, And good recompenseth the righteous.

22 A good man causeth sons' sons to inherit, And laid up for the righteous [is] the sinner's wealth.

23 Abundance of food--the tillage of the poor, And substance is consumed without judgment.

24 Whoso is sparing his rod is hating his son, And whoso is loving him hath hastened him chastisement.

25 The righteous is eating to the satiety of his soul, And the belly of the wicked lacketh!

Proverbs 14

1 Every wise woman hath builded her house, And the foolish with her hands breaketh it down.

2 Whoso is walking in his uprightness is fearing Jehovah, And the perverted [in] his ways is despising Him.

3 In the mouth of a fool [is] a rod of pride, And the lips of the wise preserve them.

4 Without oxen a stall [is] clean, And great [is] the increase by the power of the ox.

5 A faithful witness lieth not, And a false witness breatheth out lies.

6 A scorner hath sought wisdom, and it is not, And knowledge to the intelligent [is] easy.

7 Go from before a foolish man, Or thou hast not known the lips of knowledge.

8 The wisdom of the prudent [is] to understand his way, And the folly of fools [is] deceit.

9 Fools mock at a guilt-offering, And among the upright--a pleasing thing.

10 The heart knoweth its own bitterness, And with its joy a stranger doth not intermeddle.

11 The house of the wicked is destroyed, And the tent of the upright flourisheth.

12 There is a way--right before a man, And its latter end [are] ways of death.

13 Even in laughter is the heart pained, And the latter end of joy [is] affliction.

14 From his ways is the backslider in heart filled, And a good man--from his fruits.

15 The simple giveth credence to everything, And the prudent attendeth to his step.

16 The wise is fearing and turning from evil, And a fool is transgressing and is confident.

17 Whoso is short of temper doth folly, And a man of wicked devices is hated.

18 The simple have inherited folly, And the prudent are crowned [with] knowledge.

19 The evil have bowed down before the good, And the wicked at the gates of the righteous.

20 Even of his neighbour is the poor hated, And those loving the rich [are] many.

21 Whoso is despising his neighbour sinneth, Whoso is favouring the humble, O his happiness.

22 Do not they err who are devising evil? And kindness and truth [are] to those devising good,

23 In all labour there is advantage, And a thing of the lips [is] only to want.

24 The crown of the wise is their wealth, The folly of fools [is] folly.

25 A true witness is delivering souls, And a deceitful one breatheth out lies.

26 In the fear of Jehovah [is] strong confidence, And to His sons there is a refuge.

27 The fear of Jehovah [is] a fountain of life, To turn aside from snares of death.

28 In the multitude of a people [is] the honour of a king, And in lack of people the ruin of a prince.

29 Whoso is slow to anger [is] of great understanding, And whoso is short in temper is exalting folly.

30 A healed heart [is] life to the flesh, And rottenness to the bones [is] envy.

31 An oppressor of the poor reproacheth his Maker, And whoso is honouring Him Is favouring the needy.

32 In his wickedness is the wicked driven away, And trustful in his death [is] the righteous.

33 In the heart of the intelligent wisdom doth rest. And in the midst of fools it is known.

34 Righteousness exalteth a nation, And the goodliness of peoples [is] a sin-offering.

35 The favour of a king [is] to a wise servant, And an object of his wrath is one causing shame!

Proverbs 15

1 A soft answer turneth back fury, And a grievous word raiseth up anger.

2 The tongue of the wise maketh knowledge good, And the mouth of fools uttereth folly.

3 In every place are the eyes of Jehovah, Watching the evil and the good.

4 A healed tongue [is] a tree of life, And perverseness in it--a breach in the spirit.

5 A fool despiseth the instruction of his father, And whoso is regarding reproof is prudent.

6 [In] the house of the righteous [is] abundant strength, And in the increase of the wicked--trouble.

7 The lips of the wise scatter knowledge, And the heart of fools [is] not right.

8 The sacrifice of the wicked [is] an abomination to Jehovah, And the prayer of the upright [is] His delight.

9 An abomination to Jehovah [is] the way of the wicked, And whoso is pursuing righteousness He loveth.

10 Chastisement [is] grievous to him who is forsaking the path, Whoso is hating reproof dieth.

11 Sheol and destruction [are] before Jehovah, Surely also the hearts of the sons of men.

12 A scorner loveth not his reprover, Unto the wise he goeth not.

13 A joyful heart maketh glad the face, And by grief of heart is the spirit smitten.

14 The heart of the intelligent seeketh knowledge, And the mouth of fools enjoyeth folly.

15 All the days of the afflicted [are] evil, And gladness of heart [is] a perpetual banquet.

16 Better [is] a little with the fear of Jehovah, Than much treasure, and tumult with it.

17 Better [is] an allowance of green herbs and love there, Than a fatted ox, and hatred with it.

18 A man of fury stirreth up contention, And the slow to anger appeaseth strife.

19 The way of the slothful [is] as a hedge of briers, And the path of the upright is raised up.

20 A wise son rejoiceth a father. And a foolish man is despising his mother.

21 Folly is joy to one lacking heart, And a man of intelligence directeth [his] going.

22 Without counsel [is] the making void of purposes, And in a multitude of counsellors it is established.

23 Joy [is] to a man in the answer of his mouth, And a word in its season--how good!

24 A path of life [is] on high for the wise, To turn aside from Sheol beneath.

25 The house of the proud Jehovah pulleth down, And He setteth up the border of the widow.

26 An abomination to Jehovah [are] thoughts of wickedness, And pure [are] sayings of pleasantness.

27 A dishonest gainer is troubling his house, And whoso is hating gifts liveth.

28 The heart of the righteous meditateth to answer, And the mouth of the wicked uttereth evil things.

29 Far [is] Jehovah from the wicked, And the prayer of the righteous He heareth.

30 The light of the eyes rejoiceth the heart, A good report maketh fat the bone.

31 An ear that is hearing the reproof of life Doth lodge among the wise.

32 Whoso is refusing instruction is despising his soul, And whoso is hearing reproof Is getting understanding.

33 The fear of Jehovah [is] the instruction of wisdom, And before honour [is] humility!

Proverbs 16

1 Of man [are] arrangements of the heart, And from Jehovah an answer of the tongue.

2 All the ways of a man are pure in his own eyes, And Jehovah is pondering the spirits.

3 Roll unto Jehovah thy works, And established are thy purposes,

4 All things hath Jehovah wrought for Himself, And also the wicked [worketh] for a day of evil.

5 An abomination to Jehovah [is] every proud one of heart, Hand to hand he is not acquitted.

6 In kindness and truth pardoned is iniquity, And in the fear of Jehovah Turn thou aside from evil.

7 When a man's ways please Jehovah, even his enemies, He causeth to be at peace with him.

8 Better [is] a little with righteousness, Than abundance of increase without justice.

9 The heart of man deviseth his way, And Jehovah establisheth his step.

10 An oath [is] on the lips of a king, In judgment his mouth trespasseth not.

11 A just beam and balances [are] Jehovah's, His work [are] all the stones of the bag.

12 An abomination to kings [is] doing wickedness, For by righteousness is a throne established.

13 The delight of kings [are] righteous lips, And whoso is speaking uprightly he loveth,

14 The fury of a king [is] messengers of death, And a wise man pacifieth it.

15 In the light of a king's face [is] life, And his good-will [is] as a cloud of the latter rain.

16 To get wisdom--how much better than gold, And to get understanding to be chosen than silver!

17 A highway of the upright [is], `Turn from evil,' Whoso is preserving his soul is watching his way.

18 Before destruction [is] pride, And before stumbling--a haughty spirit.'

19 Better is humility of spirit with the poor, Than to apportion spoil with the proud.

20 The wise in any matter findeth good, And whoso is trusting in Jehovah, O his happiness.

21 To the wise in heart is called, `Intelligent,' And sweetness of lips increaseth learning.

22 A fountain of life [is] understanding to its possessors, The instruction of fools is folly.

23 The heart of the wise causeth his mouth to act wisely, And by his lips he increaseth learning,

24 Sayings of pleasantness [are] a honeycomb, Sweet to the soul, and healing to the bone.

25 There is a way right before a man, And its latter end--ways of death.

26 A labouring man hath laboured for himself, For his mouth hath caused [him] to bend over it.

27 A worthless man is preparing evil, And on his lips--as a burning fire.

28 A froward man sendeth forth contention, A tale-bearer is separating a familiar friend.

29 A violent man enticeth his neighbour, And hath causeth him to go in a way not good.

30 Consulting his eyes to devise froward things, Moving his lips he hath accomplished evil.

31 A crown of beauty [are] grey hairs, In the way of righteousness it is found.

32 Better [is] the slow to anger than the mighty, And the ruler over his spirit than he who is taking a city.

33 Into the centre is the lot cast, And from Jehovah [is] all its judgment!

Proverbs 17

1 Better [is] a dry morsel, and rest with it, Than a house full of the sacrifices of strife.

2 A wise servant ruleth over a son causing shame, And in the midst of brethren He apportioneth an inheritance.

3 A refining pot [is] for silver, and a furnace for gold, And the trier of hearts [is] Jehovah.

4 An evil doer is attentive to lips of vanity, Falsehood is giving ear to a mischievous tongue.

5 Whoso is mocking at the poor Hath reproached his Maker, Whoso is rejoicing at calamity is not acquitted.

6 Sons' sons [are] the crown of old men, And the glory of sons [are] their fathers.

7 Not comely for a fool is a lip of excellency, Much less for a noble a lip of falsehood.

8 A stone of grace [is] the bribe in the eyes of its possessors, Whithersoever it turneth, it prospereth.

9 Whoso is covering transgression is seeking love, And whoso is repeating a matter Is separating a familiar friend.

10 Rebuke cometh down on the intelligent More than a hundred stripes on a fool.

11 An evil man seeketh only rebellion, And a fierce messenger is sent against him.

12 The meeting of a bereaved bear by a man, And--not a fool in his folly.

13 Whoso is returning evil for good, Evil moveth not from his house.

14 The beginning of contention [is] a letting out of waters, And before it is meddled with leave the strife.

15 Whoso is justifying the wicked, And condemning the righteous, Even both of these [are] an abomination to Jehovah.

16 Why [is] this--a price in the hand of a fool to buy wisdom, And a heart there is none?

17 At all times is the friend loving, And a brother for adversity is born.

18 A man lacking heart is striking hands, A surety he becometh before his friend.

19 Whoso is loving transgression is loving debate, Whoso is making high his entrance is seeking destruction.

20 The perverse of heart findeth not good, And the turned in his tongue falleth into evil.

21 Whoso is begetting a fool hath affliction for it, Yea, the father of a fool rejoiceth not.

22 A rejoicing heart doth good to the body, And a smitten spirit drieth the bone.

23 A bribe from the bosom the wicked taketh, To turn aside the paths of judgment.

24 The face of the intelligent [is] to wisdom, And the eyes of a fool--at the end of the earth.

25 A provocation to his father [is] a foolish son, And bitterness to her that bare him.

26 Also, to fine the righteous is not good, To smite nobles for uprightness.

27 One acquainted with knowledge is sparing his words, And the cool of temper [is] a man of understanding.

28 Even a fool keeping silence is reckoned wise, He who is shutting his lips intelligent!

Proverbs 18

1 For [an object of] desire he who is separated doth seek, With all wisdom he intermeddleth.

2 A fool delighteth not in understanding, But--in uncovering his heart.

3 With the coming of the wicked come also hath contempt, And with shame-- reproach.

4 Deep waters [are] the words of a man's mouth, The fountain of wisdom [is] a flowing brook.

5 Acceptance of the face of the wicked [is] not good, To turn aside the righteous in judgment.

6 The lips of a fool enter into strife, And his mouth for stripes calleth.

7 The mouth of a fool [is] ruin to him, And his lips [are] the snare of his soul.

8 The words of a tale-bearer [are] as self-inflicted wounds, And they have gone down [to] the inner parts of the heart.

9 He also that is remiss in his work, A brother he [is] to a destroyer.

10 A tower of strength [is] the name of Jehovah, Into it the righteous runneth, and is set on high.

11 The wealth of the rich [is] the city of his strength, And as a wall set on high in his own imagination.

12 Before destruction the heart of man is high, And before honour [is] humility.

13 Whoso is answering a matter before he heareth, Folly it is to him and shame.

14 The spirit of a man sustaineth his sickness, And a smitten spirit who doth bear?

15 The heart of the intelligent getteth knowledge, And the ear of the wise seeketh knowledge.

16 The gift of a man maketh room for him, And before the great it leadeth him.

17 Righteous [is] the first in his own cause, His neighbour cometh and hath searched him.

18 The lot causeth contentions to cease, And between the mighty it separateth.

19 A brother transgressed against is as a strong city, And contentions as the bar of a palace.

20 From the fruit of a man's mouth is his belly satisfied, [From the] increase of his lips he is satisfied.

21 Death and life [are] in the power of the tongue, And those loving it eat its fruit.

22 [Whoso] hath found a wife hath found good, And bringeth out good-will from Jehovah.

23 [With] supplications doth the poor speak, And the rich answereth fierce things.

24 A man with friends [is] to show himself friendly, And there is a lover adhering more than a brother!

Proverbs 19

1 Better [is] the poor walking in his integrity, Than the perverse [in] his lips, who [is] a fool.

2 Also, without knowledge the soul [is] not good, And the hasty in feet is sinning.

3 The folly of man perverteth his way, And against Jehovah is his heart wroth.

4 Wealth addeth many friends, And the poor from his neighbour is separated.

5 A false witness is not acquitted, Whoso breatheth out lies is not delivered.

6 Many entreat the face of the noble, And all have made friendship to a man of gifts.

7 All the brethren of the poor have hated him, Surely also his friends have been far from him, He is pursuing words--they are not!

8 Whoso is getting heart is loving his soul, He is keeping understanding to find good.

9 A false witness is not acquitted, And whoso breatheth out lies perisheth.

10 Luxury is not comely for a fool, Much less for a servant to rule among princes.

11 The wisdom of a man hath deferred his anger, And his glory [is] to pass over transgression.

12 The wrath of a king [is] a growl as of a young lion, And as dew on the herb his good-will.

13 A calamity to his father [is] a foolish son, And the contentions of a wife [are] a continual dropping.

14 House and wealth [are] the inheritance of fathers, And from Jehovah [is] an understanding wife.

15 Sloth causeth deep sleep to fall, And an indolent soul doth hunger.

16 Whoso is keeping the command is keeping his soul, Whoso is despising His ways dieth.

17 Whoso is lending [to] Jehovah is favouring the poor, And his deed He repayeth to him.

18 Chastise thy son, for there is hope, And to put him to death lift not up thy soul.

19 A man of great wrath is bearing punishment, For, if thou dost deliver, yet again thou dost add.

20 Hear counsel and receive instruction, So that thou art wise in thy latter end.

21 Many [are] the purposes in a man's heart, And the counsel of Jehovah it standeth.

22 The desirableness of a man [is] his kindness, And better [is] the poor than a liar.

23 The fear of Jehovah [is] to life, And satisfied he remaineth--he is not charged with evil.

24 The slothful hath hidden his hand in a dish, Even unto his mouth he bringeth it not back.

25 A scorner smite, and the simple acts prudently, And give reproof to the intelligent, He understandeth knowledge.

26 Whoso is spoiling a father causeth a mother to flee, A son causing shame, and bringing confusion.

27 Cease, my son, to hear instruction--To err from sayings of knowledge.

28 A worthless witness scorneth judgment, And the mouth of the wicked swalloweth iniquity.

29 Judgments have been prepared for scorners, And stripes for the back of fools!

Proverbs 20

1 Wine [is] a scorner--strong drink [is] noisy, And any going astray in it is not wise.

2 The fear of a king [is] a growl as of a young lion, He who is causing him to be wroth is wronging his soul.

3 An honour to a man is cessation from strife, And every fool intermeddleth.

4 Because of winter the slothful plougheth not, He asketh in harvest, and there is nothing.

5 Counsel in the heart of a man [is] deep water, And a man of understanding draweth it up.

6 A multitude of men proclaim each his kindness, And a man of stedfastness who doth find?

7 The righteous is walking habitually in his integrity, O the happiness of his sons after him!

8 A king sitting on a throne of judgment, Is scattering with his eyes all evil,

9 Who saith, `I have purified my heart, I have been cleansed from my sin?'

10 A stone and a stone, an ephah and an ephah, Even both of them [are] an abomination to Jehovah.

11 Even by his actions a youth maketh himself known, Whether his work be pure or upright.

12 A hearing ear, and a seeing eye, Jehovah hath made even both of them.

13 Love not sleep, lest thou become poor, Open thine eyes--be satisfied [with] bread.

14 `Bad, bad,' saith the buyer, And going his way then he boasteth himself.

15 Substance, gold, and a multitude of rubies, Yea, a precious vessel, [are] lips of knowledge.

16 Take his garment when a stranger hath been surety, And for strangers pledge it.

17 Sweet to a man [is] the bread of falsehood, And afterwards is his mouth filled [with] gravel.

18 Purposes by counsel thou dost establish, And with plans make thou war.

19 A revealer of secret counsels is the busybody, And for a deceiver [with] his lips make not thyself surety.

20 Whoso is vilifying his father and his mother, Extinguished is his lamp in blackness of darkness.

21 An inheritance gotten wrongly at first, Even its latter end is not blessed.

22 Do not say, `I recompense evil,' Wait for Jehovah, and He delivereth thee.

23 An abomination to Jehovah [are] a stone and a stone, And balances of deceit [are] not good.

24 From Jehovah [are] the steps of a man, And man--how understandeth he his way?

25 A snare to a man [is] he hath swallowed a holy thing, And after vows to make inquiry.

26 A wise king is scattering the wicked, And turneth back on them the wheel.

27 The breath of man [is] a lamp of Jehovah, Searching all the inner parts of the heart.

28 Kindness and truth keep a king, And he hath supported by kindness his throne.

29 The beauty of young men is their strength, And the honour of old men is grey hairs.

30 The bandages of a wound thou removest with the evil, Also the plagues of the inner parts of the heart!

Proverbs 21

1 Rivulets of waters [is] the heart of a king in the hand of Jehovah, Wherever He pleaseth He inclineth it.

2 Every way of a man [is] right in his own eyes, And Jehovah is pondering hearts.

3 To do righteousness and judgment, Is chosen of Jehovah rather than sacrifice.

4 Loftiness of eyes, and breadth of heart, Tillage of the wicked [is] sin.

5 The purposes of the diligent [are] only to advantage, And of every hasty one, only to want.

6 The making of treasures by a lying tongue, [Is] a vanity driven away of those seeking death.

7 The spoil of the wicked catcheth them, Because they have refused to do judgment.

8 Froward [is] the way of a man who is vile, And the pure--upright [is] his work.

9 Better to sit on a corner of the roof, Than [with] a woman of contentions and a house of company.

10 The soul of the wicked hath desired evil, Not gracious in his eyes is his neighbour.

11 When the scorner is punished, the simple becometh wise, And in giving understanding to the wise He receiveth knowledge.

12 The Righteous One is acting wisely Towards the house of the wicked, He is overthrowing the wicked for wickedness.

13 Whoso is shutting his ear from the cry of the poor, He also doth cry, and is not answered.

14 A gift in secret pacifieth anger, And a bribe in the bosom strong fury.

15 To do justice [is] joy to the righteous, But ruin to workers of iniquity.

16 A man who is wandering from the way of understanding, In an assembly of Rephaim resteth.

17 Whoso [is] loving mirth [is] a poor man, Whoso is loving wine and oil maketh no wealth.

18 The wicked [is] an atonement for the righteous, And for the upright the treacherous dealer.

19 Better to dwell in a wilderness land, Than [with] a woman of contentions and anger.

20 A treasure to be desired, and oil, [Is] in the habitation of the wise, And a foolish man swalloweth it up.

21 Whoso is pursuing righteousness and kindness, Findeth life, righteousness, and honour.

22 A city of the mighty hath the wise gone up, And bringeth down the strength of its confidence.

23 Whoso is keeping his mouth and his tongue, Is keeping from adversities his soul.

24 Proud, haughty, scorner [is] his name, Who is working in the wrath of pride.

25 The desire of the slothful slayeth him, For his hands have refused to work.

26 All the day desiring he hath desired, And the righteous giveth and withholdeth not.

27 The sacrifice of the wicked [is] abomination, Much more when in wickedness he bringeth it.

28 A false witness doth perish, And an attentive man for ever speaketh.

29 A wicked man hath hardened by his face, And the upright--he prepareth his way.

30 There is no wisdom, nor understanding, Nor counsel, over-against Jehovah.

31 A horse is prepared for a day of battle, And the deliverance [is] of Jehovah!

Proverbs 22

1 A name is chosen rather than much wealth, Than silver and than gold--good grace.

2 Rich and poor have met together, The Maker of them all [is] Jehovah.

3 The prudent hath seen the evil, and is hidden, And the simple have passed on, and are punished.

4 The end of humility [is] the fear of Jehovah, Riches, and honour, and life.

5 Thorns--snares [are] in the way of the perverse, Whoso is keeping his soul is far from them.

6 Give instruction to a youth about his way, Even when he is old he turneth not from it.

7 The rich over the poor ruleth, And a servant [is] the borrower to the lender.

8 Whoso is sowing perverseness reapeth sorrow, And the rod of his anger weareth out.

9 The good of eye--he is blessed, For he hath given of his bread to the poor.

10 Cast out a scorner--and contention goeth out, And strife and shame cease.

11 Whoso is loving cleanness of heart, Grace [are] his lips, a king [is] his friend.

12 The eyes of Jehovah have kept knowledge, And He overthroweth the words of the treacherous.

13 The slothful hath said, `A lion [is] without, In the midst of the broad places I am slain.'

14 A deep pit [is] the mouth of strange women, The abhorred of Jehovah falleth there.

15 Folly is bound up in the heart of a youth, The rod of chastisement putteth it far from him.

16 He is oppressing the poor to multiply to him, He is giving to the rich--only to want.

17 Incline thine ear, and hear words of the wise, And thy heart set to my knowledge,

18 For they are pleasant when thou dost keep them in thy heart, They are prepared together for thy lips.

19 That thy trust may be in Jehovah, I caused thee to know to-day, even thou.

20 Have I not written to thee three times With counsels and knowledge?

21 To cause thee to know the certainty of sayings of truth, To return sayings of truth to those sending thee.

22 Rob not the poor because he [is] poor, And bruise not the afflicted in the gate.

23 For Jehovah pleadeth their cause, And hath spoiled the soul of their spoilers.

24 Shew not thyself friendly with an angry man, And with a man of fury go not in,

25 Lest thou learn his paths, And have received a snare to thy soul.

26 Be not thou among those striking hands, Among sureties [for] burdens.

27 If thou hast nothing to pay, Why doth he take thy bed from under thee?

28 Remove not a border of olden times, That thy fathers have made.

29 Hast thou seen a man speedy in his business? Before kings he doth station himself, He stations not himself before obscure men!

Proverbs 23

1 When thou sittest to eat with a ruler, Thou considerest diligently that which [is] before thee,

2 And thou hast put a knife to thy throat, If thou [art] a man of appetite.

3 Have no desire to his dainties, seeing it [is] lying food.

4 Labour not to make wealth, From thine own understanding cease, Dost thou cause thine eyes to fly upon it? Then it is not.

5 For wealth maketh to itself wings, As an eagle it flieth to the heavens.

6 Eat not the bread of an evil eye, And have no desire to his dainties,

7 For as he hath thought in his soul, so [is] he, `Eat and drink,' saith he to thee, And his heart [is] not with thee.

8 Thy morsel thou hast eaten thou dost vomit up, And hast marred thy words that [are] sweet.

9 In the ears of a fool speak not, For he treadeth on the wisdom of thy words.

10 Remove not a border of olden times, And into fields of the fatherless enter not,

11 For their Redeemer [is] strong, He doth plead their cause with thee.

12 Bring in to instruction thy heart, And thine ear to sayings of knowledge.

13 Withhold not from a youth chastisement, When thou smitest him with a rod he dieth not.

14 Thou with a rod smitest him, And his soul from Sheol thou deliverest.

15 My son, if thy heart hath been wise, My heart rejoiceth, even mine,

16 And my reins exult when thy lips speak uprightly.

17 Let not thy heart be envious at sinners, But--in the fear of Jehovah all the day.

18 For, is there a posterity? Then thy hope is not cut off.

19 Hear thou, my son, and be wise, And make happy in the way thy heart,

20 Be not thou among quaffers of wine, Among gluttonous ones of flesh,

21 For the quaffer and glutton become poor, And drowsiness clotheth with rags.

22 Hearken to thy father, who begat thee, And despise not thy mother when she hath become old.

23 Truth buy, and sell not, Wisdom, and instruction, and understanding,

24 The father of the righteous rejoiceth greatly, The begetter of the wise rejoiceth in him.

25 Rejoice doth thy father and thy mother, Yea, she that bare thee is joyful.

26 Give, my son, thy heart to me, And let thine eyes watch my ways.

27 For a harlot [is] a deep ditch, And a strange woman [is] a strait pit.

28 She also, as catching prey, lieth in wait, And the treacherous among men she increaseth.

29 Who hath woe? who hath sorrow? Who hath contentions? who hath plaint? Who hath wounds without cause? Who hath redness of eyes?

30 Those tarrying by the wine, Those going in to search out mixed wine.

31 See not wine when it showeth itself red, When it giveth in the cup its colour, It goeth up and down through the upright.

32 Its latter end--as a serpent it biteth, And as a basilisk it stingeth.

33 Thine eyes see strange women, And thy heart speaketh perverse things.

34 And thou hast been as one lying down in the heart of the sea, And as one lying down on the top of a mast.

35 `They smote me, I have not been sick, They beat me, I have not known. When I awake--I seek it yet again!'

Proverbs 24

1 Be not envious of evil men, And desire not to be with them.

2 For destruction doth their heart meditate, And perverseness do their lips speak.

3 By wisdom is a house builded, And by understanding it establisheth itself.

4 And by knowledge the inner parts are filled, [With] all precious and pleasant wealth.

5 Mighty [is] the wise in strength, And a man of knowledge is strengthening power,

6 For by plans thou makest for thyself war, And deliverance [is] in a multitude of counsellors.

7 Wisdom [is] high for a fool, In the gate he openeth not his mouth.

8 Whoso is devising to do evil, Him they call a master of wicked thoughts.

9 The thought of folly [is] sin, And an abomination to man [is] a scorner.

10 Thou hast shewed thyself weak in a day of adversity, Straitened is thy power,

11 If [from] delivering those taken to death, And those slipping to the slaughter--thou keepest back.

12 When thou sayest, `Lo, we knew not this.' Is not the Ponderer of hearts He who understandeth? And the Keeper of thy soul He who knoweth? And He hath rendered to man according to his work.

13 Eat my son, honey that [is] good, And the honeycomb--sweet to thy palate.

14 So [is] the knowledge of wisdom to thy soul, If thou hast found that there is a posterity And thy hope is not cut off.

15 Lay not wait, O wicked one, At the habitation of the righteous. Do not spoil his resting-place.

16 For seven [times] doth the righteous fall and rise, And the wicked stumble in evil.

17 In the falling of thine enemy rejoice not, And in his stumbling let not thy heart be joyful,

18 Lest Jehovah see, and [it be] evil in His eyes, And He hath turned from off him His anger.

19 Fret not thyself at evil doers, Be not envious at the wicked,

20 For there is not a posterity to the evil, The lamp of the wicked is extinguished.

21 Fear Jehovah, my son, and the king, With changers mix not up thyself,

22 For suddenly doth their calamity rise, And the ruin of them both--who knoweth!

23 These also are for the wise: --To discern faces in judgment is not good.

24 Whoso is saying to the wicked, `Thou [art] righteous,' Peoples execrate him-- nations abhor him.

25 And to those reproving it is pleasant, And on them cometh a good blessing.

26 Lips he kisseth who is returning straightforward words.

27 Prepare in an out-place thy work, And make it ready in the field--go afterwards, Then thou hast built thy house.

28 Be not a witness for nought against thy neighbour, Or thou hast enticed with thy lips.

29 Say not, `As he did to me, so I do to him, I render to each according to his work.'

30 Near the field of a slothful man I passed by, And near the vineyard of a man lacking heart.

31 And lo, it hath gone up--all of it--thorns! Covered its face have nettles, And its stone wall hath been broken down.

32 And I see--I--I do set my heart, I have seen--I have received instruction,

33 A little sleep--a little slumber--A little folding of the hands to lie down.

34 And thy poverty hath come [as] a traveller, And thy want as an armed man!

Proverbs 25

1 Also these are Proverbs of Solomon, that men of Hezekiah king of Judah transcribed: --

2 The honour of God [is] to hide a thing, And the honour of kings to search out a matter.

3 The heavens for height, and the earth for depth, And the heart of kings--[are] unsearchable.

4 Take away dross from silver, And a vessel for the refiner goeth forth,

5 Take away the wicked before a king, And established in righteousness is his throne.

6 Honour not thyself before a king, And in the place of the great stand not.

7 For better [that] he hath said to thee, `Come thou up hither,' Than [that] he humble thee before a noble, Whom thine eyes have seen.

8 Go not forth to strive, haste, turn, What dost thou in its latter end, When thy neighbour causeth thee to blush?

9 Thy cause plead with thy neighbour, And the secret counsel of another reveal not,

10 Lest the hearer put thee to shame, And thine evil report turn not back.

11 Apples of gold in imagery of silver, [Is] the word spoken at its fit times.

12 A ring of gold, and an ornament of pure gold, [Is] the wise reprover to an attentive ear.

13 As a vessel of snow in a day of harvest, [So is] a faithful ambassador to those sending him, And the soul of his masters he refresheth.

14 Clouds and wind, and rain there is none, [Is] a man boasting himself in a false gift.

15 By long-suffering is a ruler persuaded, And a soft tongue breaketh a bone.

16 Honey thou hast found--eat thy sufficiency, Lest thou be satiated [with] it, and hast vomited it.

17 Withdraw thy foot from thy neighbour's house, Lest he be satiated [with] thee, and have hated thee.

18 A maul, and a sword, and a sharp arrow, [Is] the man testifying against his neighbour a false testimony.

19 A bad tooth, and a tottering foot, [Is] the confidence of the treacherous in a day of adversity.

20 Whoso is taking away a garment in a cold day, [Is as] vinegar on nitre, And a singer of songs on a sad heart.

21 If he who is hating thee doth hunger, cause him to eat bread, And if he thirst, cause him to drink water.

22 For coals thou art putting on his head, And Jehovah giveth recompense to thee.

23 A north wind bringeth forth rain, And a secret tongue--indignant faces.

24 Better to sit on a corner of a roof, Than [with] a woman of contentions, and a house of company.

25 [As] cold waters for a weary soul, So [is] a good report from a far country.

26 A spring troubled, and a fountain corrupt, [Is] the righteous falling before the wicked.

27 The eating of much honey is not good, Nor a searching out of one's own honour-- honour.

28 A city broken down without walls, [Is] a man without restraint over his spirit!

Proverbs 26

1 As snow in summer, and as rain in harvest, So honour [is] not comely for a fool.

2 As a bird by wandering, as a swallow by flying, So reviling without cause doth not come.

3 A whip is for a horse, a bridle for an ass, And a rod for the back of fools.

4 Answer not a fool according to his folly, Lest thou be like to him--even thou.

5 Answer a fool according to his folly, Lest he be wise in his own eyes.

6 He is cutting off feet, he is drinking injury, Who is sending things by the hand of a fool.

7 Weak have been the two legs of the lame, And a parable in the mouth of fools.

8 As one who is binding a stone in a sling, So [is] he who is giving honour to a fool.

9 A thorn hath gone up into the hand of a drunkard, And a parable in the mouth of fools.

10 Great [is] the Former of all, And He is rewarding a fool, And is rewarding transgressors.

11 As a dog hath returned to its vomit, A fool is repeating his folly.

12 Thou hast seen a man wise in his own eyes, More hope of a fool than of him!

13 The slothful hath said, `A lion [is] in the way, A lion [is] in the broad places.'

14 The door turneth round on its hinge, And the slothful on his bed.

15 The slothful hath hid his hand in a dish, He is weary of bringing it back to his mouth.

16 Wiser [is] the slothful in his own eyes, Than seven [men] returning a reason.

17 Laying hold on the ears of a dog, [Is] a passer-by making himself wrath for strife not his own.

18 As [one] pretending to be feeble, Who is casting sparks, arrows, and death,

19 So hath a man deceived his neighbour, And hath said, `Am not I playing?'

20 Without wood is fire going out, And without a tale-bearer, contention ceaseth,

21 Coal to burning coals, and wood to fire, And a man of contentions to kindle strife.

22 The words of a tale-bearer [are] as self-inflicted wounds, And they have gone down [to] the inner parts of the heart.

23 Silver of dross spread over potsherd, [Are] burning lips and an evil heart.

24 By his lips doth a hater dissemble, And in his heart he placeth deceit,

25 When his voice is gracious trust not in him, For seven abominations [are] in his heart.

26 Hatred is covered by deceit, Revealed is its wickedness in an assembly.

27 Whoso is digging a pit falleth into it, And the roller of a stone, to him it turneth.

28 A lying tongue hateth its bruised ones, And a flattering mouth worketh an overthrow!

Proverbs 27

1 Boast not thyself of to-morrow, For thou knowest not what a day bringeth forth.

2 Let another praise thee, and not thine own mouth, A stranger, and not thine own lips.

3 A stone [is] heavy, and the sand [is] heavy, And the anger of a fool Is heavier than they both.

4 Fury [is] fierce, and anger [is] overflowing, And who standeth before jealousy?

5 Better [is] open reproof than hidden love.

6 Faithful are the wounds of a lover, And abundant the kisses of an enemy.

7 A satiated soul treadeth down a honeycomb, And [to] a hungry soul every bitter thing [is] sweet.

8 As a bird wandering from her nest, So [is] a man wandering from his place.

9 Ointment and perfume rejoice the heart, And the sweetness of one's friend--from counsel of the soul.

10 Thine own friend, and the friend of thy father, forsake not, And the house of thy brother enter not In a day of thy calamity, Better [is] a near neighbour than a brother afar off.

11 Be wise, my son, and rejoice my heart. And I return my reproacher a word.

12 The prudent hath seen the evil, he is hidden, The simple have passed on, they are punished.

13 Take his garment, when a stranger hath been surety, And for a strange woman pledge it.

14 Whoso is saluting his friend with a loud voice, In the morning rising early, A light thing it is reckoned to him.

15 A continual dropping in a day of rain, And a woman of contentions are alike,

16 Whoso is hiding her hath hidden the wind, And the ointment of his right hand calleth out.

17 Iron by iron is sharpened, And a man sharpens the face of his friend.

18 The keeper of a fig-tree eateth its fruit, And the preserver of his master is honoured.

19 As [in] water the face [is] to face, So the heart of man to man.

20 Sheol and destruction are not satisfied, And the eyes of man are not satisfied.

21 A refining pot [is] for silver, and a furnace for gold, And a man according to his praise.

22 If thou dost beat the foolish in a mortar, Among washed things--with a pestle, His folly turneth not aside from off him.

23 Know well the face of thy flock, Set thy heart to the droves,

24 For riches [are] not to the age, Nor a crown to generation and generation.

25 Revealed was the hay, and seen the tender grass, And gathered the herbs of mountains.

26 Lambs [are] for thy clothing, And the price of the field [are] he-goats,

27 And a sufficiency of goats' milk [is] for thy bread, For bread to thy house, and life to thy damsels!

Proverbs 28

1 The wicked have fled and there is no pursuer. And the righteous as a young lion is confident.

2 By the transgression of a land many [are] its heads. And by an intelligent man, Who knoweth right--it is prolonged.

3 A man--poor and oppressing the weak, [Is] a sweeping rain, and there is no bread.

4 Those forsaking the law praise the wicked, Those keeping the law plead against them.

5 Evil men understand not judgment, And those seeking Jehovah understand all.

6 Better [is] the poor walking in his integrity, Than the perverse of ways who is rich.

7 Whoso is keeping the law is an intelligent son, And a friend of gluttons, Doth cause his father to blush.

8 Whoso is multiplying his wealth by biting and usury, For one favouring the poor doth gather it.

9 Whoso is turning his ear from hearing the law, Even his prayer [is] an abomination.

10 Whoso is causing the upright to err in an evil way, Into his own pit he doth fall, And the perfect do inherit good.

11 A rich man is wise in his own eyes, And the intelligent poor searcheth him.

12 In the exulting of the righteous the glory [is] abundant, And in the rising of the wicked man is apprehensive.

13 Whoso is covering his transgressions prospereth not, And he who is confessing and forsaking hath mercy.

14 O the happiness of a man fearing continually, And whoso is hardening his heart falleth into evil.

15 A growling lion, and a ranging bear, [Is] the wicked ruler over a poor people.

16 A leader lacking understanding multiplieth oppressions, Whoso is hating dishonest gain prolongeth days.

17 A man oppressed with the blood of a soul, Unto the pit fleeth, none taketh hold on him.

18 Whoso is walking uprightly is saved, And the perverted of ways falleth at once.

19 Whoso is tilling his ground is satisfied [with] bread, And whoso is pursuing vanity, Is filled [with] poverty.

20 A stedfast man hath multiplied blessings, And whoso is hasting to be rich is not acquitted.

21 To discern faces is not good, And for a piece of bread doth a man transgress.

22 Troubled for wealth [is] the man [with] an evil eye, And he knoweth not that want doth meet him.

23 Whoso is reproving a man afterwards findeth grace, More than a flatterer with the tongue.

24 Whoso is robbing his father, or his mother, And is saying, `It is not transgression,' A companion he is to a destroyer.

25 Whoso is proud in soul stirreth up contention, And whoso is trusting on Jehovah is made fat.

26 Whoso is trusting in his heart is a fool, And whoso is walking in wisdom is delivered.

27 Whoso is giving to the poor hath no lack, And whoso is hiding his eyes multiplied curses.

28 In the rising of the wicked a man is hidden, And in their destruction the righteous multiply!

Proverbs 29

1 A man often reproved, hardening the neck, Is suddenly broken, and there is no healing.

2 In the multiplying of the righteous the people rejoice, And in the ruling of the wicked the people sigh.

3 A man loving wisdom rejoiceth his father, And a friend of harlots destroyeth wealth.

4 A king by judgment establisheth a land, And one receiving gifts throweth it down.

5 A man taking a portion above his neighbour, Spreadeth a net for his own steps.

6 In the transgression of the evil [is] a snare, And the righteous doth sing and rejoice.

7 The righteous knoweth the plea of the poor, The wicked understandeth not knowledge.

8 Men of scorning ensnare a city, And the wise turn back anger.

9 A wise man is judged by the foolish man, And he hath been angry, And he hath laughed, and there is no rest.

10 Men of blood hate the perfect, And the upright seek his soul.

11 A fool bringeth out all his mind, And the wise till afterwards restraineth it.

12 A ruler who is attending to lying words, All his ministers [are] wicked.

13 The poor and the man of frauds have met together, Jehovah is enlightening the eyes of them both.

14 a king that is judging truly the poor, His throne for ever is established.

15 A rod and reproof give wisdom, And a youth let away is shaming his mother.

16 In the multiplying of the wicked transgression multiplieth, And the righteous on their fall do look.

17 Chastise thy son, and he giveth thee comfort, Yea, he giveth delights to thy soul.

18 Without a Vision is a people made naked, And whoso is keeping the law, O his happiness!

19 By words a servant is not instructed though he understand, And there is nothing answering.

20 Thou hast seen a man hasty in his words! More hope of a fool than of him.

21 Whoso is bringing up his servant delicately, from youth, [At] his latter end also he is continuator.

22 An angry man stirreth up contention, And a furious man is multiplying transgression.

23 The pride of man humbleth him, And humility of spirit upholdeth honour.

24 Whoso is sharing with a thief is hating his own soul, Execration he heareth, and telleth not.

25 Fear of man causeth a snare, And the confident in Jehovah is set on high.

26 Many are seeking the face of a ruler, And from Jehovah [is] the judgment of each.

27 An abomination to the righteous [is] the perverse man, And an abomination to the wicked [is] the upright in the way!

Proverbs 30

1 Words of a Gatherer, son of an obedient one, the declaration, an affirmation of the man: --I have wearied myself [for] God, I have wearied myself [for] God, and am consumed.

2 For I am more brutish than any one, And have not the understanding of a man.

3 Nor have I learned wisdom, Yet the knowledge of Holy Ones I know.

4 Who went up to heaven, and cometh down? Who hath gathered the wind in his fists? Who hath bound waters in a garment? Who established all ends of the earth? What [is] His name? and what His son's name? Surely thou knowest!

5 Every saying of God [is] tried, A shield He [is] to those trusting in Him.

6 Add not to His words, lest He reason with thee, And thou hast been found false.

7 Two things I have asked from Thee, Withhold not from me before I die.

8 Vanity and a lying word put far from me, Poverty or wealth give not to me, Cause me to eat the bread of my portion,

9 Lest I become satiated, and have denied, And have said, `Who [is] Jehovah?' And lest I be poor, and have stolen, And have laid hold of the name of my God.

10 Accuse not a servant unto his lord, Lest he disesteem thee, and thou be found guilty.

11 A generation [is], that lightly esteemeth their father, And their mother doth not bless.

12 A generation--pure in their own eyes, But from their own filth not washed.

13 A generation--how high are their eyes, Yea, their eyelids are lifted up.

14 A generation--swords [are] their teeth, And knives--their jaw-teeth, To consume the poor from earth, And the needy from [among] men.

15 To the leech [are] two daughters, `Give, give, Lo, three things are not satisfied, Four have not said `Sufficiency;'

16 Sheol, and a restrained womb, Earth--it [is] not satisfied [with] water, And fire--it hath not said, `Sufficiency,'

17 An eye that mocketh at a father, And despiseth to obey a mother, Dig it out do ravens of the valley, And eat it do young eagles.

18 Three things have been too wonderful for me, Yea, four that I have not known:

19 The way of the eagle in the heavens, The way of a serpent on a rock, The way of a ship in the heart of the sea, And the way of a man in youth.

20 So--the way of an adulterous woman, She hath eaten and hath wiped her mouth, And hath said, `I have not done iniquity.'

21 For three things hath earth been troubled, And for four--it is not able to bear:

22 For a servant when he reigneth, And a fool when he is satisfied with bread,

23 For a hated one when she ruleth, And a maid-servant when she succeedeth her mistress.

24 Four [are] little ones of earth, And they are made wiser than the wise:

25 The ants [are] a people not strong, And they prepare in summer their food,

26 Conies [are] a people not strong, And they place in a rock their house,

27 A king there is not to the locust, And it goeth out--each one shouting,

28 A spider with two hands taketh hold, And is in the palaces of a king.

29 Three there are going well, Yea, four are good in going:

30 An old lion--mighty among beasts, That turneth not back from the face of any,

31 A girt one of the loins, or a he-goat, And a king--no rising up with him.

32 If thou hast been foolish in lifting up thyself, And if thou hast devised evil--hand to mouth!

33 For the churning of milk bringeth out butter, And the wringing of the nose bringeth out blood, And the forcing of anger bringeth out strife!

Proverbs 31

1 Words of Lemuel a king, a declaration that his mother taught him:

2 `What, my son? and what, son of my womb? And what, son of my vows?

3 Give not to women thy strength, And thy ways to wiping away of kings.

4 Not for kings, O Lemuel, Not for kings, to drink wine, And for princes a desire of strong drink.

5 Lest he drink, and forget the decree, And change the judgment of any of the sons of affliction.

6 Give strong drink to the perishing, And wine to the bitter in soul,

7 He drinketh, and forgetteth his poverty, And his misery he remembereth not again.

8 Open thy mouth for the dumb, For the right of all sons of change.

9 Open thy mouth, judge righteously, Both the cause of the poor and needy!'

10 A woman of worth who doth find? Yea, far above rubies [is] her price.

11 The heart of her husband hath trusted in her, And spoil he lacketh not.

12 She hath done him good, and not evil, All days of her life.

13 She hath sought wool and flax, And with delight she worketh [with] her hands.

14 She hath been as ships of the merchant, From afar she bringeth in her bread.

15 Yea, she riseth while yet night, And giveth food to her household, And a portion to her damsels.

16 She hath considered a field, and taketh it, From the fruit of her hands she hath planted a vineyard.

17 She hath girded with might her loins, And doth strengthen her arms.

18 She hath perceived when her merchandise [is] good, Her lamp is not extinguished in the night.

19 Her hands she hath sent forth on a spindle, And her hands have held a distaff.

20 Her hand she hath spread forth to the poor, Yea, her hands she sent forth to the needy.

21 She is not afraid of her household from snow, For all her household are clothed [with] scarlet.

22 Ornamental coverings she hath made for herself, Silk and purple [are] her clothing.

23 Known in the gates is her husband, In his sitting with elders of the land.

24 Linen garments she hath made, and selleth, And a girdle she hath given to the merchant.

25 Strength and honour [are] her clothing, And she rejoiceth at a latter day.

26 Her mouth she hath opened in wisdom, And the law of kindness [is] on her tongue.

27 She [is] watching the ways of her household, And bread of sloth she eateth not.

28 Her sons have risen up, and pronounce her happy, Her husband, and he praiseth her,

29 `Many [are] the daughters who have done worthily, Thou hast gone up above them all.'

30 The grace [is] false, and the beauty [is] vain, A woman fearing Jehovah, she may boast herself.

31 Give ye to her of the fruit of her hands, And her works do praise her in the gates!

Ecclesiastes 1

1 Words of a preacher, son of David, king in Jerusalem:

2 Vanity of vanities, said the Preacher, Vanity of vanities: the whole [is] vanity.

3 What advantage [is] to man by all his labour that he laboureth at under the sun?

4 A generation is going, and a generation is coming, and the earth to the age is standing.

5 Also, the sun hath risen, and the sun hath gone in, and unto its place panting it is rising there.

6 Going unto the south, and turning round unto the north, turning round, turning round, the wind is going, and by its circuits the wind hath returned.

7 All the streams are going unto the sea, and the sea is not full; unto a place whither the streams are going, thither they are turning back to go.

8 All these things are wearying; a man is not able to speak, the eye is not satisfied by seeing, nor filled is the ear from hearing.

9 What [is] that which hath been? it [is] that which is, and what [is] that which hath been done? it [is] that which is done, and there is not an entirely new thing under the sun.

10 There is a thing of which [one] saith: `See this, it [is] new!' already it hath been in the ages that were before us!

11 There is not a remembrance of former [generations]; and also of the latter that are, there is no remembrance of them with those that are at the last.

12 I, a preacher, have been king over Israel in Jerusalem.

13 And I have given my heart to seek and to search out by wisdom concerning all that hath been done under the heavens. It [is] a sad travail God hath given to the sons of man to be humbled by it.

14 I have seen all the works that have been done under the sun, and lo, the whole [is] vanity and vexation of spirit!

15 A crooked thing [one] is not able to make straight, and a lacking thing is not able to be numbered.

16 I--I spake with my heart, saying, `I, lo, I have magnified and added wisdom above every one who hath been before me at Jerusalem, and my heart hath seen abundantly wisdom and knowledge.

17 And I give my heart to know wisdom, and to know madness and folly: I have known that even this [is] vexation of spirit;

18 for, in abundance of wisdom [is] abundance of sadness, and he who addeth knowledge addeth pain.'

Ecclesiastes 2

1 I said in my heart, `Pray, come, I try thee with mirth, and look thou on gladness;' and lo, even it [is] vanity.

2 Of laughter I said, `Foolish!' and of mirth, `What [is] this it is doing?'

3 I have sought in my heart to draw out with wine my appetite, (and my heart leading in wisdom), and to take hold on folly till that I see where [is] this--the good to the sons of man of that which they do under the heavens, the number of the days of their lives.

4 I made great my works, I builded for me houses, I planted for me vineyards.

5 I made for me gardens and paradises, and I planted in them trees of every fruit.

6 I made for me pools of water, to water from them a forest shooting forth trees.

7 I got men-servants, and maid-servants, and sons of the house were to me; also, I had much substance--herd and flock--above all who had been before me in Jerusalem.

8 I gathered for me also silver and gold, and the peculiar treasure of kings and of the provinces. I prepared for me men-singers and women-singers, and the luxuries of the sons of man-- a wife and wives.

9 And I became great, and increased above every one who had been before me in Jerusalem; also, my wisdom stood with me.

10 And all that mine eyes asked I kept not back from them; I withheld not my heart from any joy, for my heart rejoiced because of all my labour, and this hath been my portion, from all my labour,

11 and I have looked on all my works that my hands have done, and on the labour that I have laboured to do, and lo, the whole [is] vanity and vexation of spirit, and there is no advantage under the sun!

12 And I turned to see wisdom, and madness, and folly, but what [is] the man who cometh after the king? that which [is] already--they have done it!

13 And I saw that there is an advantage to wisdom above folly, like the advantage of the light above the darkness.

14 The wise! --his eyes [are] in his head, and the fool in darkness is walking, and I also knew that one event happeneth with them all;

15 and I said in my heart, `As it happeneth with the fool, it happeneth also with me, and why am I then more wise?' And I spake in my heart, that also this [is] vanity:

16 That there is no remembrance to the wise--with the fool--to the age, for that which [is] already, [in] the days that are coming is all forgotten, and how dieth the wise? with the fool!

17 And I have hated life, for sad to me [is] the work that hath been done under the sun, for the whole [is] vanity and vexation of spirit.

18 And I have hated all my labour that I labour at under the sun, because I leave it to a man who is after me.

19 And who knoweth whether he is wise or foolish? yet he doth rule over all my labour that I have laboured at, and that I have done wisely under the sun! this also [is] vanity.

20 And I turned round to cause my heart to despair concerning all the labour that I laboured at under the sun.

21 For there is a man whose labour [is] in wisdom, and in knowledge, and in equity, and to a man who hath not laboured therein he giveth it--his portion! Even this [is] vanity and a great evil.

22 For what hath been to a man by all his labour, and by the thought of his heart that he laboured at under the sun?

23 For all his days are sorrows, and his travail sadness; even at night his heart hath not lain down; this also [is] vanity.

24 There is nothing good in a man who eateth, and hath drunk, and hath shewn his soul good in his labour. This also I have seen that it [is] from the hand of God.

25 For who eateth and who hasteth out more than I?

26 For to a man who [is] good before Him, He hath given wisdom, and knowledge, and joy; and to a sinner He hath given travail, to gather and to heap up, to give to the good before God. Even this [is] vanity and vexation of spirit.

Ecclesiastes 3

1 To everything--a season, and a time to every delight under the heavens:

2 A time to bring forth, And a time to die. A time to plant, And a time to eradicate the planted.

3 A time to slay, And a time to heal, A time to break down, And a time to build up.

4 A time to weep, And a time to laugh. A time to mourn, And a time to skip.

5 A time to cast away stones, And a time to heap up stones. A time to embrace, And a time to be far from embracing.

6 A time to seek, And a time to destroy. A time to keep, And a time to cast away.

7 A time to rend, And a time to sew. A time to be silent, And a time to speak.

8 A time to love, And a time to hate. A time of war, And a time of peace.

9 What advantage hath the doer in that which he is labouring at?

10 I have seen the travail that God hath given to the sons of man to be humbled by it.

11 The whole He hath made beautiful in its season; also, that knowledge He hath put in their heart without which man findeth not out the work that God hath done from the beginning even unto the end.

12 I have known that there is no good for them except to rejoice and to do good during their life,

13 yea, even every man who eateth and hath drunk and seen good by all his labour, it [is] a gift of God.

14 I have known that all that God doth is to the age, to it nothing is to be added, and from it nothing is to be withdrawn; and God hath wrought that they do fear before Him.

15 What is that which hath been? already it is, and that which [is] to be hath already been, and God requireth that which is pursued.

16 And again, I have seen under the sun the place of judgment--there [is] the wicked; and the place of righteousness--there [is] the wicked.

17 I said in my heart, `The righteous and the wicked doth God judge, for a time [is] to every matter and for every work there.'

18 I said in my heart concerning the matter of the sons of man that God might cleanse them, so as to see that they themselves [are] beasts.

19 For an event [is to] the sons of man, and an event [is to] the beasts, even one event [is] to them; as the death of this, so [is] the death of that; and one spirit [is] to all, and the advantage of man above the beast is nothing, for the whole [is] vanity.

20 The whole are going unto one place, the whole have been from the dust, and the whole are turning back unto the dust.

21 Who knoweth the spirit of the sons of man that is going up on high, and the spirit of the beast that is going down below to the earth?

22 And I have seen that there is nothing better than that man rejoice in his works, for it [is] his portion; for who doth bring him in to look on that which is after him?

Ecclesiastes 4

1 And I have turned, and I see all the oppressions that are done under the sun, and lo, the tear of the oppressed, and they have no comforter; and at the hand of their oppressors [is] power, and they have no comforter.

2 And I am praising the dead who have already died above the living who are yet alive.

3 And better than both of them [is] he who hath not yet been, in that he hath not seen the evil work that hath been done under the sun.

4 And I have seen all the labour, and all the benefit of the work, because for it a man is the envy of his neighbour. Even this [is] vanity and vexation of spirit.

5 The fool is clasping his hands, and eating his own flesh:

6 `Better [is] a handful [with] quietness, than two handfuls [with] labour and vexation of spirit.'

7 And I have turned, and I see a vain thing under the sun:

8 There is one, and there is not a second; even son or brother he hath not, and there is no end to all his labour! His eye also is not satisfied with riches, and [he saith not], `For whom am I labouring and bereaving my soul of good?' Thisalso is vanity, it is a sad travail.

9 The two [are] better than the one, in that they have a good reward by their labour.

10 For if they fall, the one raiseth up his companion, but woe to the one who falleth and there is not a second to raise him up!

11 Also, if two lie down, then they have heat, but how hath one heat?

12 And if the one strengthen himself, the two stand against him; and the threefold cord is not hastily broken.

13 Better is a poor and wise youth than an old and foolish king, who hath not known to be warned any more.

14 For from a house of prisoners he hath come out to reign, for even in his own kingdom he hath been poor.

15 I have seen all the living, who are walking under the sun, with the second youth who doth stand in his place;

16 there is no end to all the people, to all who were before them; also, the latter rejoice not in him. Surely this also is vanity and vexation of spirit.

Ecclesiastes 5

1 Keep thy feet when thou goest unto a house of God, and draw near to hear rather than to give of fools the sacrifice, for they do not know they do evil.

2 Cause not thy mouth to hasten, and let not thy heart hasten to bring out a word before God, for God is in the heavens, and thou on the earth, therefore let thy words be few.

3 For the dream hath come by abundance of business, and the voice of a fool by abundance of words.

4 When thou vowest a vow to God, delay not to complete it, for there is no pleasure in fools; that which thou vowest--complete.

5 Better that thou do not vow, than that thou dost vow and dost not complete.

6 Suffer not thy mouth to cause thy flesh to sin, nor say before the messenger, that `it [is] an error,' why is God wroth because of thy voice, and hath destroyed the work of thy hands?

7 For, in the abundance of dreams both vanities and words abound; but fear thou God.

8 If oppression of the poor, and violent taking away of judgment and righteousness thou seest in a province, do not marvel at the matter, for a higher than the high is observing, and high ones [are] over them.

9 And the abundance of a land is for all. A king for a field is served.

10 Whoso is loving silver is not satisfied [with] silver, nor he who is in love with stores [with] increase. Even this [is] vanity.

11 In the multiplying of good have its consumers been multiplied, and what benefit [is] to its possessor except the sight of his eyes?

12 Sweet [is] the sleep of the labourer whether he eat little or much; and the sufficiency of the wealthy is not suffering him to sleep.

13 There is a painful evil I have seen under the sun: wealth kept for its possessor, for his evil.

14 And that wealth hath been lost in an evil business, and he hath begotten a son and there is nothing in his hand!

15 As he came out from the belly of his mother, naked he turneth back to go as he came, and he taketh not away anything of his labour, that doth go in his hand.

16 And this also [is] a painful evil, just as he came, so he goeth, and what advantage [is] to him who laboureth for wind?

17 Also all his days in darkness he consumeth, and sadness, and wrath, and sickness abound.

18 Lo, that which I have seen: [It is] good, because beautiful, to eat, and to drink, and to see good in all one's labour that he laboureth at under the sun, the number of the days of his life that God hath given to him, for it [is] his portion.

19 Every man also to whom God hath given wealth and riches, and hath given him power to eat of it, and to accept his portion, and to rejoice in his labour, this is a gift of God.

20 For he doth not much remember the days of his life, for God is answering through the joy of his heart.

Ecclesiastes 6

1 There is an evil that I have seen under the sun, and it [is] great on man:

2 A man to whom God giveth wealth, and riches, and honour, and there is no lack to his soul of all that he desireth, and God giveth him not power to eat of it, but a stranger eateth it; this [is] vanity, and it [is] an evil disease.

3 If a man doth beget a hundred, and live many years, and is great, because they are the days of his years, and his soul is not satisfied from the goodness, and also he hath not had a grave, I have said, `Better than he [is] the untimely birth.'

4 For in vanity he came in, and in darkness he goeth, and in darkness his name is covered,

5 Even the sun he hath not seen nor known, more rest hath this than that.

6 And though he had lived a thousand years twice over, yet good he hath not seen; to the same place doth not every one go?

7 All the labour of man [is] for his mouth, and yet the soul is not filled.

8 For what advantage [is] to the wise above the fool? What to the poor who knoweth to walk before the living?

9 Better [is] the sight of the eyes than the going of the soul. This also [is] vanity and vexation of spirit.

10 What [is] that which hath been? already is its name called, and it is known that it [is] man, and he is not able to contend with him who is stronger than he.

11 For there are many things multiplying vanity; what advantage [is] to man?

12 For who knoweth what [is] good for a man in life, the number of the days of the life of his vanity, and he maketh them as a shadow? for who declareth to man what is after him under the sun?

Ecclesiastes 7

1 Better [is] a name than good perfume, And the day of death than the day of birth.

2 Better to go unto a house of mourning, Than to go unto a house of banqueting, For that is the end of all men, And the living layeth [it] unto his heart.

3 Better [is] sorrow than laughter, For by the sadness of the face the heart becometh better.

4 The heart of the wise [is] in a house of mourning, And the heart of fools in a house of mirth.

5 Better to hear a rebuke of a wise man, Than [for] a man to hear a song of fools,

6 For as the noise of thorns under the pot, So [is] the laughter of a fool, even this [is] vanity.

7 Surely oppression maketh the wise mad, And a gift destroyeth the heart.

8 Better [is] the latter end of a thing than its beginning, Better [is] the patient of spirit, than the haughty of spirit.

9 Be not hasty in thy spirit to be angry, For anger in the bosom of fools resteth.

10 Say not thou, `What was it, That the former days were better than these?' For thou hast not asked wisely of this.

11 Wisdom [is] good with an inheritance, And an advantage [it is] to those beholding the sun.

12 For wisdom [is] a defense, money [is] a defence, And the advantage of the knowledge of wisdom [is], She reviveth her possessors.

13 See the work of God, For who is able to make straight that which He made crooked?

14 In a day of prosperity be in gladness, And in a day of evil consider. Also this over-against that hath God made, To the intent that man doth not find anything after him.

15 The whole I have considered in the days of my vanity. There is a righteous one perishing in his righteousness, and there is a wrong-doer prolonging [himself] in his wrong.

16 Be not over-righteous, nor show thyself too wise, why art thou desolate?

17 Do not much wrong, neither be thou a fool, why dost thou die within thy time?

18 [It is] good that thou dost lay hold on this, and also, from that withdrawest not thy hand, for whoso is fearing God goeth out with them all.

19 The wisdom giveth strength to a wise man, more than wealth the rulers who have been in a city.

20 Because there is not a righteous man on earth that doth good and sinneth not.

21 Also to all the words that they speak give not thy heart, that thou hear not thy servant reviling thee.

22 For many times also hath thy heart known that thou thyself also hast reviled others.

23 All this I have tried by wisdom; I have said, `I am wise,' and it [is] far from me.

24 Far off [is] that which hath been, and deep, deep, who doth find it?

25 I have turned round, also my heart, to know and to search, and to seek out wisdom, and reason, and to know the wrong of folly, and of foolishness the madness.

26 And I am finding more bitter than death, the woman whose heart [is] nets and snares, her hands [are] bands; the good before God escapeth from her, but the sinner is captured by her.

27 See, this I have found, said the Preacher, one to one, to find out the reason

28 (that still my soul had sought, and I had not found), One man, a teacher, I have found, and a woman among all these I have not found.

29 See, this alone I have found, that God made man upright, and they--they have sought out many devices.

Ecclesiastes 8

1 Who [is] as the wise? and who knoweth the interpretation of a thing? The wisdom of man causeth his face to shine, and the hardness of his face is changed.

2 I pray thee, the commandment of a king keep, even for the sake of the oath of God.

3 Be not troubled at his presence, thou mayest go, stand not in an evil thing, for all that he pleaseth he doth.

4 Where the word of a king [is] power [is], and who saith to him, `What dost thou?'

5 Whoso is keeping a command knoweth no evil thing, and time and judgment the heart of the wise knoweth.

6 For to every delight there is a time and a judgment, for the misfortune of man is great upon him.

7 For he knoweth not that which shall be, for when it shall be who declareth to him?

8 There is no man ruling over the spirit to restrain the spirit, and there is no authority over the day of death, and there is no discharge in battle, and wickedness delivereth not its possessors.

9 All this I have seen so as to give my heart to every work that hath been done under the sun; a time that man hath ruled over man to his own evil.

10 And so I have seen the wicked buried, and they went in, even from the Holy Place they go, and they are forgotten in the city whether they had so done. This also [is] vanity.

11 Because sentence hath not been done [on] an evil work speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of man is full within them to do evil.

12 Though a sinner is doing evil a hundred [times], and prolonging [himself] for it, surely also I know that there is good to those fearing God, who fear before Him.

13 And good is not to the wicked, and he doth not prolong days as a shadow, because he is not fearing before God.

14 There is a vanity that hath been done upon the earth, that there are righteous ones unto whom it is coming according to the work of the wicked, and there are wicked ones unto whom it is coming according to the work of the righteous. I have said that this also [is] vanity.

15 And I have praised mirth because there is no good to man under the sun except to eat and to drink, and to rejoice, and it remaineth with him of his labour the days of his life that God hath given to him under the sun.

16 When I gave my heart to know wisdom and to see the business that hath been done on the earth, (for there is also a spectator in whose eyes sleep is not by day and by night),

17 then I considered all the work of God, that man is not able to find out the work that hath been done under the sun, because though man labour to seek, yet he doth not find; and even though the wise man speak of knowing he is not able tofind.

Ecclesiastes 9

1 But all this I have laid unto my heart, so as to clear up the whole of this, that the righteous and the wise, and their works, [are] in the hand of God, neither love nor hatred doth man know, the whole [is] before them.

2 The whole [is] as to the whole; one event is to the righteous and to the wicked, to the good, and to the clean, and to the unclean, and to him who is sacrificing, and to him who is not sacrificing; as [is] the good, so [is] the sinner, he who is swearing as he who is fearing an oath.

3 This [is] an evil among all that hath been done under the sun, that one event [is] to all, and also the heart of the sons of man is full of evil, and madness [is] in their heart during their life, and after it--unto the dead.

4 But [to] him who is joined unto all the living there is confidence, for to a living dog it [is] better than to the dead lion.

5 For the living know that they die, and the dead know not anything, and there is no more to them a reward, for their remembrance hath been forgotten.

6 Their love also, their hatred also, their envy also, hath already perished, and they have no more a portion to the age in all that hath been done under the sun.

7 Go, eat with joy thy bread, and drink with a glad heart thy wine, for already hath God been pleased with thy works.

8 At all times let thy garments be white, and let not perfume be lacking on thy head.

9 See life with the wife whom thou hast loved, all the days of the life of thy vanity, that He hath given to thee under the sun, all the days of thy vanity, for it [is] thy portion in life, even of thy labour that thou art labouring at under the sun.

10 All that thy hand findeth to do, with thy power do, for there is no work, and device, and knowledge, and wisdom in Sheol whither thou art going.

11 I have turned so as to see under the sun, that not to the swift [is] the race, nor to the mighty the battle, nor even to the wise bread, nor even to the intelligent wealth, nor even to the skilful grace, for time and chance happen withthem all.

12 For even man knoweth not his time; as fish that are taken hold of by an evil net, and as birds that are taken hold of by a snare, like these [are] the sons of man snared at an evil time, when it falleth upon them suddenly.

13 This also I have seen: wisdom under the sun, and it is great to me.

14 A little city, and few men in it, and a great king hath come unto it, and hath surrounded it, and hath built against it great bulwarks;

15 and there hath been found in it a poor wise man, and he hath delivered the city by his wisdom, and men have not remembered that poor man!

16 And I said, `Better [is] wisdom than might, and the wisdom of the poor is despised, and his words are not heard.' --

17 The words of the wise in quiet are heard, More than the cry of a ruler over fools.

18 Better [is] wisdom than weapons of conflict, And one sinner destroyeth much good!

Ecclesiastes 10

1 Dead flies cause a perfumer's perfume To send forth a stink; The precious by reason of wisdom--By reason of honour--a little folly!

2 The heart of the wise [is] at his right hand, And the heart of a fool at his left.

3 And also, when he that is a fool Is walking in the way, his heart is lacking, And he hath said to every one, `He [is] a fool.'

4 If the spirit of the ruler go up against thee, Thy place leave not, For yielding quieteth great sinners.

5 There is an evil I have seen under the sun, As an error that goeth out from the ruler,

6 He hath set the fool in many high places, And the rich in a low place do sit.

7 I have seen servants on horses, And princes walking as servants on the earth.

8 Whoso is digging a pit falleth into it, And whoso is breaking a hedge, a serpent biteth him.

9 Whoso is removing stones is grieved by them, Whoso is cleaving trees endangered by them.

10 If the iron hath been blunt, And he the face hath not sharpened, Then doth he increase strength, And wisdom [is] advantageous to make right.

11 If the serpent biteth without enchantment, Then there is no advantage to a master of the tongue.

12 Words of the mouth of the wise [are] gracious, And the lips of a fool swallow him up.

13 The beginning of the words of his mouth [is] folly, And the latter end of his mouth [Is] mischievous madness.

14 And the fool multiplieth words: `Man knoweth not that which is, And that which is after him, who doth declare to him?'

15 The labour of the foolish wearieth him, In that he hath not known to go unto the city.

16 Woe to thee, O land, when thy king [is] a youth, And thy princes do eat in the morning.

17 Happy art thou, O land, When thy king [is] a son of freemen, And thy princes do eat in due season, For might, and not for drunkenness.

18 By slothfulness is the wall brought low, And by idleness of the hands doth the house drop.

19 For mirth they are making a feast, And wine maketh life joyful, And the silver answereth with all.

20 Even in thy mind a king revile not, And in the inner parts of thy bed-chamber Revile not the rich: For a fowl of the heavens causeth the voice to go, And a possessor of wings declareth the word.

Ecclesiastes 11

1 Send forth thy bread on the face of the waters, For in the multitude of the days thou dost find it.

2 Give a portion to seven, and even to eight, For thou knowest not what evil is on the earth.

3 If the thick clouds are full of rain, On the earth they empty [themselves]; And if a tree doth fall in the south or to the north, The place where the tree falleth, there it is.

4 Whoso is observing the wind soweth not, And whoso is looking on the thick clouds reapeth not.

5 As thou knowest not what [is] the way of the spirit, How--bones in the womb of the full one, So thou knowest not the work of God who maketh the whole.

6 In the morning sow thy seed, And at even withdraw not thy hand, For thou knowest not which is right, this or that, Or whether both of them alike [are] good.

7 Sweet also [is] the light, And good for the eyes to see the sun.

8 But, if man liveth many years, In all of them let him rejoice, And remember the days of darkness, For they are many! all that is coming [is] vanity.

9 Rejoice, O young man, in thy childhood, And let thy heart gladden thee in days of thy youth, And walk in the ways of thy heart, And in the sight of thine eyes, And know thou that for all these, Doth God bring thee into judgment.

10 And turn aside anger from thy heart, And cause evil to pass from thy flesh, For the childhood and the age [are] vanity!

Ecclesiastes 12

1 Remember also thy Creators in days of thy youth, While that the evil days come not, Nor the years have arrived, that thou sayest, `I have no pleasure in them.'

2 While that the sun is not darkened, and the light, And the moon, and the stars, And the thick clouds returned after the rain.

3 In the day that keepers of the house tremble, And men of strength have bowed themselves, And grinders have ceased, because they have become few. And those looking out at the windows have become dim,

4 And doors have been shut in the street. When the noise of the grinding is low, And [one] riseth at the voice of the bird, And all daughters of song are bowed down.

5 Also of that which is high they are afraid, And of the low places in the way, And the almond-tree is despised, And the grasshopper is become a burden, And want is increased, For man is going unto his home age-during, And the mourners have gone round through the street.

6 While that the silver cord is not removed, And the golden bowl broken, And the pitcher broken by the fountain, And the wheel broken at the well.

7 And the dust returneth to the earth as it was, And the spirit returneth to God who gave it.

8 Vanity of vanities, said the preacher, the whole [is] vanity.

9 And further, because the preacher was wise, he still taught the people knowledge, and gave ear, and sought out--he made right many similes.

10 The preacher sought to find out pleasing words, and, written [by] the upright, words of truth.

11 Words of the wise [are] as goads, and as fences planted [by] the masters of collections, they have been given by one shepherd.

12 And further, from these, my son, be warned; the making of many books hath no end, and much study [is] a weariness of the flesh.

13 The end of the whole matter let us hear: --`Fear God, and keep His commands, for this [is] the whole of man.

14 For every work doth God bring into judgment, with every hidden thing, whether good or bad.'

Song of Solomon 1

1 The Song of Songs, that [is] Solomon's.

2 Let him kiss me with kisses of his mouth, For better [are] thy loves than wine.

3 For fragrance [are] thy perfumes good. Perfume emptied out--thy name, Therefore have virgins loved thee!

4 Draw me: after thee we run, The king hath brought me into his inner chambers, We do joy and rejoice in thee, We mention thy loves more than wine, Uprightly they have loved thee!

5 Dark [am] I, and comely, daughters of Jerusalem, As tents of Kedar, as curtains of Solomon.

6 Fear me not, because I [am] very dark, Because the sun hath scorched me, The sons of my mother were angry with me, They made me keeper of the vineyards, My vineyard-- my own--I have not kept.

7 Declare to me, thou whom my soul hath loved, Where thou delightest, Where thou liest down at noon, For why am I as one veiled, By the ranks of thy companions?

8 If thou knowest not, O fair among women, Get thee forth by the traces of the flock, And feed thy kids by the shepherds' dwellings!

9 To my joyous one in chariots of Pharaoh, I have compared thee, my friend,

10 Comely have been thy cheeks with garlands, Thy neck with chains.

11 Garlands of gold we do make for thee, With studs of silver!

12 While the king [is] in his circle, My spikenard hath given its fragrance.

13 A bundle of myrrh [is] my beloved to me, Between my breasts it lodgeth.

14 A cluster of cypress [is] my beloved to me, In the vineyards of En-Gedi!

15 Lo, thou [art] fair, my friend, Lo, thou [art] fair, thine eyes [are] doves!

16 Lo, thou [art] fair, my love, yea, pleasant, Yea, our couch [is] green,

17 The beams of our houses [are] cedars, Our rafters [are] firs, I [am] a rose of Sharon, a lily of the valleys!

Song of Solomon 2

1 As a lily among the thorns,

2 So [is] my friend among the daughters!

3 As a citron among trees of the forest, So [is] my beloved among the sons, In his shade I delighted, and sat down, And his fruit [is] sweet to my palate.

4 He hath brought me in unto a house of wine, And his banner over me [is] love,

5 Sustain me with grape-cakes, Support me with citrons, for I [am] sick with love.

6 His left hand [is] under my head, And his right doth embrace me.

7 I have adjured you, daughters of Jerusalem, By the roes or by the hinds of the field, Stir not up nor wake the love till she please!

8 The voice of my beloved! lo, this--he is coming, Leaping on the mountains, skipping on the hills.

9 My beloved [is] like to a roe, Or to a young one of the harts. Lo, this--he is standing behind our wall, Looking from the windows, Blooming from the lattice.

10 My beloved hath answered and said to me, `Rise up, my friend, my fair one, and come away,

11 For lo, the winter hath passed by, The rain hath passed away--it hath gone.

12 The flowers have appeared in the earth, The time of the singing hath come, And the voice of the turtle was heard in our land,

13 The fig-tree hath ripened her green figs, And the sweet-smelling vines have given forth fragrance, Rise, come, my friend, my fair one, yea, come away.

14 My dove, in clefts of the rock, In a secret place of the ascent, Cause me to see thine appearance, Cause me to hear thy voice, For thy voice [is] sweet, and thy appearance comely.

15 Seize ye for us foxes, Little foxes--destroyers of vineyards, Even our sweetsmelling vineyards.

16 My beloved [is] mine, and I [am] his, Who is delighting among the lilies,

17 Till the day doth break forth, And the shadows have fled away, Turn, be like, my beloved, To a roe, or to a young one of the harts, On the mountains of separation!

Song of Solomon 3

1 On my couch by night, I sought him whom my soul hath loved; I sought him, and I found him not!

2 --Pray, let me rise, and go round the city, In the streets and in the broad places, I seek him whom my soul hath loved! --I sought him, and I found him not.

3 The watchmen have found me, (Who are going round about the city), `Him whom my soul have loved saw ye?'

4 But a little I passed on from them, Till I found him whom my soul hath loved! I seized him, and let him not go, Till I brought him in unto the house of my mother--And the chamber of her that conceived me.

5 I have adjured you, daughters of Jerusalem, By the roes or by the hinds of the field, Stir not up nor wake the love till she please!

6 Who [is] this coming up from the wilderness, Like palm-trees of smoke, Perfumed [with] myrrh and frankincense, From every powder of the merchant?

7 Lo, his couch, that [is] Solomon's, Sixty mighty ones [are] around it, Of the mighty of Israel,

8 All of them holding sword, taught of battle, Each his sword by his thigh, for fear at night.

9 A palanquin king Solomon made for himself, Of the wood of Lebanon,

10 Its pillars he made of silver, Its bottom of gold, its seat of purple, Its midst lined [with] love, By the daughters of Jerusalem.

11 Go forth, and look, ye daughters of Zion, On king Solomon, with the crown, With which his mother crowned him, In the day of his espousals, And in the day of the joy of his heart!

Song of Solomon 4

1 Lo, thou [art] fair, my friend, lo, thou [art] fair, Thine eyes [are] doves behind thy veil, Thy hair as a row of the goats That have shone from mount Gilead,

2 Thy teeth as a row of the shorn ones That have come up from the washing, For all of them are forming twins, And a bereaved one is not among them.

3 As a thread of scarlet [are] thy lips, And thy speech [is] comely, As the work of the pomegranate [is] thy temple behind thy veil,

4 As the tower of David [is] thy neck, built for an armoury, The chief of the shields are hung on it, All shields of the mighty.

5 Thy two breasts [are] as two fawns, Twins of a roe, that are feeding among lilies.

6 Till the day doth break forth, And the shadows have fled away, I will get me unto the mountain of myrrh, And unto the hill of frankincense.

7 Thou [art] all fair, my friend, And a blemish there is not in thee. Come from Lebanon, O spouse,

8 Come from Lebanon, come thou in. Look from the top of Amana, From the top of Shenir and Hermon, From the habitations of lions, From the mountains of leopards.

9 Thou hast emboldened me, my sister-spouse, Emboldened me with one of thine eyes, With one chain of thy neck.

10 How wonderful have been thy loves, my sister-spouse, How much better have been thy loves than wine, And the fragrance of thy perfumes than all spices.

11 Thy lips drop honey, O spouse, Honey and milk [are] under thy tongue, And the fragrance of thy garments [Is] as the fragrance of Lebanon.

12 A garden shut up [is] my sister-spouse, A spring shut up--a fountain sealed.

13 Thy shoots a paradise of pomegranates, With precious fruits,

14 Cypresses with nard--nard and saffron, Cane and cinnamon, With all trees of frankincense, Myrrh and aloes, with all chief spices.

15 A fount of gardens, a well of living waters, And flowings from Lebanon!

16 Awake, O north wind, and come, O south, Cause my garden to breathe forth, its spices let flow, Let my beloved come to his garden, And eat its pleasant fruits!

Song of Solomon 5

1 I have come in to my garden, my sister-spouse, I have plucked my myrrh with my spice, I have eaten my comb with my honey, I have drunk my wine with my milk. Eat, O friends, drink, Yea, drink abundantly, O beloved ones!

2 I am sleeping, but my heart waketh: The sound of my beloved knocking! `Open to me, my sister, my friend, My dove, my perfect one, For my head is filled [with] dew, My locks [with] drops of the night.'

3 I have put off my coat, how do I put it on? I have washed my feet, how do I defile them?

4 My beloved sent his hand from the net-work, And my bowels were moved for him.

5 I rose to open to my beloved, And my hands dropped myrrh, Yea, my fingers flowing myrrh, On the handles of the lock.

6 I opened to my beloved, But my beloved withdrew--he passed on, My soul went forth when he spake, I sought him, and found him not. I called him, and he answered me not.

7 The watchmen who go round about the city, Found me, smote me, wounded me, Keepers of the walls lifted up my veil from off me.

8 I have adjured you, daughters of Jerusalem, If ye find my beloved--What do ye tell him? that I [am] sick with love!

9 What [is] thy beloved above [any] beloved, O fair among women? What [is] thy beloved above [any] beloved, That thus thou hast adjured us?

10 My beloved [is] clear and ruddy, Conspicuous above a myriad!

11 His head [is] pure gold--fine gold, His locks flowing, dark as a raven,

12 His eyes as doves by streams of water, Washing in milk, sitting in fulness.

13 His cheeks as a bed of the spice, towers of perfumes, His lips [are] lilies, dropping flowing myrrh,

14 His hands rings of gold, set with beryl, His heart bright ivory, covered with sapphires,

15 His limbs pillars of marble, Founded on sockets of fine gold, His appearance as Lebanon, choice as the cedars.

16 His mouth is sweetness--and all of him desirable, This [is] my beloved, and this my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem!

Song of Solomon 6

1 Whither hath thy beloved gone, O fair among women? Whither hath thy beloved turned, And we seek him with thee?

2 My beloved went down to his garden, To the beds of the spice, To delight himself in the gardens, and to gather lilies.

3 I [am] my beloved's, and my beloved [is] mine, Who is delighting himself among the lilies.

4 Fair [art] thou, my friend, as Tirzah, Comely as Jerusalem, Awe-inspiring as bannered hosts.

5 Turn round thine eyes from before me, Because they have made me proud. Thy hair [is] as a row of the goats, That have shone from Gilead,

6 Thy teeth as a row of the lambs, That have come up from the washing, Because all of them are forming twins, And a bereaved one is not among them.

7 As the work of the pomegranate [is] thy temple behind thy veil.

8 Sixty are queens, and eighty concubines, And virgins without number.

9 One is my dove, my perfect one, One she [is] of her mother, The choice one she [is] of her that bare her, Daughters saw, and pronounce her happy, Queens and concubines, and they praise her.

10 `Who [is] this that is looking forth as morning, Fair as the moon--clear as the sun, Awe-inspiring as bannered hosts?'

11 Unto a garden of nuts I went down, To look on the buds of the valley, To see whither the vine had flourished, The pomegranates had blossomed--

12 I knew not my soul, It made me--chariots of my people Nadib.

13 Return, return, O Shulammith! Return, return, and we look upon thee. What do ye see in Shulammith?

Song of Solomon 7

1 As the chorus of `Mahanaim.' How beautiful were thy feet with sandals, O daughter of Nadib. The turnings of thy sides [are] as ornaments, Work of the hands of an artificer.

2 Thy waist [is] a basin of roundness, It lacketh not the mixture, Thy body a heap of wheat, fenced with lilies,

3 Thy two breasts as two young ones, twins of a roe,

4 Thy neck as a tower of the ivory, Thine eyes pools in Heshbon, near the gate of Bath-Rabbim, Thy face as a tower of Lebanon looking to Damascus,

5 Thy head upon thee as Carmel, And the locks of thy head as purple, The king is bound with the flowings!

6 How fair and how pleasant hast thou been, O love, in delights.

7 This thy stature hath been like to a palm, And thy breasts to clusters.

8 I said, `Let me go up on the palm, Let me lay hold on its boughs, Yea, let thy breasts be, I pray thee, as clusters of the vine, And the fragrance of thy face as citrons,

9 And thy palate as the good wine--'Flowing to my beloved in uprightness, Strengthening the lips of the aged!

10 I [am] my beloved's, and on me [is] his desire.

11 Come, my beloved, we go forth to the field,

12 We lodge in the villages, we go early to the vineyards, We see if the vine hath flourished, The sweet smelling-flower hath opened. The pomegranates have blossomed, There do I give to thee my loves;

13 The mandrakes have given fragrance, And at our openings all pleasant things, New, yea, old, my beloved, I laid up for thee!

Song of Solomon 8

1 Who doth make thee as a brother to me, Sucking the breasts of my mother? I find thee without, I kiss thee, Yea, they do not despise me,

2 I lead thee, I bring thee in unto my mother's house, She doth teach me, I cause thee to drink of the perfumed wine, Of the juice of my pomegranate,

3 His left hand [is] under my head, And his right doth embrace me.

4 I have adjured you, daughters of Jerusalem, How ye stir up, And how ye wake the love till she please!

5 Who [is] this coming from the wilderness, Hasting herself for her beloved? Under the citron-tree I have waked thee, There did thy mother pledge thee, There she gave a pledge [that] bare thee.

6 Set me as a seal on thy heart, as a seal on thine arm, For strong as death is love, Sharp as Sheol is jealousy, Its burnings [are] burnings of fire, a flame of Jah!

7 Many waters are not able to quench the love, And floods do not wash it away. If one give all the wealth of his house for love, Treading down--they tread upon it.

8 We have a little sister, and breasts she hath not, What do we do for our sister, In the day that it is told of her?

9 If she is a wall, we build by her a palace of silver. And if she is a door, We fashion by her board-work of cedar.

10 I [am] a wall, and my breasts as towers, Then I have been in his eyes as one finding peace.

11 Solomon hath a vineyard in Baal-Hamon, He hath given the vineyard to keepers, Each bringeth for its fruit a thousand silverlings;

12 My vineyard--my own--is before me, The thousand [is] for thee, O Solomon. And the two hundred for those keeping its fruit. O dweller in gardens!

13 The companions are attending to thy voice, Cause me to hear. Flee, my beloved, and be like to a roe,

14 Or to a young one of the harts on mountains of spices!

Isaiah 1

1 The Visions of Isaiah son of Amoz, that he hath seen concerning Judah and Jerusalem, in the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, kings of Judah.

2 Hear, O heavens, and give ear, O earth, For Jehovah hath spoken: Sons I have nourished and brought up, And they--they transgressed against Me.

3 An ox hath known its owner, And an ass the crib of its master, Israel hath not known, My people hath not understood.

4 Ah, sinning nation, a people heavy [with] iniquity, A seed of evil doers, sons-- corrupters! They have forsaken Jehovah, They have despised the Holy One of Israel, They have gone away backward.

5 Wherefore are ye stricken any more? Ye do add apostasy! Every head is become diseased, and every heart [is] sick.

6 From the sole of the foot--unto the head, There is no soundness in it, Wound, and bruise, and fresh smiting! They have not been closed nor bound, Nor have they softened with ointment.

7 Your land [is] a desolation, your cities burnt with fire, Your ground, before you strangers are consuming it, And a desolation as overthrown by strangers!

8 And left hath been the daughter of Zion, As a booth in a vineyard, As a lodge in a place of cucumbers--as a city besieged.

9 Unless Jehovah of Hosts had left to us a remnant, Shortly--as Sodom we had been, To Gomorrah we had been like!

10 Hear the word of Jehovah, ye rulers of Sodom, Give ear to the law of our God, ye people of Gomorrah,

11 `Why to Me the abundance of your sacrifices? saith Jehovah, I have been satiated [with] burnt-offerings of rams, And fat of fatlings; And blood of bullocks, and lambs, And he-goats I have not desired.

12 When ye come in to appear before Me, Who hath required this of your hand, To trample My courts?

13 Add not to bring in a vain present, Incense--an abomination it [is] to Me, New moon, and sabbath, calling of convocation! Rendure not iniquity--and a restraint!

14 Your new moons and your set seasons hath My soul hated, They have been upon me for a burden, I have been weary of bearing.

15 And in your spreading forth your hands, I hide mine eyes from you, Also when ye increase prayer, I do not hear, Your hands of blood have been full.

16 Wash ye, make ye pure, Turn aside the evil of your doings, from before Mine eyes, Cease to do evil, learn to do good.

17 Seek judgment, make happy the oppressed, Judge the fatherless, strive [for] the widow.

18 Come, I pray you, and we reason, saith Jehovah, If your sins are as scarlet, as snow they shall be white, If they are red as crimson, as wool they shall be!

19 If ye are willing, and have hearkened, The good of the land ye consume,

20 And if ye refuse, and have rebelled, [By] the sword ye are consumed, For the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken.

21 How hath a faithful city become a harlot? I have filled it [with] judgment, Righteousness lodgeth in it--now murderers.

22 Thy silver hath become dross, Thy drink polluted with water.

23 Thy princes [are] apostates, and companions of thieves, Every one loving a bribe, and pursuing rewards, The fatherless they judge not, And the plea of the widow cometh not to them.

24 Therefore--the affirmation of the Lord--Jehovah of Hosts, the Mighty One of Israel: Ah, I am eased of Mine adversaries, And I am avenged of Mine enemies,

25 And I turn back My hand upon thee, And I refine as purity thy dross, And I turn aside all thy tin,

26 And I give back thy judges as at the first, And thy counsellors as in the beginning, After this thou art called, `A city of righteousness--a faithful city.'

27 Zion in judgment is redeemed, And her captivity in righteousness.

28 And the destruction of transgressors and sinners [is] together, And those forsaking Jehovah are consumed.

29 For [men] are ashamed because of the oaks That ye have desired, And ye are confounded because of the gardens That ye have chosen.

30 For ye are as an oak whose leaf is fading, And as a garden that hath no water.

31 And the strong hath been for tow, And his work for a spark, And burned have both of them together, And there is none quenching!

Isaiah 2

1 The thing that Isaiah son of Amoz hath seen concerning Judah and Jerusalem:

2 And it hath come to pass, In the latter end of the days, Established is the mount of Jehovah's house, Above the top of the mounts, And it hath been lifted up above the heights, And flowed unto it have all the nations.

3 And gone have many peoples and said, `Come, and we go up unto the mount of Jehovah, Unto the house of the God of Jacob, And He doth teach us of His ways, And we walk in His paths, For from Zion goeth forth a law, And a word of Jehovah from Jerusalem.

4 And He hath judged between the nations, And hath given a decision to many peoples, And they have beat their swords to ploughshares, And their spears to pruning-hooks, Nation doth not lift up sword unto nation, Nor do they learn any more--war.

5 O house of Jacob, come, And we walk in the light of Jehovah.'

6 For Thou hast left Thy people, the house of Jacob. For they have been filled from the east, And [are] sorcerers like the Philistines, And with the children of strangers strike hands.

7 And its land is full of silver and gold, And there is no end to its treasures, And its land is full of horses, And there is no end to its chariots,

8 And its land is full of idols, To the work of its hands it boweth itself, To that which its fingers have made,

9 And the low boweth down, and the high is humbled, And Thou acceptest them not.

10 Enter into a rock, and be hidden in dust, Because of the fear of Jehovah, And because of the honour of His excellency.

11 The haughty eyes of man have been humbled, And bowed down hath been the loftiness of men, And set on high hath Jehovah alone been in that day.

12 For a day [is] to Jehovah of Hosts, For every proud and high one, And for every lifted up and low one,

13 And for all cedars of Lebanon, The high and the exalted ones, And for all oaks of Bashan,

14 And for all the high mountains, And for all the exalted heights,

15 And for every high tower, And for every fenced wall,

16 And for all ships of Tarshish, And for all desirable pictures.

17 And bowed down hath been the haughtiness of man, And humbled the loftiness of men, And set on high hath Jehovah alone been in that day.

18 And the idols--they completely pass away.

19 And [men] have entered into caverns of rocks, And into caves of dust, Because of the fear of Jehovah, And because of the honour of His excellency, In His rising to terrify the earth.

20 In that day doth man cast his idols of silver, And his idols of gold, That they have made for him to worship, To moles, and to bats,

21 To enter into cavities of the rocks, And into clefts of the high places, Because of the fear of Jehovah, And because of the honour of His excellency, In His rising to terrify the earth.

22 Cease for you from man, Whose breath [is] in his nostrils, For--in what is he esteemed?

Isaiah 3

1 For, lo, the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, Is turning aside from Jerusalem, And from Judah, stay and staff, Every stay of bread, and every stay of water.

2 Hero and man of war, judge and prophet, And diviner and elder,

3 Head of fifty, and accepted of faces, And counsellor, and the wise of artificers, And the intelligent of charmers.

4 And I have made youths their heads, And sucklings rule over them.

5 And the people hath exacted--man upon man, Even a man on his neighbour, Enlarge themselves do the youths against the aged, And the lightly esteemed against the honoured.

6 When one layeth hold on his brother, [Of] the house of his father, [by] the garment, `Come, a ruler thou art to us, And this ruin [is] under thy hand.'

7 He lifteth up, in that day, saying: `I am not a binder up, And in my house is neither bread nor garment, Ye do not make me a ruler of the people.'

8 For stumbled hath Jerusalem, and Judah hath fallen, For their tongue and their doings [are] against Jehovah, To provoke the eyes of His glory.

9 The appearance of their faces witnessed against them, And their sin, as Sodom, they declared, They have not hidden! Woe to their soul, For they have done to themselves evil.

10 Say ye to the righteous, that [it is] good, Because the fruit of their doings they eat.

11 Woe to the wicked--evil, Because the deed of his hand is done to him.

12 My people--its exactors [are] sucklings, And women have ruled over it. My people-- thy eulogists are causing to err, And the way of thy paths swallowed up.

13 Jehovah hath stood up to plead, And He is standing to judge the peoples.

14 Jehovah into judgment doth enter With elders of His people, and its heads: `And ye, ye have consumed the vineyard, Plunder of the poor [is] in your houses.

15 What--to you? ye bruise My people, And the faces of the poor ye grind.' An affirmation of the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, And Jehovah saith:

16 `Because that daughters of Zion have been haughty, And they walk stretching out the neck, And deceiving [with] the eyes, Walking and mincing they go, And with their feet they make a tinkling,

17 The Lord also hath scabbed The crown of the head of daughters of Zion, And Jehovah their simplicity exposeth.

18 In that day doth the Lord turn aside The beauty of the tinkling ornaments, And of the embroidered works, And of the round tires like moons,

19 Of the drops, and the bracelets, and the mufflers,

20 Of the bonnets, and the ornaments of the legs, And of the bands, And of the perfume boxes, and the amulets,

21 Of the seals, and of the nose-rings,

22 Of the costly apparel, and of the mantles, And of the coverings, and of the purses,

23 Of the mirrors, and of the linen garments, And of the hoods, and of the vails,

24 And it hath been, instead of spice is muck, And instead of a girdle, a rope, And instead of curled work, baldness, And instead of a stomacher a girdle of sackcloth.

25 For instead of glory, thy men by sword do fall, And thy might in battle.

26 And lamented and mourned have her openings, Yea, she hath been emptied, on the earth she sitteth!

Isaiah 5

1 Let me sing, I pray you, for my beloved, A song of my beloved as to his vineyard: My beloved hath a vineyard in a fruitful hill,

2 And he fenceth it, and casteth out its stones, And planteth it [with] a choice vine, And buildeth a tower in its midst, And also a wine press hath hewn out in it, And he waiteth for the yielding of grapes, And it yieldeth bad ones!

3 And now, O inhabitant of Jerusalem, and man of Judah, Judge, I pray you, between me and my vineyard.

4 What--to do still to my vineyard, That I have not done in it! Wherefore, I waited to the yielding of grapes, And it yieldeth bad ones!

5 And now, pray, let me cause you to know, That which I am doing to my vineyard, To turn aside its hedge, And it hath been for consumption, To break down its wall, And it hath been for a treading-place.

6 And I make it a waste, It is not pruned, nor arranged, And gone up have brier and thorn, And on the thick clouds I lay a charge, From raining upon it rain.

7 Because the vineyard of Jehovah of Hosts [Is] the house of Israel, And the man of Judah His pleasant plant, And He waiteth for judgment, and lo, oppression, For righteousness, and lo, a cry.

8 Woe [to] those joining house to house, Field to field they bring near, till there is no place, And ye have been settled by yourselves In the midst of the land!

9 By the weapons of Jehovah of Hosts Do not many houses a desolation become? Great and good without inhabitant!

10 For ten acres of vineyard do yield one bath, And an homer of seed yieldeth an ephah.

11 Woe [to] those rising early in the morning, Strong drink they pursue! Tarrying in twilight, wine inflameth them!

12 And harp, and psaltery, tabret, and pipe, And wine, have been their banquets, And the work of Jehovah they behold not, Yea, the work of His hands they have not seen.

13 Therefore my people removed without knowledge, And its honourable ones are famished, And its multitude dried up of thirst.

14 Therefore hath Sheol enlarged herself, And hath opened her mouth without limit. And gone down hath its honour, and its multitude, And its noise, and its exulting one--into her.

15 And bowed down is the low, and humbled the high, And the eyes of the haughty become low,

16 And Jehovah of Hosts is high in judgment, And the Holy God sanctified in righteousness,

17 And fed have lambs according to their leading, And waste places of the fat ones Do sojourners consume.

18 Woe [to] those drawing out iniquity with cords of vanity, And as [with] thick ropes of the cart--sin.

19 Who are saying, `Let Him hurry, Let Him hasten His work, that we may see, And let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel Draw near and come, and we know.'

20 Woe [to] those saying to evil `good,' And to good `evil,' Putting darkness for light, and light for darkness, Putting bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter.

21 Woe [to] the wise in their own eyes, And--before their own faces--intelligent!

22 Woe [to] the mighty to drink wine, And men of strength to mingle strong drink.

23 Declaring righteous the wicked for a bribe, And the righteousness of the righteous They turn aside from him.

24 Therefore, as a tongue of fire devoureth stubble, And flaming hay falleth, Their root is as muck, And their flower as dust goeth up. Because they have rejected the law of Jehovah of Hosts, And the saying of the Holy One of Israel despised.

25 Therefore hath the anger of Jehovah burned among His people, And He stretcheth out His hand against it, And smiteth it, and the mountains tremble, And their carcase is as filth in the midst of the out-places. With all this His anger did not turn back, And still His hand is stretched out!

26 And He lifted up an ensign to nations afar off, And hissed to it from the end of the earth, And lo, with haste, swift it cometh.

27 There is none weary, nor stumbling in it, It doth not slumber, nor sleep, Nor opened hath been the girdle of its loins, Nor drawn away the latchet of its sandals.

28 Whose arrows [are] sharp, and all its bows bent, Hoofs of its horses as flint have been reckoned, And its wheels as a hurricane!

29 Its roaring [is] like a lioness, It roareth like young lions, And it howleth, and seizeth prey, And carrieth away safely, and there is none delivering.

30 And it howleth against it in that day as the howling of a sea, And it hath looked attentively to the land, And lo, darkness--distress, And light hath been darkened by its abundance!

Isaiah 7

1 And it cometh to pass in the days of Ahaz, son of Jotham, son of Uzziah, king of Judah, gone up hath Rezin king of Aram, and Pekah, son of Remaliah, king of Israel, to Jerusalem, to battle against it, and he is not able to fight against it.

2 And it is declared to the house of David, saying, `Aram hath been led towards Ephraim,' And his heart and the heart of his people is moved, like the moving of trees of a forest by the presence of wind.

3 And Jehovah saith unto Isaiah, `Go forth, I pray thee, to meet Ahaz, thou, and Shear- Jashub thy son, unto the end of the conduit of the upper pool, unto the highway of the fuller's field,

4 and thou hast said unto him: `Take heed, and be quiet, fear not, And let not thy heart be timid, Because of these two tails of smoking brands, For the fierceness of the anger of Rezin and Aram, And the son of Remaliah.

5 Because that Aram counselled against thee evil, Ephraim and the son of Remaliah, saying:

6 We go up into Judah, and we vex it, And we rend it unto ourselves, And we cause a king to reign in its midst--The son of Tabeal.

7 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: It doth not stand, nor shall it be!

8 For the head of Aram [is] Damascus, And the head of Damascus [is] Rezin, And within sixty and five years Is Ephraim broken from [being] a people.

9 And the head of Ephraim [is] Samaria, And the head of Samaria [is] the son of Remaliah. If ye do not give credence, Surely ye are not stedfast.'

10 And Jehovah addeth to speak unto Ahaz, saying:

11 `Ask for thee a sign from Jehovah thy God, Make deep the request, or make [it] high upwards.'

12 And Ahaz saith, `I do not ask nor try Jehovah.'

13 And he saith, `Hear, I pray you, O house of David, Is it a little thing for you to weary men, That ye weary also my God?

14 Therefore the Lord Himself giveth to you a sign, Lo, the Virgin is conceiving, And is bringing forth a son, And hath called his name Immanuel,

15 Butter and honey he doth eat, When he knoweth to refuse evil, and to fix on good.

16 For before the youth doth know To refuse evil, and to fix on good, Forsaken is the land thou art vexed with, because of her two kings.

17 Jehovah bringeth on thee, and on thy people, And on the house of thy father, Days that have not come, Even from the day of the turning aside of Ephraim from Judah, By the king of Asshur.

18 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Jehovah doth hiss for a fly that [is] in the extremity of the brooks of Egypt, And for a bee that [is] in the land of Asshur.

19 And they have come, and rested all of them in the desolate valleys, And in holes of the rocks, and on all the thorns, And on all the commendable things.

20 In that day doth the Lord shave, By a razor that is hired beyond the river, By the king of Asshur, The head, and the hair of the feet, Yea, also the beard it consumeth.

21 And it hath come to pass, in that day, A man keepeth alive a heifer of the herd, And two of the flock,

22 And it hath come to pass, From the abundance of the yielding of milk he eateth butter, For butter and honey doth every one eat Who is left in the heart of the land.

23 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Every place where there are a thousand vines, At a thousand silverlings, Is for briers and for thorns.

24 With arrows and with bow he cometh thither, Because all the land is brier and thorn.

25 And all the hills that with a mattock are kept in order, Thither cometh not the fear of brier and thorn, And it hath been for the sending forth of ox, And for the treading of sheep!'

Isaiah 8

1 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Take to thee a great tablet, and write upon it with a graving tool of man, To haste spoil, enjoy prey.'

2 And I cause faithful witnesses to testify to me, Uriah the priest, and Zechariah son of Jeberechiah.

3 And I draw near unto the prophetess, and she conceiveth, and beareth a son; and Jehovah saith unto me, `Call his name Maher-shalal-hash-baz,

4 for before the youth doth know to cry, My father, and My mother, one taketh away the wealth of Damascus and the spoil of Samaria, before the king of Asshur.'

5 And Jehovah addeth to speak unto me again, saying:

6 `Because that this people hath refused The waters of Shiloah that go softly, And is rejoicing with Rezin and the son of Remaliah,

7 Therefore, lo, the Lord is bringing up on them, The waters of the river, the mighty and the great, (The king of Asshur, and all his glory,) And it hath gone up over all its streams, And hath gone on over all its banks.

8 And it hath passed on into Judah, It hath overflown and passed over, Unto the neck it cometh, And the stretching out of its wings Hath been the fulness of the breadth of thy land, O Emmanu-El!

9 Be friends, O nations, and be broken, And give ear, all ye far off ones of earth, Gird yourselves, and be broken, Gird yourselves, and be broken.

10 Take counsel, and it is broken, Speak a word, and it doth not stand, Because of Emmanu-El!'

11 For thus hath Jehovah spoken unto me with strength of hand, and instructeth me against walking in the way of this people, saying,

12 `Ye do not say, A confederacy, To all to whom this people saith, A confederacy, And its fear ye do not fear, Nor declare fearful.

13 Jehovah of Hosts--Him ye do sanctify, And He [is] your Fear, and He your Dread,

14 And He hath been for a sanctuary, And for a stone of stumbling, and for a rock of falling, To the two houses of Israel, For a gin and for a snare to the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

15 And many among them have stumbled and fallen, And been broken, and snared, and captured.

16 Bind up the testimony, Seal the law among My disciples.

17 And I have waited for Jehovah, Who is hiding His face from the house of Jacob, And I have looked for Him.

18 Lo, I, and the children whom Jehovah hath given to me, [Are] for signs and for wonders in Israel, From Jehovah of Hosts, who is dwelling in Mount Zion.

19 And when they say unto you, `Seek unto those having familiar spirits, And unto wizards, who chatter and mutter, Doth not a people seek unto its God? --For the living unto the dead!

20 To the law and to the testimony! If not, let them say after this manner, `That there is no dawn to it.'

21 --And it hath passed over into it, hardened and hungry, And it hath come to pass, That it is hungry, and hath been wroth, And made light of its king, and of its God, And hath looked upwards.

22 And unto the land it looketh attentively, And lo, adversity and darkness! --Dimness, distress, and thick darkness is driven away, But not the dimness for which she is in distress!

Isaiah 9

1 As the former time made light The land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali, So the latter hath honoured the way of the sea, Beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the nations.

2 The people who are walking in darkness Have seen a great light, Dwellers in a land of death-shade, Light hath shone upon them.

3 Thou hast multiplied the nation, Thou hast made great its joy, They have joyed before Thee as the joy in harvest, As [men] rejoice in their apportioning spoil.

4 Because the yoke of its burden, And the staff of its shoulder, the rod of its exactor, Thou hast broken as [in] the day of Midian.

5 For every battle of a warrior [is] with rushing, and raiment rolled in blood, And it hath been for burning--fuel of fire.

6 For a Child hath been born to us, A Son hath been given to us, And the princely power is on his shoulder, And He doth call his name Wonderful, Counsellor, Mighty God, Father of Eternity, Prince of Peace.

7 To the increase of the princely power, And of peace, there is no end, On the throne of David, and on his kingdom, To establish it, and to support it, In judgment and in righteousness, Henceforth, even unto the age, The zeal of Jehovah of Hostsdoth this.

8 A word hath the Lord sent into Jacob, And it hath fallen in Israel.

9 And the people have known--all of it, Ephraim, and the inhabitant of Samaria, In pride and in greatness of heart, saying,

10 `Bricks have fallen, and hewn work we build, Sycamores have been cut down, and cedars we renew.'

11 And Jehovah setteth the adversaries of Rezin on high above him, And his enemies he joineth together,

12 Aram from before, and Philistia from behind, And they devour Israel with the whole mouth. With all this not turned back hath His anger, And still His hand is stretched out.

13 And the people hath not turned back unto Him who is smiting it, And Jehovah of Hosts they have not sought.

14 And Jehovah cutteth off from Israel head and tail, Branch and reed--the same day,

15 Elder, and accepted of face, he [is] the head, Prophet, teacher of falsehood, he [is] the tail.

16 And the eulogists of this people are causing to err, And its eulogised ones are consumed.

17 Therefore, over its young men the Lord rejoiceth not, And its orphans, and its widows He pitieth not, For every one [is] profane, and an evil doer, And every mouth is speaking folly. With all this not turned back hath His anger, And still Hishand is stretched out.

18 For burned as a fire hath wickedness, Brier and thorn it devoureth, And it kindleth in thickets of the forest, And they lift themselves up, an exaltation of smoke!

19 In the wrath of Jehovah of Hosts Hath the land been consumed, And the people is as fuel of fire; A man on his brother hath no pity,

20 And cutteth down on the right, and hath been hungry, And he devoureth on the left, And they have not been satisfied, Each the flesh of his own arm they devour.

21 Manasseh--Ephraim, and Ephraim--Manasseh, Together they [are] against Judah, With all this not turned back hath His anger. And still His hand is stretched out!

Isaiah 10

1 Woe [to] those decreeing decrees of iniquity, And writers who have prescribed perverseness.

2 To turn aside from judgment the poor, And to take violently away the judgment Of the afflicted of My people, That widows may be their prey, That the fatherless they may spoil.

3 And what do ye at a day of inspection? And at desolation? --from afar it cometh. Near whom do ye flee for help? And where do ye leave your honour?

4 Without Me it hath bowed down In the place of a bound one, And in the place of the slain they fall. With all this not turned back hath His anger, And still His hand is stretched out.

5 Woe [to] Asshur, a rod of Mine anger, And a staff in their hand [is] Mine indignation.

6 Against a profane nation I send him, And concerning a people of My wrath I charge him, To spoil spoil, and to seize prey, And to make it a treading-place as the clay of out places.

7 And he--he thinketh not so, And his heart reckoneth not so, For--to destroy [is] in his heart, And to cut off nations not a few.

8 For he saith, `Are not my princes altogether kings?

9 Is not Calno as Carchemish? Is not Hamath as Arpad? Is not Samaria as Damascus?

10 As my hand hath got to the kingdoms of a worthless thing, and their graven images, [Greater] than Jerusalem and than Samaria,

11 Do I not--as I have done to Samaria, And to her worthless things, So do to Jerusalem and to her grievous things?

12 And it hath come to pass, When the Lord doth fulfil all His work In mount Zion and in Jerusalem, I see concerning the fruit of the greatness Of the heart of the king of Asshur. And concerning the glory of the height of his eyes.

13 For he hath said, `By the power of my hand I have wrought, And by my wisdom, for I have been intelligent, And I remove borders of the peoples, And their chief ones I have spoiled, And I put down as a mighty one the inhabitants,

14 And my hand as to a nest Getteth to the wealth of the peoples, And as a gathering of forsaken eggs All the earth I--I have gathered, And there hath not been one moving wing, Or opening mouth, or whispering.'

15 --Doth the axe glorify itself Against him who is hewing with it? Doth the saw magnify itself Against him who is shaking it? As a rod waving those lifting it up! As a staff lifting up that which is not wood!

16 Therefore doth the Lord, the Lord of Hosts, Send among his fat ones leanness, And under his honour He kindleth a burning As the burning of a fire.

17 And the light of Israel hath been for a fire, And his Holy One for a flame, And it hath burned, and devoured his thorn And his brier in one day.

18 And the honour of his forest, and his fruitful field, From soul even unto flesh He doth consume, And it hath been as the fainting of a standard-bearer.

19 And the rest of the trees of his forest [are] few, And a youth doth write them.

20 And it hath come to pass, in that day, The remnant of Israel, And the escaped of the house of Jacob, Do not add any more to lean on its smiter, And have leant on Jehovah, The Holy One of Israel, in truth.

21 A remnant returneth--a remnant of Jacob, Unto the Mighty God.

22 For though thy people Israel be as the sand of the sea, A remnant doth return of it, A consumption determined, Overflowing [with] righteousness.

23 For a consumption that is determined, The Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, Is making in the midst of all the land.

24 Therefore, thus said the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, `Be not afraid, my people, inhabiting Zion, because of Asshur, With a rod he doth smite thee, And his staff lifteth up against thee, in the way of Egypt.

25 For yet a very little, And the indignation hath been completed, And Mine anger by their wearing out.

26 And awaking for him is Jehovah of Hosts, A scourge like the smiting of Midian at the rock Oreb, And his rod [is] over the sea, And he hath lifted it in the way of Egypt.

27 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Turned is his burden from off thy shoulder, And his yoke from off thy neck, And destroyed hath been the yoke, because of prosperity.

28 He hath come in against Aiath, He hath passed over into Migron, At Michmash he looketh after his vessels.

29 They have gone over the passage, Geba they have made a lodging place, Trembled hath Rama, Gibeah of Saul fled.

30 Cry aloud [with] thy voice, daughter of Gallim, Give attention, Laish! answer her, Anathoth.

31 Fled away hath Madmenah, The inhabitants of the high places have hardened themselves.

32 Yet to-day in Nob to remain, Wave its hand doth the mount of the daughter of Zion, The hill of Jerusalem.

33 Lo, the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, Is lopping a branch with violence, And the high of stature are cut down, And the lofty are become low,

34 And He hath gone round the thickets of the forest with iron, And Lebanon by a mighty one falleth!

Isaiah 11

1 And a rod hath come out from the stock of Jesse, And a branch from his roots is fruitful.

2 Rested on him hath the Spirit of Jehovah, The spirit of wisdom and understanding, The spirit of counsel and might, The spirit of knowledge and fear of Jehovah.

3 To refresh him in the fear of Jehovah, And by the sight of his eyes he judgeth not, Nor by the hearing of his ears decideth.

4 And he hath judged in righteousness the poor, And decided in uprightness for the humble of earth, And hath smitten earth with the rod of his mouth, And with the breath of his lips he putteth the wicked to death.

5 And righteousness hath been the girdle of his loins, And faithfulness--the girdle of his reins.

6 And a wolf hath sojourned with a lamb, And a leopard with a kid doth lie down, And calf, and young lion, and fatling [are] together, And a little youth is leader over them.

7 And cow and bear do feed, Together lie down their young ones, And a lion as an ox eateth straw.

8 And played hath a suckling by the hole of an asp, And on the den of a cockatrice Hath the weaned one put his hand.

9 Evil they do not, nor destroy in all My holy mountain, For full hath been the earth with the knowledge of Jehovah, As the waters are covering the sea.

10 And there hath been, in that day, A root of Jesse that is standing for an ensign of peoples, Unto him do nations seek, And his rest hath been--honour!

11 And it hath come to pass, in that day, The Lord addeth a second time his power, To get the remnant of His people that is left, From Asshur, and from Egypt, And from Pathros, and from Cush, And from Elam, and from Shinar, And from Hamath, andfrom isles of the sea,

12 And He hath lifted up an ensign to nations, And gathereth the driven away of Israel, And the scattered of Judah He assembleth, From the four wings of the earth.

13 And turned aside hath the envy of Ephraim, And the adversaries of Judah are cut off, Ephraim doth not envy Judah, And Judah doth not distress Ephraim.

14 And they have flown on the shoulder of the Philistines westward, Together they spoil the sons of the east, Edom and Moab sending forth their hand, And sons of Ammon obeying them.

15 And Jehovah hath devoted to destruction The tongue of the sea of Egypt, And hath waved His hand over the river, In the terror of his wind, And hath smitten it at the seven streams, And hath caused [men] to tread [it] with shoes.

16 And there hath been a highway, For the remnant of His people that is left, from Asshur, As there was for Israel in the day of his coming up out of the land of Egypt!

Isaiah 13

1 The burden of Babylon that Isaiah son of Amoz hath seen:

2 `On a high mountain lift ye up an ensign, Raise the voice to them, wave the hand, And they go in to the openings of nobles.

3 I have given charge to My sanctified ones, Also I have called My mighty ones for Mine anger, Those rejoicing at Mine excellency.'

4 A voice of a multitude in the mountains, A likeness of a numerous people, A voice of noise from the kingdoms of nations who are gathered, Jehovah of Hosts inspecting a host of battle!

5 They are coming in from a land afar off, From the end of the heavens, Jehovah and the instruments of His indignation, To destroy all the land.

6 Howl ye, for near [is] the day of Jehovah, As destruction from the Mighty it cometh.

7 Therefore, all hands do fail, And every heart of man doth melt.

8 And they have been troubled, Pains and pangs they take, As a travailing woman they are pained, A man at his friend they marvel, The appearance of flames--their faces!

9 Lo, the day of Jehovah doth come, Fierce, with wrath, and heat of anger, To make the land become a desolation, Yea, its sinning ones He destroyeth from it.

10 For the stars of the heavens, and their constellations, Cause not their light to shine, Darkened hath been the sun in its going out, And the moon causeth not its light to come forth.

11 And I have appointed on the world evil, And on the wicked their iniquity, And have caused to cease the excellency of the proud, And the excellency of the terrible I make low.

12 I make man more rare than fine gold, And a common man than pure gold of Ophir.

13 Therefore the heavens I cause to tremble, And the earth doth shake from its place, In the wrath of Jehovah of Hosts, And in a day of the heat of his anger.

14 And it hath been, as a roe driven away, And as a flock that hath no gatherer, Each unto his people--they turn, And each unto his land--they flee.

15 Every one who is found is thrust through, And every one who is added falleth by sword.

16 And their sucklings are dashed to pieces before their eyes, Spoiled are their houses, and their wives lain with.

17 Lo, I am stirring up against them the Medes, Who silver esteem not, And gold--they delight not in it.

18 And bows dash young men to pieces, And the fruit of the womb they pity not, On sons their eye hath no pity.

19 And Babylon, the beauty of kingdoms, The glory, the excellency of the Chaldeans, Hath been as overthrown by God, With Sodom and with Gomorrah.

20 She doth not sit for ever, Nor continueth unto many generations, Nor doth Arab pitch tent there, And shepherds lie not down there.

21 And Ziim have lain down there, And full have been their houses of howlings, And dwelt there have daughters of an ostrich, And goats do skip there.

22 And Aiim have responded in his forsaken habitations, And dragons in palaces of delight, And near to come [is] her time, And her days are not drawn out!

Isaiah 14

1 Because Jehovah loveth Jacob, And hath fixed again on Israel, And given them rest on their own land, And joined hath been the sojourner to them, And they have been admitted to the house of Jacob.

2 And peoples have taken them, And have brought them in unto their place, And the house of Israel have inherited them, On the land of Jehovah, For men-servants and for maidservants, And they have been captors of their captors, And have ruled over their exactors.

3 And it hath come to pass, In the day of Jehovah's giving rest to thee, From thy grief, and from thy trouble, And from the sharp bondage, That hath been served upon thee,

4 That thou hast taken up this simile Concerning the king of Babylon, and said, How hath the exactor ceased,

5 Ceased hath the golden one. Broken hath Jehovah the staff of the wicked, The sceptre of rulers.

6 He who is smiting peoples in wrath, A smiting without intermission, He who is ruling in anger nations, Pursuing without restraint!

7 At rest--quiet hath been all the earth, They have broken forth [into] singing.

8 Even firs have rejoiced over thee, Cedars of Lebanon--[saying]: Since thou hast lain down, The hewer cometh not up against us.

9 Sheol beneath hath been troubled at thee, To meet thy coming in, It is waking up for thee Rephaim, All chiefs ones of earth, It hath raised up from their thrones All kings of nations.

10 All of them answer and say unto thee, Even thou hast become weak like us! Unto us thou hast become like!

11 Brought down to Sheol hath been thine excellency, The noise of thy psaltery, Under thee spread out hath been the worm, Yea, covering thee is the worm.

12 How hast thou fallen from the heavens, O shining one, son of the dawn! Thou hast been cut down to earth, O weakener of nations.

13 And thou saidst in thy heart: the heavens I go up, Above stars of God I raise my throne, And I sit in the mount of meeting in the sides of the north.

14 I go up above the heights of a thick cloud, I am like to the Most High.

15 Only--unto Sheol thou art brought down, Unto the sides of the pit.

16 Thy beholders look to thee, to thee they attend, Is this the man causing the earth to tremble, Shaking kingdoms?

17 He hath made the world as a wilderness, And his cities he hath broken down, Of his bound ones he opened not the house.

18 All kings of nations--all of them, Have lain down in honour, each in his house,

19 And--thou hast been cast out of thy grave, As an abominable branch, raiment of the slain, Thrust through ones of the sword, Going down unto the sons of the pit, As a carcase trodden down.

20 Thou art not united with them in burial, For thy land thou hast destroyed, Thy people thou hast slain, Not named to the age is the seed of evil doers.

21 Prepare ye for his sons slaughter; Because of the iniquity of their fathers, They rise not, nor have possessed the land, Nor filled the face of the world [with] cities.

22 And I have risen up against them, (The affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts,) And have cut off, in reference to Babylon, Name and remnant, and continuator and successor, The affirmation of Jehovah.

23 And have made it for a possession of a bittern, And ponds of waters, And daubed it with the mire of destruction, The affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts!

24 Sworn hath Jehovah of Hosts, saying, `As I thought--so hath it not been? And as I counselled--it standeth;

25 To break Asshur in My land, And on My mountains I tread him down, And turned from off them hath his yoke, Yea, his burden from off their shoulder turneth aside.

26 This [is] the counsel that is counselled for all the earth, And this [is] the hand that is stretched out for all the nations.

27 For Jehovah of Hosts hath purposed, And who doth make void? And His hand that is stretched out, Who doth turn it back?'

28 In the year of the death of king Ahaz was this burden:

29 Rejoice not thou, Philistia, all of thee, That broken hath been the rod of thy smiter, For from the root of a serpent cometh out a viper, And its fruit [is] a flying saraph.

30 And delighted have the first-born of the poor, And the needy in confidence lie down, And I have put to death with famine thy root, And thy remnant it slayeth.

31 Howl, O gate; cry, O city, Melted art thou, Philistia, all of thee, For from the north smoke hath come, And there is none alone in his set places.

32 And what doth one answer the messengers of a nation? `That Jehovah hath founded Zion, And in it do the poor of His people trust!'

Isaiah 15

1 The burden of Moab. Because in a night destroyed was Ar of Moab--It hath been cut off, Because in a night destroyed was Kir of Moab--It hath been cut off.

2 He hath gone up to Bajith and Dibon, The high places--to weep, On Nebo and on Medeba Moab howleth, On all its heads [is] baldness, every beard cut off.

3 In its out-places they girded on sackcloth, On its pinnacles, and in its broad places, Every one howleth--going down with weeping.

4 And cry doth Heshbon and Elealeh, Unto Jahaz heard hath been their voice, Therefore the armed ones of Moab do shout, His life hath been grievous to him.

5 My heart [is] toward Moab, Cry do her fugitives unto Zoar, a heifer of the third [year], For--the ascent of Luhith--With weeping he goeth up in it, For, in the way of Horonaim, A cry of destruction they wake up.

6 For, the waters of Nimrim are desolations, For, withered hath been the hay, Finished hath been the tender grass, A green thing there hath not been.

7 Therefore the abundance he made, and their store, Unto the brook of the willows they carry.

8 For gone round hath the cry the border of Moab, Unto Eglaim [is] its howling, And to Beer-Elim [is] its howling.

9 For the waters of Dimon have been full of blood, For I set on Dimon additions, For the escaped of Moab a lion, And for the remnant of Adamah!

Isaiah 16

1 Send ye a lamb [to] the ruler of the land, From Selah in the wilderness, Unto the mount of the daughter of Zion.

2 And it hath come to pass, As a wandering bird, a nest cast out, Are daughters of Moab, [at] fords of Arnon.

3 Bring ye in counsel, do judgment, Make as night thy shadow in the midst of noon, Hide outcasts, the wanderer reveal not.

4 Sojourn in thee do My outcasts, O Moab, Be a secret hiding-place to them, From the face of a destroyer, For ceased hath the extortioner, Finished hath been a destroyer, Consumed the treaders down out of the land.

5 And established in kindness is the throne, And [one] hath sat on it in truth, in the tent of David, Judging and seeking judgment, and hasting righteousness.

6 We have heard of the pride of Moab--very proud, His pride, and his arrogance, and his wrath, Not right [are] his devices.

7 Therefore howl doth Moab for Moab, all of it doth howl, For the grape-cakes of Kir- Hareseth it meditateth, Surely they are smitten.

8 Because fields of Heshbon languish, The vine of Sibmah, Lords of nations did beat her choice vines, Unto Jazer they have come, They have wandered in a wilderness, Her plants have spread themselves, They have passed over a sea.

9 Therefore I weep with the weeping of Jazer, The vine of Sibmah, I water thee [with] my tear, O Heshbon and Elealeh, For--for thy summer fruits, and for thy harvest, The shouting hath fallen.

10 And removed have been gladness and joy from the fruitful field, And in vineyards they sing not, nor shout, Wine in the presses treadeth not the treader, Shouting I have caused to cease.

11 Therefore my bowels for Moab as a harp do sound, And mine inward parts for Kir- Haresh.

12 And it hath come to pass, when it hath been seen, That weary hath been Moab on the high place, And he hath come unto his sanctuary to pray, And is not able.

13 This [is] the word that Jehovah hath spoken unto Moab from that time,

14 And now hath Jehovah spoken, saying, `In three years, as years of an hireling, Lightly esteemed is the honour of Moab, With all the great multitude, And the remnant [is] little, small, not mighty!'

Isaiah 17

1 The burden of Damascus. Lo, Damascus is taken away from [being] a city, And it hath been a heap--a ruin.

2 Forsaken are the cities of Aroer, For droves they are, and they have lain down, And there is none troubling.

3 And ceased hath the fortress from Ephraim, And the kingdom from Damascus, And the remnant of Aram are as the honour of the sons of Israel, The affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts!

4 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Wax poor doth the honour of Jacob, And the fatness of his flesh doth wax lean.

5 And it hath come to pass, As the gathering by the reaper of the standing corn, And his arm the ears reapeth, And it hath come to pass, As the gathering of the ears in the valley of Rephaim,

6 And left in him have been gleanings, As the compassing of an olive, Two--three berries on the top of a branch, Four--five on the fruitful boughs, The affirmation of Jehovah, God of Israel!

7 In that day doth man look to His Maker, Yea, his eyes to the Holy One of Israel look,

8 And he looketh not unto the altars. The work of his own hands, And that which his own fingers made He seeth not--the shrines and the images.

9 In that day are the cities of his strength As the forsaken thing of the forest, And the branch that they have left, Because of the sons of Israel, It also hath been a desolation.

10 Because thou hast forgotten the God of thy salvation, And the rock of thy strength hast not remembered, Therefore thou plantest plants of pleasantness, And with a strange slip sowest it,

11 In the day thy plant thou causest to become great, And in the morning thy seed makest to flourish, A heap [is] the harvest in a day of overflowing, And of mortal pain.

12 Woe [to] the multitude of many peoples, As the sounding of seas they sound; And [to] the wasting of nations, As the wasting of mighty waters they are wasted.

13 Nations as the wasting of many waters are wasted, And He hath pushed against it, And it hath fled afar off, And been pursued as chaff of hills before wind, And as a rolling thing before a hurricane.

14 At even-time, lo, terror, before morning it is not, This [is] the portion of our spoilers, And the lot of our plunderers!

Isaiah 19

1 The burden of Egypt. Lo, Jehovah is riding on a swift thick cloud, And He hath entered Egypt, And moved have been the idols of Egypt at His presence, And the heart of Egypt melteth in its midst.

2 And I armed Egyptians against Egyptians, And they fought, each against his brother, And each against his neighbour, City against city, kingdom against kingdom.

3 And emptied out hath been in its midst the spirit of Egypt. And its counsel I swallow up, And they have sought unto the idols, And unto the charmers, And unto those having familiar spirits, And unto the wizards.

4 And I have delivered the Egyptians Into the hand of a hard lord, And a strong king doth rule over them, An affirmation of the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts.

5 And failed have waters from the sea, And a river is wasted and dried up.

6 And they have turned away the flowings, Weak and dried up have been brooks of the bulwark, Reed and flag have withered.

7 Exposed things by the brook, by the edge of the brook, And every sown thing of the brook, hath withered, It hath been driven away, and is not.

8 And lamented have the fishers, And mourned have all casting angle into a brook, And those spreading nets on the face of the waters have languished.

9 And ashamed have been makers of fine flax, And weavers of net-works.

10 And its foundations have been smitten, All making wages [are] afflicted in soul.

11 Only, fools [are] the princes of Zoan, The counsel of the wise ones of the counsellors of Pharaoh hath become brutish. How say ye unto Pharaoh, `A son of the wise am I, a son of kings of antiquity?'

12 Where [are] they now, thy wise ones? Yea, let them tell to thee, I pray thee, And they know what Jehovah of Hosts hath counselled against Egypt!

13 Foolish have been princes of Zoan, Lifted up have been princes of Noph, And they have caused Egypt to err, The chief of her tribes.

14 Jehovah hath mingled in her midst A spirit of perverseness, And they have caused Egypt to err in all its work, As a drunkard erreth in his vomit.

15 And there is no work to Egypt, That head or tail, branch or reed, may do.

16 In that day is Egypt like women, And it hath mourned, and been afraid, Because of the waving of the hand of Jehovah of Hosts, That He is waving over it.

17 And the land of Judah hath been to Egypt for a cause of staggering, Every one who doth mention it, for himself feareth, Because of the counsel of Jehovah of Hosts, That He is counselling against it.

18 In that day there are five cities in the land of Egypt, Speaking the lip of Canaan, And swearing to Jehovah of Hosts, `The city of destruction,' is said of one.

19 In that day there is an altar to Jehovah In the midst of the land of Egypt, And a standing pillar near its border to Jehovah,

20 And it hath been for a sign and for a testimony, To Jehovah of Hosts in the land of Egypt, For they cry unto Jehovah from the face of oppressors, And He sendeth to them a saviour, Even a great one, and hath delivered them.

21 And known hath been Jehovah to Egypt, And the Egyptians have known Jehovah in that day, And done sacrifice and present, And vowed a vow to Jehovah, and completed [it].

22 And Jehovah hath smitten Egypt, smiting and healing, And they have turned back unto Jehovah, And He hath been entreated of them, And hath healed them.

23 In that day is a highway out of Egypt to Asshur, And come in have the Assyrians to Egypt, And the Egyptians into Asshur, And the Egyptians have served with the Assyrians.

24 In that day is Israel third, After Egypt, and after Asshur, A blessing in the heart of the earth.

25 In that Jehovah of Hosts did bless it, saying, `Blessed [is] My people--Egypt, And the work of My hands--Asshur, And Mine inheritance--Israel!'

Isaiah 21

1 The burden of the wilderness of the sea. `Like hurricanes in the south for passing through, From the wilderness it hath come, From a fearful land.

2 A hard vision hath been declared to me, The treacherous dealer is dealing treacherously, And the destroyer is destroying. Go up, O Elam, besiege, O Media, All its sighing I have caused to cease.

3 Therefore filled have been my loins [with] great pain, Pangs have seized me as pangs of a travailing woman, I have been bent down by hearing, I have been troubled by seeing.

4 Wandered hath my heart, trembling hath terrified me, The twilight of my desire He hath made a fear to me,

5 Arrange the table, watch in the watch-tower, Eat, drink, rise, ye heads, anoint the shield,

6 For thus said the Lord unto me: `Go, station the watchman, That which he seeth let him declare.'

7 And he hath seen a chariot--a couple of horsemen, The rider of an ass, the rider of a camel, And he hath given attention--He hath increased attention!

8 And he crieth--a lion, `On a watch-tower my lord, I am standing continually by day, And on my ward I am stationed whole nights.

9 And lo, this, the chariot of a man is coming, A couple of horsemen.' And he answereth and saith: `Fallen, fallen hath Babylon, And all the graven images of her gods He hath broken to the earth.

10 O my threshing, and the son of my floor, That which I heard from Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel, I have declared to you!'

11 The burden of Dumah. Unto me is [one] calling from Seir `Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night?'

12 The watchman hath said, `Come hath morning, and also night, If ye inquire, inquire ye, turn back, come.'

13 The burden on Arabia. In a forest in Arabia ye lodge, O travellers of Dedanim.

14 To meet the thirsty brought water have Inhabitants of the land of Tema, With his bread they came before a fugitive.

15 For from the face of destructions they fled, From the face of a stretched-out sword, And from the face of a trodden bow, And from the face of the grievousness of battle.

16 For thus said the Lord unto me: `Within a year, as years of a hireling, Consumed hath been all the honour of Kedar.

17 And the remnant of the number of bow-men, The mighty of the sons of Kedar are few, For Jehovah, God of Israel, hath spoken!'

Isaiah 22

1 The burden of the Valley of Vision. What--to thee, now, that thou hast gone up, All of thee--to the roofs?

2 Full of stirs--a noisy city--an exulting city, Thy pierced are not pierced of the sword, Nor dead in battle.

3 All thy rulers fled together from the bow, Bound have been all found of thee, They have been kept bound together, Afar off they have fled.

4 Therefore I said, `Look ye from me, I am bitter in my weeping, Haste not to comfort me, For the destruction of the daughter of my people.'

5 For a day of noise, and of treading down, And of perplexity, [is] to the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, In the valley of vision, digging down a wall, And crying unto the mountain.

6 And Elam hath borne a quiver, In a chariot of men--horsemen, And Kir hath exposed a shield.

7 And it cometh to pass, The choice of thy valleys have been full of chariots, And the horsemen place themselves diligently at the gate.

8 And one removeth the covering of Judah, And thou lookest in that day Unto the armour of the house of the forest,

9 And the breaches of the city of David ye have seen, For they have become many, And ye gather the waters of the lower pool,

10 And the houses of Jerusalem ye did number, And ye break down the houses to fence the wall.

11 And a ditch ye made between the two walls, For the waters of the old pool, And ye have not looked unto its Maker, And its Framer of old ye have not seen.

12 And call doth the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, In that day, to weeping and to lamentation, And to baldness and to girding on of sackcloth,

13 And lo, joy and gladness, slaying of oxen, And slaughtering of sheep, Eating of flesh, and drinking of wine, Eat and drink, for to-morrow we die.

14 And revealed it hath been in mine ears, [By] Jehovah of Hosts: Not pardoned is this iniquity to you, Till ye die, said the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts.

15 Thus said the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts: `Go, enter in unto this steward, Unto Shebna, who [is] over the house:

16 What--to thee here? And who--to thee here? That thou hast hewn out to thee here--a sepulchre? Hewing on high his sepulchre, Graving in a rock a dwelling for himself.

17 Lo, Jehovah is casting thee up and down, A casting up and down, O mighty one,

18 And thy coverer covering, wrapping round, Wrappeth thee round, O babbler, On a land broad of sides--there thou diest, And there the chariots of thine honour [Are] the shame of the house of thy lord.

19 And I have thrust thee from thy station, And from thine office he throweth thee down.

20 And it hath come to pass, in that day, That I have called to my servant, To Eliakim son of Hilkiah.

21 And I have clothed him with thy coat, And with thy girdle I strengthen him, And thy garment I give into his hand, And he hath been for a father to the inhabitant of Jerusalem, And to the house of Judah.

22 And I have placed the key Of the house of David on his shoulder, And he hath opened, and none is shutting, And hath shut, and none is opening.

23 And I have fixed him a nail in a stedfast place, And he hath been for a throne of honour To the house of his father.

24 And they have hanged on him All the honour of the house of his father, The offspring and the issue, All vessels of small quality, From vessels of basins to all vessels of flagons.

25 In that day--an affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, Moved is the nail that is fixed In a stedfast place, Yea, it hath been cut down, and hath fallen, And cut off hath been the burden that [is] on it, For Jehovah hath spoken!'

Isaiah 23

1 The Burden of Tyre. Howl, ye ships of Tarshish, For it hath been destroyed, Without house, without entrance, From the land of Chittim it was revealed to them.

2 Be silent, ye inhabitants of the isle, Trader of Zidon, passing the sea, they filled thee.

3 And in many waters [is] the seed of Sihor, The harvest of the brook [is] her increase, And she is a mart of nations.

4 Be ashamed, O Zidon; for the sea spake, The strength of the sea, saying: `I have not been pained, nor have I brought forth, Nor have I nourished young men, [nor] brought up virgins.'

5 As [at] the report of Egypt they are pained, So [at] the report of Tyre.

6 Pass over to Tarshish, howl, ye inhabitants of the isle,

7 Is this your exulting one? From the days of old [is] her antiquity, Carry her do her own feet afar off to sojourn.

8 Who hath counselled this against Tyre, The crowning one, whose traders [are] princes, Her merchants the honoured of earth?'

9 Jehovah of Hosts hath counselled it, To pollute the excellency of all beauty, To make light all the honoured of earth.

10 Pass through thy land as a brook, Daughter of Tarshish, there is no more a girdle.

11 His hand He hath stretched out over the sea, He hath caused kingdoms to tremble, Jehovah hath charged concerning the merchant one, To destroy her strong places.

12 And He saith, `Thou dost not add any more to exult, O oppressed one, virgin daughter of Zidon, To Chittim arise, pass over, Even there--there is no rest for thee.'

13 Lo, the land of the Chaldeans--this people was not, Asshur founded it for the Ziim, They raised its watch-towers, They lifted up her palaces, --He hath appointed her for a ruin!

14 Howl, ye ships of Tarshish, For your strength hath been destroyed.

15 And it hath come to pass, in that day, That forgotten is Tyre seventy years, According to the days of one king. At the end of seventy years there is to Tyre as the song of the harlot.

16 Take a harp, go round the city, O forgotten harlot, play well, Multiply song that thou mayest be remembered.

17 And it hath come to pass, At the end of seventy years Jehovah inspecteth Tyre, And she hath repented of her gift, That she committed fornication With all kingdoms of the earth on the face of the ground.

18 And her merchandise and her gift have been holy to Jehovah, Not treasured up nor stored, For to those sitting before Jehovah is her merchandise, To eat to satiety, and for a lasting covering!

Isaiah 24

1 Lo, Jehovah is emptying the land, And is making it waste, And hath overturned [it on] its face, And hath scattered its inhabitants.

2 And it hath been--as a people so a priest, As the servant so his master, As the maidservant so her mistress, As the buyer so the seller, As the lender so the borrower, As the usurer so he who is lifting [it] on himself.

3 Utterly emptied is the land, and utterly spoiled, For Jehovah hath spoken this word:

4 Mourned, faded hath the land, Languished, faded hath the world, Languished have they--the high place of the people of the land.

5 And the land hath been defiled under its inhabitants, Because they have transgressed laws, They have changed a statute, They have made void a covenant age-during.

6 Therefore a curse hath consumed the land, And the inhabitants in it are become desolate, Therefore consumed have been inhabitants of the land, And few men have been left.

7 Mourned hath the new wine, languished the vine, Sighed have all the joyful of heart.

8 Ceased hath the joy of tabrets, Ceased hath the noise of exulting ones, Ceased hath the joy of a harp.

9 With a song they drink not wine, Bitter is strong drink to those drinking it.

10 It was broken down--a city of emptiness, Shut hath been every house from entrance.

11 A cry over the wine [is] in out-places, Darkened hath been all joy, Removed hath been the joy of the land.

12 Left in the city [is] desolation, And [with] wasting is the gate smitten.

13 When thus it is in the heart of the land, In the midst of the peoples, As the compassing of the olive, As gleanings when harvest hath been finished,

14 They--they lift up their voice, They sing of the excellency of Jehovah, They have cried aloud from the sea.

15 Therefore in prosperity honour ye Jehovah, In isles of the sea, the name of Jehovah, God of Israel.

16 From the skirt of the earth we heard songs, The desire of the righteous. And I say, `Leanness [is] to me, Leanness [is] to me, woe [is] to me.' Treacherous dealers dealt treacherously, Yea, treachery, treacherous dealers dealt treacherously.

17 Fear, and a snare, and a gin, [Are] on thee, O inhabitant of the land.

18 And it hath come to pass, He who is fleeing from the noise of the fear Doth fall into the snare, And he who is coming up from the midst of the snare, Is captured by the gin, For windows on high have been opened, And shaken are foundations ofthe land.

19 Utterly broken down hath been the land, Utterly broken hath been the land, Utterly moved hath been the land.

20 Stagger greatly doth the land as a drunkard, And it hath been moved as a lodge, And heavy on it hath been its transgression, And it hath fallen, and addeth not to rise.

21 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Jehovah layeth a charge on the host of the high place in the high place, And on the kings of the land on the land.

22 And they have been gathered--A gathering of bound ones in a pit, And shut up they have been in a prison, And after a multitude of days are inspected.

23 And confounded hath been the moon, And ashamed hath been the sun, For reigned hath Jehovah of Hosts In mount Zion, and in Jerusalem, And over-against His elders--honour!

Isaiah 25

1 O Jehovah, my God [art] Thou, I exalt Thee, I confess Thy name, For Thou hast done a wonderful thing, Counsels of old, stedfastness, O stedfast One.

2 For Thou didst make of a city a heap, Of a fenced city a ruin, A high place of strangers from [being] a city, To the age it is not built.

3 Therefore honour Thee do a strong people, A city of the terrible nations feareth Thee.

4 For Thou hast been a stronghold for the poor, A stronghold for the needy in his distress, A refuge from storm, a shadow from heat, When the spirit of the terrible [is] as a storm--a wall.

5 As heat in a dry place, The noise of strangers Thou humblest, Heat with the shadow of a thick cloud, The singing of the terrible is humbled.

6 And made hath Jehovah of Hosts, For all the peoples in this mount, A banquet of fat things, a banquet of preserved things, Fat things full of marrow, preserved things refined.

7 And swallowed up hath He in this mountain The face of the wrapping that is wrapped over all the peoples, And of the covering that is spread over all the nations.

8 He hath swallowed up death in victory, And wiped hath the Lord Jehovah, The tear from off all faces, And the reproach of His people He turneth aside from off all the earth, For Jehovah hath spoken.

9 And [one] hath said in that day, `Lo, this [is] our God, We waited for Him, and He saveth us, This [is] Jehovah, we have waited for Him, We joy and rejoice in His salvation.'

10 For rest doth the hand of Jehovah on this mountain, And trodden down is Moab under Him, As trodden down is straw on a dunghill.

11 And he spread out his hands in its midst, As spread out doth the swimmer to swim; And He hath humbled his excellency With the machinations of his hands.

12 And the fortress of the high place of thy walls He hath bowed down--He hath made low, He hath caused [it] to come to the earth, --unto dust.

Isaiah 26

1 In that day sung is this song in the land of Judah: `We have a strong city, Salvation He doth make walls and bulwark.

2 Open ye the gates, that enter may a righteous nation, Preserving stedfastness.

3 An imagination supported Thou fortifiest peace--peace! For in Thee it is confident.

4 Trust ye in Jehovah for ever, For in Jah Jehovah [is] a rock of ages,

5 For He bowed down the dwellers on high, A city set on high He maketh low, He maketh it low unto the earth, He causeth it to come unto the dust,

6 Tread it down doth a foot, Feet of the poor--steps of the weak.

7 The path for the righteous [is] uprightness, O upright One, The path of the righteous Thou dost ponder.

8 Also, [in] the path of Thy judgments, O Jehovah, we have waited [for] Thee, To Thy name and to Thy remembrance [Is] the desire of the soul.

9 [With] my soul I desired Thee in the night, Also, [with] my spirit within me I seek Thee earnestly, For when Thy judgments [are] on the earth, The inhabitants of the world have learned righteousness.

10 The wicked findeth favour, He hath not learned righteousness, In a land of straightforwardness he dealeth perversely, And seeth not the excellency of Jehovah.

11 O Jehovah, high [is] Thy hand--they see not, They see the zeal of the people, and are ashamed, Also, the fire--Thine adversaries, consumeth them.

12 O Jehovah, Thou appointest peace to us, For, all our works also Thou hast wrought for us.

13 O Jehovah our God, lords have ruled us besides Thee, Only, by Thee we make mention of Thy name.

14 Dead--they live not, Rephaim, they rise not, Therefore Thou hast inspected and dost destroy them, Yea, thou destroyest all their memory.

15 Thou hast added to the nation, O Jehovah, Thou hast added to the nation, Thou hast been honoured, Thou hast put far off all the ends of earth.

16 O Jehovah, in distress they missed Thee, They have poured out a whisper, Thy chastisement [is] on them.

17 When a pregnant woman cometh near to the birth, She is pained--she crieth in her pangs, So we have been from Thy face, O Jehovah.

18 We have conceived, we have been pained. We have brought forth as it were wind, Salvation we do not work in the earth, Nor do the inhabitants of the world fall.

19 `Thy dead live--My dead body they rise. Awake and sing, ye dwellers in the dust, For the dew of herbs [is] thy dew, And the land of Rephaim thou causest to fall.

20 Come, My people, enter into thy inner chambers, And shut thy doors behind thee, Hide thyself shortly a moment till the indignation pass over.

21 For, lo, Jehovah is coming out of His place, To charge the iniquity of the inhabitant of the earth upon him, And revealed hath the earth her blood, Nor doth she cover any more her slain!'

Isaiah 27

1 In that day lay a charge doth Jehovah, With his sword--the sharp, and the great, and the strong, On leviathan--a fleeing serpent, And on leviathan--a crooked serpent, And He hath slain the dragon that [is] in the sea.

2 In that day, `A desirable vineyard,' respond ye to her,

3 I, Jehovah, am its keeper, every moment I water it, Lest any lay a charge against it, Night and day I keep it!

4 Fury is not in Me; Who giveth Me a brier--a thorn in battle? I step into it, I burn it at once.

5 Or--he doth take hold on My strength, He doth make peace with Me, Peace he doth make with Me.

6 Those coming in He causeth to take root, Jacob doth blossom, and flourished hath Israel, And they have filled the face of the world [with] increase.

7 As the smiting of his smiter hath He smitten him? As the slaying of his slain doth He slay?

8 In measure, in sending it forth, thou strivest with it, He hath taken away by His sharp wind, In the day of an east wind,

9 Therefore by this is the iniquity of Jacob covered, And this [is] all the fruit--To take away his sin, in His setting all the stones of an altar, As chalkstones beaten in pieces, They rise not- -shrines and images.

10 For the fenced city [is] alone, A habitation cast out and forsaken as a wilderness, There doth the calf delight, And there it lieth down, And hath consumed its branches.

11 In the withering of its branch it is broken off, Women are coming in setting it on fire, For it [is] not a people of understanding, Therefore pity it not doth its Maker, And its Former doth not favour it.

12 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Beat out doth Jehovah from the branch of the river, Unto the stream of Egypt, And ye are gathered one by one, O sons of Israel.

13 And it hath come to pass, in that day, It is blown with a great trumpet, And come in have those perishing in the land of Asshur, And those cast out in the land of Egypt, And have bowed themselves to Jehovah, In the holy mount--in Jerusalem!

Isaiah 28

1 Woe [to] the proud crown of the drunkards of Ephraim. And the fading flower of the beauty of his glory, That [is] on the head of the fat valley of the broken down of wine.

2 Lo, a mighty and strong one [is] to the Lord, As a storm of hail--a destructive shower, As an inundation of mighty waters overflowing, He cast down to the earth with the hand.

3 By feet trodden down is the proud crown of the drunkards of Ephraim,

4 And the fading flower of the beauty of his glory That [is] on the head of the fat valley, Hath been as its first-fruit before summer, That its beholder seeth, While it [is] yet in his hand he swalloweth it.

5 In that day is Jehovah of Hosts For a crown of beauty, and for a diadem of glory, To the remnant of His people.

6 And for a spirit of judgment To him who is sitting in the judgment, And for might [to] those turning back the battle to the gate.

7 And even these through wine have erred, And through strong drink have wandered, Priest and prophet erred through strong drink, They have been swallowed up of the wine, They wandered because of the strong drink, They have erred in seeing, Theyhave stumbled judicially.

8 For all tables have been full of vomit, Filth--without place!

9 By whom doth He teach knowledge? And by whom doth He cause to understand the report? The weaned from milk, the removed from breasts,

10 For rule [is] on rule, rule on rule, line on line, line on line, A little here, a little there,

11 For by scorned lip, and by another tongue, Doth He speak unto this people.

12 Unto whom He hath said, `This [is] the rest, give ye rest to the weary, And this--the refreshing:' And they have not been willing to hear,

13 And to whom a word of Jehovah hath been, Rule on rule, rule on rule, line on line, line on line, A little here, a little there, So that they go and have stumbled backward, And been broken, and snared, and captured.

14 Therefore, hear a word of Jehovah, ye men of scorning, Ruling this people that [is] in Jerusalem.

15 Because ye have said: `We have made a covenant with death, And with Sheol we have made a provision, An overflowing scourge, when it passeth over, Doth not meet us, Though we have made a lie our refuge, And in falsehood have been hidden.'

16 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: `Lo, I am laying a foundation in Zion, A stone- -a tried stone, a corner stone precious, a settled foundation, He who is believing doth not make haste.

17 And I have put judgment for a line, And righteousness for a plummet, And sweep away doth hail the refuge of lies, And the secret hiding-place do waters overflow.

18 And disannulled hath been your covenant with death, And your provision with Sheol doth not stand, An overflowing scourge, when it passeth over, Then ye have been to it for a treading-place.

19 From the fulness of its passing over it taketh you, For morning by morning it passeth over, By day and by night, And it hath been only a trembling to consider the report.

20 For shorter hath been the bed Than to stretch one's self out in, And the covering hath been narrower Than to wrap one's self up in.

21 For as [at] mount Perazim rise doth Jehovah, As [at] the valley in Gibeon He is troubled, To do His work--strange [is] His work, And to do His deed--strange [is] His deed.'

22 And now, show not yourselves scorners, Lest strong be your bands, For a consumption, that is determined, I have heard, by the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, [Is] for all the land.

23 Give ear, and hear my voice, Attend, and hear my saying:

24 The whole day plougheth the ploughman to sow? He openeth and harroweth his ground!

25 Hath he not, if he have made level its face, Then scattered fitches, and cummin sprinkle, And hath placed the principal wheat, And the appointed barley, And the rie [in] its own border?

26 And instruct him for judgment doth his God, He doth direct him.

27 For not with a sharp-pointed thing threshed are fitches, And the wheel of a cart on cummin turned round, For with a staff beaten out are fitches, And cummin with a rod.

28 Bread -[corn] is beaten small, For not for ever doth he sorely thresh it, Nor crushed [it] hath a wheel of his cart, Nor do his hoofs beat it small.

29 Even this from Jehovah of Hosts hath gone out, He hath made counsel wonderful, He hath made wisdom great!

Isaiah 29

1 Woe [to] Ariel, Ariel, The city of the encampment of David! Add year to year, let festivals go round.

2 And I have sent distress to Ariel, And it hath been lamentation and mourning, And it hath been to me as Ariel.

3 And I encamped, O babbler, against thee, And I laid siege against thee--a camp. And I raised up against thee bulwarks.

4 And thou hast been low, From the earth thou speakest, And from the dust makest thy saying low, And thy voice hath been from the earth, As one having a familiar spirit, And from the dust thy saying whisperest,

5 And as small dust hath been The multitude of those scattering thee, And as chaff passing on the multitude of the terrible, And it hath been at an instant--suddenly.

6 By Jehovah of Hosts thou art inspected, With thunder, and with an earthquake, And great noise, hurricane, and whirlwind, And flame of devouring fire.

7 And as a dream, a vision of night, hath been The multitude of all the nations Who are warring against Ariel, And all its warriors, and its bulwark, Even of those distressing her.

8 And it hath been, as when the hungry dreameth, And lo, he is eating, And he hath waked, and empty [is] his soul, And as when the thirsty dreameth, And lo, he is drinking, and he hath waked, And lo, he is weary, and his soul is longing, So is the multitude of all the nations Who are warring against mount Zion.

9 Tarry and wonder, look ye, yea, look, Be drunk, and not with wine, Stagger, and not with strong drink.

10 For poured out on you hath Jehovah a spirit of deep sleep, And He closeth your eyes-- the prophets, And your heads--the seers--He covered.

11 And the vision of the whole is to you, As words of the sealed book, That they give unto one knowing books, Saying, `Read this, we pray thee,' And he hath said, `I am not able, for it [is] sealed;'

12 And the book is given to him who hath not known books, Saying, `Read this, we pray thee,' And he hath said, `I have not known books.'

13 And the Lord saith: Because drawn near hath this people, with its mouth, And with its lips they have honoured Me, And its heart it hath put far off from Me, And their fear of Me is--A precept of men is taught!

14 Therefore, lo, I am adding to do wonderfully with this people, A wonder, and a marvel, And perished hath the wisdom of its wise ones, And the understanding of its intelligent ones hideth itself.'

15 Woe [to] those going deep from Jehovah to hide counsel, And whose works have been in darkness. And they say, `Who is seeing us? And who is knowing us?'

16 Your perversion! as clay is the potter esteemed? That the work saith of its maker, `He hath not made me?' And the framed thing said of its framer, `He did not understand?'

17 Is it not yet a very little, And turned hath Lebanon to a fruitful field, And the fruitful field for a forest is reckoned?

18 And heard in that day have the deaf the words of a book, And out of thick darkness, and out of darkness, The eyes of the blind do see.

19 And the humble have added joy in Jehovah, And the poor among men In the Holy One of Israel rejoice.

20 For ceased hath the terrible one, And consumed hath been the scorner, And cut off have been all watching for iniquity,

21 Causing men to sin in word, And for a reprover in the gate lay a snare, And turn aside into emptiness the righteous.

22 Therefore, thus said Jehovah, Who ransomed Abraham, Concerning the house of Jacob: `Not now ashamed is Jacob, Nor now doth his face become pale,

23 For in his seeing his children, The work of My hand, in his midst, They sanctify My name, And have sanctified the Holy One of Jacob, And the God of Israel they declare fearful.

24 And the erring in spirit have known understanding, And murmurers learn doctrine!'

Isaiah 30

1 Woe [to] apostate sons, The affirmation of Jehovah! To do counsel, and not from Me, And to spread out a covering, and not of My spirit, So as to add sin to sin.

2 Who are walking to go down to Egypt, And My mouth have not asked, To be strong in the strength of Pharaoh, And to trust in the shadow of Egypt.

3 And the strength of Pharaoh Hath been to you for shame, And the trust in the shadow of Egypt confusion,

4 For in Zoan were his princes, And his messengers reach Hanes.

5 All he made ashamed of a people that profit not, Neither for help, not for profit, But for shame, and also for reproach!

6 The burden of the beasts of the south. Into a land of adversity and distress, Of young lion and of old lion, Whence [are] viper and flying saraph, They carry on the shoulder of asses their wealth, And on the hump of camels their treasures, Unto a people not profitable.

7 Yea, Egyptians [are] vanity, and in vain do help, Therefore I have cried concerning this: `Their strength [is] to sit still.'

8 No, go in, write it on a tablet with them, And on a book engrave it, And it is for a latter day, for a witness unto the age,

9 That a rebellious people [is] this, sons--liars, Sons not willing to hear the law of Jehovah.

10 Who have said to seers, `Ye do not see,' And to prophets, `Ye do not prophesy to us Straightforward things, Speak to us smooth things, prophesy deceits,

11 Turn aside from the way, decline from the path, Cause to cease from before us the Holy One of Israel.'

12 Therefore, thus said the Holy One of Israel, Because of your kicking against this word, And ye trust in oppression, And perverseness, and rely on it,

13 Therefore is this iniquity to you as a breach falling, Swelled out in a wall set on high, Whose destruction suddenly, at an instant cometh.

14 And He hath broken it As the breaking of the potters' bottle, Beaten down--He doth not spare, Nor is there found, in its beating down, A potsherd to take fire from the burning, And to draw out waters from a ditch.

15 For thus said the Lord Jehovah, The Holy One of Israel: `In returning and rest ye are saved, In keeping quiet and in confidence is your might, And ye have not been willing.

16 And ye say, No, for on a horse we flee? Therefore ye flee, And on the swift we ride! Therefore swift are your pursuers.

17 One thousand because of the rebuke of one, Because of the rebuke of five ye flee, Till ye have been surely left as a pole On the top of the mountain, And as an ensign on the height.

18 And therefore doth wait Jehovah to favour you, And therefore He is exalted to pity you, For a God of judgment [is] Jehovah, O the blessedness of all waiting for Him.

19 For the people in Zion dwell in Jerusalem, Weep thou not, weeping, Pitying, He pitieth thee at the voice of thy cry, When He heareth He answereth thee.

20 And the Lord hath given to you bread of adversity, And water of oppression. And thy directors remove no more, And thine eyes have seen thy directors,

21 And thine ear heareth a word behind thee, Saying, `This [is] the way, go ye in it,' When ye turn to the right, And when ye turn to the left.

22 And ye have defiled the covering of Thy graven images of silver, And the ephod of thy molten image of gold, Thou scatterest them as a sickening thing, `Go out,' thou sayest to it.

23 And He hath given rain [for] thy seed, With which thou dost sow the ground, And bread, the increase of the ground, And it hath been fat and plenteous, Enjoy do thy cattle in that day an enlarged pasture.

24 And the oxen and the young asses serving the ground, Fermented provender do eat, That one is winnowing with shovel and fan.

25 And there hath been on every high mount, And on every exalted hill, Rivulets-- streams of waters, In a day of much slaughter, in the falling of towers.

26 And the light of the moon hath been as the light of the sun, And the light of the sun is sevenfold, As the light of seven days, In the day of Jehovah's binding up the breach of His people, When the stroke of its wound He healeth.

27 Lo, the name of Jehovah is coming from far, Burning is His anger, and great the flame, His lips have been full of indignation, And His tongue [is] as a devouring fire.

28 And His breath [is] as an overflowing stream, Unto the neck it divideth, To sift nations with a sieve of vanity, And a bridle causing to err, [Is] on the jaws of the peoples.

29 Singing is to you as in a night sanctified for a festival, And joy of heart as he who is going with a pipe, To go in to the mountain of Jehovah, Unto the rock of Israel.

30 And caused to be heard hath Jehovah The honour of His voice, And the coming down of His arm He doth shew with the raging of anger, And the flame of a consuming fire, Scattering, and inundation, and hailstone.

31 For from the voice of Jehovah broken down [is] Asshur, With a rod He smiteth.

32 And every passage of the settled staff, That Jehovah causeth to rest on him, Hath been with tabrets, and with harps, And in battles of shaking he hath fought with it.

33 For, arranged from former time is Tophet, Even it for the king is prepared, He hath made deep, He hath made large, Its pile [is] fire and much wood, The breath of Jehovah, As a stream of brim stone, is burning in it!

Isaiah 31

1 Woe [to] those going down to Egypt for help, And on horses lean, And trust on chariots, because many, And on horsemen, because very strong, And have not looked on the Holy One of Israel, And Jehovah have not sought.

2 And He also [is] wise, and bringeth in evil, And His words He hath not turned aside, And He hath risen against a house of evil doers, And against the help of workers of iniquity.

3 And the Egyptians [are men], and not God, And their horses [are] flesh, and not spirit, And Jehovah stretcheth out His hand, And stumbled hath the helper, And fallen hath the helped one, And together all of them are consumed.

4 For thus said Jehovah unto me: `As growl doth the lion and the young lion over his prey, Called against whom is a multitude of shepherds, From their voice he is not affrighted, And from their noise he is not humbled; So come down doth Jehovahof Hosts To war on mount Zion, and on her height.

5 As birds flying, so doth Jehovah of Hosts Cover over Jerusalem, covering and delivering, Passing over, and causing to escape.'

6 Turn back to Him from whom sons of Israel Have deepened apostasy.

7 For in that day despise doth each His idols of silver, and his idols of gold, That your hands made to you--a sin.

8 And fallen hath Asshur by sword, not of the high, Yea, a sword--not of the low, doth consume him, And he hath fled for himself from the face of a sword, And his young men become tributary.

9 And [to] his rock from fear he passeth on, And affrighted by the ensign have been his princes--an affirmation of Jehovah, Who hath a light in Zion, And who hath a furnace in Jerusalem!

Isaiah 32

1 Lo, for righteousness doth a king reign, As to princes, for judgment they rule.

2 And each hath been as a hiding-place [from] wind, And as a secret hiding-place [from] inundation, As rivulets of waters in a dry place, As a shadow of a heavy rock in a weary land.

3 And not dazzled are the eyes of beholders, And the ears of hearers do attend.

4 And the heart of those hastened Understandeth to know, And the tongue of stammerers hasteth to speak clearly.

5 A fool is no more called `noble,' And to a miser it is not said, `rich;'

6 For a fool speaketh folly, And his heart doth iniquity, to do profanity, And to speak concerning Jehovah error, To empty the soul of the hungry, Yea, drink of the thirsty he causeth to lack.

7 And the miser--his instruments [are] evil, He hath counselled wicked devices, To corrupt the poor with lying sayings, Even when the needy speaketh justly.

8 And the noble counselled noble things, And he for noble things riseth up.

9 Women, easy ones, rise, hear my voice, Daughters, confident ones, give ear [to] my saying,

10 Days and a year ye are troubled, O confident ones, For consumed hath been harvest, The gathering cometh not.

11 Tremble ye women, ye easy ones, Be troubled, ye confident ones, Strip and make bare, with a girdle on the loins,

12 For breasts they are lamenting, For fields of desire, for the fruitful vine.

13 Over the ground of my people thorn--brier goeth up, Surely over all houses of joy of the exulting city,

14 Surely the palace hath been left, The multitude of the city forsaken, Fort and watchtower hath been for dens unto the age, A joy of wild asses--a pasture of herds;

15 Till emptied out on us is the Spirit from on high, And a wilderness hath become a fruitful field, And the fruitful field for a forest is reckoned.

16 And dwelt in the wilderness hath judgment, And righteousness in the fruitful field remaineth.

17 And a work of the righteousness hath been peace, And a service of the righteousness-- Keeping quiet and confidence unto the age.

18 And dwelt hath My people in a peaceful habitation, And in stedfast tabernacles, And in quiet resting-places.

19 And it hath hailed in the going down of the forest, And in the valley is the city low.

20 Happy [are] ye sowing by all waters, Sending forth the foot of the ox and the ass!

Isaiah 34

1 Come near, ye nations, to hear, And ye peoples, give attention, Hear doth the earth and its fulness, The world, and all its productions.

2 For wrath [is] to Jehovah against all the nations, And fury against all their host, He hath devoted them to destruction, He hath given them to slaughter.

3 And their wounded are cast out, And their carcases cause their stench to ascend, And melted have been mountains from their blood.

4 And consumed have been all the host of the heavens, And rolled together as a book have been the heavens, And all their hosts do fade, As the fading of a leaf of a vine, And as the fading one of a fig-tree.

5 For soaked in the heavens was My sword, Lo, on Edom it cometh down, On the people of My curse for judgment.

6 A sword [is] to Jehovah--it hath been full of blood, It hath been made fat with fatness, With blood of lambs and he-goats. With fat of kidneys of rams, For a sacrifice [is] to Jehovah in Bozrah, And a great slaughter in the land of Edom.

7 And come down have reems with them, And bullocks with bulls, And soaked hath been their land from blood, And their dust from fatness is made fat.

8 (For a day of vengeance [is] to Jehovah, A year of recompences for Zion's strife,)

9 And turned have been her streams to pitch, And her dust to brimstone, And her land hath become burning pitch.

10 By night and by day she is not quenched, To the age go up doth her smoke, From generation to generation she is waste, For ever and ever, none is passing into her.

11 And possess her do pelican and hedge-hog, And owl and raven dwell in her, And He hath stretched out over her A line of vacancy, and stones of emptiness.

12 [To] the kingdom her freemen they call, But there are none there, And all her princes are at an end.

13 And gone up her palaces have thorns, Nettle and bramble [are] in her fortresses, And it hath been a habitation of dragons, A court for daughters of an ostrich.

14 And met have Ziim with Aiim, And the goat for its companion calleth, Only there rested hath the night-owl, And hath found for herself a place of rest.

15 There made her nest hath the bittern, Yea, she layeth, and hath hatched, And hath gathered under her shadow, Only there gathered have been vultures, Each with its companion.

16 Seek out of the book of Jehovah, and read, One of these hath not been lacking, None hath missed its companion, For My mouth--it hath commanded, And His spirit--He hath gathered them.

17 And He hath cast for them a lot, And His hand hath apportioned [it] to them by line, Unto the age they possess it, To all generations they dwell in it!

Isaiah 36

1 And it cometh to pass, in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, come up hath Sennacherib king of Asshur against all the fenced cities of Judah, and seizeth them.

2 And the king of Asshur sendeth Rabshakeh from Lachish to Jerusalem, unto the king Hezekiah, with a heavy force, and he standeth by the conduit of the upper pool, in the highway of the fuller's field,

3 and go forth unto him doth Eliakim son of Hilkiah, who [is] over the house, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah son of Asaph, the remembrancer.

4 And Rabshakeh saith unto them, `Say ye, I pray you, unto Hezekiah, `Thus said the great king, the king of Asshur, What [is] this confidence in which thou hast confided?

5 I have said: Only, a word of the lips! counsel and might [are] for battle: now, on whom hast thou trusted, that thou hast rebelled against me?

6 `Lo, thou hast trusted on the staff of this broken reed--on Egypt--which a man leaneth on, and it hath gone into his hand, and pierced it--so [is] Pharaoh king of Egypt to all those trusting on him.

7 `And dost thou say unto me, Unto Jehovah our God we have trusted? is it not He, whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah hath turned aside, and saith to Judah and to Jerusalem, Before this altar ye do bow yourselves?

8 `And now, negotiate, I pray thee, with my lord the king of Asshur, and I give to thee two thousand horses, if thou art able to put for thee riders on them.

9 And how dost thou turn back the face of one captain of the least of the servants of my lord, and dost trust for thee on Egypt, for chariot and for horsemen?

10 And now, without Jehovah have I come up against this land to destroy it? Jehovah said unto me, Go up unto this land, and thou hast destroyed it.'

11 And Eliakim saith--and Shebna and Joah--unto Rabshakeh, `Speak, we pray thee, unto thy servants [in] Aramaean, for we are understanding; and do not speak unto us [in] Jewish, in the ears of the people who [are] on the wall.'

12 And Rabshakeh saith, `Unto thy lord, and unto thee, hath my lord sent me to speak these words? is it not for the men--those sitting on the wall to eat their own dung and to drink their own water with you?'

13 And Rabshakeh standeth and calleth with a great voice [in] Jewish, and saith, `Hear ye the words of the great king, the king of Asshur:

14 Thus said the king, Let not Hezekiah lift you up, for he is not able to deliver you;

15 and let not Hezekiah make you trust unto Jehovah, saying, Jehovah doth certainly deliver us, this city is not given into the hand of the king of Asshur.

16 `Do not hearken unto Hezekiah, for thus said the king of Asshur, Make ye with me a blessing, and come out unto me, and eat ye each of his vine, and each of his fig-tree, and drink ye each the waters of his own well,

17 till my coming in, and I have taken you unto a land like your own land, a land of corn and wine, a land of bread and vineyards;

18 lest Hezekiah doth persuade you, saying, Jehovah doth deliver us. `Have the gods of the nations delivered each his land out of the hand of the king of Asshur?

19 Where [are] the gods of Hamath and Arpad? Where the gods of Sepharvaim, that they have delivered Samaria out of my hand?

20 Who among all the gods of these lands [are] they who have delivered their land out of my hand, that Jehovah doth deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?'

21 And they keep silent, and have not answered him a word, for a command of the king is, saying, `Do not answer him.'

22 And Eliakim son of Hilkiah, who [is] over the house, cometh in, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah son of Asaph, the remembrancer, unto Hezekiah with rent garments, and they declare to him the words of Rabshakeh.

Isaiah 37

1 And it cometh to pass, at the king Hezekiah's hearing, that he rendeth his garments, and covereth himself with sackcloth, and entereth the house of Jehovah,

2 and sendeth Eliakim, who [is] over the house, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covering themselves with sackcloth, unto Isaiah son of Amoz the prophet,

3 and they say unto him, `Thus said Hezekiah, A day of distress, and rebuke, and despising, [is] this day; for come have sons unto the birth, and power there is not to bear.

4 `It may be Jehovah thy God doth hear the words of Rabshakeh with which the king of Asshur his lord hath sent him to reproach the living God, and hath decided concerning the words that Jehovah thy God hath heard, and thou hast lifted up prayerfor the remnant that is found.'

5 And the servants of king Hezekiah come in unto Isaiah,

6 and Isaiah saith unto them, `Thus do ye say unto your lord, Thus said Jehovah, Be not afraid because of the words that thou hast heard, with which the servants of the king of Asshur have reviled Me.

7 Lo, I am giving in him a spirit, and he hath heard a report, and hath turned back unto his land, and I have caused him to fall by the sword in his land.'

8 And Rabshakeh turneth back and findeth the king of Asshur fighting against Libnah, for he hath heard that he hath journeyed from Lachish.

9 And he heareth concerning Tirhakah king of Cush, saying, `He hath come out to fight with thee;' and he heareth, and sendeth messengers unto Hezekiah, saying,

10 `Thus do ye speak unto Hezekiah king of Judah, saying, Let not thy God lift thee up in whom thou art trusting, saying, Jerusalem is not given into the hand of the king of Asshur.

11 Lo, thou hast heard that which the kings of Asshur have done to all the lands--to devote them--and thou art delivered!

12 Did the gods of the nations deliver them whom my fathers destroyed--Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the sons of Eden, who [are] in Telassar?

13 Where [is] the king of Hamath, and the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, Hena, and Ivvah?'

14 And Hezekiah taketh the letters out of the hand of the messengers, and readeth them, and Hezekiah goeth up to the house of Jehovah, and Hezekiah spreadeth it before Jehovah.

15 And Hezekiah prayeth unto Jehovah, saying,

16 `Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel, inhabiting the cherubs, Thou [art] God Himself-- Thyself alone--to all kingdoms of the earth, Thou hast made the heavens and the earth.

17 Incline, O Jehovah, Thine ear, and hear; open, O Jehovah, Thine eyes and see; and hear Thou all the words of Sennacherib that he hath sent to reproach the living God.

18 `Truly, O Jehovah, kings of Asshur have laid waste all the lands and their land,

19 so as to put their gods into fire--for they [are] no gods, but work of the hands of man, wood and stone--and they destroy them.

20 And now, Jehovah our God, save us from his hand, and all kingdoms of the earth do know that Thou [art] Jehovah, Thyself alone.'

21 And Isaiah son of Amoz sendeth unto Hezekiah, saying, `Thus said Jehovah, God of Israel, That which thou hast prayed unto me concerning Sennacherib king of Asshur--

22 this [is] the word that Jehovah spake concerning him: Trampled on thee, laughed at thee, Hath the virgin daughter of Zion, Behind thee shaken the head hath the daughter of Jerusalem.

23 Whom hast thou reproached and reviled? And against whom lifted up the voice? Yea, thou dost lift up on high thine eyes Against the Holy One of Israel.

24 By the hand of thy servants Thou hast reviled the Lord, and sayest: In the multitude of my chariots I have come up to a high place of hills, The sides of Lebanon, And I cut down the height of its cedars, The choice of its firs, And I enter the high place of its extremity, The forest of its Carmel.

25 I--I have dug and drunk waters, And I dry up with the sole of my steps All floods of a bulwark.

26 Hast thou not heard from afar? --it I did, From days of old--that I formed it. Now, I have brought it in, And it is to make desolate, Ruinous heaps--fenced cities,

27 And their inhabitants are feeble-handed, They were broken down, and are dried up. They have been the herb of the field, And the greenness of the tender grass, Grass of the roofs, And blasted corn, before it hath risen up.

28 And thy sitting down, and thy going out, And thy coming in, I have known, And thy anger towards Me.

29 Because of thy anger towards Me, And thy noise--it came up into Mine ears, I have put My hook in thy nose, And My bridle in thy lips, And I have caused thee to turn back In the way in which thou camest.

30 --And this to thee [is] the sign, Food of the year [is] self-sown grain, And in the second year the spontaneous growth, And in the third year, sow ye and reap, And plant vineyards, and eat their fruit.

31 And it hath continued--the escaped Of the house of Judah that hath been left--To take root beneath, And it hath made fruit upward.

32 For from Jerusalem goeth forth a remnant, And an escape from mount Zion, The zeal of Jehovah of Hosts doth this.

33 Therefore, thus said Jehovah, Concerning the king of Asshur: He doth not come in unto this city, Nor doth he shoot there an arrow, Nor doth he come before it [with] shield, Nor doth he pour out against it a mount.

34 In the way that he came, in it he turneth back, And unto this city he doth not come in, An affirmation of Jehovah,

35 And I have covered over this city, To save it, for Mine own sake, And for the sake of David My servant.'

36 And a messenger of Jehovah goeth out, and smiteth in the camp of Asshur a hundred and eighty and five thousand; and [men] rise early in the morning, and lo, all of them [are] dead corpses.

37 And journey, and go, and turn back doth Sennacherib king of Asshur, and dwelleth in Nineveh.

38 And it cometh to pass, he is bowing himself in the house of Nisroch his god, and Adrammelech and Sharezer his sons have smitten him with the sword, and they have escaped to the land of Ararat, and Esar-Haddon his son reigneth in his stead.

Isaiah 38

1 In those days hath Hezekiah been sick unto death, and come in unto him doth Isaiah son of Amoz, the prophet, and saith unto him, `Thus said Jehovah: Give a charge to thy house, for thou [art] dying, and dost not live.'

2 And Hezekiah turneth round his face unto the wall, and prayeth unto Jehovah,

3 and saith, `I pray thee, O Jehovah, remember, I pray Thee, how I have walked habitually before Thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and that which [is] good in thine eyes I have done;' and Hezekiah weepeth--a great weeping.

4 And a word of Jehovah is unto Isaiah, saying,

5 Go, and thou hast said to Hezekiah, Thus said Jehovah, God of David thy father, `I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tear, lo, I am adding to thy days fifteen years,

6 and out of the hand of the king of Asshur I deliver thee and this city, and have covered over this city.

7 And this [is] to thee the sign from Jehovah, that Jehovah doth this thing that He hath spoken.

8 Lo, I am bringing back the shadow of the degrees that it hath gone down on the degrees of Ahaz, by the sun, backward ten degrees:' and the sun turneth back ten degrees in the degrees that it had gone down.

9 A writing of Hezekiah king of Judah concerning his being sick, when he reviveth from his sickness:

10 `I--I said in the cutting off of my days, I go in to the gates of Sheol, I have numbered the remnant of mine years.

11 I said, I do not see Jah--Jah! In the land of the living, I do not behold man any more, With the inhabitants of the world.

12 My sojourning hath departed, And been removed from me as a shepherd's tent, I have drawn together, as a weaver, my life, By weakness it cutteth me off, From day unto night Thou dost end me.

13 I have set [Him] till morning as a lion, So doth He break all my bones, From day unto night Thou dost end me.

14 As a crane--a swallow--so I chatter, I mourn as a dove, Drawn up have been mine eyes on high, O Jehovah, oppression [is] on me, be my surety.

15 --What do I say? seeing He said to me, And He Himself hath wrought, I go softly all my years for the bitterness of my soul.

16 Lord, by these do [men] live, And by all in them [is] the life of my spirit, And Thou savest me, make me also to live,

17 Lo, to peace He changed for me bitterness, And Thou hast delighted in my soul without corruption, For Thou hast cast behind Thy back all my sins.

18 For Sheol doth not confess Thee, Death doth not praise Thee, Those going down to the pit hope not for Thy truth.

19 The living, the living, he doth confess Thee.

20 Like myself to-day--a father to sons Doth make known of Thy faithfulness, O Jehovah--to save me: And my songs we sing all days of our lives In the house of Jehovah.'

21 And Isaiah saith, `Let them take a bunch of figs, and plaster over the ulcer, and he liveth.'

22 And Hezekiah saith, `What [is] the sign that I go up to the house of Jehovah!'

Isaiah 40

1 Comfort ye, comfort ye, My people, saith your God.

2 Speak to the heart of Jerusalem, and call to her, That her warfare hath been completed, That accepted hath been her punishment, That she hath received from the hand of Jehovah Double for all her sins.

3 A voice is crying--in a wilderness--Prepare ye the way of Jehovah, Make straight in a desert a highway to our God.

4 Every valley is raised up, And every mountain and hill become low, And the crooked place hath become a plain, And the entangled places a valley.

5 And revealed hath been the honour of Jehovah, And seen [it] have all flesh together, For the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken.

6 A voice is saying, `Call,' And he said, `What do I call?' All flesh [is] grass, and all its goodliness [is] As a flower of the field:

7 Withered hath grass, faded the flower, For the Spirit of Jehovah blew upon it, Surely the people [is] grass;

8 Withered hath grass, faded the flower, But a word of our God riseth for ever.

9 On a high mountain get thee up, O Zion, Proclaiming tidings, Lift up with power thy voice, O Jerusalem, proclaiming tidings, Lift up, fear not, say to cities of Judah, `Lo, your God.'

10 Lo, the Lord Jehovah with strength cometh, And His arm is ruling for Him, Lo, His hire [is] with Him, and His wage before Him.

11 As a shepherd His flock He feedeth, With His arm He gathereth lambs, And in His bosom He carrieth [them]: Suckling ones He leadeth.

12 Who hath measured in the hollow of his hand the waters? And the heavens by a span hath meted out, And comprehended in a measure the dust of the earth, And hath weighed in scales the mountains, And the hills in a balance?

13 Who hath meted out the Spirit of Jehovah, And, [being] His counsellor, doth teach Him!

14 With whom consulted He, That he causeth Him to understand? And teacheth Him in the path of judgment, And teacheth Him knowledge? And the way of understanding causeth Him to know?

15 Lo, nations as a drop from a bucket, And as small dust of the balance, have been reckoned, Lo, isles as a small thing He taketh up.

16 And Lebanon is not sufficient to burn, Nor its beasts sufficient for a burnt-offering.

17 All the nations [are] as nothing before Him, Less than nothing and emptiness, They have been reckoned to Him.

18 And unto whom do ye liken God, And what likeness do ye compare to Him?

19 The graven image poured out hath a artisan, And a refiner with gold spreadeth it over, And chains of silver he is refining.

20 He who is poor [by] heave-offerings, A tree not rotten doth choose, A skilful artisan he seeketh for it, To establish a graven image--not moved.

21 Do ye not know--do ye not hear? Hath it not been declared from the first to you? Have ye not understood [From] the foundations of the earth?

22 He who is sitting on the circle of the earth, And its inhabitants [are] as grasshoppers, He who is stretching out as a thin thing the heavens, And spreadeth them as a tent to dwell in.

23 He who is making princes become nothing, Judges of earth as emptiness hath made;

24 Yea, they have not been planted, Yea, they have not been sown, Yea, not taking root in the earth is their stock, And also He hath blown upon them, and they wither, And a whirlwind as stubble taketh them away.

25 And unto whom do ye liken Me, And [am] I equal? saith the Holy One.

26 Lift up on high your eyes, And see--who hath prepared these? He who is bringing out by number their host, To all of them by name He calleth, By abundance of strength (And [he is] strong in power) not one is lacking.

27 Why sayest thou, O Jacob? and speakest thou, O Israel? `My way hath been hid from Jehovah, And from my God my judgment passeth over.'

28 Hast thou not known? hast thou not heard? The God of the age--Jehovah, Preparer of the ends of the earth, Is not wearied nor fatigued, There is no searching of His understanding.

29 He is giving power to the weary, And to those not strong He increaseth might.

30 Even youths are wearied and fatigued, And young men utterly stumble,

31 But those expecting Jehovah pass [to] power, They raise up the pinion as eagles, They run and are not fatigued, They go on and do not faint!

Isaiah 41

1 Keep silent towards Me, O isles, And the peoples pass on [to] power, They come nigh, then they speak, `Together--to judgment we draw near.'

2 Who stirred up from the east a righteous one? He calleth him to His foot, He giveth before him nations, And kings He causeth him to rule, He giveth [them] as dust [to] his sword, As driven stubble [to] his bow.

3 He pursueth them, he passeth over in safety A path with his feet he entereth not.

4 Who hath wrought and done, Calling the generations from the first? I, Jehovah, the first, and with the last I [am] He.

5 Seen have isles and fear, ends of the earth tremble, They have drawn near, yea, they come.

6 Each his neighbour they help, And to his brother he saith, `Be strong.'

7 And strengthen doth an artisan the refiner, A smoother [with] a hammer, Him who is beating [on] an anvil, Saying, `For joining it [is] good,' And he strengtheneth it with nails, it is not moved!

8 --And thou, O Israel, My servant, Jacob, whom I have chosen, Seed of Abraham, My lover,

9 Whom I have taken hold of, from the ends of the earth, And from its near places I have called thee, And I say to thee, My servant Thou [art], I have chosen thee, and not rejected thee.

10 Be not afraid, for with thee I [am], Look not around, for I [am] thy God, I have strengthened thee, Yea, I have helped thee, yea, I upheld thee, With the right hand of My righteousness.

11 Lo, all those displeased with thee, They are ashamed and blush, They are as nothing, yea, perish Do the men who strive with thee.

12 Thou seekest them, and findest them not, The men who debate with thee, They are as nothing, yea, as nothing, The men who war with thee.

13 For I, Jehovah thy God, Am strengthening thy right hand, He who is saying to thee, `Fear not, I have helped thee.'

14 Fear not, O worm Jacob, ye men of Israel, I helped thee, an affirmation of Jehovah, Even thy redeemer, the Holy One of Israel.

15 Lo, I have set thee for a new sharp threshing instrument, Possessing teeth, thou threshest mountains, And beatest small, and hills as chaff thou makest.

16 Thou winnowest them, and a wind lifteth them up, And a whirlwind scattereth them, And thou--thou rejoicest in Jehovah, In the Holy One of Israel dost boast thyself.

17 The poor and the needy are seeking water, And there is none, Their tongue with thirst hath failed, I, Jehovah do answer them, The God of Israel--I forsake them not.

18 I open on high places rivers, And in midst of valleys fountains, I make a wilderness become a pond of water, And a dry land become springs of water.

19 I give in a wilderness the cedar, Shittah, and myrtle, and oil-tree, I set in a desert the fir-pine and box-wood together.

20 So that they see, and know, And regard, and act wisely together, For the hand of Jehovah hath done this, And the Holy One of Israel hath prepared it.

21 Bring near your cause, saith Jehovah, Bring nigh your mighty ones, saith the king of Jacob.

22 They bring nigh, and declare to us that which doth happen, The first things--what they [are] declare ye, And we set our heart, and know their latter end, Or the coming things cause us to hear.

23 Declare the things that are coming hereafter, And we know that ye [are] gods, Yea, ye may do good or do evil, And we look around and see [it] together.

24 Lo, ye [are] of nothing, and your work of nought, An abomination--it fixeth on you.

25 I have stirred up [one] from the north, And he cometh, From the rising of the sun he calleth in My name, And he cometh in [on] prefects as [on] clay, And as a potter treadeth down mire.

26 Who hath declared from the first, and we know? And beforetime, and we say, `Righteous?' yea, there is none declaring, Yea, there is none proclaiming, Yea, there is none hearing your sayings.

27 First to Zion, Behold, behold them, And to Jerusalem one proclaiming tidings I give,

28 And I see that there is no man, Yea, of these that there is no counsellor, And I ask them, and they return word:

29 `Lo, all of them [are] vanity, Nought [are] their works, Wind and emptiness their molten images!'

Isaiah 42

1 Lo, My servant, I take hold on him, My chosen one--My soul hath accepted, I have put My Spirit upon him, Judgment to nations he bringeth forth.

2 He doth not cry, nor lift up, Nor cause his voice to be heard, in the street.

3 A bruised reed he breaketh not, And dim flax he quencheth not, To truth he bringeth forth judgment.

4 He doth not become weak nor bruised, Till he setteth judgment in the earth, And for his law isles wait with hope.

5 Thus said God, Jehovah, preparing The heavens, and stretching them out, Spreading out the earth and its productions, Giving breath to the people on it, And spirit to those walking in it.

6 I, Jehovah, did call thee in righteousness, And I lay hold on thy hand, and keep thee, And I give thee for a covenant of a people, And a light of nations.

7 To open the eyes of the blind, To bring forth from prison the bound one, From the house of restraint those sitting in darkness.

8 I [am] Jehovah, this [is] My name, And Mine honour to another I give not, Nor My praise to graven images.

9 The former things, lo, have come, And new things I am declaring, Before they spring up I cause you to hear.

10 Sing to Jehovah a new song, His praise from the end of the earth, Ye who are going down to the sea, and its fulness, Isles, and their inhabitants.

11 The wilderness and its cities do lift up [the voice], The villages Kedar doth inhabit, Sing do the inhabitants of Sela, From the top of mountains they cry.

12 They ascribe to Jehovah honour, And His praise in the isles they declare.

13 Jehovah as a mighty one goeth forth. As a man of war He stirreth up zeal, He crieth, yea, He shrieketh, Against His enemies He showeth Himself mighty.

14 I have kept silent from of old, I keep silent, I refrain myself, As a travailing woman I cry out, I desolate and swallow up together.

15 I make waste mountains and hills, And all their herbs I dry up, And I have made rivers become isles, And ponds I dry up.

16 And I have caused the blind to go, In a way they have not known, In paths they have not known I cause them to tread, I make a dark place before them become light, And unlevelled places become a plain, These [are] the things I have done to them, And I have not forsaken them.

17 Removed backward--utterly ashamed, Are those trusting in a graven image, Those saying to a molten image, `Ye [are] our gods.'

18 Ye deaf, hear; and ye blind, look to see.

19 Who [is] blind but My servant? And deaf as My messenger I send? Who [is] blind as he who is at peace, Yea, blind, as the servant of Jehovah?

20 Seeing many things, and thou observest not, Opening ears, and he heareth not.

21 Jehovah hath delight for the sake of His righteousness, He magnifieth law, and maketh honourable.

22 And this [is] a people seized and spoiled, Snared in holes--all of them, And in houses of restraint they were hidden, They have been for a prey, And there is no deliverer, A spoil, and none is saying, `Restore.'

23 Who among you giveth ear [to] this? Attendeth, and heareth afterwards.

24 Who hath given Jacob for a spoil, And Israel to the spoilers? Is it not Jehovah--He against whom we sinned? Yea, they have not been willing in His ways to walk, Nor have they hearkened to His law.

25 And He poureth on him fury, His anger, and the strength of battle, And it setteth him on fire round about, And he hath not known, And it burneth against him, and he layeth it not to heart!

Isaiah 43

1 And now, thus said Jehovah, Thy Creator, O Jacob, and thy Fashioner, O Israel, Be not afraid, for I have redeemed thee, I have called on thy name--thou [art] Mine.

2 When thou passest into waters, I [am] with thee, And into floods, they do not overflow thee, When thou goest into fire, thou art not burnt, And a flame doth not burn against thee.

3 For I--Jehovah thy God, The Holy One of Israel, thy Saviour, I have appointed Egypt thine atonement, Cush and Seba in thy stead.

4 Since thou wast precious in Mine eyes, Thou wast honoured, and I have loved thee, And I appoint men in thy stead, And peoples instead of thy life.

5 Be not afraid, for I [am] with thee, From the east I bring in thy seed, And from the west I gather thee.

6 I am saying to the north, `Give up,' And to the south, `Restrain not.' Bring in My sons from afar, And My daughters from the end of the earth.

7 Every one who is called by My name, Even for My honour I have created him, I have formed him, yea, I have made him.

8 He brought out a blind people who have eyes, And deaf ones who have ears.

9 All the nations have been gathered together, And the peoples are assembled, Who among them declareth this, And former things causeth us to hear? They give their witnesses, And they are declared righteous, And they hear and say, `Truth.'

10 Ye [are] My witnesses, an affirmation of Jehovah, And My servant whom I have chosen, So that ye know and give credence to Me, And understand that I [am] He, Before Me there was no God formed, And after Me there is none.

11 I--I [am] Jehovah, And besides Me there is no saviour.

12 I--I declared, and saved, and proclaimed, And there is no stranger with you, And ye [are] My witnesses, an affirmation of Jehovah, And I [am] God.

13 Even from the day I [am] He, And there is no deliverer from My hand, I work, and who doth turn it back?

14 Thus said Jehovah, your Redeemer, The Holy One of Israel: `For your sake I have sent to Babylon, And caused bars to descend--all of them, And the Chaldeans, whose song [is] in the ships.

15 I [am] Jehovah, your Holy One, Creator of Israel, your King.'

16 Thus said Jehovah, Who is giving in the sea a way, And in the strong waters a path.

17 Who is bringing forth chariot and horse, A force, even a strong one: `Together they lie down--they rise not, They have been extinguished, As flax they have been quenched.'

18 Remember not former things, And ancient things consider not.

19 Lo, I am doing a new thing, now it springeth up, Do ye not know it? Yea, I put in a wilderness a way, In a desolate place--floods.

20 Honour me doth the beast of the field, Dragons and daughters of an ostrich, For I have given in a wilderness waters, Floods in a desolate place, To give drink to My people--My chosen.

21 This people I have formed for Myself, My praise they recount.

22 And Me thou hast not called, O Jacob, For thou hast been wearied of me, O Israel,

23 Thou hast not brought in to Me, The lamb of thy burnt-offerings, And [with] thy sacrifices thou hast not honoured Me, I have not caused thee to serve with a present, Nor wearied thee with frankincense.

24 Thou hast not bought for Me with money sweet cane, And [with] the fat of thy sacrifices hast not filled Me, Only--thou hast caused Me to serve with thy sins, Thou hast wearied Me with thine iniquities.

25 I--I [am] He who is blotting out Thy transgressions for Mine own sake, And thy sins I do not remember.

26 Cause me to remember--we are judged together, Declare thou that thou mayest be justified.

27 Thy first father sinned, And thine interpreters transgressed against me,

28 And I pollute princes of the sanctuary, And I give Jacob to destruction, and Israel to revilings!

Isaiah 44

1 And now, hear, O Jacob, My servant, And Israel, whom I have fixed on:

2 Thus said Jehovah, thy Maker, and thy Former, From the womb He doth help thee; Fear not, my servant Jacob, And Jeshurun, whom I have fixed on.

3 For I pour waters on a thirsty one, And floods on a dry land, I pour My Spirit on thy seed, And My blessing on thine offspring.

4 And they have sprung up as among grass, As willows by streams of water.

5 This [one] saith, For Jehovah I [am], And this calleth [himself] by the name of Jacob, And this [one] writeth [with] his hand, `For Jehovah,' and by the name of Israel surnameth himself.

6 Thus said Jehovah, king of Israel, And his Redeemer, Jehovah of Hosts: `I [am] the first, and I the last, And besides Me there is no God.

7 And who as I, doth call and declare it, And arrange it for Me, Since My placing the people of antiquity, And things that are coming, And those that do come, declare they to them?

8 Fear not, nor be afraid, Have I not from that time caused thee to hear, and declared? And ye [are] My witnesses, Is there a God besides Me? yea, there is none, A Rock I have not known.

9 Framers of a graven image [are] all of them emptiness, And their desirable things do not profit, And their own witnesses they [are], They see not, nor know, that they may be ashamed.

10 Who hath formed a god, And a molten image poured out--not profitable?

11 Lo, all his companions are ashamed, As to artisans--they [are] of men, All of them gather together, they stand up, They fear, they are ashamed together.

12 He hath wrought iron [with] an axe, And hath wrought with coals, And with hammers doth form it, And doth work it by his powerful arm, Yea, he is hungry, and there is no power, He doth not drink water, and he is wearied.

13 He hath wrought [with] wood, He hath stretched out a rule, He doth mark it out with a line, He maketh it with carving tools, And with a compass he marketh it out, And maketh it according to the form of a man, According to the beauty of a man, To remain in the house.

14 Cutting down to himself cedars, He taketh also a cypress, and an oak, And he strengtheneth [it] for himself Among the trees of a forest, He hath planted an ash, and the shower doth nourish [it].

15 And it hath been for man to burn, And he taketh of them, and becometh warm, Yea, he kindleth [it], and hath baked bread, Yea, he maketh a god, and boweth himself, He hath made it a graven image, And he falleth down to it.

16 Half of it he hath burnt in the fire, By [this] half of it he eateth flesh, He roasteth a roasting, and is satisfied, Yea, he is warm, and saith: `Aha, I have become warm, I have enjoyed the light.

17 And its remnant for a god he hath made--For his graven image, He falleth down to it, and worshippeth, And prayeth unto it, and he saith, `Deliver me, for my god thou [art].'

18 They have not known, nor do they understand, For He hath daubed their eyes from seeing, Their heart from acting wisely.

19 And none doth turn [it] back unto his heart, Nor hath knowledge nor understanding to say, `Half of it I have burned in the fire, Yea, also, I have baked bread over its coals, I roast flesh and I eat, And its remnant for an abomination I make, To the stock of a tree I fall down.'

20 Feeding on ashes, the heart is deceived, It hath turned him aside, And he delivereth not his soul, nor saith: `Is there not a lie in my right hand?'

21 Remember these, O Jacob, and Israel, For My servant thou [art], I formed thee, a servant to Me thou [art], O Israel, thou dost not forget Me.

22 I have blotted out, as [by] a thick cloud, Thy transgressions, And as [by] a cloud thy sins, Return unto Me, for I have redeemed thee.

23 Sing, O heavens, for Jehovah hath wrought, Shout, O lower parts of earth, Break forth, O mountains, with singing, Forest, and every tree in it, For Jehovah hath redeemed Jacob, And in Israel He doth beautify Himself.

24 Thus said Jehovah, thy redeemer, And thy framer from the womb: `I [am] Jehovah, doing all things, Stretching out the heavens by Myself, Spreading out the earth--who [is] with Me?

25 Making void the tokens of devisers, And diviners it maketh mad, Turning the wise backward, And their knowledge it maketh foolish.

26 Confirming the word of His servant, The counsel of His messengers it perfecteth, Who is saying of Jerusalem, She is inhabited, And of cities of Judah, They shall be built, and her wastes I raise up,

27 Who is saying to the deep, Be dry, and thy rivers I cause to dry up,

28 Who is saying of Cyrus, My shepherd, And all my delight He doth perfect, So as to say of Jerusalem, Thou art built, And of the temple, Thou art founded.

Isaiah 45

1 Thus said Jehovah, To His anointed, to Cyrus, Whose right hand I have laid hold on, To subdue nations before him, Yea, loins of kings I loose, To open before him two-leaved doors, Yea, gates are not shut:

2 `I go before thee, and crooked places make straight, Two-leaved doors of brass I shiver, And bars of iron I cut asunder,

3 And have given to thee treasures of darkness, Even treasures of secret places, So that thou knowest that I, Jehovah, Who am calling on thy name--[am] the God of Israel.

4 For the sake of my servant Jacob, And of Israel My chosen, I call also thee by thy name, I surname thee, And thou hast not known Me.

5 I [am] Jehovah, and there is none else, Except Me there is no God, I gird thee, and thou hast not known Me.

6 So that they know from the rising of the sun, And from the west, that there is none besides Me, I [am] Jehovah, and there is none else,

7 Forming light, and preparing darkness, Making peace, and preparing evil, I [am] Jehovah, doing all these things.'

8 Drop, ye heavens, from above, And clouds do cause righteousness to flow, Earth openeth, and they are fruitful, Salvation and righteousness spring up together, I, Jehovah, have prepared it.

9 Woe [to] him who is striving with his Former, (A potsherd with potsherds of the ground!) Doth clay say to its Framer, `What dost thou?' And thy work, `He hath no hands?'

10 Woe [to] him who is saying to a father, `What dost thou beget?' Or to a wife, `What dost thou bring forth?

11 Thus said Jehovah, The Holy One of Israel, and his Former: Ask Me of the things coming concerning My sons, Yea, concerning the work of My hands, ye command Me.'

12 I made earth, and man on it prepared, I--My hands stretched out the heavens, And all their host I have commanded.

13 I have stirred him up in righteousness, And all his ways I make straight, He doth build My city, and My captivity doth send out, Not for price, nor for bribe, said Jehovah of Hosts.

14 Thus said Jehovah, `The labour of Egypt, And the merchandise of Cush, And of the Sebaim--men of measure, Unto thee pass over, and thine they are, After thee they go, in fetters they pass over, And unto thee they bow themselves, Unto thee they pray: Only in thee [is] God, And there is none else, no [other] God.

15 Surely Thou [art] a God hiding Thyself, God of Israel--Saviour!

16 They have been ashamed, And they have even blushed--all of them, Together gone in confusion have those carving images.

17 Israel hath been saved in Jehovah, A salvation age-during! Ye are not ashamed nor confounded Unto the ages of eternity!

18 For thus said Jehovah, Creator of heaven, He is God, Former of earth, and its Maker, He established it--not empty He prepared it, For inhabiting He formed it: `I [am] Jehovah, and there is none else.

19 Not in secret have I spoken, in a dark place of the earth, I have not said to the seed of Jacob, In vain seek ye Me, I [am] Jehovah, speaking righteousness, Declaring uprightness.

20 Be gathered, and come in, Come nigh together, ye escaped of the nations, They have not known, Who are lifting up the wood of their graven image, And praying unto a god [that] saveth not.

21 Declare ye, and bring near, Yea, they take counsel together, Who hath proclaimed this from of old? From that time hath declared it? Is it not I--Jehovah? And there is no other god besides Me, A God righteous and saving, there is none save Me.

22 Turn to Me, and be saved, all ends of the earth, For I [am] God, and there is none else.

23 By Myself I have sworn, Gone out from my mouth in righteousness hath a word, And it turneth not back, That to Me, bow doth every knee, every tongue swear.

24 Only in Jehovah, said hath one, Have I righteousness and strength, Unto Him he cometh in, And ashamed are all those displeased with Him.

25 In Jehovah are all the seed of Israel justified, And they boast themselves.'

Isaiah 46

1 Bowed down hath Bel, stooping is Nebo, Their idols have been for the beast and for cattle, Your burdens are loaded, a burden to the weary.

2 They have stooped, they have bowed together, They have not been able to deliver the burden, And themselves into captivity have gone.

3 Hearken unto Me, O house of Jacob, And all the remnant of Israel, Who are borne from the belly, Who are carried from the womb,

4 Even to old age I [am] He, and to grey hairs I carry, I made, and I bear, yea, I carry and deliver.

5 To whom do ye liken Me, and make equal? And compare Me, that we may be like?

6 --They are pouring out gold from a bag, And silver on the beam they weigh, They hire a refiner, and he maketh it a god, They fall down, yea, they bow themselves.

7 They lift him up on the shoulder, They carry him, and cause him to rest in his place, And he standeth, from his place he moveth not, Yea, one crieth unto him, and he answereth not, From his adversity he saveth him not.

8 Remember this, and shew yourselves men, Turn [it] back, O transgressors, to the heart.

9 Remember former things of old, For I [am] Mighty, and there is none else, God--and there is none like Me.

10 Declaring from the beginning the latter end, And from of old that which hath not been done, Saying, `My counsel doth stand, And all My delight I do.'

11 Calling from the east a ravenous bird, From a far land the man of My counsel, Yea, I have spoken, yea, I bring it in, I have formed [it], yea, I do it.

12 Hearken unto Me, ye mighty in heart, Who are far from righteousness.

13 I have brought near My righteousness, It is not far off, And My salvation--it doth not tarry, And I have given in Zion salvation, To Israel My glory!

Isaiah 47

1 Come down, and sit on the dust, O virgin daughter of Babylon, Sit on the earth, there is no throne, O daughter of the Chaldeans, For no more do they cry to thee, `O tender and delicate one.'

2 Take millstones, and grind flour, Remove thy veil, draw up the skirt, Uncover the leg, pass over the floods.

3 Revealed is thy nakedness, yea, seen is thy reproach, Vengeance I take, and I meet not a man.

4 Our redeemer [is] Jehovah of Hosts, His name [is] the Holy One of Israel.

5 Sit silent, and go into darkness, O daughter of the Chaldeans, For no more do they cry to thee, `Mistress of kingdoms.'

6 I have been wroth against My people, I have polluted Mine inheritance And I give them into thy hand, Thou hast not appointed for them mercies, On the aged thou hast made thy yoke very heavy,

7 And thou sayest, `To the age I am mistress,' While thou hast not laid these things to thy heart, Thou hast not remembered the latter end of it.

8 And now, hear this, O luxurious one, Who is sitting confidently--Who is saying in her heart, `I [am], and none else, I sit not a widow, nor know bereavement.'

9 And come in to thee do these two things, In a moment, in one day, childlessness and widowhood, According to their perfection they have come upon thee, In the multitude of thy sorceries, In the exceeding might of thy charms.

10 And thou art confident in thy wickedness, Thou hast said, `There is none seeing me,' Thy wisdom and thy knowledge, It is turning thee back, And thou sayest in thy heart, `I [am], and none else.'

11 And come in on thee hath evil, Thou knowest not its rising, And fall on thee doth mischief, Thou art not able to pacify it, And come on thee suddenly doth desolation, Thou knowest not.

12 Stand, I pray thee, in thy charms, And in the multitude of thy sorceries, In which thou hast laboured from thy youth, It may be thou art able to profit, It may be thou dost terrify!

13 Thou hast been wearied in the multitude of thy counsels, Stand up, I pray thee, and save thee, Let the charmers of the heavens, Those looking on the stars, Those teaching concerning the months, From those things that come on thee!

14 Lo, they have been as stubble! Fire hath burned them, They deliver not themselves from the power of the flame, There is not a coal to warm them, a light to sit before it.

15 So have they been to thee with whom thou hast laboured, Thy merchants from thy youth, Each to his passage they have wandered, Thy saviour is not!

Isaiah 48

1 Hear ye this, O house of Jacob, Who are called by the name of Israel, And from the waters of Judah came out, Who are swearing by the name of Jehovah, And of the God of Israel make mention, Not in truth nor in righteousness.

2 For from the Holy City they have been called, And on the God of Israel been supported, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name.

3 The former things from that time I declared, And from my mouth they have gone forth, And I proclaim them, Suddenly I have done, and it cometh.

4 From my knowing that thou art obstinate, And a sinew of iron thy neck, And thy forehead brass,

5 And I declare to thee from that time, Before it cometh I have caused thee to hear, Lest thou say, `Mine idol hath done them, And my graven image, And my molten image did command them.

6 Thou hast heard, see the whole of it, And ye, do ye not declare? I have caused thee to hear new things from this time, And things reserved that ye knew not.

7 Now they have been produced and not from that time, Yea, before the day, and thou hast not heard them, Lest thou say, `Lo, I have known them.'

8 Yea, thou hast not heard, Yea, thou hast not known, Yea, from that time not opened hath thine ear, For I have known thou dealest treacherously, And `Transgressor from the belly,' One is crying to thee.

9 For My name's sake I defer Mine anger, And My praise I restrain for thee, So as not to cut thee off.

10 Lo, I have refined thee, and not with silver, I have chosen thee in a furnace of affliction.

11 For My sake, for Mine own sake, I do [it], For how is it polluted? And Mine honour to another I give not.

12 Hearken to me, O Jacob, and Israel, My called one, I [am] He, I [am] first, and I [am] last;

13 Also, My hand hath founded earth, And My right hand stretched out the heavens, I am calling unto them, they stand together.

14 Be gathered all of you, and hear, Who among them did declare these things? Jehovah hath loved him, He doth His pleasure on Babylon, And His arm [is on] the Chaldeans.

15 I--I have spoken, yea, I have called him, I have brought him in, And he hath made prosperous his way.

16 Come ye near unto me, hear this, Not from the beginning in secret spake I, From the time of its being, there [am] I, And now the Lord Jehovah hath sent me, and His Spirit.

17 Thus said Jehovah, thy redeemer, The Holy One of Israel, `I [am] Jehovah thy God, teaching thee to profit, Causing thee to tread in the way thou goest.

18 O that thou hadst attended to My commands, Then as a river is thy peace, And thy righteousness as billows of the sea,

19 And as sand is thy seed, And the offspring of thy bowels as its gravel, Not cut off nor destroyed his name before Me.

20 Go out from Babylon, flee from the Chaldeans, With a voice of singing declare, Cause ye this to be heard, Bring it forth unto the end of the earth, Say, Redeemed hath Jehovah His servant Jacob.

21 And they have not thirsted in waste places, He hath caused them to go on, Waters from a rock he hath caused to flow to them, Yea, he cleaveth a rock, and flow do waters.

22 There is no peace, said Jehovah, to the wicked!

Isaiah 49

1 Hearken, O isles, unto me, And attend, O peoples, from afar, Jehovah from the womb hath called me, From the bowels of my mother He hath made mention of my name.

2 And he maketh my mouth as a sharp sword, In the shadow of His hand He hath hid me, And He maketh me for a clear arrow, In His quiver He hath hid me.

3 And He saith to me, `My servant Thou art, O Israel, In whom I beautify Myself.'

4 And I said, `For a vain thing I laboured, For emptiness and vanity my power I consumed, But my judgment [is] with Jehovah, And my wage with my God.

5 And now, said Jehovah, who is forming me from the belly for a servant to Him, To bring back Jacob unto Him, (Though Israel is not gathered, Yet I am honoured in the eyes of Jehovah, And my God hath been my strength.)

6 And He saith, `It hath been a light thing That thou art to Me for a servant To raise up the tribes of Jacob, And the preserved of Israel to bring back, And I have given thee for a light of nations, To be My salvation unto the end of the earth.'

7 Thus said Jehovah, Redeemer of Israel, His Holy One, To the despised in soul, To the abominated of a nation, To the servant of rulers: `Kings see, and have risen, princes, and worship, For the sake of Jehovah, who is faithful, The Holy of Israel, and He chooseth thee.'

8 Thus said Jehovah: `In a time of good pleasure I answered thee, And in a day of salvation I helped thee, And I keep thee, and give thee, For a covenant of the people, To establish the earth, To cause to inherit desolate inheritances.

9 To say to the bound, Go out, To those in darkness, Be uncovered. On the ways they feed, And in all high places is their pasture.

10 They do not hunger, nor thirst, Nor smite them doth mirage and sun, For He who is pitying them doth lead them, And by fountains of waters doth tend them.

11 And I have made all My mountains for a way, And My highways are lifted up.

12 Lo, these from afar come in, And lo, these from the north, and from the sea, And these from the land of Sinim.

13 Sing, O heavens, and joy, O earth, And break forth, O mountains, with singing, For comforted hath Jehovah His people, And His afflicted ones He doth pity.

14 And Zion saith, `Jehovah hath forsaken me, And my Lord hath forgotten me.'

15 Forget doth a woman her suckling, The loved one--the son of her womb? Yea, these forget--but I--I forget not thee.

16 Lo, on the palms of the hand I have graven thee, Thy walls [are] before Me continually.

17 Hastened have those building thee, Those destroying thee, and laying thee waste, go out from thee.

18 Lift up round about thine eyes and see, All of them have been gathered, They have come to thee. I live, an affirmation of Jehovah! Surely all of them as an ornament thou puttest on, And thou bindest them on like a bride.

19 Because thy wastes, and thy desolate places, And the land of thy ruins, Surely now are straitened because of inhabitants, And far off have been those consuming thee.

20 Again do the sons of thy bereavement say in thine ears: `The place is too strait for me, Come nigh to me--and I dwell.'

21 And thou hast said in thy heart: `Who hath begotten for me--these? And I bereaved and gloomy, A captive, and turned aside, And these--who hath nourished? Lo, I--I was left by myself, these--whence [are] they?

22 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: `Lo, I lift up unto nations My hand, And unto peoples I raise up Mine ensign, And they have brought thy sons in the bosom, And thy daughters on the shoulder are carried.

23 And kings have been thy nursing fathers, And their princesses thy nursing mothers; Face to the earth--they bow down to thee, And the dust of thy feet they lick up, And thou hast known that I [am] Jehovah, That those expecting Me are not ashamed.

24 Is prey taken from the mighty? And the captive of the righteous delivered?

25 For thus said Jehovah: Even the captive of the mighty is taken, And the prey of the terrible is delivered, And with thy striver I strive, and thy sons I save.

26 And I have caused thine oppressors to eat their own flesh, And as new wine they drink their own blood, And known have all flesh that I, Jehovah, Thy saviour, and thy redeemer, [Am] the Mighty One of Jacob!'

Isaiah 50

1 Thus said Jehovah: `Where [is] this--the bill of your mother's divorce, Whom I sent away? Or to which of My creditors have I sold you? Lo, for your iniquities ye have been sold, And for your transgressions Hath your mother been sent away.

2 Wherefore have I come, and there is no one? I called, and there is none answering, Hath My hand been at all short of redemption? And is there not in me power to deliver? Lo, by My rebuke I dry up a sea, I make rivers a wilderness, Their fish stinketh, for there is no water, And dieth with thirst.

3 I clothe the heavens [with] blackness, And sackcloth I make their covering.

4 The Lord Jehovah hath given to me The tongue of taught ones, To know to aid the weary [by] a word, He waketh morning by morning, He waketh for me an ear to hear as taught ones.

5 The Lord Jehovah opened for me the ear, And I rebelled not--backward I moved not.

6 My back I have given to those smiting, And my cheeks to those plucking out, My face I hid not from shame and spitting.

7 And the Lord Jehovah giveth help to me, Therefore I have not been ashamed, Therefore I have set my face as a flint, And I know that I am not ashamed.

8 Near [is] He who is justifying me, Who doth contend with me? We stand together, who [is] mine opponent? Let him come nigh unto me.

9 Lo, the Lord Jehovah giveth help to me, Who [is] he that declareth me wicked? Lo, all of them as a garment wear out, A moth doth eat them.

10 Who [is] among you, fearing Jehovah, Hearkening to the voice of His servant, That hath walked in dark places, And there is no brightness for him? Let him trust in the name of Jehovah, And lean upon his God.

11 Lo, all ye kindling a fire, girding on sparks, Walk ye in the light of your fire, And in the sparks ye have caused to burn, From my hand hath this been to you, In grief ye lie down!

Isaiah 51

1 Hearken unto Me, ye pursuing righteousness, Seeking Jehovah, Look attentively unto the rock--ye have been hewn, And unto the hole of the pit--ye have been digged.

2 Look attentively unto Abraham your father, And unto Sarah--she bringeth you forth, For--one--I have called him, And I bless him, and multiply him.

3 For Jehovah hath comforted Zion, He hath comforted all her wastes, And He setteth her wilderness as Eden, And her desert as a garden of Jehovah, Joy, yea, gladness is found in her, Confession, and the voice of song.

4 Attend unto Me, O My people, And, O My nation, unto Me give ear. For a law from Me goeth out, And My judgment to the light, Peoples I do cause to rest.

5 Near [is] My righteousness, Gone out hath My salvation and Mine arms, Peoples they judge, on Me isles do wait, Yea, on Mine arm they do wait with hope.

6 Lift ye up to the heavens your eyes, And look attentively unto the earth beneath, For the heavens as smoke have vanished, And the earth as a garment weareth out, And its inhabitants as gnats do die, And My salvation is to the age, And My righteousness is not broken.

7 Hearken unto Me, ye who know righteousness, A people, in whose heart [is] My law, Fear ye not the reproach of men, And for their reviling be not affrighted,

8 For as a garment eat them doth a moth, And as wool eat them doth a worm, And My righteousness is to the age, And My salvation to all generations.

9 Awake, awake, put on strength, O arm of Jehovah, Awake, as [in] days of old, generations of the ages, Art not Thou it that is hewing down Rahab, Piercing a dragon!

10 Art not Thou it that is drying up a sea, Waters of a great deep? That hath made deep places of a sea A way for the passing of the redeemed?

11 And the ransomed of Jehovah turn back, And they have come to Zion with singing, And joy age-during [is] on their head, Gladness and joy they attain, Fled away have sorrow and sighing,

12 I--I [am] He--your comforter, Who [art] thou--and thou art afraid of man? he dieth! And of the son of man--grass he is made!

13 And thou dost forget Jehovah thy maker, Who is stretching out the heavens, and founding earth, And thou dost fear continually all the day, Because of the fury of the oppressor, As he hath prepared to destroy. And where [is] the fury of the oppressor?

14 Hastened hath a wanderer to be loosed, And he doth not die at the pit, And his bread is not lacking.

15 And I [am] Jehovah thy God, Quieting the sea, when its billows roar, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name.

16 And I put My words in thy mouth, And with the shadow of My hand have covered thee, To plant the heavens, and to found earth, And to say to Zion, `My people [art] thou.'

17 Stir thyself, stir thyself, rise, Jerusalem, Who hast drunk from the hand of Jehovah The cup of His fury, The goblet, the cup of trembling, thou hast drunk, Thou hast wrung out.

18 There is not a leader to her Out of all the sons she hath borne, And there is none laying hold on her hand Out of all the sons she hath nourished.

19 These two are meeting thee, who is moved for thee? Spoiling and destruction-- Famine and sword, who--I comfort thee?

20 Thy sons have been wrapped up, they have lain down, At the head of all out places, as a wild ox [in] a net, They are full of the fury of Jehovah, The rebuke of Thy God.

21 Therefore, hear, I pray thee, this, O afflicted and drunken one, and not with wine,

22 Thus said thy Lord Jehovah, and thy God, He pleadeth [for] his people: `Lo, I have taken out of thy hand the cup of trembling, The goblet, the cup of My fury, Thou dost not add to drink it any more.

23 And I have put it into the hand of those afflicting thee, Who have said to thy soul, Bow down, and we pass over, And thou makest as the earth thy body, And as the street to those passing by!'

Isaiah 52

1 Awake, awake, put on thy strength, O Zion, Put on the garments of thy beauty, Jerusalem--the Holy City; For enter no more into thee again, Do the uncircumcised and unclean.

2 Shake thyself from dust, arise, sit, O Jerusalem, Bands of thy neck have loosed themselves, O captive, daughter of Zion.

3 For thus said Jehovah: `For nought ye have been sold, And not by money are ye redeemed.'

4 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: `To Egypt My people went down at first to sojourn there, And Asshur--for nought he hath oppressed it.

5 And now, what--to Me here, An affirmation of Jehovah, That taken is My people for nought? Its rulers cause howling, --an affirmation of Jehovah, And continually all the day My name is despised.

6 Therefore doth My people know My name, Therefore, in that day, Surely I [am] He who is speaking, behold Me.'

7 How comely on the mountains, Have been the feet of one proclaiming tidings, Sounding peace, proclaiming good tidings, Sounding salvation, Saying to Zion, `Reigned hath thy God.'

8 The voice of thy watchmen! They have lifted up the voice, together they cry aloud, Because eye to eye they see, in Jehovah's turning back [to] Zion.

9 Break forth, sing together, O wastes of Jerusalem, For Jehovah hath comforted His people, He hath redeemed Jerusalem.

10 Jehovah hath made bare His holy arm Before the eyes of all the nations, And seen have all the ends of the earth, The salvation of our God.

11 Turn aside, turn aside, go out thence, The unclean touch not, go out from her midst, Be ye pure, who are bearing the weapons of Jehovah.

12 For not in haste do ye go out, Yea, with flight ye go not on, For going before you [is] Jehovah, And gathering you [is] the God of Israel!

13 Lo, My servant doth act wisely, He is high, and hath been lifted up, And hath been very high.

14 As astonished at thee have been many, (So marred by man his appearance, And his form by sons of men.)

15 So doth he sprinkle many nations. Concerning him kings shut their mouth, For that which was not recounted to them they have seen, And that which they had not heard they have understood!

Isaiah 53

1 Who hath given credence to that which we heard? And the arm of Jehovah, On whom hath it been revealed?

2 Yea, he cometh up as a tender plant before Him, And as a root out of a dry land, He hath no form, nor honour, when we observe him, Nor appearance, when we desire him.

3 He is despised, and left of men, A man of pains, and acquainted with sickness, And as one hiding the face from us, He is despised, and we esteemed him not.

4 Surely our sicknesses he hath borne, And our pains--he hath carried them, And we--we have esteemed him plagued, Smitten of God, and afflicted.

5 And he is pierced for our transgressions, Bruised for our iniquities, The chastisement of our peace [is] on him, And by his bruise there is healing to us.

6 All of us like sheep have wandered, Each to his own way we have turned, And Jehovah hath caused to meet on him, The punishment of us all.

7 It hath been exacted, and he hath answered, And he openeth not his mouth, As a lamb to the slaughter he is brought, And as a sheep before its shearers is dumb, And he openeth not his mouth.

8 By restraint and by judgment he hath been taken, And of his generation who doth meditate, That he hath been cut off from the land of the living? By the transgression of My people he is plagued,

9 And it appointeth with the wicked his grave, And with the rich [are] his high places, Because he hath done no violence, Nor [is] deceit in his mouth.

10 And Jehovah hath delighted to bruise him, He hath made him sick, If his soul doth make an offering for guilt, He seeth seed--he prolongeth days, And the pleasure of Jehovah in his hand doth prosper.

11 Of the labour of his soul he seeth--he is satisfied, Through his knowledge give righteousness Doth the righteous one, My servant, to many, And their iniquities he doth bear.

12 Therefore I give a portion to him among the many, And with the mighty he apportioneth spoil, Because that he exposed to death his soul, And with transgressors he was numbered, And he the sin of many hath borne, And for transgressors he intercedeth.

Isaiah 54

1 Sing, O barren, she hath not borne! Break forth with singing, and cry aloud, She hath not brought forth! For more [are] the sons of the desolate, Than the sons of the married one, said Jehovah.

2 Enlarge the place of thy tent, And the curtains of thy tabernacles they stretch out, Restrain not--lengthen thy cords, And thy pins make strong.

3 For right and left thou breakest forth, And thy seed doth nations possess,

4 And desolate cities they cause to be inhabited. Fear not, for thou art not ashamed, Nor blush, for thou art not confounded, For the shame of thy youth thou forgettest, And the reproach of thy widowhood Thou dost not remember any more.

5 For thy Maker [is] thy husband, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name, And thy Redeemer [is] the Holy One of Israel, `God of all the earth,' He is called.

6 For, as a woman forsaken and grieved in spirit, Called thee hath Jehovah, Even a youthful wife when she is refused, said thy God.

7 In a small moment I have forsaken thee, And in great mercies I do gather thee,

8 In overflowing wrath I hid my face [for] a moment from thee, And in kindness ageduring I have loved thee, Said thy Redeemer--Jehovah!

9 For, the waters of Noah [is] this to Me, In that I have sworn--the waters of Noah Do not pass again over the earth--So I have sworn, Wrath is not upon thee, Nor rebuke against thee.

10 For the mountains depart, and the hills remove, And My kindness from thee departeth not, And the covenant of My peace removeth not, Said hath thy loving one--Jehovah.

11 O afflicted, storm-tossed, not comforted, Lo, I am laying with cement thy stones, And have founded thee with sapphires,

12 And have made of agate thy pinnacles, And thy gates of carbuncle stones, And all thy border of stones of delight,

13 And all thy sons are taught of Jehovah, And abundant [is] the peace of thy sons.

14 In righteousness thou establishest thyself, Be far from oppression, for thou fearest not, And from ruin, for it cometh not near unto thee.

15 Lo, he doth diligently assemble without My desire, Who hath assembled near thee? By thee he falleth!

16 Lo, I--I have prepared an artisan, Blowing on a fire of coals, And bringing out an instrument for his work, And I have prepared a destroyer to destroy.

17 No weapon formed against thee prospereth, And every tongue rising against thee, In judgment thou condemnest. This [is] the inheritance of the servants of Jehovah, And their righteousness from me, an affirmation of Jehovah!

Isaiah 55

1 Ho, every thirsty one, come ye to the waters, And he who hath no money, Come ye, buy and eat, yea, come, buy Without money and without price, wine and milk.

2 Why do ye weigh money for that which is not bread? And your labour for that which is not for satiety? Hearken diligently unto me, and eat good, And your soul doth delight itself in fatness.

3 Incline your ear, and come unto me, Hear, and your soul doth live, And I make for you a covenant age-during, The kind acts of David--that are stedfast.

4 Lo, a witness to peoples I have given him, A leader and commander to peoples.

5 Lo, a nation thou knowest not, thou callest, And a nation who know thee not unto thee do run, For the sake of Jehovah thy God, And for the Holy One of Israel, Because He hath beautified thee.

6 Seek ye Jehovah, while He is found, Call ye Him, while He is near,

7 Forsake doth the wicked his way, And the man of iniquity his thoughts, And he returneth to Jehovah, and He pitieth him, And unto our God for He multiplieth to pardon.

8 For not My thoughts [are] your thoughts, Nor your ways My ways, --an affirmation of Jehovah,

9 For high have the heavens been above the earth, So high have been My ways above your ways, And My thoughts above your thoughts.

10 For, as come down doth the shower, And the snow from the heavens, And thither returneth not, But hath watered the earth, And hath caused it to yield, and to spring up, And hath given seed to the sower, and bread to the eater,

11 So is My word that goeth out of My mouth, It turneth not back unto Me empty, But hath done that which I desired, And prosperously effected that [for] which I sent it.

12 For with joy ye go forth, And with peace ye are brought in, The mountains and the hills Break forth before you [with] singing, And all trees of the field clap the hand.

13 Instead of the thorn come up doth fir, Instead of the brier come up doth myrtle, And it hath been to Jehovah for a name, For a sign age-during--it is not cut off!

Isaiah 57

1 The righteous hath perished, And there is none laying [it] to heart, And men of kindness are gathered, Without any considering that from the face of evil Gathered is the righteous one.

2 He entereth into peace, they rest on their beds, [Each] is going straightforward.

3 And ye, come near hither, O sons of a sorceress, seed of an adulterer, Even thou dost commit whoredom.

4 Against whom do ye sport yourselves? Against whom enlarge ye the mouth? Prolong ye the tongue? Are not ye children of transgression? a false seed?

5 Who are inflamed among oaks, under every green tree, Slaughtering the children in valleys, Under clefts of the rocks.

6 Among the smooth things of a brook [is] thy portion, They--they [are] thy lot, Also to them thou hast poured out an oblation, Thou hast caused a present to ascend, For these things am I comforted?

7 On a mountain, high and exalted, Thou hast set thy couch, Also thither thou hast gone up to make a sacrifice.

8 And behind the door, and the post, Thou hast set up thy memorial, For from Me thou hast removed, and goest up, Thou hast enlarged thy couch, And dost covenant for thyself among them, Thou hast loved their couch, the station thou sawest,

9 And goest joyfully to the king in ointment, And dost multiply thy perfumes, And sendest thine ambassadors afar off, And humblest thyself unto Sheol.

10 In the greatness of thy way thou hast laboured, Thou hast not said, `It is desperate.' The life of thy hand thou hast found, Therefore thou hast not been sick.

11 And of whom hast thou been afraid, and fearest, That thou liest, and Me hast not remembered? Thou hast not laid [it] to thy heart, Am not I silent, even from of old? And Me thou fearest not?

12 I declare thy righteousness, and thy works, And they do not profit thee.

13 When thou criest, let thy gatherings deliver thee, And all of them carry away doth wind, Take away doth vanity, And whoso is trusting in Me inheriteth the land, And doth possess My holy mountain.

14 And he hath said, `Raise up, raise up, prepare a way, Lift a stumbling-block out of the way of My people.'

15 For thus said the high and exalted One, Inhabiting eternity, and holy [is] His name: `In the high and holy place I dwell, And with the bruised and humble of spirit, To revive the spirit of the humble, And to revive the heart of bruised ones,'

16 For, not to the age do I strive, nor for ever am I wroth, For the spirit from before Me is feeble, And the souls I have made.

17 For the iniquity of his dishonest gain, I have been wroth, and I smite him, Hiding-- and am wroth, And he goeth on turning back in the way of his heart.

18 His ways I have seen, and I heal him, yea, I lead him, And recompense comforts to him and to his mourning ones.

19 Producing the fruit of the lips, `Peace, peace,' to the far off, and to the near, And I have healed him, said Jehovah.

20 And the wicked [are] as the driven out sea, For to rest it is not able, And its waters cast out filth and mire.

21 There is no peace, said my God, to the wicked!

Isaiah 58

1 Call with the throat, restrain not, As a trumpet lift up thy voice, And declare to My people their transgression, And to the house of Jacob their sins;

2 Seeing--Me day by day they seek, And the knowledge of My ways they desire, As a nation that righteousness hath done, And the judgment of its God hath not forsaken, They ask of me judgments of righteousness, The drawing near of God they desire:

3 `Why have we fasted, and Thou hast not seen? We have afflicted our soul, and Thou knowest not.' Lo, in the day of your fast ye find pleasure, And all your labours ye exact.

4 Lo, for strife and debate ye fast, And to smite with the fist of wickedness, Ye fast not as [to] -day, To sound in the high place your voice.

5 Like this is the fast that I choose? The day of a man's afflicting his soul? To bow as a reed his head, And sackcloth and ashes spread out? This dost thou call a fast, And a desirable day-- to Jehovah?

6 Is not this the fast that I chose--To loose the bands of wickedness, To shake off the burdens of the yoke, And to send out the oppressed free, And every yoke ye draw off?

7 Is it not to deal to the hungry thy bread, And the mourning poor bring home, That thou seest the naked and cover him, And from thine own flesh hide not thyself?

8 Then broken up as the dawn is thy light, And thy health in haste springeth up, Gone before thee hath thy righteousness, The honour of Jehovah doth gather thee.

9 Then thou callest, and Jehovah answereth, Thou criest, and He saith, `Behold Me.' If thou turn aside from thy midst the yoke, The sending forth of the finger, And the speaking of vanity,

10 And dost bring out to the hungry thy soul, And the afflicted soul dost satisfy, Then risen in the darkness hath thy light, And thy thick darkness [is] as noon.

11 And Jehovah doth lead thee continually, And hath satisfied in drought thy soul, And thy bones He armeth, And thou hast been as a watered garden, And as an outlet of waters, whose waters lie not.

12 And they have built out of thee the wastes of old, The foundations of many generations thou raisest up, And one calleth thee, `Repairer of the breach, Restorer of paths to rest in.'

13 If thou dost turn from the sabbath thy foot, Doing thine own pleasure on My holy day, And hast cried to the sabbath, `A delight,' To the holy of Jehovah, `Honoured,' And hast honoured it, without doing thine own ways, Without finding thine own pleasure, And speaking a word.

14 Then dost thou delight thyself on Jehovah, And I have caused thee to ride on high places of earth, And have caused thee to eat the inheritance of Jacob thy father, For the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken!

Isaiah 59

1 Lo, the hand of Jehovah Hath not been shortened from saving, Nor heavy his ear from hearing.

2 But your iniquities have been separating Between you and your God, And your sins have hidden The Presence from you--from hearing.

3 For your hands have been polluted with blood, And your fingers with iniquity, Your lips have spoken falsehood, Your tongue perverseness doth mutter.

4 There is none calling in righteousness, And there is none pleading in faithfulness, Trusting on emptiness, and speaking falsehood, Conceiving perverseness, and bearing iniquity.

5 Eggs of a viper they have hatched, And webs of a spider they weave, Whoso is eating their eggs doth die, And the crushed hatcheth a viper.

6 Their webs become not a garment, Nor do they cover themselves with their works, Their works [are] works of iniquity, And a deed of violence [is] in their hands.

7 Their feet to evil do run, And they haste to shed innocent blood, Their thoughts [are] thoughts of iniquity, Spoiling and destruction [are] in their highways.

8 A way of peace they have not known, And there is no judgment in their paths, Their paths they have made perverse for themselves, No treader in it hath known peace.

9 Therefore hath judgment been far from us, And righteousness reacheth us not, We wait for light, and lo, darkness, For brightness--in thick darkness we go,

10 We feel like the blind [for] the wall, Yea, as without eyes we feel, We have stumbled at noon as at twilight, In desolate places as the dead.

11 We make a noise as bears--all of us, And as doves we coo sorely; We wait for judgment, and there is none, For salvation--it hath been far from us.

12 For our transgressions have been multiplied before Thee, And our sins have testified against us, For our transgressions [are] with us, And our iniquities--we have known them.

13 Transgressing, and lying against Jehovah, And removing from after our God, Speaking oppression and apostasy, Conceiving and uttering from the heart Words of falsehood.

14 And removed backward is judgment, And righteousness afar off standeth, For truth hath been feeble in the street, And straightforwardness is not able to enter,

15 And the truth is lacking, And whoso is turning aside from evil, Is making himself a spoil. And Jehovah seeth, and it is evil in His eyes, That there is no judgment.

16 And He seeth that there is no man, And is astonished that there is no intercessor, And His own arm giveth salvation to Him, And His righteousness--it sustained Him.

17 And He putteth on righteousness as a breastplate, And an helmet of salvation on His head, And He putteth on garments of vengeance [for] clothing, And is covered, as [with] an upperrobe, [with] zeal.

18 According to deeds--so He repayeth. Fury to His adversaries, [their] deed to His enemies, To the isles [their] deed He repayeth.

19 And they fear from the west the name of Jehovah, And from the rising of the sun--His honour, When come in as a flood doth an adversary, The Spirit of Jehovah hath raised an ensign against him.

20 And come to Zion hath a redeemer, Even to captives of transgression in Jacob, An affirmation of Jehovah.

21 And I--this [is] My covenant with them, said Jehovah, My Spirit that [is] on thee, And My words that I have put in thy mouth, Depart not from thy mouth, And from the mouth of thy seed, And from the mouth of thy seed's seed, said Jehovah, From henceforth unto the age!

Isaiah 60

1 Arise, be bright, for come hath thy light, And the honour of Jehovah hath risen on thee.

2 For, lo, the darkness doth cover the earth, And thick darkness the peoples, And on thee rise doth Jehovah, And His honour on thee is seen.

3 And come have nations to thy light, And kings to the brightness of thy rising.

4 Lift up round about thine eyes and see, All of them have been gathered, they have come to thee, Thy sons from afar do come, And thy daughters on the side are supported.

5 Then thou seest, and hast become bright, And thine heart hath been afraid and enlarged, For turn unto thee doth the multitude of the sea, The forces of nations do come to thee.

6 A company of camels covereth thee, Dromedaries of Midian and Ephah, All of them from Sheba do come, Gold and frankincense they bear, And of the praises of Jehovah they proclaim the tidings.

7 All the flock of Kedar are gathered to thee, The rams of Nebaioth do serve thee, They ascend for acceptance Mine altar, And the house of My beauty I beautify.

8 Who [are] these--as a thick cloud they fly, And as doves unto their windows?

9 Surely for Me isles do wait, And ships of Tarshish first, To bring thy sons from afar, Their silver and their gold with them, To the name of Jehovah thy God, And to the Holy One of Israel, Because He hath beautified thee.

10 And sons of a stranger have built thy walls, And their kings do serve thee, For in My wrath I have smitten thee, And in My good pleasure I have pitied thee.

11 And opened have thy gates continually, By day and by night they are not shut, To bring unto thee the force of nations, Even their kings are led.

12 For the nation and the kingdom that do not serve thee perish, Yea, the nations are utterly wasted.

13 The honour of Lebanon unto thee doth come, Fir, pine, and box together, To beautify the place of My sanctuary, And the place of My feet I make honourable.

14 And come unto thee, bowing down, Have sons of those afflicting thee, And bowed themselves to the soles of thy feet Have all despising thee, And they have cried to thee: `City of Jehovah, Zion of the Holy One of Israel.'

15 Instead of thy being forsaken and hated, And none passing through, I have made thee for an excellency age-during, A joy of generation and generation.

16 And thou hast sucked the milk of nations, Yea, the breast of kings thou suckest, And thou hast known that I, Jehovah, Thy Saviour, and Thy Redeemer, [Am] the Mighty One of Jacob.

17 Instead of the brass I bring in gold, And instead of the iron I bring in silver, And instead of the wood brass, And instead of the stone iron, And I have made thy inspection peace, And thy exactors righteousness.

18 Violence is not heard any more in thy land, Spoiling and destruction in thy borders, And thou hast called `Salvation' thy walls, And thy gates, `Praise.'

19 To thee no more is the sun for a light by day, And for brightness the moon giveth not light to thee, And Jehovah hath become to thee A light age-during, and thy God thy beauty.

20 Thy sun goeth no more in, And thy moon is not removed, For Jehovah becometh to thee a light age-during. And the days of thy mourning have been completed.

21 And thy people [are] all of them righteous, To the age they possess the earth, A branch of My planting, A work of My hands, to be beautified.

22 The little one doth become a chief, And the small one a mighty nation, I, Jehovah, in its own time do hasten it!

Isaiah 61

1 The Spirit of the Lord Jehovah [is] on me, Because Jehovah did anoint me To proclaim tidings to the humble, He sent me to bind the broken of heart, To proclaim to captives liberty, And to bound ones an opening of bands.

2 To proclaim the year of the good pleasure of Jehovah, And the day of vengeance of our God, To comfort all mourners.

3 To appoint to mourners in Zion, To give to them beauty instead of ashes, The oil of joy instead of mourning, A covering of praise for a spirit of weakness, And He is calling to them, `Trees of righteousness, The planting of Jehovah--to be beautified.'

4 And they have built the wastes of old, The desolations of the ancients they raise up, And they have renewed waste cities, The desolations of generation and generation.

5 And strangers have stood and fed your flock, Sons of a foreigner [are] your husbandmen, And your vine-dressers.

6 And ye are called `Priests of Jehovah,' `Ministers of our God,' is said of you, The strength of nations ye consume, And in their honour ye do boast yourselves.

7 Instead of your shame and confusion, A second time they sing of their portion, Therefore in their land A second time do they take possession, Joy age-during [is] for them.

8 For I [am] Jehovah, loving judgment, Hating plunder for a burnt-offering, And I have given their wage in truth, And a covenant age-during I make for them.

9 And known among nations hath been their seed, And their offspring in the midst of the peoples, All their beholders acknowledge them, For they [are] a seed Jehovah hath blessed.

10 I greatly rejoice in Jehovah, Joy doth my soul in my God, For He clothed me with garments of salvation, With a robe of righteousness covereth Me, As a bridegroom prepareth ornaments, And as a bride putteth on her jewels.

11 For, as the earth bringeth forth her shoots, And as a garden causeth its sown things to shoot up, So the Lord Jehovah causeth righteousness and praise To shoot up before all the nations!

Isaiah 62

1 For Zion's sake I am not silent, And for Jerusalem's sake I do not rest, Till her righteousness go out as brightness, And her salvation, as a torch that burneth.

2 And nations have seen thy righteousness, And all kings thine honour, And He is giving to thee a new name, That the mouth of Jehovah doth define.

3 And thou hast been a crown of beauty in the hand of Jehovah, And a diadem of royalty in the hand of thy God,

4 It is not said of thee any more, `Forsaken!' And of thy land it is not said any more, `Desolate,' For to thee is cried, `My delight [is] in her,' And to thy land, `Married,' For Jehovah hath delighted in thee, And thy land is married.

5 For a young man doth marry a virgin, Thy Builders do marry thee, With the joy of a bridegroom over a bride, Rejoice over thee doth thy God.

6 `On thy walls, O Jerusalem, I have appointed watchmen, All the day, and all the night, Continually, they are not silent.' O ye remembrancers of Jehovah, Keep not silence for yourselves,

7 And give not silence to Him, Till He establish, and till He make Jerusalem A praise in the earth.

8 Sworn hath Jehovah by His right hand, Even by the arm of His strength: `I give not thy corn any more [as] food for thine enemies, Nor do sons of a stranger drink thy new wine, For which thou hast laboured.

9 For, those gathering it do eat it, and have praised Jehovah, And those collecting it do drink it in My holy courts.'

10 Pass ye on, pass on through the gates, Prepare ye the way of the people, Raise up, raise up the highway, clear it from stones, Lift up an ensign over the peoples.

11 Lo, Jehovah hath proclaimed unto the end of the earth: `Say ye to the daughter of Zion, Lo, thy salvation hath come,' Lo, his hire [is] with him, and his wage before him.

12 And they have cried to them, `People of the Holy One, Redeemed of Jehovah,' Yea, to thee is called, `Sought out one, a city not forsaken!'

Isaiah 63

1 `Who [is] this coming from Edom? With dyed garments from Bozrah? This that is honourable in his clothing, Travelling in the abundance of his power?' --`I, speaking in righteousness, mighty to save.'

2 `Wherefore [is] thy clothing red? And thy garments as treading in a wine fat?'

3 --`A wine-press I have trodden by myself, And of the peoples there is no one with me, And I tread them in mine anger, And I trample them in my fury, Sprinkled is their strength on my garments, And all my clothing I have polluted.

4 For the day of vengeance [is] in my heart, And the year of my redeemed hath come.

5 And I look attentively, and there is none helping, And I am astonished that there is none supporting, And give salvation to me doth mine own arm. And my wrath--it hath supported me.

6 And I tread down peoples in mine anger, And I make them drunk in my fury, And I bring down to earth their strength.

7 The kind acts of Jehovah I make mention of, The praises of Jehovah, According to all that Jehovah hath done for us, And the abundance of the goodness to the house of Israel, That He hath done for them, According to His mercies, And accordingto the abundance of His kind acts.

8 And He saith, Only My people they [are], Sons--they lie not, and He is to them for a saviour.

9 In all their distress [He is] no adversary, And the messenger of His presence saved them, In His love and in His pity He redeemed them, And He doth lift them up, And beareth them all the days of old.

10 And they have rebelled and grieved His Holy Spirit, And He turneth to them for an enemy, He Himself hath fought against them.

11 And He remembereth the days of old, Moses--his people. Where [is] He who is bringing them up from the sea, The shepherd of his flock? Where [is] He who is putting in its midst His Holy Spirit?

12 Leading by the right hand of Moses, the arm of His glory, Cleaving waters from before them, To make to Himself a name age-during.

13 Leading them through the depths, As a horse in a plain they stumble not.

14 As a beast into a valley goeth down, The Spirit of Jehovah causeth him to rest, So hast Thou led Thy people, To make to Thyself a glorious name.

15 Look attentively from the heavens, And see from Thy holy and beauteous habitation, Where [is] Thy zeal and Thy might? The multitude of Thy bowels and Thy mercies Towards me have refrained themselves.

16 For Thou [art] our Father, For Abraham hath not known us, And Israel doth not acknowledge us, Thou, O Jehovah, [art] our Father, Our redeemer from the age, [is] Thy name.

17 Why causest Thou us to wander, O Jehovah, from Thy ways? Thou hardenest our heart from Thy fear, Turn back for Thy servants' sake, The tribes of Thine inheritance.

18 For a little while did Thy holy people possess, Our adversaries have trodden down Thy sanctuary.

19 We have been from of old, Thou hast not ruled over them, Not called is Thy name upon them!

Isaiah 64

1 Didst Thou not rend the heavens? Thou didst come down, From thy presence did mountains flow,

2 (As fire kindleth stubble--Fire causeth water to boil,) To make known Thy name to Thine adversaries, From Thy presence do nations tremble.

3 In Thy doing fearful things--we expect not, Thou didst come down, From Thy presence did mountains flow.

4 Even from antiquity [men] have not heard, They have not given ear, Eye hath not seen a God save Thee, He doth work for those waiting for Him.

5 Thou hast met with the rejoicer And the doer of righteousness, In Thy ways they remember Thee, Lo, Thou hast been wroth when we sin, By them [is] continuance, and we are saved.

6 And we are as unclean--all of us, And as a garment passing away, all our righteous acts; And we fade as a leaf--all of us. And our iniquities as wind do take us away.

7 And there is none calling in Thy name, Stirring up himself to lay hold on Thee, For Thou hast hid Thy face from us, And thou meltest us away by our iniquities.

8 And now, O Jehovah, thou [art] our Father, We [are] the clay, and Thou our Framer, And the work of Thy hand--all of us.

9 Be not wroth, O Jehovah, very sore, Nor for ever remember iniquity, Lo, look attentively, we beseech Thee, Thy people [are] we all.

10 Thy holy cities have been a wilderness, Zion a wilderness hath been, Jerusalem a desolation.

11 Our holy and our beautiful house, Where praise Thee did our fathers, Hath become burnt with fire, And all our desirable things have become a waste.

12 For these dost Thou refrain Thyself, Jehovah? Thou art silent, and dost afflict us very sore!'

Isaiah 65

1 I have been inquired of by those who asked not, I have been found by those who sought Me not, I have said, `Behold Me, behold Me,' Unto a nation not calling in My name.

2 I have spread out My hands all the day Unto an apostate people, Who are going in the way not good after their own thoughts.

3 The people who are provoking Me to anger, To My face continually, Sacrificing in gardens, and making perfume on the bricks:

4 Who are dwelling among sepulchres, And lodge in reserved places, Who are eating flesh of the sow, And a piece of abominable things--their vessels.

5 Who are saying, `Keep to thyself, come not nigh to me, For I have declared thee unholy.' These [are] a smoke in Mine anger, A fire burning all the day.

6 Lo, it is written before Me: `I am not silent, but have recompensed; And I have recompensed into their bosom,

7 Your iniquities, and the iniquities of your fathers together, said Jehovah, Who have made perfume on the mountains, And on the heights have reproached Me, And I have measured their former work into their bosom.'

8 Thus said Jehovah: As the new wine is found in the cluster, And one hath said, `Destroy it not for a blessing [is] in it,' So I do for My servants' sake, not to destroy the whole.

9 And I have brought out from Jacob a seed, And from Judah a possessor of My mount, And possess it do My chosen ones, And My servants do dwell there.

10 And Sharon hath been for the habitation of a flock, And the valley of Achor for the lying down of a herd, For My people who have sought Me.

11 And ye [are] those forsaking Jehovah, Who are forgetting My holy mountain, Who are setting in array for Gad a table, And who are filling for Meni a mixture.

12 And I have numbered you for the sword, And all of you for slaughter bow down, Because I called, and ye have not answered, I have spoken, and ye have not hearkened, And ye do the evil thing in Mine eyes, And on that which I desired not--fixed.

13 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, My servants do eat, and ye do hunger, Lo, My servants do drink, and ye do thirst, Lo, My servants rejoice, and ye are ashamed,

14 Lo, My servants sing from joy of heart, And ye cry from pain of heart, And from breaking of spirit ye do howl.

15 And ye have left your name For an oath for My chosen ones, And the Lord Jehovah hath put thee to death, And to His servants He giveth another name.

16 So that he who is blessing himself in the earth, Doth bless himself In the God of faithfulness, And he who is swearing in the earth, Doth swear by the God of faithfulness, Because the former distresses have been forgotten, And because they have been hid from Mine eyes.

17 For, lo, I am creating new heavens, and a new earth, And the former things are not remembered, Nor do they ascend on the heart.

18 But joy ye, and rejoice for ever, that I [am] Creator, For, lo, I am creating Jerusalem a rejoicing, And her people a joy.

19 And I have rejoiced in Jerusalem, And have joyed in My people, And not heard in her any more Is the voice of weeping, and the voice of crying.

20 There is not thence any more a suckling of days, And an aged man who doth not complete his days, For the youth a hundred years old dieth, And the sinner, a hundred years old, is lightly esteemed.

21 And they have built houses, and inhabited, And planted vineyards, and eaten their fruit.

22 They do not build, and another inhabit, They do not plant, and another eat, For as the days of a tree [are] the days of My people, And the work of their hands wear out do My chosen ones.

23 They labour not for a vain thing, Nor do they bring forth for trouble, For the seed of the blessed of Jehovah [are] they, And their offspring with them.

24 And it hath come to pass, They do not yet call, and I answer, They are yet speaking, and I hear.

25 Wolf and lamb do feed as one, And a lion as an ox eateth straw, As to the serpent-- dust [is] its food, They do no evil, nor destroy, In all My holy mountain, said Jehovah!

Isaiah 66

1 Thus said Jehovah: The heavens [are] My throne, And the earth My footstool, Where [is] this--the house that ye build for Me? And where [is] this--the place--My rest?

2 And all these My hand hath made, And all these things are, An affirmation of Jehovah! And unto this one I look attentively, Unto the humble and bruised in spirit, And who is trembling at My word.

3 Whoso slaughtereth the ox smiteth a man, Whoso sacrificeth the lamb beheadeth a dog, Whoso is bringing up a present--The blood of a sow, Whoso is making mention of frankincense, Is blessing iniquity. Yea, they have fixed on their own ways, And in their abominations their soul hath delighted.

4 I also--I fix on their vexations, And their fears I bring in to them, Because I have called, and there is none answering, I spake, and they have not hearkened, And they do the evil things in Mine eyes, And on that which I desired not--fixed.

5 Hear a word of Jehovah, Ye who are trembling unto His word, Said have your brethren who are hating you, Who are driving you out, for My name's sake: `Honoured is Jehovah, and we look on your joy,' But they are ashamed.

6 A voice of noise [is] from the city, a voice from the temple, The voice of Jehovah, giving recompence to His enemies.

7 Before she is pained she hath brought forth, Before a pang cometh to her, She hath delivered a male.

8 Who hath heard anything like this? Who hath seen anything like these? Is earth caused to bring forth in one day? Born is a nation at once? For she hath been pained, Zion also hath borne her sons.

9 `Do I bring to the birth, And not cause to bring forth?' saith Jehovah, `Am not I He who is causing to beget? I have also restrained,' said thy God.

10 Rejoice ye with Jerusalem, And be glad in her, all ye loving her, Rejoice ye with her for joy, All ye are mourning for her,

11 So that ye suck, and have been satisfied, From the breast of her consolations, So that ye wring out, and have delighted yourselves From the abundance of her honour.

12 For thus said Jehovah: `Lo, I am stretching out to her peace as a river, And as an overflowing stream the honour of nations, And ye have sucked, on the side ye are carried, And on the knees ye are dandled.

13 As one whom his mother comforteth, so do I comfort you, Yea, in Jerusalem ye are comforted.

14 And ye have seen, and rejoiced hath your heart, And your bones as tender grass do flourish, And the hand of Jehovah hath been known unto His servants, And He hath been indignant with His enemies.

15 For, lo, Jehovah in fire cometh, And as a hurricane His chariots, To refresh in fury His anger, And His rebuke in flames of fire.

16 For by fire and by His sword, Doth Jehovah do judgment with all flesh. And many have been Jehovah's pierced ones.'

17 Those sanctifying and cleansing themselves at the gardens, After Ahad in the midst, Eating flesh of the sow, And of the abomination, and of the mouse, Together are consumed, An affirmation of Jehovah.

18 And I--their works and their thoughts, I come to gather all the nations and tongues, And they have come and seen My honour.

19 And I have set among them a sign, And have sent out of them those escaping unto the nations, (Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, drawing bow, Tubal and Javan, the isles that are far off,) Who have not heard My fame, nor seen Mine honour, And they have declared Mine honour among nations.

20 And they have brought all your brethren out of all the nations, A present to Jehovah, On horses, and on chariot, and on litters, And on mules, and on dromedaries, Unto My holy mountain Jerusalem, said Jehovah, As the sons of Israel bring thepresent in a clean vessel, Into the house of Jehovah.

21 And also of them I take for priests, For Levites, said Jehovah.

22 For, as the new heavens and the new earth that I am making, Are standing before Me, An affirmation of Jehovah! So remain doth your seed and your name.

23 And it hath been from month to month, And from sabbath to sabbath, Come do all flesh to bow themselves before Me, Said Jehovah.

24 And they have gone forth, And looked on the carcases of the men Who are transgressing against me, For their worm dieth not, And their fire is not quenched, And they have been an abhorrence to all flesh!

Jeremiah 1

1 Words of Jeremiah son of Hilkiah, of the priests who [are] in Anathoth, in the land of Benjamin,

2 unto whom the word of Jehovah hath been in the days of Josiah son of Amon, king of Judah, in the thirteenth year of his reign,

3 and it is in the days of Jehoiakim son of Josiah, king of Judah, till the completion of the eleventh year of Zedekiah son of Josiah, king of Judah, till the removal of Jerusalem in the fifth month.

4 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

5 `Before I form thee in the belly, I have known thee; and before thou comest forth from the womb I have separated thee, a prophet to nations I have made thee.'

6 And I say, `Ah, Lord Jehovah! lo, I have not known--to speak, for I [am] a youth.'

7 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Do not say, I [am] a youth, for to all to whom I send thee thou goest, and all that I command thee thou speakest.

8 Be not afraid of their faces, for with thee [am] I to deliver thee, --an affirmation of Jehovah.'

9 And Jehovah putteth forth His hand, and striketh against my mouth, and Jehovah saith unto me, `Lo, I have put my words in thy mouth.

10 See, I have charged thee this day concerning the nations, and concerning the kingdoms, to pluck up, and to break down, and to destroy, and to throw down, to build, and to plant.'

11 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying, `What art thou seeing, Jeremiah?' And I say, `A rod of an almond tree I am seeing.'

12 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Thou hast well seen: for I am watching over My word to do it.'

13 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me a second time, saying, `What art thou seeing?' And I say, `A blown pot I am seeing, and its face [is] from the north.'

14 And Jehovah saith unto me, `From the north is the evil loosed against all inhabitants of the land.

15 For, lo, I am calling for all families of the kingdoms of the north, --an affirmation of Jehovah--and they have come, and put each his throne at the opening of the gates of Jerusalem, and by its walls round about, and by all cities of Judah.

16 And I have spoken My judgments with them concerning all their evil, in that they have forsaken Me, and make perfume to other gods, and bow themselves to the works of their own hands.

17 `And thou, thou dost gird up thy loins, and hast arisen, and spoken unto them all that I command thee: be not affrighted because of them, lest I affright thee before them.

18 And I, lo, I have given thee this day for a fenced city, and for an iron pillar, and for brazen walls over all the land, to the kings of Judah, to its heads, to its priests, and to the people of the land;

19 and they have fought against thee, and they prevail not against thee; for with thee [am] I, --an affirmation of Jehovah--to deliver thee.

Jeremiah 3

1 Saying, `Lo, one sendeth away his wife, And she hath gone from him, And she hath been to another man, Doth he turn back unto her again? Greatly defiled is not that land? And thou hast committed whoredom with many lovers, And turn again to Me, an affirmation of Jehovah.

2 Lift thine eyes to the high places, and see, Where hast thou not been lain with? On the ways thou hast sat for them, As an Arab in a wilderness, And thou defilest the land, By thy fornications, and by thy wickedness.

3 And withheld are showers, and gathered rain hath not been. The forehead of a whorish woman thou hast, Thou hast refused to be ashamed.

4 Hast thou not henceforth called to Me, `My father, Thou [art] the leader of my youth?

5 Doth He keep to the age? watch for ever?' Lo, these things thou hast spoken, And thou dost the evil things, and prevailest.

6 And Jehovah saith unto me, in the days of Josiah the king, `Hast thou seen that which backsliding Israel hath done? She is going on every high mountain, and unto the place of every green tree, and committeth fornication there.

7 And I say, after her doing all these, Unto Me thou dost turn back, and she hath not turned back, and see [it] doth her treacherous sister Judah.

8 And I see when (for all the causes whereby backsliding Israel committed adultery) I have sent her away, and I give the bill of her divorce unto her, that treacherous Judah her sister hath not feared, and goeth and committeth fornication--shealso.

9 And it hath come to pass, from the vileness of her fornication, that the land is defiled, and she committeth fornication with stone and with wood.

10 And even in all this her treacherous sister Judah hath not turned back unto Me with all her heart, but with falsehood, an affirmation of Jehovah.'

11 And Jehovah saith unto me: `Justified herself hath backsliding Israel, More than treacherous Judah.

12 Go, and thou hast proclaimed these words toward the north, and hast said, Turn back, O backsliding Israel, An affirmation of Jehovah! I cause not Mine anger to fall upon you, For I [am] kind, an affirmation of Jehovah, I watch not to the age.

13 Only, know thine iniquity, For against Jehovah thy God thou hast transgressed, And thou dost scatter thy ways to strangers, Under every green tree, And to My voice thou hast not hearkened, An affirmation of Jehovah.

14 Turn back, O backsliding sons, An affirmation of Jehovah. For I have ruled over you, And taken you one of a city, and two of a family, And have brought you to Zion,

15 And I have given to you shepherds According to Mine own heart, And they have fed you with knowledge and understanding.

16 And it hath come to pass, when ye are multiplied, And have been fruitful in the land, In those days--an affirmation of Jehovah, They say not any more, `The ark of the covenant of Jehovah,' Nor doth it go up on the heart, Nor do they remember concerning it, Nor do they inspect, nor is it made again.

17 At that time they cry to Jerusalem, `O throne of Jehovah,' And gathered unto her hath been all the nations, For the name of Jehovah, to Jerusalem, Nor do they go any more after the stubbornness of their evil heart.

18 In those days do the house of Judah Go unto the house of Israel, And they come together from the land of the south, unto the land That I caused your fathers to inherit.

19 And I have said, How do I put thee among the sons, And give to thee a desirable land, A beauteous inheritance of the hosts of nations, And I say, My father--ye do call to Me, And from after Me ye do not turn back.

20 But--a woman hath deceived her friend, So ye have dealt treacherously with Me, O house of Israel, an affirmation of Jehovah.

21 A voice on high places is heard--weeping, Supplications of the sons of Israel, For they have made perverse their way, They have forgotten Jehovah their God.

22 Turn back, O backsliding sons, I cause your backslidings to cease. --Behold us, we have come to Thee, For Thou [art] Jehovah our God.

23 Surely in vain from the heights, The multitude of mountains--Surely in Jehovah our God [is] the salvation of Israel.

24 And the shameful thing hath devoured The labour of our fathers from our youth, Their flock and their herd, Their sons and their daughters.

25 We have lain down in our shame, and cover us doth our confusion, For against Jehovah our God we have sinned, We, and our fathers, from our youth even unto this day, Nor have we hearkened to the voice of Jehovah our God!

Jeremiah 4

1 If thou dost turn back, O Israel, An affirmation of Jehovah, unto Me turn back, And if thou dost turn aside Thine abominations from My face, Then thou dost not bemoan.

2 And thou hast sworn--Jehovah liveth, In truth, in judgment, and in righteousness, And blessed themselves in Him have nations, And in Him they boast themselves.

3 For thus said Jehovah, To the man of Judah, and to Jerusalem: Till for yourselves tillage, And do not sow unto the thorns.

4 Be circumcised to Jehovah, And turn aside the foreskins of your heart, O man of Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem, Lest My fury go out as fire, and hath burned, And there is none quenching, Because of the evil of your doings.

5 Declare in Judah, and in Jerusalem sound, And say ye, `Blow a trumpet in the land,' Call ye fully, and say ye: `Be gathered, and we go in to the fenced city.'

6 Lift up an ensign Zionward, Strengthen yourselves, stand not still, For evil I am bringing in from the north, And a great destruction.

7 Gone up hath a lion from his thicket, And a destroyer of nations hath journeyed, He hath come forth from his place To make thy land become a desolation, Thy cities are laid waste, without inhabitant.

8 For this, gird on sackcloth, lament and howl, For the fierce anger of Jehovah hath not turned back from us.

9 And it hath come to pass, in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah: `Perish doth the heart of the king, And the heart of the princes, And astonished have been the priests, And the prophets do wonder.'

10 And I say, `Ah, Lord Jehovah, Surely thou hast entirely forgotten this people and Jerusalem, saying, Peace is for you, And struck hath a sword unto the soul!'

11 At that time it is said of this people, And of Jerusalem: `A dry wind of high places in the wilderness,' The way of the daughter of My people, (Not for winnowing, nor for cleansing,)

12 A full wind from these doth come for Me, Now, also, I speak judgments with them.

13 Lo, as clouds he cometh up, And as a hurricane his chariots, Lighter than eagles have been his horses, Woe to us, for we have been spoiled.

14 Wash from evil thy heart, O Jerusalem, That thou mayest be saved, Till when dost thou lodge in thy heart Thoughts of thy strength?

15 For a voice is declaring from Dan, And sounding sorrow from mount Ephraim.

16 Make ye mention to the nations, Lo, sound ye to Jerusalem: `Besiegers are coming from the land afar off, And they give forth against cities of Judah their voice.

17 As the keepers of a field They have been against her round about, For with Me she hath been rebellious, An affirmation of Jehovah.'

18 Thy way and thy doings have done these to thee, This [is] thy vexation, for [it is] bitter, For it hath struck unto thy heart.

19 My bowels, my bowels! I am pained [at] the walls of my heart, Make a noise for me doth My heart, I am not silent, For the voice of a trumpet I have heard, O my soul--a shout of battle!

20 Destruction on destruction is proclaimed, For spoiled hath been all the land, Suddenly spoiled have been my tents, In a moment--my curtains.

21 Till when do I see an ensign? Do I hear the voice of a trumpet?

22 For my people [are] foolish, me they have not known, Foolish sons [are] they, yea, they [are] not intelligent, Wise [are] they to do evil, And to do good they have not known.

23 I looked [to] the land, and lo, waste and void, And unto the heavens, and their light is not.

24 I have looked [to] the mountains, And lo, they are trembling. And all the hills moved themselves lightly.

25 I have looked, and lo, man is not, And all fowls of the heavens have fled.

26 I have looked, and lo, The fruitful place [is] a wilderness, And all its cities have been broken down, Because of Jehovah, Because of the fierceness of His anger.

27 For thus said Jehovah: All the land is a desolation, but a completion I make not.

28 For this doth the land mourn, And black have been the heavens above, because I have spoken--I have purposed, And I have not repented, Nor do I turn back from it.

29 From the voice of the horseman, And of him shooting with the bow, all the city is fleeing, They have come into thickets, And on cliffs they have gone up, All the city is forsaken, And there is no one dwelling in them.

30 And thou, O spoiled one, what dost thou? For thou puttest on scarlet, For thou adornest thyself [with] ornaments of gold. For thou rendest with pain thine eyes, In vain thou dost make thyself fair, Kicked against thee have doting ones, Thy life they do seek.

31 For a voice as of a sick woman I have heard, Distress, as of one bringing forth a first-born, The voice of the daughter of Zion, She bewaileth herself, she spreadeth out her hands, `Woe to me now, for weary is my soul of slayers!'

Jeremiah 5

1 Go to and fro in streets of Jerusalem, And see, I pray you, and know, And seek in her broad places, if ye find a man, If there be one doing judgment, seeking stedfastness--Then am I propitious to her.

2 And if they say, `Jehovah liveth,' Surely to a falsehood they swear.

3 Jehovah, Thine eyes, are they not on stedfastness? Thou hast smitten them, and they have not grieved, Thou hast consumed them, They have refused to receive instruction, They made their faces harder than a rock, They have refused to turn back.

4 And I--I said, `Surely these [are] poor, They have been foolish, For they have not known the way of Jehovah, The judgment of their God.

5 I get me to the great, and I speak with them, For they have known the way of Jehovah, The judgment of their God.' Surely they together have broken the yoke, They have drawn away the bands.

6 Therefore smitten them hath a lion out of the forest, A wolf of the deserts doth spoil them, A leopard is watching over their cities, Every one who is going out of them is torn, For many have been their transgressions, Mighty have been theirbackslidings.

7 For this I am not propitious to thee, Thy sons have forsaken Me, And are satisfied by that which is not god, I satisfy them, and they commit adultery, And at the house of a harlot They gather themselves together.

8 Fed horses--they have been early risers, Each to the wife of his neighbour they neigh.

9 For these do I not lay a charge? An affirmation of Jehovah, And on a nation such as this, Doth not My soul avenge itself?

10 Go ye up on her walls, and destroy, And a completion make not, Turn aside her branches, for they [are] not Jehovah's,

11 For dealt treacherously against Me have the house of Israel, And the house of Judah, an affirmation of Jehovah.

12 They have lied against Jehovah, And they say, `[It is] not He, Nor come in against us doth evil, Yea, sword and famine we do not see.

13 And the prophets become wind, And the word is not in them,' --thus it is done by them.

14 Therefore, thus said Jehovah, God of Hosts, Because of your speaking this word, Lo, I am making My words in thy mouth become fire, And this people wood, and it hath devoured them.

15 Lo, I am bringing against you a nation from afar, O house of Israel, an affirmation of Jehovah, A nation--strong it [is], a nation--from of old it [is], A nation--thou knowest not its tongue, Nor understandest what it speaketh.

16 Its quiver [is] as an open sepulchre, All of them--mighty ones.

17 And it hath consumed thy harvest and thy bread, They consume thy sons, and thy daughters, It consumeth thy flock, and thy herd, It consumeth thy vine, and thy fig-tree, It maketh poor thy fenced cities, In which thou art trusting--by the sword.

18 And even in those days, an affirmation of Jehovah, I do not make you a completion.

19 And it hath come to pass, when ye say, `For what hath Jehovah our God done to us all these?' That thou hast said unto them, `As ye have forsaken Me, And serve the gods of a foreigner in your land, So do ye serve strangers in a land not yours.

20 Declare ye this in the house of Jacob, And sound ye it in Judah, saying,

21 Hear ye, I pray you, this, O people, foolish and without heart, Eyes they have, and they see not, Ears they have, and they hear not.

22 Me do ye not fear, an affirmation of Jehovah? From My presence are ye not pained? Who hath made sand the border of the sea, A limit age-during, and it passeth not over it, They shake themselves, and they are not able, Yea, sounded have its billows, and they pass not over.

23 And this people hath an apostate and rebellious heart, They have turned aside, and they go on.

24 And they have not said in their heart, `Let us fear, we pray you, Jehovah our God, who is giving rain, The sprinkling and the gathered, in its season, The appointed weeks of harvest He keepeth for us.'

25 Your iniquities have turned these away, And your sins have kept the good from you.

26 For the wicked have been found among My people. It looketh about the covering of snares, They have set up a trap--men they capture.

27 As a cage full of fowls, So their houses are full of deceit, Therefore they have been great, and are rich.

28 They have been fat, they have shone, Yea, they have overpassed the acts of the evil, Judgment they have not judged, The judgment of the fatherless--and they prosper, And the judgment of the needy they have not judged.

29 For these do not I inspect, an affirmation of Jehovah, On a nation such as this, Doth not My soul avenge itself?

30 An astonishing and horrible thing hath been in the land.

31 The prophets have prophesied falsely, And the priests bear rule by their means, And My people have loved [it] so, And what do they at its latter end?

Jeremiah 6

1 Strengthen yourselves, sons of Benjamin, From the midst of Jerusalem, And in Tekoa blow ye a trumpet, And over Beth-Haccerem lift ye up a flame, For evil hath been seen from the north, And great destruction.

2 The comely and the delicate one I have cut off, The daughter of Zion.

3 Unto her come do shepherds and their droves, They have stricken tents by her round about, They have fed each [in] his own station.

4 Sanctify ye against her the battle, Rise, and we go up at noon. Woe to us, for turned hath the day, For stretched out are the shades of evening,

5 `Rise, and we go up by night, And we destroy her palaces.'

6 For thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Cut down her wood, And pour out against Jerusalem a mount, She [is] the city to be inspected, Wholly--she is oppression in her midst.

7 As the digging of a well, is [for] its waters, So she hath digged [for] her wickedness, Violence and spoil is heard in her, Before My face continually [are] sickness and smiting.

8 Be instructed, O Jerusalem, Lest My soul be alienated from thee, Lest I make thee a desolation, a land not inhabited.

9 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: They surely glean, as a vine, the remnant of Israel, Put back thy hand, as a gatherer to the baskets.

10 To whom do I speak, and testify, and they hear? Lo, their ear [is] uncircumcised, And they are not able to attend. Lo, a word of Jehovah hath been to them for a reproach, They delight not in it.

11 And with the fury of Jehovah I have been filled, (I have been weary of containing,) To pour [it] on the suckling in the street, And on the assembly of youths together, For even husband with wife are captured, An elder with one full of days,

12 And their houses have been turned to others, Fields and wives together, For I stretch out My hand against the inhabitants of the land, An affirmation of Jehovah.

13 For from their least unto their greatest, Every one is gaining dishonest gain, And from prophet even unto priest, Every one is dealing falsely,

14 And they heal the breach of the daughter of my people slightly, Saying, `Peace, peace!' and there is no peace.

15 They were ashamed when they did abomination! Yea, they are not at all ashamed, Yea, blushing they have not known, Therefore they do fall among those falling, In the time I have inspected them, They stumble, said Jehovah.

16 Thus said Jehovah: Stand ye by the ways and see, and ask for paths of old, Where [is] this--the good way? and go ye in it, And find rest for yourselves. And they say, `We do not go.'

17 And I have raised up for you watchmen, Attend ye to the voice of the trumpet. And they say, `We do not attend.'

18 Therefore hear, O nations, and know, O company, That which [is] upon them.

19 Hear, O earth, lo, I am bringing evil on this people, The fruit of their devices, For to My words they gave no attention, And My law--they kick against it.

20 Why [is] this to Me? frankincense from Sheba cometh, And the sweet cane from a land afar off, Your burnt-offerings [are] not for acceptance, And your sacrifices have not been sweet to Me.

21 Therefore thus said Jehovah: Lo, I do give to this people stumbling blocks, And stumbled against them have fathers and sons together, The neighbour and his friend do perish.

22 Thus said Jehovah: Lo, a people hath come from a north country, And a great nation is stirred up from the sides of the earth.

23 Bow and javelin they take hold of, Fierce it [is], and they have no mercy, Their voice as a sea doth sound, And on horses they ride, set in array as a man of war, Against thee, O daughter of Zion.

24 `We have heard its sound, feeble have been our hands, Distress hath seized us, pain as of a travailing woman.

25 Go not forth to the field, And in the way walk not, For a sword hath the enemy, fear [is] round about.

26 O daughter of My people, Gird on sackcloth, and roll thyself in ashes, The mourning of an only one make for thee, A lamentation most bitter, For suddenly come doth the spoiler against us.

27 A watch-tower I have given thee, Among My people a fortress, And thou knowest, and hast tried their way.

28 All of them are turned aside by apostates, Walking slanderously--brass and iron, All of them are corrupters.

29 The bellows have been burnt, By fire hath the lead been consumed, In vain hath a refiner refined, And the wicked have not been drawn away.

30 `Silver rejected,' they have called to them, For Jehovah hath kicked against them!

Jeremiah 7

1 The word that hath been unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying,

2 Stand in the gate of the house of Jehovah, and thou hast proclaimed there this word, and hast said, Hear a word of Jehovah, all ye of Judah, who are coming in at these gates, to bow before Jehovah:

3 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel, Amend your ways, and your doings, And I cause you to dwell in this place.

4 Do not trust for yourselves Unto the words of falsehood, saying, The temple of Jehovah, the temple of Jehovah, The temple of Jehovah [are] they!

5 For, if ye do thoroughly amend your ways and your doings, If ye do judgment thoroughly Between a man and his neighbour,

6 Sojourner, fatherless, and widow, ye oppress not, And innocent blood do not shed in this place, And after other gods do not walk, for evil to yourselves,

7 Then I have caused you to dwell in this place, In the land that I gave to your fathers, From age even unto age.

8 Lo, ye are trusting for yourselves On the words of falsehood, so as not to profit.

9 Stealing, murdering, and committing adultery, And swearing to falsehood, and giving perfume to Baal, And going after other gods whom ye knew not.

10 And ye have come in and stood before Me, In this house on which My name is called, And have said, `We have been delivered,' In order to do all these abominations.

11 A den of burglars hath this house, On which My name is called, been in your eyes? Even I, lo, I have seen, an affirmation of Jehovah.

12 But go ye, I pray you, Unto My place that [is] in Shiloh, Where I caused My name to dwell at first, And see that which I have done to it, For the wickedness of My people Israel.

13 And now, because of your doing all these works, An affirmation of Jehovah, And I speak unto you, rising early and speaking, And ye have not hearkened, And I call you, and ye have not answered,

14 I also to the house on which My name is called, In which ye are trusting, And to the place that I gave to you, and to your fathers, Have done, as I have done to Shiloh.

15 And I have cast you from before My face, As I have cast out all your brethren, The whole seed of Ephraim.

16 And thou dost not pray for this people, Nor lift up for them crying and prayer, Nor intercede with Me, for I hear thee not.

17 Art thou not seeing what they are doing In cities of Judah, and in streets of Jerusalem?

18 The sons are gathering wood, And the fathers are causing the fire to burn, And the women are kneading dough, To make cakes to the queen of the heavens, And to pour out libations to other gods, So as to provoke Me to anger.

19 Me are they provoking to anger? an affirmation of Jehovah, Is it not themselves, For the shame of their own faces?

20 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah, Lo, Mine anger and My fury is poured out on this place, On man, and beast, and on tree of the field, And on fruit of the ground, And it hath burned, and it is not quenched.

21 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel, Your burnt-offerings add to your sacrifices, And eat ye flesh.

22 For I did not speak with your fathers, Nor did I command them in the day of My bringing them out of the land of Egypt, Concerning the matters of burnt-offering and sacrifice,

23 But this thing I commanded them, saying: Hearken to My voice, And I have been to you for God, And ye--ye are to Me for a people, And have walked in all the way that I command you, So that it is well for you.

24 And they have not hearkened, nor inclined their ear, And they walk in the counsels, In the stubbornness, of their evil heart, And are for backward, and not for forward.

25 Even from the day when your fathers Went out of the land of Egypt till this day, I send to you all my servants the prophets, Daily rising early and sending,

26 And they have not hearkened unto Me, Nor inclined their ear, and harden their neck, They have done evil above their fathers.

27 And thou hast spoken unto them all these words, And they do not hearken to thee, And thou hast called unto them, And they do not answer thee.

28 And thou hast said unto them: This [is] the nation that hath not hearkened, To the voice of Jehovah its God, Nor have they accepted instruction, Perished hath stedfastness, Yea, it hath been cut off from their mouth.

29 Cut off thy crown, and cast [it] away, And lift up on high places lamentation, For Jehovah hath rejected, And He leaveth the generation of His wrath.

30 For the sons of Judah Have done the evil thing in Mine eyes, An affirmation of Jehovah, They have set their abominations in the house On which My name is called--to defile it,

31 And have built the high places of Tophet, That [are] in the valley of the son of Hinnom, To burn their sons and their daughters with fire, Which I did not command, Nor did it come up on My heart.

32 Therefore, lo, days are coming, An affirmation of Jehovah, And it is not said any more, `The Tophet,' And `Valley of the son of Hinnom,' But `Valley of the slaughter,' And they have buried in Tophet--without place.

33 And the carcase of this people hath been for food To a fowl of the heavens, and to a beast of the earth, And there is none troubling.

34 And I have caused to cease from cities of Judah, And from streets of Jerusalem, The voice of joy, and the voice of gladness, Voice of bridegroom, and voice of bride, For the land doth become a desolation!

Jeremiah 8

1 At that time, an affirmation of Jehovah, They bring the bones of the kings of Judah, And the bones of its princes, And the bones of the priests, And the bones of the prophets, And the bones of inhabitants of Jerusalem, Out of their graves,

2 And have spread them to sun, and to moon, And to all the host of the heavens, that they have loved, And that they have served, And that they have walked after, And that they have sought, And to which they have bowed themselves, They are not gathered, nor buried, They are for dung on the face of the ground.

3 And chosen is death rather than life By all the remnant who are left of this evil family, In all the remaining places, whither I have driven them, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts.

4 And thou hast said unto them: Thus said Jehovah, Do they fall, and not rise? Doth he turn back, and not return?

5 Wherefore hath this people of Jerusalem Turned back--a perpetual backsliding? They have kept hold on deceit, They have refused to turn back.

6 I have given attention, yea, I hearken, They do not speak right, No man hath repented of his wickedness, Saying, What have I done? Every one hath turned to his courses, As a horse is rushing into battle.

7 Even a stork in the heavens hath known her seasons, And turtle, and swallow, and crane, Have watched the time of their coming, And--My people have not known the judgment of Jehovah.

8 How do ye say, We [are] wise, And the law of Jehovah [is] with us? Surely, lo, falsely it hath wrought, The false pen of scribes.

9 Ashamed have been the wise, They have been affrighted, and are captured, Lo, against a word of Jehovah they kicked, And the wisdom of what--have they?

10 Therefore, I give their wives to others, Their fields to dispossessors, For from the least even unto the greatest, Every one is gaining dishonest gain, From prophet even unto priest, every one is dealing falsely.

11 And they heal the breach of the daughter of my people slightly, Saying, Peace, peace! and there is no peace.

12 They were ashamed when they did abomination! Yea, they are not at all ashamed, And blushing they have not known, Therefore, they do fall among falling ones, In the time of their inspection they stumble, said Jehovah.

13 I utterly consume them, an affirmation of Jehovah, There are no grapes in the vine, Yea, there are no figs in the fig-tree, And the leaf hath faded, And the strength they have passeth from them.

14 Wherefore are we sitting still? Be gathered, and we go in to the fenced cities, And we are silent there, For Jehovah our God hath made us silent, Yea, He causeth us to drink water of gall, For we have sinned against Jehovah.

15 Looking for peace--and there is no good, For a time of healing, and lo, terror.

16 From Dan hath been heard the snorting of his horses, From the voice of the neighings of his mighty ones, Trembled hath all the land, And they come in and consume the land and its fulness, The city and the inhabitants in it.

17 For, lo, I am sending among you serpents, Vipers that have no charmer, And they have bitten you, an affirmation of Jehovah.

18 My refreshing for me [is] sorrow, For me my heart [is] sick.

19 Lo, the voice of a cry of the daughter of my people from a land afar off, Is Jehovah not in Zion? is her king not in her? Wherefore have they provoked Me with their graven images, With the vanities of a foreigner?

20 Harvest hath passed, summer hath ended, And we--we have not been saved.

21 For a breach of the daughter of my people have I been broken, I have been black, astonishment hath seized me.

22 Is there no balm in Gilead? Is there no physician there? For wherefore hath not the health of the daughter of my people gone up?

Jeremiah 9

1 Who doth make my head waters, And mine eye a fountain of tears? And I weep by day and by night, For the wounded of the daughter of my people.

2 Who doth give me in a wilderness A lodging-place of travellers? And I leave my people, and go from them, For all of them [are] adulterers, An assembly of treacherous ones.

3 And they bend their tongue, their bow [is] a lie, And not for stedfastness have they been mighty in the land, For from evil unto evil they have gone forth, And Me they have not known, An affirmation of Jehovah!

4 Each of his friend--beware ye, And on any brother, do not trust, For every brother doth utterly supplant, For every friend slanderously doth walk,

5 And each at his friend they mock, And truth they do not speak, They taught their tongue to speak falsehood, To commit iniquity they have laboured.

6 thy dwelling [is] in the midst of deceit, Through deceit they refused to know Me, An affirmation of Jehovah.

7 Therefore, thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Lo, I am refining them, and have tried them, For how do I do because of the daughter of My people?

8 A slaughtering arrow [is] their tongue, Deceit it hath spoken in its mouth, Peace with its neighbour it speaketh, And in its heart it layeth its ambush,

9 For these things do not I see after them? An affirmation of Jehovah, Against a nation such as this doth not My soul avenge itself?

10 For the mountains I lift up weeping and wailing, And for the habitations of the wilderness a lamentation, For they have been burnt up without any passing over, Nor have they heard the voice of cattle, From the fowl of the heavens unto the beast they have fled, they have gone.

11 And I make Jerusalem become heaps, A habitation of dragons, And the cities of Judah I make a desolation, Without inhabitant.

12 Who [is] the wise man? and he understandeth this, And he to whom the mouth of Jehovah spake? And he doth declare it, For what hath the land perished? It hath been burnt up as a wilderness, Without any passing through.

13 And Jehovah saith: Because of their forsaking My law that I set before them, And they have not hearkened to My voice nor walked in it,

14 And they walk after the stubbornness of their heart, And after the Baalim, that their fathers taught them,

15 Therefore, thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel: Lo, I am causing them--this people--to eat wormwood, And I have caused them to drink water of gall,

16 And I have scattered them among nations Which they knew not, they and their fathers, And have sent after them the sword, Till I have consumed them.

17 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Consider ye, and call for mourning women, And they come, And to the wise women send, and they come,

18 And they hasten, and lift up for us a wailing. And run down our eyes do tears, And from our eyelids do waters flow.

19 For--a voice of wailing is heard from Zion: How have we been spoiled! We have been greatly ashamed, Because we have forsaken the land, Because they have cast down our tabernacles.

20 But hear, ye women, a word of Jehovah, And your ear receiveth a word of His mouth, And teach ye your daughters wailing, and each her neighbour lamentation.

21 For death hath come up into our windows, It hath come into our palaces, To cut off the suckling from without, Young men from the broad places.

22 Speak thus--an affirmation of Jehovah, And fallen hath the carcase of man, As dung on the face of the field, And as a handful after the reaper, And there is none gathering.

23 Thus said Jehovah: Let not the wise boast himself in his wisdom, Nor let the mighty boast himself in his might, Let not the rich boast himself in his riches,

24 But--in this let the boaster boast himself, In understanding and knowing Me, For I [am] Jehovah, doing kindness, Judgment, and righteousness, in the earth, For in these I have delighted, An affirmation of Jehovah.

25 Lo, days are coming--an affirmation of Jehovah, And I have laid a charge on all circumcised in the foreskin,

26 On Egypt, and on Judah, and on Edom, And on the sons of Ammon, and on Moab, And on all cutting the corner [of the beard], Who are dwelling in the wilderness, For all the nations [are] uncircumcised, And all the house of Israel [are] uncircumcised in heart!

Jeremiah 10

1 Hear ye the word, O house of Israel, That Jehovah hath spoken for you.

2 Thus said Jehovah: Unto the way of the nations accustom not yourselves, And by the signs of the heavens be not affrighted, For the nations are affrighted by them.

3 For the statutes of the peoples are vanity, For a tree from a forest hath one cut, Work of the hands of an artificer, with an axe,

4 With silver and with gold they beautify it, With nails and with hammers they fix it, And it doth not stumble.

5 As a palm they [are] stiff, and they speak not, They are surely borne, for they step not, Be not afraid of them, for they do no evil, Yea, also to do good is not in them.

6 Because there is none like Thee, O Jehovah, Great [art] Thou, and great Thy name in might.

7 Who doth not fear Thee, king of the nations? For to Thee it is becoming, For among all the wise of the nations, And in all their kingdom there is none like Thee.

8 And in one they are brutish and foolish, An instruction of vanities [is] the tree itself.

9 Spread-out silver from Tarshish is brought, And gold from Uphaz, Work of an artisan, and of the hands of a refiner, Blue and purple [is] their clothing, Work of the skilful--all of them.

10 And Jehovah [is] a God of truth, He [is] a living God, and a king age-during, From His wrath shake doth the earth, And nations endure not His indignation.

11 Thus do ye say to them, The gods Who the heavens and earth have not made, They do perish from the earth, And from under these heavens.

12 The maker of the earth by His power, The establisher of the world by His wisdom, Who, by His understanding, stretched forth the heavens,

13 At the voice He giveth forth, A multitude of waters [is] in the heavens, And He causeth vapours to come up from the end of the earth, Lightnings for rain He hath made, And bringeth out wind from His treasures.

14 Brutish is every man by knowledge, Put to shame is every refiner by a graven image, For false [is] his molten image. And there is no breath in them.

15 Vanity [are] they, work of erring ones, In the time of their inspection they perish.

16 Not like these [is] the Portion of Jacob, For framer of all things [is] He, And Israel [is] the rod of His inheritance, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name.

17 Gather from the land thy merchandise, O dweller in the bulwark,

18 For thus said Jehovah: Lo, I am slinging out the inhabitants of the land at this time, And have been an adversary to them, So that they are found out.

19 Woe to me for my breaking, Grievious hath been my smiting, And I said, Only, this [is] my sickness, and I bear it.

20 My tent hath been spoiled, And all my cords have been broken, My sons have gone out from me, and they are not, There is none stretching out any more my tent, And raising up my curtains.

21 For the shepherds have become brutish, And Jehovah they have not sought, Therefore they have not acted wisely, And all their flock is scattered.

22 A voice of a report, lo, it hath come, Even a great shaking from the north country, To make the cities of Judah a desolation, A habitation of dragons.

23 I have known, O Jehovah, that not of man [is] his way, Not of man the going and establishing of his step.

24 Chastise me, O Jehovah, only in judgment, Not in Thine anger, lest Thou make me small.

25 Pour out Thy fury on the nations that have not known Thee, And on the families that have not called in Thy name, For they have eaten up Jacob, Yea, they have eaten him up, yea, they consume him, And his habitation they have made desolate!

Jeremiah 11

1 The word that hath been unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying:

2 `Hear ye the words of this covenant, and ye have spoken unto the men of Judah, and unto the inhabitants of Jerusalem,

3 and thou hast said unto them, Thus said Jehovah God of Israel: Cursed [is] the man who doth not obey the words of this covenant,

4 That I commanded your fathers, In the day of My bringing them out from the land of Egypt, Out of the iron furnace, saying, Hearken to My voice, and ye have done them, According to all that I command you, And ye have been to Me for a people,And I am to you for God,

5 In order to establish the oath that I have sworn to your fathers, To give to them a land flowing with milk and honey, as this day. And I answer and say, `Amen, O Jehovah.'

6 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Proclaim all these words in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem, saying: Hear ye the words of this covenant, And ye have done them.

7 For I certainly testified against your fathers, In the day of My bringing them up out of the land of Egypt--till this day, Rising early and testifying, saying, Hearken to My voice,

8 And they have not hearkened nor inclined their ear, And they walk each in the stubbornness of their evil heart, And I bring on them all the words of this covenant, That I commanded to do, and they did not.'

9 And Jehovah saith unto me: `A conspiracy is found in the men of Judah, And in the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

10 They have turned back to the iniquities of their first fathers, Who refused to hear My words, And they have gone after other gods to serve them, The house of Israel, and the house of Judah, Have made void My covenant, that I made with their fathers.

11 Therefore thus said Jehovah: Lo, I am bringing in unto them evil, That they are not able to go out from, And they have cried unto Me, And I do not hearken unto them.

12 And the cities of Judah, and inhabitants of Jerusalem have gone, And they have cried unto the gods, To whom they are making perfume, And they give no deliverance at all to them, In the time of their vexation.

13 For--the number of thy cities have been thy gods, O Judah, And--the number of the streets of Jerusalem Ye have placed altars to a shameful thing, Altars to make perfume to Baal.

14 And thou, thou dost not pray for this people, Nor dost thou lift up for them cry and prayer, For I do not hearken in the time of their calling unto Me for their vexation.

15 What--to My beloved in My house, Her doing wickedness with many, And the holy flesh do pass over from thee? When thou dost evil, then thou exultest.

16 `An olive, green, fair, of goodly fruit,' Hath Jehovah called thy name, At the noise of a great tumult He hath kindled fire against it, And broken have been its thin branches.

17 And Jehovah of Hosts, who is planting thee, Hath spoken evil concerning thee, For the evil of the house of Israel, and of the house of Judah, That they have done to themselves, To provoke Me to anger, to make perfume to Baal.

18 And, O Jehovah, cause me to know, and I know, Then Thou hast showed me their doings.

19 And I [am] as a trained lamb brought to slaughter, And I have not known That against me they have devised devices: We destroy the tree with its food, and cut him off From the land of the living, And his name is not remembered again.

20 And O Jehovah of Hosts, judging righteousness, Trying reins and heart, I do see Thy vengeance against them, For unto Thee I have revealed my cause.'

21 Therefore, thus said Jehovah concerning the men of Anathoth, who are seeking thy life, saying: Do not prophesy in the name of Jehovah, And thou dost not die by our hands.

22 Therefore, thus said Jehovah of Hosts: `Lo, I am seeing after them, The chosen ones die by sword, Their sons and their daughters die by famine,

23 And they have no remnant, For I bring evil unto the men of Anathoth, The year of their inspection!'

Jeremiah 12

1 Righteous [art] Thou, O Jehovah, When I plead towards thee, Only, judgments do I speak with Thee, Wherefore did the way of the wicked prosper? At rest have been all treacherous dealers.

2 Thou hast planted them, yea, they have taken root, They go on, yea, they have made fruit, Near [art] Thou in their mouth, And far off from their reins.

3 And Thou, O Jehovah, Thou hast known me, Thou seest me, and hast tried my heart with Thee, Draw them away as sheep to slaughter, And separate them for a day of slaughter.

4 Till when doth the earth mourn, And the herb of the whole field wither? For the wickedness of those dwelling in it, Consumed have been beast and fowl, Because they said, `He doth not see our latter end.'

5 For--with footmen thou hast run, And they weary thee, And how dost thou fret thyself with horses! Even in the land of peace, [In which] thou art confident--And how dost thou in the rising of Jordan!

6 For even thy brethren and the house of thy father, Even they dealt treacherously against thee, Even they--they called after thee fully, Trust not in them, when they speak to thee good things.

7 I have forsaken My house, I have left Mine inheritance, I have given the beloved of My soul Into the hand of her enemies.

8 Mine inheritance hath been to Me as a lion in a forest, She gave forth against Me with her voice, Therefore I have hated her.

9 A speckled fowl [is] Mine inheritance to Me? Is the fowl round about against her? Come, assemble, every beast of the field, Come ye for food.

10 Many shepherds did destroy My vineyard, They have trodden down My portion, They have made My desirable portion Become a wilderness--a desolation.

11 He hath made it become a desolation, The desolation hath mourned unto Me, Desolated hath been all the land, But there is no one laying it to heart.

12 On all high places in the plain have spoilers come in, For the sword of Jehovah is consuming, From the end of the land even unto the end of the land, There is no peace to any flesh.

13 They sowed wheat, and have thorns reaped, They have become sick--they profit not, And they have been ashamed of your increases, Because of the fierceness of the anger of Jehovah.

14 Thus said Jehovah concerning all my evil neighbours, who are striking against the inheritance that I caused my people--Israel--to inherit: `Lo, I am plucking them from off their ground, And the house of Judah I pluck out of their midst.

15 And it hath been, after My plucking them out, I turn back, and have pitied them, And I have brought them back, Each to his inheritance, and each to his land.

16 And it hath come to pass, If they learn well the ways of My people, To swear by My name, `Jehovah liveth,' As they taught My people to swear by Baal, Then they have been built up in the midst of My people.

17 And if they do not hearken, Then I have plucked up that nation, Plucking up and destroying, An affirmation of Jehovah!'

Jeremiah 13

1 Thus said Jehovah unto me, `Go, and thou hast got for thee a girdle of linen, and hast placed it on thy loins, and into water thou dost not cause it to enter:'

2 and I get the girdle, according to the word of Jehovah, and I place [it] on my loins.

3 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me a second time, saying,

4 `Take the girdle that thou hast got, that [is] on thy loins, and rise, go to Phrat, and hide it there in a hole of the rock;

5 and I go and hide it by Phrat, as Jehovah commanded me.

6 And it cometh to pass, at the end of many days, that Jehovah saith unto me, `Rise, go to Phrat, and take thence the girdle, that I commanded thee to hide there;'

7 and I go to Phrat, and dig, and take the girdle from the place where I had hid it; and lo, the girdle hath been marred, it is not profitable for anything.

8 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying, `Thus said Jehovah:

9 Thus do I mar the excellency of Judah, And the great excellency of Jerusalem.

10 This evil people, who refuse to hear My words, Who walk in the stubbornness of their heart, And go after other gods to serve them, And to bow themselves to them, Yea it is--as this girdle, that is not profitable for anything.

11 For, as the girdle cleaveth unto the loins of a man, So I caused to cleave unto Me The whole house of Israel, And the whole house of Judah, an affirmation of Jehovah, To be to Me for a people, and for a name, And for praise, and for beauty, And they have not hearkened.

12 And thou hast said unto them this word, Thus said Jehovah, God of Israel, `Every bottle is full of wine,' And they have said unto thee: `Do we not certainly know that every bottle is full of wine?'

13 And thou hast said unto them, `Thus said Jehovah: Lo, I am filling all the inhabitants of this land, And the kings who sit for David on his throne, And the priests, and the prophets, And all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, [With] drunkenness,

14 And have dashed them one against another, And the fathers and the sons together, An affirmation of Jehovah, I do not pity, nor spare, nor have I mercy, So as not to destroy them.

15 Hear, and give ear--be not haughty, For Jehovah hath spoken.

16 Give ye to Jehovah your God honour, Before He doth cause darkness, And before your feet stumble on dark mountains, And ye have waited for light, And He hath made it for deathshade, And hath appointed [it] for thick darkness.

17 And if ye do not hear it, In secret places doth my soul weep, because of pride, Yea, it weepeth sore, And the tear cometh down mine eyes, For the flock of Jehovah hath been taken captive.

18 Say to the king and to the mistress: Make yourselves low--sit still, For come down have your principalities, The crown of your beauty.

19 The cities of the south have been shut up, And there is none opening, Judah hath been removed--all of her, She hath been removed completely--

20 Lift up your eyes, and see those coming in from the north, Where [is] the drove given to thee, thy beautiful flock?

21 What dost thou say, when He looketh after thee? And thou--thou hast taught them [to be] over thee--leaders for head? Do not pangs seize thee as a travailing woman?

22 And when thou dost say in thy heart, `Wherefore have these met me?' For the abundance of thine iniquity Have thy skirts been uncovered, Have thy heels suffered violence.

23 Doth a Cushite change his skin? and a leopard his spots? Ye also are able to do good, who are accustomed to do evil.

24 And I scatter them as stubble, Passing away, by a wind of the wilderness.

25 This [is] thy lot, the portion of thy measures from Me--an affirmation of Jehovah, Because thou hast forgotten me, And dost trust in falsehood.

26 I also have made bare thy skirts before thy face, And thy shame hath been seen.

27 Thine adulteries, and thy neighings, The wickedness of thy whoredom, on heights in a field, I have seen thine abominations. Woe to thee, O Jerusalem, Thou art not cleansed, after when [is it] again?

Jeremiah 14

1 That which hath been the word of Jehovah unto Jeremiah concerning the matters of the dearths:

2 Mourned hath Judah, and her gates have languished, They have mourned to the earth, And the cry of Jerusalem hath gone up.

3 And their honourable ones have sent their little ones to the water, They have come unto ditches, They have not found water, They have turned back--their vessels empty! They have been ashamed, And have blushed and covered their head.

4 Because the ground hath been broken, For there hath been no rain in the land, Ashamed have been husbandmen, They have covered their head.

5 For even the hind in the field hath brought forth--to forsake [it!] For there hath been no grass.

6 And wild asses have stood on high places, They have swallowed up wind like dragons, Consumed have been their eyes, for there is no herb.

7 Surely our iniquities have testified against us, O Jehovah, work for Thy name's sake, For many have been our backslidings, Against Thee we have sinned.

8 O Hope of Israel--its saviour in time of trouble, Why art Thou as a sojourner in the land? And as a traveller turned aside to lodge?

9 Why art Thou as one dumb? As a mighty one not able to save? And Thou [art] in our midst, O Jehovah, And Thy name over us is called, leave us not.

10 Thus said Jehovah concerning this people: Well they have loved to wander, Their feet they have not restrained, And Jehovah hath not accepted them, Now doth He remember their iniquity, And inspect their sin.

11 And Jehovah saith unto me: Thou dost not pray for this people for good,

12 When they fast, I hearken not unto their cry, And when they cause to ascend burnt-offering and present, I accept them not, For by sword, and by famine, And by pestilence, I am consuming them.

13 And I say, `Ah, Lord Jehovah, Lo, the prophets are saying to them: Ye do not see a sword, yea, famine is not to you, For true peace I give to you in this place.'

14 And Jehovah saith unto me: Falsehood the prophets are prophesying in My name, I did not send them, nor command them, Nor have I spoken unto them: A false vision, and divination, and vanity, And the deceit of their own heart, they are prophesying to you.

15 Therefore, thus said Jehovah concerning the prophets who are prophesying in My name, and I have not sent them, and they are saying, Sword and famine is not in this land: By sword and by famine are these prophets consumed.

16 And the people to whom they are prophesying, Are cast into out-places of Jerusalem, Because of the famine, and of the sword, And they have none burying them, Them, their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, And I have poured out upon them this evil.

17 And thou hast said unto them this word: Tears come down mine eyes night and day, And they do not cease, For, [with] a great breach, Broken hath been the virgin daughter of my people, A very grievous stroke.

18 If I have gone forth to the field, Then, lo, the pierced of the sword! And if I have entered the city, Then, lo, the diseased of famine! For both prophet and priest have gone up and down Unto a land that they knew not.

19 Hast Thou utterly rejected Judah? Zion hath Thy soul loathed? Wherefore hast Thou smitten us, And there is no healing to us? Looking for peace, and there is no good, And for a time of healing, and lo, terror.

20 We have known, O Jehovah, our wickedness, The iniquity of our fathers, For we have sinned against Thee.

21 Do not despise, for Thy name's sake, Dishonour not the throne of Thine honour, Remember, break not Thy covenant with us.

22 Are there among the vanities of the nations any causing rain? And do the heavens give showers? Art not Thou He, O Jehovah our God? And we wait for thee, for Thou--Thou hast done all these!

Jeremiah 15

1 And Jehovah saith unto me: Though Moses and Samuel should stand before Me, My soul is not toward this people, Send from before My face, and they go out.

2 And it hath come to pass, when they say to thee, Whither do we go out? that thou hast said unto them, Thus said Jehovah: Those who [are] for death--to death, And those who are for the sword, to the sword, And those who are for famine, to famine, And those who are for captivity, to captivity.

3 And I have appointed over them four kinds, an affirmation of Jehovah, The sword to slay, and the dogs to drag, And the fowl of the heavens, And the beast of the earth, to consume and to devour.

4 And I have given them for a trembling To all kingdoms of the earth, Because of Manasseh son of Hezekiah king of Judah, For that which he did in Jerusalem.

5 For who hath pity on thee, O Jerusalem? And who doth bemoan for thee? And who turneth aside to ask of thy welfare?

6 Thou--thou hast left Me--an affirmation of Jehovah, Backward thou goest, And I stretch out My hand against thee, And I destroy thee, I have been weary of repenting,

7 And I scatter them with a fan, in the gates the land, I bereaved, I have destroyed My people, From their ways they turned not back.

8 Its widows have been more to Me than the sand of the seas, I brought in to them-- against the mother--A young man--a spoiler--at noon. I caused to fall upon her suddenly, wrath and trouble.

9 Languished hath the bearer of seven, She hath breathed out her spirit, Gone in hath her sun while yet day, It hath been ashamed and confounded, And their residue to the sword I give up before their enemies, An affirmation of Jehovah.

10 Woe to me, my mother, For thou hast borne me a man of strife, And a man of contention to all the land, I have not lent on usury, Nor have they lent on usury to me--All of them are reviling me.

11 Jehovah said, Did I not direct thee for good? Did not I intercede for thee in a time of evil, And in a time of adversity, with the enemy?

12 Doth one break iron--northern iron, and brass?

13 Thy strength and thy treasures For a prey I do give--not for price, Even for all thy sins, and in all thy borders.

14 And I have caused thine enemies To pass over into the land--Thou hast not known, For a fire hath been kindled in Mine anger, Against you it doth burn.

15 Thou, Thou hast known, O Jehovah, Remember me, and inspect me, And take vengeance for me of my pursuers, In Thy long-suffering take me not away, Know--I have borne for Thee reproach.

16 Thy words have been found, and I eat them, And Thy word is to me for a joy, And for the rejoicing of my heart, For Thy name is called on me, O Jehovah, God of Hosts.

17 I have not sat in an assembly of deriders, Nor do I exult, because of thy hand, -- Alone I have sat, For [with] indignation Thou hast filled me.

18 Why hath my pain been perpetual? And my wound incurable? It hath refused to be healed, Thou art surely to me as a failing stream, Waters not stedfast.

19 Therefore, thus said Jehovah: If thou turnest back, then I bring thee back, Before Me thou dost stand, And if thou bringest out the precious from the vile, As My mouth thou art! They--they turn back unto thee, And thou dost not turn back unto them.

20 And I have made thee to this people For a wall--brazen--fenced, And they have fought against thee, And they do not prevail against thee, For with thee [am] I to save thee, And to deliver thee--an affirmation of Jehovah,

21 And I have delivered thee from the hand of evil doers, And I have ransomed thee From the hand of the terrible!

Jeremiah 16

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 Thou dost not take to thee a wife, Nor hast thou sons and daughters in this place.

3 For thus said Jehovah, Of the sons and of the daughters who are born in this place, And of their mothers--those bearing them, And of their fathers--those begetting them in this land:

4 Of painful deaths they die, They are not lamented, nor are they buried, For dung on the face of the ground they are, And by sword and by famine are consumed, And their carcase hath been for food To the fowl of the heavens, And to the beast of the earth.

5 For thus said Jehovah: Do not enter the house of a mourning-feast, Nor go to lament nor bemoan for them, For I have removed My peace from this people, An affirmation of Jehovah, The kindness and the mercies.

6 And died have great and small in this land, They are not buried, and none lament for them, Nor doth any cut himself, nor become bald for them.

7 Nor do they deal out to them for mourning, To comfort him concerning the dead, Nor cause them to drink a cup of consolations For his father and for his mother.

8 A house of banqueting thou dost not enter, To sit with them, to eat and to drink,

9 For thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel: Lo, I am causing to cease from this place, Before your eyes, and in your days, The voice of joy, and the voice of rejoicing, The voice of bridegroom and voice of bride.

10 And it hath come to pass when thou declarest to this people all these words, and they have said unto thee, `For what hath Jehovah spoken against us all this great evil? yea, what [is] our iniquity, and what our sin, that we have sinned against Jehovah our God?'

11 Then thou hast said unto them: Because that your fathers have forsaken Me, An affirmation of Jehovah, And go after other gods, and serve them, And they bow themselves to them, And Me have forsaken, and My law not kept,

12 Ye also have done evil above your fathers, And lo, ye are walking each after the stubbornness of his evil heart, So as not to hearken unto Me.

13 And I have cast you from off this land, On to a land that ye have not known, Ye and your fathers, And ye have served there other gods by day and by night, Where I do not give to you grace.

14 Therefore, lo, days are coming, An affirmation of Jehovah, And it is not said any more: `Jehovah liveth, who brought up The sons of Israel out of the land of Egypt,'

15 But, `Jehovah liveth, who brought up The sons of Israel out of the land of the north, And out of all the lands whither He drove them,' And I have brought them back to their land, That I gave to their fathers.

16 Lo, I am sending for many fishers, An affirmation of Jehovah, And they have fished them, And after this I send for many hunters, And they have hunted them from off every mountain, And from off every hill, and from holes of the rocks.

17 For Mine eyes [are] upon all their ways, They have not been hidden from My face, Nor hath their iniquity been concealed from before Mine eyes.

18 And I have recompensed a first--A second time--their iniquity and their sin, Because of their polluting My land, With the carcase of their detestable things, Yea, their abominable things have filled Mine inheritance.

19 O Jehovah, my strength, and my fortress, And my refuge in a day of adversity, Unto Thee nations do come from the ends of earth, And say, Only falsehood did our fathers inherit, Vanity, and none among them is profitable.

20 Doth man make for himself gods, And they--no gods?

21 Therefore, lo, I am causing them to know at this time, I cause them to know My hand and My might, And they have known that My name [is] Jehovah!

Jeremiah 18

1 The word that hath been unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying,

2 Rise, and thou hast gone down [to] the potter's house, and there I cause thee to hear My words;

3 and I go down [to] the potter's house, and lo, he is doing a work on the stones,

4 and marred is the vessel that he is making, as clay in the hand of the potter, and he hath turned and he maketh it another vessel, as it was right in the eyes of the potter to make.

5 And there is a word of Jehovah to me, saying:

6 As this potter am I not able to do to you? O house of Israel, an affirmation of Jehovah. Lo, as clay in the hand of the potter, So [are] ye in My hand, O house of Israel.

7 The moment I speak concerning a nation, And concerning a kingdom, To pluck up and to break down, and to destroy,

8 And that nation hath turned from its evil, Because I have spoken against it, Then I have repented of the evil that I thought to do to it.

9 And the moment I speak concerning a nation, And concerning a kingdom, to build, and to plant,

10 And it hath done the evil thing in Mine eyes, So as not to hearken to My voice, Then I have repented of the good That I have spoken of doing to it.

11 And now, speak, I pray thee, unto men of Judah, And against inhabitants of Jerusalem, Saying: Thus said Jehovah: Lo, I am framing against you evil, And devising against you a device, Turn back, I pray you, each from his evil way And amen your ways and your doings.

12 And they have said, It is incurable, For after our own devices we do go, And each the stubbornness of his evil heart we do.

13 Therefore, thus said Jehovah: Ask, I pray you, among the nations, Who hath heard like these? A very horrible thing hath the virgin of Israel done.

14 Doth snow of Lebanon Cease from the rock of the field? Failed are the cold strange waters that flow?

15 But My people have forgotten Me, to a vain thing they make perfume, And they cause them to stumble in their ways--paths of old, To walk in paths--a way not raised up,

16 To make their land become a desolation, A hissing age-during, Every passer by it is astonished, And bemoaneth with his head.

17 As an east wind I scatter them before an enemy, The neck, and not the face, I shew them, In the day of their calamity.'

18 And they say, Come, And we devise against Jeremiah devices, For law doth not perish from the priest, Nor counsel from the wise, Nor the word from the prophet, Come, and we smite him with the tongue, And we do not attend to any of his words.

19 Give attention, O Jehovah, unto me, And hearken to the voice of those contending with me.

20 Is evil recompensed instead of good, That they have dug a pit for my soul? Remember my standing before Thee to speak good of them, To turn back Thy wrath from them.

21 Therefore, give up their sons to famine, And cause them to run on the sides of the sword, And their wives are bereaved and widows, And their men are slain by death, Their young men smitten by sword in battle,

22 A cry is heard from their houses, For Thou bringest against them suddenly a troop, For they dug a pit to capture me, And snares they have hidden for my feet.

23 And Thou, O Jehovah, Thou hast known, All their counsel against me [is] for death, Thou dost not cover over their iniquity, Nor their sin from before Thee blottest out, And they are made to stumble before Thee, In the time of Thine anger work against them!

Jeremiah 20

1 And Pashhur son of Immer the priest--who also [is] overseer, leader in the house of Jehovah--heareth Jeremiah prophesying these things,

2 and Pashhur smiteth Jeremiah the prophet, and putteth him unto the stocks, that [are] by the high gate of Benjamin, that [is] by the house of Jehovah.

3 and it cometh to pass on the morrow, that Pashhur bringeth out Jeremiah from the stocks, and Jeremiah saith unto him, `Not Pashhur hath Jehovah called thy name, but--Magor- Missabib.

4 For thus said Jehovah: Lo, I am making thee for a fear to thyself, And to all loving thee, And they have fallen by the sword of their enemies, and thine eyes are beholding, And all Judah I give into the hand of the king of Babylon, And he hath removed them to Babylon, And he hath smitten them with the sword.

5 And I have given all the strength of this city, And all its labour, and all its precious things, Yea, all the treasures of the kings of Judah I do give into the hand of their enemies, And they have spoiled them, and taken them, And have brought them into Babylon.

6 And thou, Pashhur, and all dwelling in thy house, Do go into captivity. and Babylon thou dost enter, And there thou diest, and there thou art buried, Thou and all loving thee, To whom thou hast prophesied falsely.'

7 Thou hast persuaded me, O Jehovah, and I am persuaded; Thou hast hardened me, and dost prevail, I have been for a laughter all the day, Every one is mocking at me,

8 Because from the time I speak I cry out, `Violence and destruction,' I cry, For the word of Jehovah hath been to me For reproach and for derision all the day.

9 And I said, `I do not mention Him, Nor do I speak any more in His name,' And it hath been in my heart As a burning fire shut up in my bones, And I have been weary of containing, And I am not able.

10 For I have heard the evil report of many, Fear [is] round about: `Declare, and we declare it,' All mine allies are watching [for] my halting, `Perhaps he is enticed, and we prevail over him, And we take our vengeance out of him.'

11 And Jehovah [is] with me, as a terrible mighty one, Therefore my persecutors stumble and prevail not, They have been exceedingly ashamed, For they have not acted wisely, Confusion age-during is not forgotten.

12 And, O Jehovah of Hosts, trier of the righteous, Beholder of reins and heart, I do see Thy vengeance out of them, For unto Thee I have revealed my cause.

13 Sing ye to Jehovah, praise Jehovah, For He hath delivered the soul of the needy From the hand of evil doers.

14 Cursed [is] the day in which I was born, The day that my mother bare me, Let it not be blessed!

15 Cursed [is] the man who bore tidings [to] my father, saying, `Born to thee hath been a child--a male,' Making him very glad!

16 Then hath that man been as the cities, That Jehovah overthrew, and repented not, And he hath heard a cry at morning, And a shout at time of noon.

17 Because he hath not put me to death from the womb, And my mother is to me--my grave, And her womb a pregnancy age-during.

18 Why [is] this? from the womb I have come out, To see labour and sorrow, Yea, consumed in shame are my days!

Jeremiah 21

1 The word that hath been unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, in the king Zedekiah's sending unto him Pashhur son of Malchiah, and Zephaniah son of Maaseiah the priest, saying,

2 `Inquire, we pray thee, for us at Jehovah, for Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon hath fought against us; perhaps Jehovah doth deal with us according to all His wonders, and doth cause him to go up from off us.'

3 And Jeremiah saith unto them, `Thus do ye say unto Zedekiah,

4 Thus said Jehovah, God of Israel: Lo, I am turning round the weapons of battle That [are] in your hand, With which ye do fight the king of Babylon, And the Chaldeans, who are laying siege against you, At the outside of the wall, And I have gathered them into the midst of this city,

5 And I--I have fought against you, With a stretched-out hand, and with a strong arm, And in anger, and in fury, and in great wrath,

6 And I have smitten the inhabitants of this city, Both man and beast, By a great pestilence do they die.

7 And after this--an affirmation of Jehovah, I give Zedekiah king of Judah, And his servants, and the people, And those left in this city, From the pestilence, from the sword, and from the famine, Into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, And into the hand of their enemies, And into the hand of those seeking their life, And he hath smitten them by the mouth of the sword, He hath no pity on them, Nor doth he spare, nor hath he mercy.

8 And unto this people thou dost say, Thus said Jehovah: Lo, I am setting before you the way of life, And the way of death!

9 Whoso is abiding in this city--dieth, By sword, and by famine, and by pestilence, And whoso is going forth, And hath fallen unto the Chaldeans, Who are laying siege against you-- liveth, And his life hath been to him for a spoil.

10 For I have set My face against this city for evil, And not for good--an affirmation of Jehovah. Into the hand of the king of Babylon it is given, And he hath burned it with fire.

11 And as to the house of the king of Judah, Hear ye a word of Jehovah;

12 O house of David, thus said Jehovah: Decide ye judgment at morning, And deliver the plundered from the hand of the oppressor, Lest My fury go forth as fire, And hath burned, and none is quenching, Because of the evil of your doings.

13 Lo, I [am] against thee--an affirmation of Jehovah, O inhabitant of the valley, rock of the plain, Who are saying, Who cometh down against us? And who cometh into our habitations?

14 And I have laid a charge against you, According to the fruit of your doings, An affirmation of Jehovah, And I have kindled a fire in its forest, And it hath consumed--all its suburbs!

Jeremiah 22

1 Thus said Jehovah, `Go down [to] the house of the king of Judah, and thou hast spoken there this word, and hast said,

2 Hear a word of Jehovah, O king of Judah, who art sitting on the throne of David, thou, and thy servants, and thy people, who are coming in at these gates,

3 Thus said Jehovah: Do ye judgment and righteousness, And deliver the plundered from the hand of the oppressor, And sojourner, orphan, and widow, ye do not oppress nor wrong, And innocent blood ye do not shed in this place.

4 For, if ye certainly do this thing, Then come in by the gates of this house Have kings sitting for David on his throne, Riding on chariot, and on horses, He, and his servants, and his people.

5 And if ye do not hear these words, By myself I have sworn--an affirmation of Jehovah, That this house is for a desolation.

6 For thus said Jehovah, Concerning the house of the king of Judah: Gilead [art] thou to Me--head of Lebanon, If not--I make thee a wilderness, Cities not inhabited.

7 And I have separated for thee destroyers, Each with his weapons, And they have cut down the choice of thy cedars, And have cast them on the fire.

8 And many nations have passed by this city, And they have said, each to his neighbour, For what hath Jehovah done thus to this great city?

9 And they have said, `Because that they have forsaken The covenant of Jehovah their God, And bow themselves to other gods, and serve them.'

10 Ye do not weep for the dead, nor bemoan for him, Weep ye sore for the traveller, For he doth not return again, Nor hath he seen the land of his birth.

11 For thus said Jehovah concerning Shallum son of Josiah king of Judah, who is reigning instead of Josiah his father, who hath gone forth from this place: He doth not turn back hither again;

12 For in the place whither they have removed him he dieth, And this land he doth not see again.

13 Woe to him who is building his house by unrighteousness, And his upper chambers by injustice, On his neighbour he layeth service for nought, And his wage he doth not give to him.

14 Who is saying, `I build for myself a large house, And airy upper chambers,' And he hath cut out for himself its windows, Ceiled with cedar, and painted with vermilion.

15 Dost thou reign, because thou art fretting thyself in cedar? Thy father--did he not eat and drink? Yea, he did judgment and righteousness, Then [it is] well with him.

16 He decided the cause of the poor and needy, Then [it is] well--is it not to know Me? An affirmation of Jehovah.

17 But thine eyes and thy heart are not, Except on thy dishonest gain, And on shedding of innocent blood, And on oppression, and on doing of violence.

18 Therefore, thus said Jehovah concerning Jehoiakim son of Josiah king of Judah: They do not lament for him, Ah, my brother, and Ah, sister, They do not lament for him, Ah, lord, and Ah, his honour.

19 The burial of an ass--he is buried, Dragged and cast out thence to the gates of Jerusalem.

20 Go up to Lebanon, and cry, And in Bashan give forth thy voice, And cry from Abarim, For destroyed have been all loving thee.

21 I have spoken unto thee in thine ease, Thou hast said, `I do not hearken,' This [is] thy way from thy youth, For thou hast not hearkened to My voice.

22 All thy friends consume doth wind, And thy lovers into captivity do go, Surely then thou art ashamed, And hast blushed for all thy wickedness.

23 O dweller in Lebanon, making a nest among cedars, How gracious hast thou been when pangs come to thee, Pain--as of a travailing woman.

24 I live--an affirmation of Jehovah, Though Coniah son of Jehoiakim king of Judah Were a seal on My right hand, Surely thence I draw thee away,

25 And I have given thee into the hand of those seeking thy life, And into hands of which thou art afraid, Into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, And into the hand of the Chaldeans.

26 And I have cast thee, And thy mother who bore thee, unto another country, Where ye were not born, and there do ye die.

27 And to the land whither they are lifting up their soul to return, Thither they do not return.

28 A grief--a despised broken thing--is this man Coniah? A vessel in which there is no pleasure? Wherefore have they been cast up and down, He and his seed, Yea, they were cast on to a land that they knew not?

29 Earth, earth, earth, hear a word of Jehovah,

30 Thus said Jehovah: Write ye this man childless, A man--he doth not prosper in his days, For none of his seed doth prosper, Sitting on the throne of David, And ruling again in Judah!

Jeremiah 23

1 Woe to shepherds destroying, And scattering the flock of My pasture, An affirmation of Jehovah.

2 Therefore, thus said Jehovah, God of Israel, Against the shepherds who feed My people, Ye have scattered My flock, and drive them away, And have not inspected them, Lo, I am charging on you the evil of your doings, An affirmation of Jehovah.

3 And I do gather the remnant of My flock Out of all the lands whither I drove them, And have brought them back unto their fold, And they have been fruitful, and multiplied.

4 And I have raised for them shepherds, And they have fed them, And they fear no more, nor are affrighted, Nor are they lacking--an affirmation of Jehovah.

5 Lo, days are coming--an affirmation of Jehovah, And I have raised to David a righteous shoot, And a king hath reigned and acted wisely, And done judgment and righteousness in the earth.

6 In his days is Judah saved, and Israel dwelleth confidently, And this his name that Jehovah proclaimeth him, `Our Righteousness.'

7 Therefore, lo, days are coming, An affirmation of Jehovah, And they do not say any more, Jehovah liveth who brought up The sons of Israel out of the land of Egypt,

8 But--Jehovah liveth, who brought up, And who brought in, the seed of the house of Israel, From the land of the north, And from all the lands whither I drove them, And they have dwelt on their own ground!

9 In reference to the prophets: Broken hath been my heart in my midst, Fluttered have all my bones, I have been as a man--a drunkard, And as a man--wine hath passed over him, Because of Jehovah, and of His holy words.

10 For of adulterers hath the land been full, For because of these hath the land mourned, Dried up hath been the pleasant places of the wilderness, And their course is evil, and their might--not right.

11 For both prophet and priest have been profane, Yea, in My house I found their wickedness, An affirmation of Jehovah.

12 Therefore is their way to them as slippery places, Into thick darkness they are driven, And they have fallen in it, For I bring in against them evil, The year of their inspection, An affirmation of Jehovah.

13 And in prophets of Samaria I have seen folly, They have prophesied by Baal, And cause my people--Israel--to err.

14 And in prophets of Jerusalem I have seen a horrible thing, Committing adultery, and walking falsely, Yea, they strengthened the hands of evil doers, So that they have not turned back Each from his wickedness, They have been to me--all of them--as Sodom, And its inhabitants as Gomorrah.

15 Therefore, thus said Jehovah of Hosts, concerning the prophets: Lo, I am causing them to eat wormwood, And have caused them to drink water of gall, For, from prophets of Jerusalem Hath profanity gone forth to all the land.

16 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Ye do not hearken unto the words Of the prophets who are prophesying to you, They are making you vain things, A vision of their own heart they speak, Not from the mouth of Jehovah.

17 Saying diligently to those despising The word of Jehovah: Peace is for you, And [to] every one walking in the stubbornness of his heart they have said: Evil doth not come in unto you.

18 For who hath stood in the counsel of Jehovah, And seeth and heareth His word? Who hath regarded My word, and hearkeneth?

19 Lo, a whirlwind of Jehovah--Fury hath gone out, even a piercing whirlwind, On the head of the wicked it stayeth.

20 The anger of Jehovah doth not turn back Till His doing, and till His establishing, The thoughts of His heart, In the latter end of the days ye attend to it With understanding.

21 I have not sent the prophets, and they have run, I have not spoken unto them, and they have prophesied.

22 But--if they stood in My counsel, Then they cause My people to hear My words, And they turn them back from their evil way, And from the evil of their doings.

23 A God near [am] I--an affirmation of Jehovah, And not a God afar off?

24 Is any one hidden in secret places, And I see him not? an affirmation of Jehovah, Do not I fill the heavens and the earth? An affirmation of Jehovah.

25 I have heard that which the prophets said, Who prophesy in My name falsehood, saying, `I have dreamed, I have dreamed.'

26 Till when is it in the heart of the prophets? The prophets of falsehood, Yea, prophets of the deceit of their heart,

27 Who are devising to cause My people To forget My name by their dreams, That they recount each to his neighbour, As their fathers forgot my name for Baal.

28 The prophet with whom [is] a dream, Let him recount the dream, And he with whom [is] My word, Let him truly speak My word. What--to the straw with the corn? An affirmation of Jehovah.

29 Is it not thus? My word [is] as a fire, An affirmation of Jehovah. And as a hammer--it breaketh in pieces a rock.

30 Therefore, lo, I [am] against the prophets, An affirmation of Jehovah, Stealing My words each from his neighbour.

31 Lo, I [am] against the prophets, An affirmation of Jehovah, Who are making smooth their tongue, And they affirm--an affirmation.

32 Lo, I [am] against the prophets of false dreams, An affirmation of Jehovah, And they recount them, and cause my people to err, By their falsehoods, and by their instability, And I-- I have not sent them, Nor have I commanded them, And they are not at all profitable to this people, An affirmation of Jehovah.

33 And when this people, or the prophet, Or a priest, doth ask thee, saying, What [is] the burden of Jehovah? Then thou hast said unto them: Ye [are] the burden, and I have left you, An affirmation of Jehovah.

34 And the prophet, and the priest, and the people, That saith, The burden of Jehovah, I have seen after that man, and after his house.

35 Thus do ye say each unto his neighbour, And each unto his brother: What hath Jehovah answered? And what hath Jehovah spoken?

36 And the burden of Jehovah ye do not mention any more, For the burden to each is- -His word, And ye have overturned the words of the living God, Jehovah of Hosts, our God.

37 Thus dost thou say unto the prophet What hath Jehovah answered thee? And what hath Jehovah spoken?

38 And if the burden of Jehovah ye say, Therefore thus said Jehovah: Because of your saying this word, The burden of Jehovah, And I do send unto you, saying, Ye do not say, The burden of Jehovah.

39 Therefore, lo, I--I have taken you utterly away, And I have sent you out, And the city that I gave to you, And to your fathers, from before My face,

40 And I have put on you reproach age-during, And shame age-during that is not forgotten!

Jeremiah 25

1 The word that hath been unto Jeremiah concerning all the people of Judah, in the fourth year of Jehoiakim son of Josiah king of Judah, --it [is] the first year of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, --

2 Which Jeremiah the prophet hath spoken concerning all the people of Judah, even unto all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying:

3 `From the thirteenth year of Josiah son of Amon king of Judah, and unto this day-- this three and twentieth year--hath the word of Jehovah been unto me, and I speak unto you, rising early and speaking, and ye have not hearkened;

4 And Jehovah hath sent unto you all His servants, the prophets, rising early and sending, and ye have not hearkened, nor inclined your ear to hear, saying:

5 `Turn back, I pray you, each from his evil way, and from the evil of your doings, and dwell on the ground that Jehovah hath given to you and to your fathers from age unto age,

6 And ye do not go after other gods to serve them, and to bow yourselves to them, nor do ye provoke Me to anger with the work of your hands, and I do no evil to you;

7 And ye have not hearkened unto Me--an affirmation of Jehovah--so as to provoke Me to anger with the work of your hands for evil to you.

8 `Therefore thus said Jehovah of Hosts, Because that ye have not obeyed My words,

9 Lo, I am sending, and have taken all the families of the north--an affirmation of Jehovah--even unto Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, My servant, and have brought them in against this land, and against its inhabitants, and against all these nations round about, and have devoted them, and appointed them for an astonishment, and for a hissing, and for wastes ageduring.

10 And I have destroyed from them the voice of rejoicing, and the voice of joy, voice of bridegroom and voice of bride, noise of millstones, and the light of lamps.

11 And all this land hath been for a waste, for an astonishment, and these nations have served the king of Babylon seventy years.

12 `And it hath come to pass, at the fulness of seventy years, I charge against the king of Babylon, and against that nation--an affirmation of Jehovah--their iniquity, and against the land of the Chaldeans, and have appointed it for desolations age-during.

13 And I have brought in on that land all My words that I have spoken against it, all that is written in this book, that Jeremiah hath prophesied concerning all the nations.

14 For laid service on them--also them--have many nations and great kings, and I have given recompence to them according to their doing, and according to the work of their hands.

15 `For thus said Jehovah God of Israel unto me, Take the wine cup of this fury out of My hand, and thou hast caused all the nations to drink it unto whom I am sending thee;

16 And they have drunk, and shaken themselves and shewn themselves foolish, because of the sword that I am sending among them.

17 `And I take the cup out of the hand of Jehovah, and cause all the nations to drink unto whom Jehovah sent me:

18 Jerusalem, and the cities of Judah, And its kings, its heads, To give them to waste, to astonishment, To hissing, and to reviling, as [at] this day.

19 Pharaoh king of Egypt, and his servants, And his heads, and all his people,

20 And all the mixed people, And all the kings of the land of Uz, And all the kings of the land of the Philistines, And Ashkelon, and Gazzah, and Ekron, And the remnant of Ashdod,

21 Edom, and Moab, and the sons of Ammon,

22 And all the kings of Tyre, And all the kings of Zidon, And the kings of the isle that [is] beyond the sea,

23 Dedan, and Tema, and Buz, And all cutting the corners [of the beard],

24 And all the kings of Arabia, And all the kings of the mixed people, Who are dwelling in the wilderness,

25 And all the kings of Zimri, And all the kings of Elam, And all the kings of Media,

26 And all the kings of the north, The near and the far off, one unto another, And all the kingdoms of the earth, That [are] on the face of the ground, And king Sheshach drinketh after them.

27 And thou hast said unto them: Thus said Jehovah of Hosts God of Israel, Drink ye, yea drink abundantly, And vomit, and fall, and rise not, Because of the sword that I am sending among you.

28 And it hath come to pass, When they refuse to receive the cup out of thy hand to drink, That thou hast said unto them: Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, Ye do certainly drink.

29 For lo, in the city over which My name is called, I am beginning to do evil, And ye--ye are entirely acquitted! Ye are not acquitted, for a sword I am proclaiming, For all inhabitants of the land, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts.

30 And thou, thou dost prophesy unto them all these words, and hast said unto them: Jehovah from the high place doth roar, And from His holy habitation giveth forth His voice, He surely roareth for His habitation, A shout as of treaders down, God answereth all the inhabitants of the land,

31 Wasting hath come unto the end of the earth, For a controversy hath Jehovah with nations, He hath executed judgment for all flesh, The wicked! He hath given them to the sword, An affirmation of Jehovah.

32 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Lo, evil is going out from nation to nation, And a great whirlwind is stirred up from the sides of the earth.

33 And the pierced of Jehovah have been in that day, From the end of the earth even unto the end of the earth, They are not lamented, nor gathered, nor buried, For dung on the face of the ground they are.

34 Howl, ye shepherds, and cry, And roll yourselves, ye honourable of the flock, For full have been your days, For slaughtering, and [for] your scatterings, And ye have fallen as a desirable vessel.

35 And perished hath refuge from the shepherds, And escape from the honourable of the flock.

36 A voice [is] of the cry of the shepherds, And a howling of the honourable of the flock, For Jehovah is spoiling their pasture.

37 And the peaceable habitations have been cut down, Because of the fierceness of the anger of Jehovah.

38 He hath forsaken, as a young lion, His covert, Surely their land hath become a desolation, Because of the oppressing fierceness, And because of the fierceness of His anger!

Jeremiah 30

1 The word that hath been unto Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying,

2 `Thus spake Jehovah, God of Israel, saying, Write for thee all the words that I have spoken unto thee on a book.

3 For, lo, days are coming--an affirmation of Jehovah--and I have turned back [to] the captivity of My people Israel and Judah, said Jehovah, and I have caused them to turn back unto the land that I gave to their fathers, and they do possess it.'

4 And these [are] the words that Jehovah hath spoken concerning Israel and concerning Judah:

5 Surely thus said Jehovah: A voice of trembling we have heard, Fear--and there is no peace.

6 Ask, I pray you, and see, is a male bringing forth? Wherefore have I seen every man, His hands on his loins, as a travailing woman, And all faces have been turned to paleness?

7 Woe! for great [is] that day, without any like it, Yea, a time of adversity it [is] to Jacob, Yet out of it he is saved.

8 And it hath come to pass, in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, I break his yoke from off thy neck, And thy bands I draw away, And lay no more service on him do strangers.

9 And they have served Jehovah their God, And David their king whom I raise up to them.

10 And thou, be not afraid, My servant Jacob, An affirmation of Jehovah, Nor be affrighted, O Israel, For, lo, I am saving thee from afar, And thy seed from the land of their captivity, And Jacob hath turned back and rested, And is quiet, and there is none troubling.

11 For with thee [am] I, An affirmation of Jehovah--to save thee, For I make an end of all the nations Whither I have scattered thee, Only, of thee I do not make an end, And I have chastised thee in judgment, And do not entirely acquit thee.

12 For thus said Jehovah: Incurable is thy breach, grievous thy stroke,

13 There is none judging thy cause to bind up, Healing medicines there are none for thee.

14 all loving thee have forgotten thee, Thee they do not seek, For with the stroke of an enemy I smote thee, The chastisement of a fierce one, Because of the abundance of thy iniquity, Mighty have been thy sins!

15 What! --thou criest concerning thy breach! Incurable [is] thy pain, Because of the abundance of thy iniquity, Mighty have been thy sins! I have done these to thee.

16 Therefore all consuming thee are consumed, And all thine adversaries--all of them--Into captivity do go, And thy spoilers have been for a spoil, And all thy plunderers I give up to plunder.

17 For I increase health to thee, And from thy strokes I do heal thee, An affirmation of Jehovah, For `Outcast' they have called to thee, `Zion it [is], there is none seeking for her.'

18 Thus said Jehovah: Lo, I turn back [to] the captivity of the tents of Jacob, And his dwelling places I pity, And the city hath been built on its heap, And the palace according to its ordinance remaineth.

19 And gone forth from them hath thanksgiving, And the voice of playful ones, And I have multiplied them and they are not few, And made them honourable, and they are not small.

20 And his sons have been as aforetime, And his company before Me is established, And I have seen after all his oppressors.

21 And his honourable one hath been of himself, And his ruler from his midst goeth forth, And I have caused him to draw near, And he hath drawn nigh unto Me, For who [is] he who hath pledged his heart To draw nigh unto Me? An affirmation of Jehovah.

22 And ye have been to Me for a people, And I am to you for God.

23 Lo, a whirlwind of Jehovah--Fury hath gone forth--a cutting whirlwind, On the head of the wicked it stayeth.

24 The fierceness of the anger of Jehovah Doth not turn back till His doing, Yea, till His establishing the devices of His heart, In the latter end of the days we consider it!

Jeremiah 31

1 At that time, an affirmation of Jehovah, I am for God to all families of Israel, And they--they are to Me for a people.

2 Thus said Jehovah: Found grace in the wilderness Hath a people remaining from the sword Going to cause it to rest--Israel.

3 From afar Jehovah hath appeared to me, With love age-during I have loved thee, Therefore I have drawn thee [with] kindness.

4 Again do I build thee, And thou hast been built, O virgin of Israel, Again thou puttest on thy tabrets, And hast gone out in the chorus of the playful.

5 Again thou dost plant vineyards In mountains of Samaria, Planters have planted, and made common.

6 For there is a day, Cried have watchmen on mount Ephraim, `Rise, and we go up to Zion, unto Jehovah our God;

7 For thus said Jehovah: Sing, O ye to Jacob, [with] joy, And cry aloud at the head of the nations, Sound ye, praise ye, and say, Save, O Jehovah, thy people, the remnant of Israel.

8 Lo, I am bringing them in from the north country, And have gathered them from the sides of the earth, Among them [are] blind and lame, Conceiving and travailing one--together, A great assembly--they turn back hither.

9 With weeping they come in, And with supplications I bring them, I cause them to go unto streams of waters, In a right way--they stumble not in it, For I have been to Israel for a father, And Ephraim--My first-born [is] he.

10 Hear a word of Jehovah, O nations, And declare ye among isles afar off, and say: He who is scattering Israel doth gather him, And hath kept him as a shepherd [doth] his flock,

11 For Jehovah hath ransomed Jacob, And redeemed him from a hand stronger than he.

12 And they have come in, And have sung in the high place of Zion, And flowed unto the goodness of Jehovah, For wheat, and for new wine, and for oil, And for the young of the flock and herd, And their soul hath been as a watered garden, And they add not to grieve any more.

13 Then rejoice doth a virgin in a chorus, Both young men and old men--together, And I have turned their mourning to joy, And have comforted them, And gladdened them above their sorrow,

14 And satisfied the soul of the priests [with] fatness, And My people with My goodness are satisfied, An affirmation of Jehovah.

15 Thus said Jehovah, A voice in Ramah is heard, wailing, weeping most bitter, Rachel is weeping for her sons, She hath refused to be comforted for her sons, because they are not.

16 Thus said Jehovah: Withhold thy voice from weeping, and thine eyes from tears, For there is a reward for thy work, An affirmation of Jehovah, And they have turned back from the land of the enemy.

17 And there is hope for thy latter end, An affirmation of Jehovah, And the sons have turned back [to] their border.

18 I have surely heard Ephraim bemoaning himself, `Thou hast chastised me, And I am chastised, as a heifer not taught, Turn me back, and I turn back, For thou [art] Jehovah my God.

19 For after my turning back I repented, And after my being instructed I struck on the thigh, I have been ashamed, I have also blushed, For I have borne the reproach of my youth.

20 A precious son is Ephraim to Me? A child of delights? For since My speaking against him, I do thoroughly remember him still, Therefore have My bowels been moved for him, I do greatly love him, An affirmation of Jehovah.

21 Set up for thee signs, make for thee heaps, Set thy heart to the highway, the way thou wentest, Turn back, O virgin of Israel, Turn back unto these thy cities.

22 Till when dost thou withdraw thyself, O backsliding daughter? For Jehovah hath prepared a new thing in the land, Woman doth compass man.

23 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel, Still they say this word in the land of Judah, And in its cities, In My turning back [to] their captivity, Jehovah doth bless thee, habitation of righteousness, Mountain of holiness.

24 And dwelt in Judah have husbandmen, and in all its cities together, And they have journeyed in order.

25 For I have satiated the weary soul, And every grieved soul I have filled.'

26 On this I have awaked, and I behold, and my sleep hath been sweet to me.

27 Lo, days are coming, an affirmation of Jehovah, And I have sown the house of Israel, And the house of Judah, With seed of man, and seed of beast.

28 And it hath been, as I watched over them to pluck up, And to break down, and to throw down, And to destroy, and to afflict; So do I watch over them to build, and to plant, An affirmation of Jehovah.

29 In those days they do not say any more: Fathers have eaten unripe fruit, And the sons' teeth are blunted.

30 But--each for his own iniquity doth die, Every man who is eating the unripe fruit, Blunted are his teeth.

31 Lo, days are coming, an affirmation of Jehovah, And I have made with the house of Israel And with the house of Judah a new covenant,

32 Not like the covenant that I made with their fathers, In the day of My laying hold on their hand, To bring them out of the land of Egypt, In that they made void My covenant, And I ruled over them--an affirmation of Jehovah.

33 For this [is] the covenant that I make, With the house of Israel, after those days, An affirmation of Jehovah, I have given My law in their inward part, And on their heart I do write it, And I have been to them for God, And they are to me for a people.

34 And they do not teach any more Each his neighbour, and each his brother, Saying, Know ye Jehovah, For they all know Me, from their least unto their greatest, An affirmation of Jehovah; For I pardon their iniquity, And of their sin I make mention no more.

35 Thus said Jehovah, Who is giving the sun for a light by day, The statutes of moon and stars for a light by night, Quieting the sea when its billows roar, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name:

36 If these statutes depart from before Me, An affirmation of Jehovah, Even the seed of Israel doth cease From being a nation before Me all the days.

37 Thus said Jehovah: If the heavens above be measured, And the foundations of earth below searched, Even I kick against all the seed of Israel, For all that they have done, An affirmation of Jehovah.

38 Lo, days [are coming], an affirmation of Jehovah, And the city hath been built to Jehovah, From the tower of Hananeel to the gate of the corner.

39 And gone out again hath the measuring line Over-against it, unto the height of Gareb, And it hath compassed to Goah.

40 And all the valley of the carcases and of the ashes, And all the fields unto the brook Kidron, Unto the corner of the horse-gate eastward, [Are] holy to Jehovah, it is not plucked up, Nor is it thrown down any more to the age!

Jeremiah 39

1 In the ninth year of Zedekiah king of Judah, in the tenth month, come hath Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon and all his force unto Jerusalem, and they lay siege against it;

2 in the eleventh year of Zedekiah, in the fourth month, in the ninth of the month, hath the city been broken up;

3 and come in do all the heads of the king of Babylon, and they sit at the middle gate, Nergal-Sharezer, Samgar-Nebo, Sarsechim, chief of the eunuchs, Nergal-Sharezer, chief of the Mages, and all the rest of the heads of the king of Babylon.

4 And it cometh to pass, when Zedekiah king of Judah, and all the men of war, have seen them, that they flee and go forth by night from the city, the way of the king's garden, through the gate between the two walls, and he goeth forth the wayof the plain.

5 And the forces of the Chaldeans pursue after them, and overtake Zedekiah in the plains of Jericho, and they take him, and bring him up unto Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, to Riblah, in the land of Hamath, and he speaketh with him--judgments.

6 And the king of Babylon slaughtereth the sons of Zedekiah, in Riblah, before his eyes, yea, all the freemen of Judah hath the king of Babylon slaughtered.

7 And the eyes of Zedekiah he hath blinded, and he bindeth him with brazen fetters, to bring him in to Babylon.

8 And the house of the king, and the house of the people, have the Chaldeans burnt with fire, and the walls of Jerusalem they have broken down.

9 And the remnant of the people who are left in the city, and those falling who have fallen to him, and the remnant of the people who are left, hath Nebuzar-Adan, chief of the executioners, removed [to] Babylon.

10 And of the poor people, who have nothing, hath Nebuzar-Adan, chief of the executioners, left in the land of Judah, and he giveth to them vineyards and fields on the same day.

11 And Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon giveth a charge concerning Jeremiah, by the hand of Nebuzar-Adan, chief of the executioners, saying,

12 `Take him, and place thine eyes upon him, and do no evil thing to him, but as he speaketh unto thee, so do with him.'

13 And Nebuzar-Adan, chief of the executioners sendeth, and Nebushazban, chief of the eunuchs, and Nergal-Sharezer, chief of the Mages, and all the chiefs of the king of Babylon;

14 yea, they send and take Jeremiah out of the court of the prison, and give him unto Gedaliah son of Ahikam, son of Shaphan, to carry him home, and he dwelleth in the midst of the people.

15 And unto Jeremiah hath a word of Jehovah been--in his being detained in the court of the prison--saying:

16 `Go, and thou hast spoken to Ebed-Melech the Cushite, saying: Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel: Lo, I am bringing in My words unto this city for evil, and not for good, and they have been before thee in that day.

17 And I have delivered thee in that day--an affirmation of Jehovah--and thou art not given into the hand of the men of whose face thou art afraid,

18 for I do certainly deliver thee, and by sword thou fallest not, and thy life hath been to thee for a spoil, for thou hast trusted in Me--an affirmation of Jehovah.'

Jeremiah 41

1 And it cometh to pass, in the seventh month, come hath Ishmael son of Nethaniah, son of Elishama, of the seed royal, and of the chiefs of the king, and ten men with him, unto Gedaliah son of Ahikam, to Mizpah, and they eat there bread together in Mizpah.

2 And Ishmael son of Nethaniah riseth, and the ten men who have been with him, and they smite Gedaliah son of Ahikam, son of Shaphan, with the sword, and he putteth him to death whom the king of Babylon hath appointed over the land.

3 And all the Jews who have been with him, with Gedaliah, in Mizpah, and the Chaldeans who have been found there--the men of war--hath Ishmael smitten.

4 And it cometh to pass, on the second day of the putting of Gedaliah to death, (and no one hath known,)

5 that men come in from Shechem, from Shiloh, and from Samaria--eighty men--with shaven beards, and rent garments, and cutting themselves, and an offering and frankincense in their hand, to bring in to the house of Jehovah.

6 And Ishmael son of Nethaniah goeth forth to meet them, from Mizpah, going on and weeping, and it cometh to pass, at meeting them, that he saith unto them, `Come in unto Gedaliah son of Ahikam.'

7 And it cometh to pass, at their coming in unto the midst of the city, that Ishmael son of Nethaniah doth slaughter them, at the midst of the pit, he and the men who [are] with him.

8 And ten men have been found among them, and they say unto Ishmael, `Do not put us to death, for we have things hidden in the field--wheat, and barley, and oil, and honey.' And he forbeareth, and hath not put them to death in the midst of their brethren.

9 And the pit whither Ishmael hath cast all the carcases of the men whom he hath smitten along with Gedaliah, is that which the king Asa made because of Baasha king of Israel--it hath Ishmael son of Nethaniah filled with the pierced.

10 And Ishmael taketh captive all the remnant of the people who [are] in Mizpah, the daughters of the king, and all the people who are left in Mizpah, whom Nebuzar-Adan, chief of the executioners, hath committed [to] Gedaliah son of Ahikam, and Ishmael son of Nethaniah taketh them captive, and goeth to pass over unto the sons of Ammon.

11 And hear doth Johanan son of Kareah, and all the heads of the forces that [are] with him, of all the evil that Ishmael son of Nethaniah hath done,

12 and they take all the men, and go to fight with Ishmael son of Nethaniah, and they find him at the great waters that [are] in Gibeon.

13 And it cometh to pass, when all the people who [are] with Ishmael see Johanan son of Kareah, and all the heads of the forces who [are] with him, that they rejoice.

14 And all the people whom Ishmael hath taken captive from Mizpah turn round, yea, they turn back, and go unto Johanan son of Kareah.

15 And Ishmael son of Nethaniah hath escaped, with eight men, from the presence of Johanan, and he goeth unto the sons of Ammon.

16 And Johanan son of Kareah, and all the heads of the forces who [are] with him, take all the remnant of the people whom he hath brought back from Ishmael son of Nethaniah, from Mizpah--after he had smitten Gedaliah son of Ahikam--mighty ones, men of war, and women, and infants, and eunuchs, whom he had brought back from Gibeon,

17 and they go and abide in the habitations of Chimham, that [are] near Beth-Lehem, to go to enter Egypt,

18 from the presence of the Chaldeans, for they have been afraid of them, for Ishmael son of Nethaniah had smitten Gedaliah son of Ahikam, whom the king of Babylon had appointed over the land.

Jeremiah 46

1 That which hath been the word of Jehovah unto Jeremiah the prophet concerning the nations,

2 For Egypt, concerning the force of Pharaoh-Necho king of Egypt, that hath been by the river Phrat, in Carchemish, that Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon hath smitten, in the fourth year of Jehoiakim son of Josiah king of Judah:

3 `Set ye in array shield and buckler, And draw nigh to battle.

4 Gird the horses, and go up, ye horsemen, And station yourselves with helmets, Polish the javelins, put on the coats of mail.

5 Wherefore have I seen them dismayed--They are turned backward, And their mighty ones are beaten down, And [to] a refuge they have fled, and not turned the face? Fear [is] round about--an affirmation of Jehovah.

6 The swift do not flee, nor do the mighty escape, Northward, by the side of the river Phrat, They have stumbled and fallen.

7 Who is this? as a flood he cometh up, As rivers do his waters shake themselves!

8 Egypt, as a flood cometh up, And as rivers the waters shake themselves. And he saith, I go up; I cover the land, I destroy the city and the inhabitants in it.

9 Go up, ye horses; and boast yourselves, ye chariots, And go forth, ye mighty, Cush and Phut handling the shield, And Lud handling--treading the bow.

10 And that day [is] to the Lord Jehovah of Hosts A day of vengeance, To be avenged of His adversaries, And the sword hath devoured, and been satisfied, And it hath been watered from their blood, For a sacrifice [is] to the Lord Jehovah of Hosts, In the land of the north, by the river Phrat.

11 Go up to Gilead, and take balm, O virgin daughter of Egypt, In vain thou hast multiplied medicines, Healing there is none for thee.

12 Nations have heard of thy shame, And thy cry hath filled the land, For the mighty on the mighty did stumble, Together they have fallen--both of them!'

13 The word that Jehovah hath spoken unto Jeremiah the prophet concerning the coming in of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, to smite the land of Egypt:

14 `Declare ye in Egypt, and sound in Migdol, Yea, sound in Noph, and in Tahpanhes say: Station thyself, yea, prepare for thee, For a sword hath devoured around thee,

15 Wherefore hath thy bull been swept away? He hath not stood, because Jehovah thrust him away.

16 He hath multiplied the stumbling, Yea one hath fallen upon his neighbour, And they say: Rise, and we turn back to our people, And unto the land of our birth, Because of the oppressing sword.

17 They have cried there: Pharaoh king of Egypt [is] a desolation, Passed by hath the appointed time.

18 I live--an affirmation of the King, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name, Surely as Tabor [is] among mountains, And as Carmel by the sea--he cometh in,

19 Goods for removal make for thee, O inhabitant, daughter of Egypt, For Noph becometh a desolation, And hath been burnt up, without inhabitant.

20 A heifer very fair [is] Egypt, Rending from the north doth come into her.

21 Even her hired ones in her midst [are] as calves of the stall, For even they have turned, They have fled together, they have not stood, For the day of their calamity hath come on them, The time of their inspection.

22 Its voice as a serpent goeth on, For with a force they go, And with axes they have come in to her, As hewers of trees.

23 They have cut down her forest, An affirmation of Jehovah--for it is not searched, For they have been more than the grasshopper, And they have no numbering.

24 Ashamed hath been the daughter of Egypt, She hath been given into the hand of the people of the north.

25 Said hath Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel: Lo, I am seeing after Amon of No, And after Pharaoh, and after Egypt, And after her gods, and after her kings, And after Pharaoh, and after those trusting in him,

26 And I have given them into the hand of those seeking their life, And into the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, And into the hand of his servants, And afterwards it is inhabited, As [in] days of old--an affirmation of Jehovah.

27 And thou, thou dost not fear, my servant Jacob, Nor [art] thou dismayed, O Israel, For lo, I am saving thee from afar, And thy seed from the land of their captivity, And Jacob hath turned back, And hath been at rest, and been at ease, And there is none disturbing.

28 Thou, thou dost not fear, My servant Jacob, An affirmation of Jehovah--for with thee I [am], For I make an end of all the nations Whither I have driven thee, And of thee I do not make an end, And I have reproved thee in judgment, And do not entirely acquit thee!'

Jeremiah 48

1 Concerning Moab: `Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel: Woe unto Nebo, for it is spoiled, Put to shame, captured hath been Kiriathaim, Put to shame hath been the high tower, Yea, it hath been broken down.

2 There is no more praise of Moab, In Heshbon they devised against it evil: Come, and we cut it off from [being] a nation, Also, O Madmen, thou art cut off, After thee goeth a sword.

3 A voice of a cry [is] from Horonaim, Spoiling and great destruction.

4 Destroyed hath been Moab, Caused a cry to be heard have her little ones.

5 For the ascent of Luhith with weeping, Go up doth weeping, For in the descent of Horonaim Adversaries a cry of desolation have heard.

6 Flee ye, deliver yourselves, Ye are as a naked thing in a wilderness.

7 For, because of thy trusting in thy works, And in thy treasures, even thou art captured, And gone out hath Chemosh in a removal, His priests and his heads together.

8 And come in doth a spoiler unto every city, And no city doth escape, And perished hath the valley, And destroyed been the plain, as Jehovah said.

9 Give wings to Moab, for she utterly goeth out, And her cities are for a desolation, Without an inhabitant in them.

10 Cursed [is] he who is doing the work of Jehovah slothfully, And cursed [is] he Who is withholding his sword from blood.

11 Secure is Moab from his youth, And at rest [is] he for his preserved things, And he hath not been emptied out from vessel unto vessel, And into captivity he hath not gone, Therefore hath his taste remained in him, And his fragrance hath not been changed.

12 Therefore, lo, days are coming, An affirmation of Jehovah, And I have sent to him wanderers, And they have caused him to wander, And his vessels they empty out, And his bottles they dash in pieces.

13 And ashamed hath been Moab because of Chemosh, As the house of Israel have been ashamed Because of Beth-El their confidence.

14 How do ye say, We [are] mighty, And men of strength for battle?

15 Spoiled is Moab, and her cities hath one gone up, And the choice of its young men Have gone down to slaughter, An affirmation of the King, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name.

16 Near is the calamity of Moab to come, And his affliction hath hasted exceedingly.

17 Bemoan for him, all ye round about him, And all knowing his name, say ye: How hath it been broken, the staff of strength, The rod of beauty.

18 Come down from honour, sit in thirst, O inhabitant, daughter of Dibon, For a spoiler of Moab hath come up to thee, He hath destroyed thy fenced places.

19 On the way stand, and watch, O inhabitant of Aroer, Ask the fugitive and escaped, Say, What hath happened?

20 Put to shame hath been Moab, For it hath been broken down, Howl and cry, declare ye in Arnon, For spoiled is Moab,

21 And judgment hath come in unto the land of the plain--unto Holon, And unto Jahazah, and on Mephaath,

22 And on Dibon, and on Nebo, And on Beth-Diblathaim, and on Kirathaim,

23 And on Beth-Gamul, and on Beth-Meon,

24 And on Kerioth, and on Bozrah, And on all cities of the land of Moab, The far off and the near.

25 Cut down hath been the horn of Moab, And his arm hath been broken, An affirmation of Jehovah.

26 Declare ye him drunk, For against Jehovah he made himself great And Moab hath stricken in his vomit, And he hath been for a derision--even he.

27 And was not Israel the derision to thee? Among thieves was he found? For since thy words concerning him, Thou dost bemoan thyself.

28 Forsake cities, and dwell in a rock, Ye inhabitants of Moab, And be as a dove making a nest in the passages of a pit's mouth.

29 We have heard of the arrogance of Moab, Exceeding proud! His haughtiness, and his arrogance, And his pride, and the height of his heart,

30 I--I have known, an affirmation of Jehovah, His wrath, and [it is] not right, His devices--not right they have done.

31 Therefore for Moab I howl, even for Moab--all of it, I cry for men of Kir-Heres, it doth mourn,

32 With the weeping of Jazer, I weep for thee, O vine of Sibmah, Thy branches have passed over a sea, Unto the sea of Jazer they have come, On thy summer fruits, and on thy harvest, A spoiler hath fallen.

33 And removed hath been joy and gladness From the fruitful field, Even from the land of Moab, And wine from wine-presses I have caused to cease, Shouting doth not proceed, The shouting [is] no shouting!

34 Because of the cry of Heshbon unto Elealeh, Unto Jahaz they have given their voice, From Zoar unto Horonaim, A heifer of the third [year], For even waters of Nimrim become desolations.

35 And I have caused to cease to Moab, An affirmation of Jehovah, Him who is offering in a high place, And him who is making perfume to his god.

36 Therefore my heart for Moab as pipes doth sound, And my heart for men of Kir- Heres As pipes doth sound, Therefore the abundance he made did perish.

37 For every head [is] bald, and every beard diminished, On all hands cuttings, and on the loins--sackcloth.

38 On all roofs of Moab, and in her broad-places, All of it--[is] lamentation, For I have broken Moab as a vessel in which there is no pleasure, An affirmation of Jehovah.

39 How hath it been broken down! they have howled, How hath Moab turned the neck ashamed, And Moab hath been for a derision. And for a terror to all round about her.

40 For thus said Jehovah: Lo, as an eagle he doth flee, And hath spread his wings unto Moab.

41 Captured have been the cities, And the strongholds are caught, And the heart of the mighty of Moab Hath been in that day as the heart of a distressed woman.

42 And Moab hath been destroyed from [being] a people, For against Jehovah he exerted himself.

43 Fear, and a snare, and a gin, [are] for thee, O inhabitant of Moab--an affirmation of Jehovah,

44 Whoso is fleeing because of the fear falleth into the snare, And whoso is coming up from the snare is captured by the gin, For I bring in unto her--unto Moab--The year of their inspection, An affirmation of Jehovah.

45 In the shadow of Heshbon stood powerless have fugitives, For fire hath gone forth from Heshbon, And a flame from within Sihon, And it consumeth the corner of Moab, And the crown of the sons of Shaon.

46 Woe to thee, O Moab, Perished hath the people of Chemosh, For thy sons were taken with the captives, And thy daughters with the captivity.

47 And I have turned back [to] the captivity of Moab, In the latter end of the days, An affirmation of Jehovah! Hitherto [is] the judgment of Moab.

Jeremiah 49

1 Concerning the sons of Ammon: `Thus said Jehovah: Sons--hath Israel none? heir- -hath he none? Wherefore hath Malcam possessed Gad? And his people in its cities have dwelt?

2 Therefore, lo, days are coming, An affirmation of Jehovah, And I have sounded unto Rabbah of the sons of Ammon a shout of battle, And it hath been for a heap--a desolation, And her daughters with fire are burnt, And Israel hath succeeded its heirs, Said hath Jehovah.

3 Howl, Heshbon, for spoiled is Ai, Cry, daughters of Rabbah, gird on sackcloth, Lament, and go to and fro by the hedges, For Malcam into captivity doth go, His priests and his princes together.

4 What--dost thou boast thyself in valleys? Flowed hath thy valley, O backsliding daughter, Who is trusting in her treasures: Who doth come in unto me?

5 Lo, I am bringing in upon thee a fear, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah of Hosts, From all round about thee, And ye have been driven out each before it, And there is no gatherer of the wandering.

6 And after this I turn back the captivity of the sons of Ammon, An affirmation of Jehovah.'

7 Concerning Edom: `Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Is wisdom no more in Teman? Perished hath counsel from the intelligent? Vanished hath their wisdom?

8 Flee, turn, go deep to dwell, ye inhabitants of Dedan, For the calamity of Esau I brought in upon him, The time I inspected him.

9 If gatherers have come in to thee, They do not leave gleanings, If thieves in the night, They have destroyed their sufficiency!

10 For I--I have made Esau bare, I have uncovered his secret places, And to be hidden he is not able, Spoiled [is] his seed, and his brethren, And his neighbours, and he is not.

11 Leave thine orphans--I do keep alive, And thy widows--on Me trust ye,

12 For thus said Jehovah: They whose judgment is not to drink of the cup, Do certainly drink, And thou [art] he that is entirely acquitted! Thou art not acquitted, for thou certainly drinkest.

13 For, by Myself, I have sworn, An affirmation of Jehovah, That for a desolation, for a reproach, For a waste, and for a reviling--is Bozrah, And all her cities are for wastes ageduring.

14 A report I have heard from Jehovah, And an ambassador among nations is sent, Gather yourselves and come in against her, And rise ye for battle.

15 For, lo, little I have made thee among nations, Despised among men.

16 Thy terribleness hath lifted thee up, The pride of thy heart, O dweller in clefts of the rock, Holding the high place of the height, For thou makest high as an eagle thy nest, From thence I bring thee down, An affirmation of Jehovah.

17 And Edom hath been for a desolation, Every passer by her is astonished, And doth hiss because of all her plagues.

18 As the overthrow of Sodom and Gomorrah, And its neighbours, said Jehovah, No one doth dwell there, Nor sojourn in her doth a son of man.

19 Lo, as a lion he cometh up, Because of the rising of the Jordan, Unto the enduring habitation, But I cause to rest, I cause him to run from off her, And who is chosen? concerning her I lay a charge, For who is like Me? and who conveneth Me? And who [is] this shepherd who standeth before Me?

20 Therefore, hear ye the counsel of Jehovah, That He hath counselled concerning Edom, And His devices that He hath devised Concerning the inhabitants of Teman: Drag them out do not little ones of the flock, Make desolate over them doth he not their habitation?

21 From the noise of their fall hath the earth shaken, The cry--at the sea of Suph is its voice heard.

22 Lo, as an eagle he cometh up, and flieth, And he spreadeth his wings over Bozrah, And the heart of the mighty of Edom hath been in that day, As the heart of a distressed woman!'

23 Concerning Damascus: Ashamed hath been Hamath and Arpad, For an evil report they have heard, They have been melted, in the sea [is] sorrow, To be quiet it is not able.

24 Feeble hath been Damascus, She turned to flee, and fear strengthened her, Distress and pangs have seized her, as a travailing woman.

25 How is it not left--the city of praise, The city of my joy!

26 Therefore fall do her young men in her broad places, And all the men of war are cut off in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts.

27 And I have kindled a fire against the wall of Damascus, And it consumed palaces of Ben-Hadad!'

28 Concerning Kedar, and concerning the kingdoms of Hazor, that Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon hath smitten: `Thus said Jehovah: Arise ye, go ye up unto Kedar, And spoil the sons of the east.

29 Their tents and their flock they do take, Their curtains, and all their vessels, And their camels, they bear away for themselves, And they called concerning them, Fear [is] round about.

30 Flee, bemoan mightily, go deep to dwell, Ye inhabitants of Hazor--an affirmation of Jehovah, For given counsel against you hath Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, Yea, he deviseth against them a device.

31 Rise ye, go up unto a nation at rest, Dwelling confidently, an affirmation of Jehovah, It hath no two-leaved doors nor bar, Alone they do dwell.

32 And their camels have been for a prey, And the multitude of their cattle for a spoil, And I have scattered them to every wind, Who cut off the corner [of the beard], And from all its passages I bring in their calamity, An affirmation of Jehovah.

33 And Hazor hath been for a habitation of dragons, A desolation--unto the age, No one doth dwell there, nor sojourn in it doth a son of man!'

34 That which hath been the word of Jehovah unto Jeremiah the prophet concerning Elam, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah king of Judah, saying:

35 `Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Lo, I am breaking the bow of Elam, The beginning of their might.

36 And I have brought in to Elam four winds, From the four ends of the heavens, And have scattered them to all these winds, And there is no nation whither outcasts of Elam come not in.

37 And I have affrighted Elam before their enemies, And before those seeking their life, And I have brought in against them evil, The heat of Mine anger, An affirmation of Jehovah, And I have sent after them the sword, Till I have consumed them;

38 And I have set My throne in Elam, And I have destroyed thence King and princes- -an affirmation of Jehovah.

39 And it hath come to pass, in the latter end of the days, I turn back [to] the captivity of Elam, An affirmation of Jehovah!'

Jeremiah 50

1 The word that Jehovah hath spoken concerning Babylon, concerning the land of the Chaldeans, by the hand of Jeremiah the prophet:

2 `Declare ye among nations, and sound, And lift up an ensign, sound, do not hide, Say ye: Captured hath been Babylon, Put to shame hath been Bel, Broken hath been Merodach, Put to shame have been her grievous things, Broken have been her idols.

3 For come up against her hath a nation from the north, It maketh her land become a desolation, And there is not an inhabitant in it. From man even unto beast, They have moved, they have gone.

4 In those days, and at that time, An affirmation of Jehovah, Come in do sons of Israel, They and sons of Judah together, Going on and weeping they go, And Jehovah their God they seek.

5 [To] Zion they ask the way, Thitherward [are] their faces: Come in, and we are joined unto Jehovah, A covenant age-during--not forgotten.

6 A perishing flock hath My people been, Their shepherds have caused them to err, [To] the mountains causing them to go back, From mountain unto hill they have gone, They have forgotten their crouching-place.

7 All finding them have devoured them, And their adversaries have said: We are not guilty, Because that they sinned against Jehovah, The habitation of righteousness, And the hope of their fathers--Jehovah.

8 Move ye from the midst of Babylon, And from the land of the Chaldeans go out. And be as he-goats before a flock.

9 For, lo, I am stirring up, And am causing to come up against Babylon, An assembly of great nations from a land of the north, And they have set in array against her, From thence she is captured, Its arrow--as a skilful hero--returneth not empty,

10 And Chaldea hath been for a spoil, All her spoilers are satisfied, An affirmation of Jehovah.

11 Because thou rejoicest, because thou exultest, O spoilers of Mine inheritance, Because thou increasest as a heifer [at] the tender grass, And dost cry aloud as bulls,

12 Ashamed hath been your mother greatly, Confounded hath she been that bare you, Lo, the hindermost of nations [is] a wilderness, A dry land, and a desert.

13 Because of the wrath of Jehovah it is not inhabited, And it hath been a desolation-- all of it. Every passer by at Babylon is astonished, And doth hiss because of all her plagues.

14 Set yourselves in array against Babylon round about, All ye treading a bow, Shoot at her, have no pity on the arrow, For against Jehovah she hath sinned.

15 Shout against her round about, She hath given forth her hand, Fallen have her foundations, Thrown down have been her walls, For it [is] the vengeance of Jehovah, Be avenged of her, as she did--do ye to her.

16 Cut off the sower from Babylon, And him handling the sickle in the time of harvest, Because of the oppressing sword, Each unto his people--they turn, And each to his land-- they flee.

17 A scattered sheep is Israel, lions have driven away, At first, devour him did the king of Asshur, And now, at last, broken his bone Hath Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon.

18 Therefore thus said Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel: Lo, I am seeing after the king of Babylon, And after his land, As I have seen after the king of Asshur;

19 And I have brought back Israel unto his habitation, And he hath fed on Carmel, and on Bashan. And in mount Ephraim, and on Gilead is his soul satisfied.

20 In those days, and at that time, An affirmation of Jehovah, Sought is the iniquity of Israel, and it is not, And the sin of Judah, and it is not found, For I am propitious to those whom I leave!

21 Against the land of Merathaim: Go up against it, and unto the inhabitants of Pekod, Waste and devote their posterity, An affirmation of Jehovah, And do according to all that I have commanded thee.

22 A noise of battle [is] in the land, and of great destruction.

23 How hath it been cut and broken, The hammer of the whole earth! How hath Babylon been for a desolation among nations!

24 I have laid a snare for thee, And also--thou art captured, O Babylon, And thou-- thou hast known, Thou hast been found, and also art caught, For against Jehovah thou hast stirred thyself up.

25 Jehovah hath opened His treasury, And He bringeth out the weapons of His indignation, For a work [is] to the Lord Jehovah of Hosts, In the land of the Chaldeans.

26 Come ye in to her from the extremity, Open ye her storehouses, Raise her up as heaps, and devote her, Let her have no remnant.

27 Slay all her kine, they go down to slaughter, Woe [is] on them, for come hath their day, The time of their inspection.

28 A voice of fugitives and escaped ones [Is] from the land of Babylon, To declare in Zion the vengeance of Jehovah our God, The vengeance of His temple.

29 Summon unto Babylon archers, all treading the bow, Encamp against her round about, Let [her] have no escape; Recompense to her according to her work, According to all that she did--do to her, For unto Jehovah she hath been proud, Unto the Holy One of Israel.

30 Therefore fall do her young men in her broad places, And all her men of war are cut off in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah.

31 Lo, I [am] against thee, O pride, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah of Hosts, For thy day hath come, the time of thy inspection.

32 And stumbled hath pride, And he hath fallen, and hath no raiser up, And I have kindled a fire in his cities, And it hath devoured all round about him.

33 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Oppressed are the sons of Israel, And the sons of Judah together, And all their captors have kept hold on them, They have refused to send them away.

34 Their Redeemer [is] strong, Jehovah of Hosts [is] His name, He doth thoroughly plead their cause, So as to cause the land to rest, And He hath given trouble to the inhabitants of Babylon.

35 A sword [is] for the Chaldeans, An affirmation of Jehovah, And it [is] on the inhabitants of Babylon, And on her heads, and on her wise men;

36 A sword [is] on the princes, And they have become foolish; A sword [is] on her mighty ones, And they have been broken down;

37 A sword [is] on his horses and on his chariot, And on all the rabble who [are] in her midst, And they have become women; A sword [is] on her treasuries, And they have been spoiled;

38 A sword [is] on her waters, and they have been dried up, For it [is] a land of graven images, And in idols they do boast themselves.

39 Therefore dwell do Ziim with Iim, Yea, dwelt in her have daughters of the ostrich, And it is not inhabited any more for ever, Nor dwelt in unto all generations.

40 As overthrown by God with Sodom, And with Gomorrah, and with its neighbours, An affirmation of Jehovah, none doth dwell there, Nor sojourn in her doth a son of man.

41 Lo, a people hath come from the north, Even a great nation, And many kings are stirred up from the sides of the earth.

42 Bow and halbert they seize, Cruel [are] they, and they have no mercy, Their voice as a sea soundeth, and on horses they ride, Set in array as a man for battle, Against thee, O daughter of Babylon.

43 Heard hath the king of Babylon their report, And feeble have been his hands, Distress hath seized him; pain as a travailing woman.

44 Lo, as a lion he cometh up, Because of the rising of the Jordan, Unto the enduring habitation, But I cause to rest, I cause them to run from off her. And who is chosen? on her I lay a charge, For who [is] like Me? And who doth convene Me? And who [is] this shepherd who standeth before Me?

45 Therefore, hear ye the counsel of Jehovah, That He counselled concerning Babylon, And His devices that He hath devised Concerning the land of the Chaldeans; Drag them out do not little ones of the flock, Doth He not make desolate over themthe habitation?

46 From the voice: Captured was Babylon, Hath the earth been shaken, And a cry among nations hath been heard!

Lamentations 1

1 How hath she sat alone, The city abounding with people! She hath been as a widow, The mighty among nations! Princes among provinces, She hath become tributary!

2 She weepeth sore in the night, And her tear [is] on her cheeks, There is no comforter for her out of all her lovers, All her friends dealt treacherously by her, They have been to her for enemies.

3 Removed hath Judah because of affliction, And because of the abundance of her service; She hath dwelt among nations, She hath not found rest, All her pursuers have overtaken her between the straits.

4 The ways of Zion are mourning, Without any coming at the appointed time, All her gates are desolate, her priests sigh, Her virgins are afflicted--and she hath bitterness.

5 Her adversaries have become chief, Her enemies have been at ease, For Jehovah hath afflicted her, For the abundance of her transgressions, Her infants have gone captive before the adversary.

6 And go out from the daughter of Zion doth all her honour, Her princes have been as harts--They have not found pasture, And they go powerless before a pursuer.

7 Remembered hath Jerusalem [In] the days of her affliction and her mournings, all her desirable things that were from the days of old, In the falling of her people into the hand of an adversary, And she hath no helper; Seen her have adversaries, They have laughed at her cessation.

8 A sin hath Jerusalem sinned, Therefore impure she hath become, All who honoured her have esteemed her lightly, For they have seen her nakedness, Yea, she herself hath sighed and turneth backward.

9 Her uncleanness [is] in her skirts, She hath not remembered her latter end, And she cometh down wonderfully, There is no comforter for her. See, O Jehovah, mine affliction, For exerted himself hath an enemy.

10 His hand spread out hath an adversary On all her desirable things, For she hath seen--Nations have entered her sanctuary, Concerning which Thou didst command, `They do not come into the assembly to thee.'

11 All her people are sighing--seeking bread, They have given their desirable things For food to refresh the body; See, O Jehovah, and behold attentively, For I have been lightly esteemed.

12 [Is it] nothing to you, all ye passing by the way? Look attentively, and see, If there is any pain like my pain, That He is rolling to me? Whom Jehovah hath afflicted In the day of the fierceness of His anger.

13 From above He hath sent fire into my bone, And it subdueth it, He hath spread a net for my feet, He hath turned me backward, He hath made me desolate--all the day sick.

14 Bound hath been the yoke of my transgressions by His hand, They are wrapped together, They have gone up on my neck, He hath caused my power to stumble, The Lord hath given me into hands, I am not able to rise.

15 Trodden down all my mighty ones hath the Lord in my midst, He proclaimed against me an appointed time, To destroy my young men, A wine-press hath the Lord trodden, To the virgin daughter of Judah.

16 For these I am weeping, My eye, my eye, is running down with waters, For, far from me hath been a comforter, Refreshing my soul, My sons have been desolate, For mighty hath been an enemy.

17 Spread forth hath Zion her hands, There is no comforter for her, Jehovah hath charged concerning Jacob, His neighbours [are] his adversaries, Jerusalem hath become impure among them.

18 Righteous is Jehovah, For His mouth I have provoked. Hear, I pray you, all ye peoples, and see my pain, My virgins and my young men have gone into captivity.

19 I called for my lovers, they--they have deceived me, My priests and my elders in the city have expired; When they have sought food for themselves, Then they give back their soul.

20 See, O Jehovah, for distress [is] to me, My bowels have been troubled, Turned hath been my heart in my midst, For I have greatly provoked, From without bereaved hath the sword, In the house [it is] as death.

21 They have heard that I have sighed, There is no comforter for me, All my enemies have heard of my calamity, They have rejoiced that Thou hast done [it], Thou hast brought in the day Thou hast called, And they are like to me.

22 Come in doth all their evil before Thee, And one is doing to them as Thou hast done to me, For all my transgressions, For many [are] my sighs, and my heart [is] sick!

Lamentations 2

1 How doth the Lord cloud in His anger the daughter of Zion, He hath cast from heaven [to] earth the beauty of Israel, And hath not remembered His footstool in the day of His anger.

2 Swallowed up hath the Lord, He hath not pitied any of the pleasant places of Jacob, He hath broken down in His wrath The fortresses of the daughter of Judah, He hath caused to come to the earth, He polluted the kingdom and its princes.

3 He hath cut off in the heat of anger every horn of Israel, He hath turned backward His right hand From the face of the enemy, And He burneth against Jacob as a flaming fire, It hath devoured round about.

4 He hath trodden His bow as an enemy, Stood hath His right hand as an adversary, And He slayeth all the desirable ones of the eye, In the tent of the daughter of Zion, He hath poured out as fire His fury.

5 The Lord hath been as an enemy, He hath swallowed up Israel, He hath swallowed up all her palaces, He hath destroyed His fortresses, And He multiplieth in the daughter of Judah Mourning and moaning.

6 And He shaketh as a garden His tabernacle, He hath destroyed His appointed place, Jehovah hath forgotten in Zion the appointed time and sabbath, And despiseth, in the indignation of His anger, king and priest.

7 The Lord hath cast off His altar, He hath rejected His sanctuary, He hath shut up into the hand of the enemy The walls of her palaces, A noise they have made in the house of Jehovah Like a day of appointment.

8 Devised hath Jehovah to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion, He hath stretched out a line, He hath not turned His hand from destroying, And He causeth bulwark and wall to mourn, Together--they have been weak.

9 Sunk into the earth have her gates, He hath destroyed and broken her bars, Her king and her princes [are] among the nations, There is no law, also her prophets Have not found vision from Jehovah.

10 Sit on the earth--keep silent do the elders of the daughter of Zion, They have caused dust to go up on their head, They have girded on sackcloth, Put down to the earth their head have the virgins of Jerusalem.

11 Consumed by tears have been my eyes, Troubled have been my bowels, Poured out to the earth hath been my liver, For the breach of the daughter of my people; In infant and suckling being feeble, In the broad places of the city,

12 To their mothers they say, `Where [are] corn and wine?' In their becoming feeble as a pierced one In the broad places of the city, In their soul pouring itself out into the bosom of their mothers.

13 What do I testify [to] thee, what do I liken to thee, O daughter of Jerusalem? What do I equal to thee, and I comfort thee, O virgin daughter of Zion? For great as a sea [is] thy breach, Who doth give healing to thee?

14 Thy prophets have seen for thee a false and insipid thing, And have not revealed concerning thine iniquity, To turn back thy captivity, And they see for thee false burdens and causes of expulsion.

15 Clapped hands at thee have all passing by the way, They have hissed--and they shake the head At the daughter of Jerusalem: `Is this the city of which they said: The perfection of beauty, a joy to all the land?'

16 Opened against thee their mouth have all thine enemies, They have hissed, yea, they gnash the teeth, They have said: `We have swallowed [her] up, Surely this [is] the day that we looked for, We have found--we have seen.'

17 Jehovah hath done that which He devised, He hath fulfilled His saying That He commanded from the days of old, He hath broken down and hath not pitied, And causeth an enemy to rejoice over thee, He lifted up the horn of thine adversaries.

18 Cried hath their heart unto the Lord; O wall of the daughter of Zion, Cause to go down as a stream tears daily and nightly, Give not rest to thyself, Let not the daughter of thine eye stand still.

19 Arise, cry aloud in the night, At the beginning of the watches. Pour out as water thy heart, Over against the face of the Lord, Lift up unto Him thy hands, for the soul of thine infants, Who are feeble with hunger at the head of all out-places.

20 See, O Jehovah, and look attentively, To whom Thou hast acted thus, Do women eat their fruit, infants of a handbreadth? Slain in the sanctuary of the Lord are priest and prophet?

21 Lain on the earth [in] out-places have young and old, My virgins and my young men have fallen by the sword, Thou hast slain in a day of Thine anger, Thou hast slaughtered--Thou hast not pitied.

22 Thou dost call as [at] a day of appointment, My fears from round about, And there hath not been in the day of the anger of Jehovah, An escaped and remaining one, They whom I stretched out and nourished, My enemy hath consumed!

Lamentations 3

1 I [am] the man [who] hath seen affliction By the rod of His wrath.

2 Me He hath led, and causeth to go [in] darkness, and without light.

3 Surely against me He turneth back, He turneth His hand all the day.

4 He hath worn out my flesh and my skin. He hath broken my bones.

5 He hath built up against me, And setteth round poverty and weariness.

6 In dark places He hath caused me to dwell, As the dead of old.

7 He hath hedged me about, and I go not out, He hath made heavy my fetter.

8 Also when I call and cry out, He hath shut out my prayer.

9 He hath hedged my ways with hewn work, My paths He hath made crooked.

10 A bear lying in wait He [is] to me, A lion in secret hiding-places.

11 My ways He is turning aside, and He pulleth me in pieces, He hath made me a desolation.

12 He hath trodden His bow, And setteth me up as a mark for an arrow.

13 He hath caused to enter into my reins The sons of His quiver.

14 I have been a derision to all my people, Their song all the day.

15 He hath filled me with bitter things, He hath filled me [with] wormwood.

16 And He breaketh with gravel my teeth, He hath covered me with ashes.

17 And Thou castest off from peace my soul, I have forgotten prosperity.

18 And I say, Perished hath my strength and my hope from Jehovah.

19 Remember my affliction and my mourning, Wormwood and gall!

20 Remember well, and bow down doth my soul in me.

21 This I turn to my heart--therefore I hope.

22 The kindnesses of Jehovah! For we have not been consumed, For not ended have His mercies.

23 New every morning, abundant [is] thy faithfulness.

24 My portion [is] Jehovah, hath my soul said, Therefore I hope for Him.

25 Good [is] Jehovah to those waiting for Him, To the soul [that] seeketh Him.

26 Good! when one doth stay and stand still For the salvation of Jehovah.

27 Good for a man that he beareth a yoke in his youth.

28 He sitteth alone, and is silent, For He hath laid [it] upon him.

29 He putteth in the dust his mouth, if so be there is hope.

30 He giveth to his smiter the cheek, He is filled with reproach.

31 For the Lord doth not cast off to the age.

32 For though He afflicted, yet He hath pitied, According to the abundance of His kindness.

33 For He hath not afflicted with His heart, Nor doth He grieve the sons of men.

34 To bruise under one's feet any bound ones of earth,

35 To turn aside the judgment of a man, Over-against the face of the Most High,

36 To subvert a man in his cause, the Lord hath not approved.

37 Who [is] this--he hath said, and it is, [And] the Lord hath not commanded [it]?

38 From the mouth of the Most High Go not forth the evils and the good.

39 What--sigh habitually doth a living man, A man for his sin?

40 We search our ways, and investigate, And turn back unto Jehovah.

41 We lift up our heart on the hands unto God in the heavens.

42 We--we have transgressed and rebelled, Thou--Thou hast not forgiven.

43 Thou hast covered Thyself with anger, And dost pursue us; Thou hast slain-- Thou hast not pitied.

44 Thou hast covered Thyself with a cloud, So that prayer doth not pass through.

45 Offscouring and refuse Thou dost make us In the midst of the peoples.

46 Opened against us their mouth have all our enemies.

47 Fear and a snare hath been for us, Desolation and destruction.

48 Rivulets of water go down my eye, For the destruction of the daughter of my people.

49 Mine eye is poured out, And doth not cease without intermission,

50 Till Jehovah looketh and seeth from the heavens,

51 My eye affecteth my soul, Because of all the daughters of my city.

52 Hunted me sore as a bird have my enemies without cause.

53 They have cut off in a pit my life, And they cast a stone against me.

54 Flowed have waters over my head, I have said, I have been cut off.

55 I called Thy name, O Jehovah, from the lower pit.

56 My voice Thou hast heard, Hide not Thine ear at my breathing--at my cry.

57 Thou hast drawn near in the day I call Thee, Thou hast said, Fear not.

58 Thou hast pleaded, O Lord, the pleadings of my soul, Thou hast redeemed my life.

59 Thou hast seen, O Jehovah, my overthrow, Judge Thou my cause.

60 Thou hast seen all their vengeance, All their thoughts of me.

61 Thou hast heard their reproach, O Jehovah, All their thoughts against me,

62 The lips of my withstanders, Even their meditation against me all the day.

63 Their sitting down, and their rising up, Behold attentively, I [am] their song.

64 Thou returnest to them the deed, O Jehovah, According to the work of their hands.

65 Thou givest to them a covered heart, Thy curse to them.

66 Thou pursuest in anger, and destroyest them, From under the heavens of Jehovah!

Lamentations 4

1 How is the gold become dim, Changed the best--the pure gold? Poured out are stones of the sanctuary At the head of all out-places.

2 The precious sons of Zion, Who are comparable with fine gold, How have they been reckoned earthen bottles, Work of the hands of a potter.

3 Even dragons have drawn out the breast, They have suckled their young ones, The daughter of my people is become cruel, Like the ostriches in a wilderness.

4 Cleaved hath the tongue of a suckling unto his palate with thirst, Infants asked bread, a dealer out they have none.

5 Those eating of dainties have been desolate in out-places, Those supported on scarlet have embraced dunghills.

6 And greater is the iniquity of the daughter of my people, Than the sin of Sodom, That was overturned as [in] a moment, And no hands were stayed on her.

7 Purer were her Nazarites than snow, Whiter than milk, ruddier of body than rubies, Of sapphire their form.

8 Darker than blackness hath been their visage, They have not been known in outplaces, Cleaved hath their skin unto their bone, It hath withered--it hath been as wood.

9 Better have been the pierced of a sword Than the pierced of famine, For these flow away, pierced through, Without the increase of the field.

10 The hands of merciful women have boiled their own children, They have been for food to them, In the destruction of the daughter of my people.

11 Completed hath Jehovah His fury, He hath poured out the fierceness of His anger, And he kindleth a fire in Zion, And it devoureth her foundations.

12 Believe not did the kings of earth, And any of the inhabitants of the world, That come would an adversary and enemy Into the gates of Jerusalem.

13 Because of the sins of her prophets, The iniquities of her priests, Who are shedding in her midst the blood of the righteous,

14 They have wandered naked in out-places, They have been polluted with blood, Without [any] being able to touch their clothing,

15 `Turn aside--unclean,' they called to them, `Turn aside, turn aside, touch not,' For they fled--yea, they have wandered, They have said among nations: `They do not add to sojourn.'

16 The face of Jehovah hath divided them, He doth not add to behold them, The face of priests they have not lifted up, Elders they have not favoured.

17 While we exist--consumed are our eyes for our vain help, In our watch-tower we have watched for a nation [that] saveth not.

18 They have hunted our steps from going in our broad-places, Near hath been our end, fulfilled our days, For come hath our end.

19 Swifter have been our pursuers, Than the eagles of the heavens, On the mountains they have burned [after] us, In the wilderness they have laid wait for us.

20 The breath of our nostrils--the anointed of Jehovah, Hath been captured in their pits, of whom we said: `In his shadow we do live among nations.'

21 Joy and rejoice, O daughter of Edom, Dwelling in the land of Uz, Even unto thee pass over doth a cup, Thou art drunk, and makest thyself naked.

22 Completed [is] thy iniquity, daughter of Zion, He doth not add to remove thee, He hath inspected thy iniquity, O daughter of Edom, He hath removed [thee] because of thy sins!

Lamentations 5

1 Remember, O Jehovah, what hath befallen us, Look attentively, and see our reproach.

2 Our inheritance hath been turned to strangers, Our houses to foreigners.

3 Orphans we have been--without a father, our mothers [are] as widows.

4 Our water for money we have drunk, Our wood for a price doth come.

5 For our neck we have been pursued, We have laboured--there hath been no rest for us.

6 [To] Egypt we have given a hand, [To] Asshur, to be satisfied with bread.

7 Our fathers have sinned--they are not, We their iniquities have borne.

8 Servants have ruled over us, A deliverer there is none from their hand.

9 With our lives we bring in our bread, Because of the sword of the wilderness.

10 Our skin as an oven hath been burning, Because of the raging of the famine.

11 Wives in Zion they have humbled, Virgins--in cities of Judah.

12 Princes by their hand have been hanged, The faces of elders have not been honoured.

13 Young men to grind they have taken, And youths with wood have stumbled.

14 The aged from the gate have ceased, Young men from their song.

15 Ceased hath the joy of our heart, Turned to mourning hath been our dancing.

16 Fallen hath the crown [from] our head, Woe [is] now to us, for we have sinned.

17 For this hath our heart been sick, For these have our eyes been dim.

18 For the mount of Zion--that is desolate, Foxes have gone up on it.

19 Thou, O Jehovah, to the age remainest, Thy throne to generation and generation.

20 Why for ever dost Thou forget us? Thou forsakest us for length of days!

21 Turn us back, O Jehovah, unto Thee, And we turn back, renew our days as of old.

22 For hast Thou utterly rejected us? Thou hast been wroth against us-- exceedingly?

Ezekiel 1

1 And it cometh to pass, in the thirtieth year, in the fourth [month], in the fifth of the month, and I [am] in the midst of the Removed by the river Chebar, the heavens have been opened, and I see visions of God.

2 In the fifth of the month--it is the fifth year of the removal of the king Jehoiachin--

3 hath the word of Jehovah certainly been unto Ezekiel son of Buzi the priest, in the land of the Chaldeans, by the river Chebar, and there is on him there a hand of Jehovah.

4 And I look, and lo, a tempestuous wind is coming from the north, a great cloud, and fire catching itself, and brightness to it round about, and out of its midst as the colour of copper, out of the midst of the fire.

5 And out of its midst [is] a likeness of four living creatures, and this [is] their appearance; a likeness of man [is] to them,

6 and four faces [are] to each, and four wings [are] to each of them,

7 and their feet [are] straight feet, and the sole of their feet [is] as a sole of a calf's foot, and they are sparkling as the colour of bright brass;

8 and hands of man under their wings--on their four sides, and their faces and their wings--[are] to them four;

9 joining one unto another [are] their wings, they turn not round in their going, each straight forward they go.

10 As to the likeness of their faces, the face of a man, and the face of a lion, toward the right [are] to them four, and the face of an ox on the left [are] to them four, and the face of an eagle [are] to them four.

11 And their faces and their wings are separate from above, to each [are] two joining together, and two are covering their bodies.

12 And each straight forward they go, whither the spirit is to go, they go, they turn not round in their going.

13 As to the likeness of the living creatures, their appearances [are] as coals of fire-- burning as the appearance of lamps; it is going up and down between the living creatures, and brightness [is] to the fire, and out of the fire is going forth lightning.

14 And the living creatures are running, and turning back, as the appearance of the flash.

15 And I see the living creatures, and lo, one wheel [is] in the earth, near the living creatures, at its four faces.

16 The appearance of the wheels and their works [is] as the colour of beryl, and one likeness [is] to them four, and their appearances and their works [are] as it were the wheel in the midst of the wheel.

17 On their four sides, in their going they go, they turn not round in their going.

18 As to their rings, they are both high and fearful, and their rings [are] full of eyes round about them four.

19 And in the going of the living creatures, the wheels go beside them, and in the living creatures being lifted up from off the earth, lifted up are the wheels.

20 Whither the spirit is to go, they go, thither the spirit [is] to go, and the wheels are lifted up over-against them, for a living spirit [is] in the wheels.

21 In their going, they go; and in their standing, they stand; and in their being lifted up from off the earth, lifted up are the wheels over-against them; for a living spirit [is] in the wheels.

22 And a likeness [is] over the heads of the living creatures of an expanse, as the colour of the fearful ice, stretched out over their heads from above.

23 And under the expanse their wings [are] straight, one toward the other, to each are two covering on this side, and to each are two covering on that side--their bodies.

24 And I hear the noise of their wings, as the noise of many waters, as the noise of the Mighty One, in their going--the noise of tumult, as the noise of a camp, in their standing they let fall their wings.

25 And there is a voice from above the expanse, that [is] above their head: in their standing they let fall their wings.

26 And above the expanse that [is] over their head, as an appearance of a sapphire stone, [is] the likeness of a throne, and on the likeness of the throne a likeness, as the appearance of man upon it from above.

27 And I see as the colour of copper, as the appearance of fire within it round about, from the appearance of his loins and upward, and from the appearance of his loins and downward, I have seen as the appearance of fire, and brightness [is] toit round about.

28 As the appearance of the bow that is in a cloud in a day of rain, so [is] the appearance of the brightness round about.

Ezekiel 3

1 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, that which thou findest eat, eat this roll, and go, speak unto the house of Israel.'

2 And I open my mouth, and He causeth me to eat this roll.

3 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, thy belly thou dost feed, and thy bowels thou dost fill with this roll that I am giving unto thee;' and I eat it, and it is in my mouth as honey for sweetness.

4 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, go, enter in unto the house of Israel, and thou hast spoken with My words unto them.

5 For, not unto a people deep of lip and heavy of tongue [art] thou sent--unto the house of Israel;

6 not unto many peoples, deep of lip and heavy of tongue, whose words thou dost not understand. If I had not sent thee unto them--they, they do hearken unto thee,

7 but the house of Israel are not willing to hearken unto thee, for they are not willing to hearken unto Me, for all the house of Israel are brazen-faced and strong-hearted.

8 `Lo, I have made thy face strong against their face, and thy forehead strong against their forehead.

9 As an adamant harder than a rock I have made thy forehead; thou dost not fear them, nor art thou affrighted before them, for a rebellious house [are] they.'

10 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, all My words, that I speak unto thee, receive with thy heart, and with thine ears hear;

11 and go, enter in unto the Removed, unto the sons of thy people, and thou hast spoken unto them, and hast said unto them: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: whether they hear, or whether they forbear.'

12 And lift me up doth a spirit, and I hear behind me a noise, a great rushing--`Blessed [is] the honour of Jehovah from His place!' --

13 even a noise of the wings of the living creatures touching one another, and a noise of the wheels over-against them, even a noise of a great rushing.

14 And a spirit hath lifted me up, and doth take me away, and I go bitterly, in the heat of my spirit, and the hand of Jehovah on me [is] strong.

15 And I come in unto the Removed, at Tel-Ahib, who are dwelling at the river Chebar, and where they are dwelling I also dwell seven days, causing astonishment in their midst.

16 And it cometh to pass, at the end of seven days,

17 that there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying, `Son of man, a watchman I have given thee to the house of Israel, and thou hast heard from My mouth a word, and hast warned them from Me.

18 In My saying to the wicked: Thou dost surely die; and thou hast not warned him, nor hast spoken to warn the wicked from his wicked way, so that he doth live; he--the wicked--in his iniquity dieth, and his blood from thy hand I require.

19 And thou, because thou hast warned the wicked, and he hath not turned back from his wickedness, and from his wicked way, he in his iniquity dieth, and thou thy soul hast delivered.

20 `And in the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, and he hath done perversity, and I have put a stumbling-block before him, he dieth; because thou hast not warned him, in his sin he dieth, and not remembered is his righteousness that he hath done, and his blood from thy hand I require.

21 And thou, because thou hast warned him--the righteous--that the righteous sin not, and he hath not sinned, he surely liveth, because he hath been warned; and thou thy soul hast delivered.'

22 And there is on me there a hand of Jehovah, and He saith to me, `Rise, go forth to the valley, and there I do speak with thee.'

23 And I rise and go forth unto the valley, and lo, there the honour of Jehovah is standing as the honour that I had seen by the river Chebar, and I fall on my face.

24 And come into me doth a spirit, and causeth me to stand on my feet, and He speaketh with me, and saith unto me, `Go in, be shut up in the midst of thy house.

25 `And thou, son of man, lo, they have put on thee thick bands, and have bound thee with them, and thou goest not forth in their midst;

26 and thy tongue I cause to cleave unto thy palate, and thou hast been dumb, and art not to them for a reprover, for a rebellious house [are] they.

27 And in My speaking with thee, I do open thy mouth, and thou hast said unto them: Thus said the Lord Jehovah; the hearer doth hear, and the forbearer doth forbear; for a rebellious house [are] they.

Ezekiel 4

1 `And thou, son of man, take to thee a brick, and thou hast put it before thee, and hast graven on it a city--Jerusalem,

2 and hast placed against it a siege, and builded against it a fortification, and poured out against it a mount, and placed against it camps, yea, set thou against it battering-rams round about.

3 And thou, take to thee an iron pan, and thou hast made it a wall of iron between thee and the city; and thou hast prepared thy face against it, and it hath been in a siege, yea, thou hast laid siege against it. A sign it [is] to the house of Israel.

4 `And thou, lie on thy left side, and thou hast placed the iniquity of the house of Israel on it; the number of the days that thou liest on it, thou bearest their iniquity.

5 And I--I have laid on thee the years of their iniquity, the number of days, three hundred and ninety days; and thou hast borne the iniquity of the house of Israel.

6 And thou hast completed these, and hast lain on thy right side, a second time, and hast borne the iniquity of the house of Judah forty days--a day for a year--a day for a year I have appointed to thee.

7 `And unto the siege of Jerusalem thou dost prepare thy face, and thine arm [is] uncovered, and thou hast prophesied concerning it.

8 And lo, I have put on thee thick bands, and thou dost not turn from side to side till thy completing the days of thy siege.

9 `And thou, take to thee wheat, and barley, and beans, and lentiles, and millet, and spelt, and thou hast put them in one vessel, and made them to thee for bread; the number of the days that thou art lying on thy side--three hundred and ninety days--thou dost eat it.

10 And thy food that thou dost eat [is] by weight, twenty shekels daily; from time to time thou dost eat it.

11 `And water by measure thou dost drink, a sixth part of the hin; from time to time thou dost drink [it].

12 A barley-cake thou dost eat it, and it with dung--the filth of man--thou dost bake before their eyes.

13 And Jehovah saith, `Thus do the sons of Israel eat their defiled bread among the nations whither I drive them.'

14 And I say, `Ah, Lord Jehovah, lo, my soul is not defiled, and carcase, and torn thing, I have not eaten from my youth, even till now; nor come into my mouth hath abominable flesh.'

15 And He saith unto me, `See, I have given to thee bullock's dung instead of man's dung, and thou hast made thy bread by it.'

16 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, lo, I am breaking the staff of bread in Jerusalem, and they have eaten bread by weight and with fear; and water by measure and with astonishment, they do drink;

17 so that they lack bread and water, and have been astonished one with another, and been consumed in their iniquity.

Ezekiel 5

1 `And thou, son of man, take to thee a sharp weapon, the barber's razor thou dost take to thee, and thou hast caused [it] to pass over thy head, and over thy beard, and thou hast taken to thee weighing scales, and apportioned them.

2 A third part with fire thou dost burn in the midst of the city, at the fulness of the days of the siege; and thou hast taken the third part, thou dost smite with a weapon round about it; and the third part thou dost scatter to the wind, and aweapon I draw out after them.

3 And thou hast taken thence a few in number--and hast bound them in thy skirts;

4 and of them thou dost take again, and hast cast them unto the midst of the fire, and hast burned them in the fire--out of it cometh forth a fire unto all the house of Israel.

5 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: this [is] Jerusalem, In the midst of the nations I have set her, And round about her [are] the lands.

6 And she changeth My judgments into wickedness more than the nations, And My statutes more than the lands that [are] round about her, For against My judgments they have kicked, And My statutes--they have not walked in them.

7 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of your multiplying above the nations that [are] around you, In My statutes ye have not walked, And My judgments ye have not done, According to the judgments of the nations That [are] round aboutyou ye have not done.

8 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, even I, And I have done in thy midst judgments, Before the eyes of the nations.

9 And I have done in thee that which I have not done, And that which I do not its like again, Because of all thine abominations.

10 Therefore fathers do eat sons in thy midst, And sons eat their fathers, And I have done in thee judgments, And have scattered all thy remnant to every wind.

11 Therefore, I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah: Because My sanctuary thou hast defiled, With all thy detestable things, And with all thine abominations, Mine eye pitieth not, and I also spare not. Do not even I also diminish?

12 Thy third part--by pestilence they die, And by famine are consumed in thy midst, And the third part, by sword they fall round about thee, And the third part, to every wind I scatter, And a sword I draw out after them.

13 And completed hath been Mine anger, And I have caused My fury to rest on them, And I have been comforted, And they have known that I, Jehovah, have spoken in My zeal, In My completing My fury on them.

14 And I give thee for a waste, And for a reproach among nations that [are] round about thee, Before the eyes of every passer by.

15 And it hath been a reproach and a reviling, An instruction and an astonishment, To nations that [are] round about thee, In My doing in thee judgments, In anger and fury, and in furious reproofs, I, Jehovah, have spoken.

16 In My sending the evil arrows of famine among them, That have been for destruction, That I send to destroy you, And famine I am adding upon you, And I have broken to you the staff of bread.

17 And I have sent on you famine and evil beasts, And they have bereaved thee, And pestilence and blood pass over on thee, And a sword I do bring in against thee, I, Jehovah, have spoken!'

Ezekiel 6

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 `Son of man, set thy face unto mountains of Israel, and prophesy concerning them:

3 And thou hast said: Mountains of Israel, Hear ye a word of the Lord Jehovah: Thus said the Lord Jehovah To the mountains, and to the hills, To the streams, and to the valleys, Lo, I, I am bringing in against you a sword, And I have destroyed your high places.

4 And desolated have been your altars, And broken your images, And I have caused your wounded to fall before your idols,

5 And put the carcases of the sons of Israel before their idols, And scattered your bones round about your altars.

6 In all your dwellings the cities are laid waste, And the high places are desolate, So that waste and desolate are your altars, And broken and ceased have your idols, And cut down have been your images, And blotted out have been your works.

7 And fallen hath the wounded in your midst, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

8 And I have caused [some] to remain, In their being to you the escaped of the sword among nations, In your being scattered through lands.

9 And remembered Me have your escaped among nations, Whither they have been taken captive, Because I have been broken with their heart that is going a-whoring, That hath turned aside from off Me, And with their eyes they are going a-whoring after their idols, And they have been loathsome in their own faces, For the evils that they have done--all their abominations.

10 And they have known that I [am] Jehovah, Not for nought have I spoken to do to them this evil.

11 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: `Smite with thy palm, and stamp with thy foot, And say: Alas, for all the evil abominations of the house of Israel, Who by sword, by famine, and by pestilence do fall.

12 The far-off by pestilence dieth, And the near by sword falleth, And the left and the besieged by famine dieth, And I have completed my fury upon them.

13 And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah, In their wounded being in the midst of their idols, Round about their altars, On every high hill, on all tops of mountains, And under every green tree, and under every thick oak, The place where they gave sweet fragrance to all their idols.

14 And I have stretched out my hand against them, And have made the land a desolation, Even a desolation from the wilderness to Diblath, In all their dwellings, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 7

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying, `And thou, son of man, Thus said the Lord Jehovah to the ground of Israel:

2 An end, come hath the end on the four corners of the land.

3 Now [is] the end unto thee, And I have sent Mine anger upon thee, And judged thee according to thy ways, And set against thee all thine abominations.

4 And no pity on thee hath Mine eye, nor do I spare, For thy ways against thee I do set, And thine abominations are in thy midst, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

5 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Evil, a single evil, lo, it hath come.

6 An end hath come, come hath the end, It hath waked for thee, lo, it hath come.

7 Come hath the morning unto thee, O inhabitant of the land! Come hath the time, near [is] a day of trouble, And not the shouting of mountains.

8 Now, shortly I pour out My fury on thee, And have completed Mine anger against thee, And judged thee according to thy ways, And set against thee all thine abominations.

9 And not pity doth Mine eye, nor do I spare, According to thy ways unto thee I give, And thine abominations are in thy midst, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah the smiter.

10 Lo, the day, lo, it hath come, Gone forth hath the morning, Blossomed hath the rod, flourished the pride.

11 The violence hath risen to a rod of wickedness, There is none of them, nor of their multitude, Nor of their noise, nor is there wailing for them.

12 Come hath the time, arrived hath the day, The buyer doth not rejoice, And the seller doth not become a mourner, For wrath [is] unto all its multitude.

13 For the seller to the sold thing turneth not, And yet among the living [is] their life, For the vision [is] unto all its multitude, It doth not turn back, And none by his iniquity doth strengthen his life.

14 They have blown with a trumpet to prepare the whole, And none is going to battle, For My wrath [is] unto all its multitude.

15 The sword [is] without, And the pestilence and the famine within, He who is in a field by sword dieth, And he who is in a city, Famine and pestilence devour him.

16 And escaped away have their fugitives, And they have been on the mountains As doves of the valleys, All of them make a noising--each for his iniquity.

17 All the hands are feeble, and all knees go--waters.

18 And they have girded on sackcloth, And covered them hath trembling, And unto all faces [is] shame, And on all their heads--baldness.

19 Their silver into out-places they cast, And their gold impurity becometh. Their silver and their gold is not able to deliver them, In a day of the wrath of Jehovah, Their soul they do not satisfy, And their bowels they do not fill, For the stumbling-block of their iniquity it hath been.

20 As to the beauty of his ornament, For excellency He set it, And the images of their abominations, Their detestable things--they made in it, Therefore I have given it to them for impurity,

21 And I have given it into the hand of the strangers for a prey, And to the wicked of the land for a spoil, And they have polluted it.

22 And I have turned My face from them, And they have polluted My hidden place, Yea, come into it have destroyers, and polluted it.

23 Make the chain; for the land Hath been full of bloody judgments, And the city hath been full of violence.

24 And I have brought in the wicked of the nations, And they have possessed their houses, And I have caused to cease the excellency of the strong, And polluted have been those sanctifying them.

25 Destruction hath come, And they have sought peace, and there is none.

26 Mischief on mischief cometh, and report is on report, And they have sought a vision from a prophet, And law doth perish from the priest, And counsel from the elders,

27 The king doth become a mourner, And a prince putteth on desolation, And the hands of the people of the land are troubled, From their own way I deal with them, And with their own judgments I judge them, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 8

1 And it cometh to pass, in the sixth year, in the sixth [month], in the fifth of the month, I am sitting in my house, and elders of Judah are sitting before me, and fall on me there doth a hand of the Lord Jehovah,

2 and I look, and lo, a likeness as the appearance of fire, from the appearance of His loins and downward--fire, and from His loins and upward, as the appearance of brightness, as the colour of copper.

3 And He putteth forth a form of a hand, and taketh me by a lock of my head, and lift me up doth a spirit between the earth and the heavens, and it bringeth me in to Jerusalem in visions of God, unto the opening of the inner gate that is facingthe north, where [is] the seat of the figure of jealousy that is making jealous,

4 and lo, there the honour of the God of Israel, as the appearance that I saw in the valley.

5 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, lift up, I pray thee, thine eyes the way of the north.' And I lift up mine eyes the way of the north, and lo, on the north of the gate of the altar this figure of jealousy, at the entrance.

6 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, art thou seeing what they are doing? the great abominations that the house of Israel are doing here, to keep far off from My sanctuary; and again thou dost turn, thou dost see great abominations.'

7 And He bringeth me in unto an opening of the court, and I look, and lo, a hole in the wall;

8 and He saith unto me, `Son of man, dig, I pray thee, through the wall;' and I dig through the wall, and lo, an opening.

9 And He saith to me, `Go in, and see the evil abominations that they are doing here.'

10 And I go in, and look, and lo, every form of creeping thing, and detestable beast--and all the Idols of the house of Israel--graved on the wall, all round about,

11 and seventy men of the elders of the house of Israel--and Jaazaniah son of Shaphan standing in their midst--are standing before them, and each his censer in his hand, and the abundance of the cloud of perfume is going up.

12 And He saith unto me, `Hast thou seen, son of man, that which elders of the house of Israel are doing in darkness, each in the inner chambers of his imagery, for they are saying, Jehovah is not seeing us, Jehovah hath forsaken the land?'

13 And He saith unto me, `Again thou dost turn, thou dost see great abominations that they are doing.'

14 And He bringeth me in unto the opening of the gate of the house of Jehovah that [is] at the north, and lo, there the women are sitting weeping for Tammuz.

15 And He saith unto me, `Hast thou seen, son of man? again thou dost turn, thou dost see greater abominations than these.'

16 And He bringeth me in unto the inner court of the house of Jehovah, and lo, at the opening of the temple of Jehovah, between the porch and the altar, about twenty-five men, their backs toward the temple of Jehovah, and their faces eastward, and they are bowing themselves eastward to the sun.

17 And He saith unto me, `Hast thou seen, son of man? hath it been a light thing to the house of Judah to do the abomination that they have done here, that they have filled the land with violence, and turn back to provoke Me to anger? and lo, they are putting forth the branch unto their nose!

18 And I also deal in fury, Mine eye doth not pity, nor do I spare, and they have cried in Mine ears--a loud voice--and I do not hear them.'

Ezekiel 10

1 And I look, and lo, on the expanse that [is] above the head of the cherubs, as a sapphire stone, as the appearance of the likeness of a throne, He hath been seen over them.

2 And He speaketh unto the man clothed with linen, and saith, `Go in unto the midst of the wheel, unto the place of the cherub, and fill thy hands with coals of fire from between the cherubs, and scatter over the city.' And he goeth in before mine eyes.

3 And the cherubs are standing on the right side of the house, at the going in of the man, and the cloud hath filled the inner court,

4 and become high doth the honour of Jehovah above the cherub, over the threshold of the house, and the house is filled with the cloud, and the court hath been filled with the brightness of the honour of Jehovah.

5 And a noise of the wings of the cherubs hath been heard unto the outer court, as the voice of God--the Mighty One--in His speaking.

6 And it cometh to pass, in His commanding the man clothed with linen, saying, `Take fire from between the wheel, from between the cherubs,' and he goeth in and standeth near the wheel,

7 that the [one] cherub putteth forth his hand from between the cherubs unto the fire that [is] between the cherubs, and lifteth up, and giveth into the hands of him who is clothed with linen, and he receiveth, and cometh forth.

8 And there appeareth in the cherubs the form of a hand of man under their wings,

9 and I look, and lo, four wheels near the cherubs, one wheel near the one cherub, and another wheel near the other cherub, and the appearance of the wheels [is] as the colour of a beryl stone.

10 As to their appearances, one likeness [is] to them four, as it were the wheel in the midst of the wheel.

11 In their going, on their four sides they go; they turn not round in their going, for to the place whither the head turneth, after it they go, they turn not round in their going.

12 And all their flesh, and their backs, and their hands, and their wings, and the wheels, are full of eyes round about; to them four [are] their wheels.

13 To the wheels--to them is one calling in mine ears, `O wheel!'

14 And four faces [are] to each; the face of the one [is] the face of the cherub, and the face of the second the face of man, and of the third the face of a lion, and of the fourth the face of an eagle.

15 And the cherubs are lifted up, it [is] the living creature that I saw by the river Chebar.

16 And in the going of the cherubs, the wheels go beside them; and in the cherubs lifting up their wings to be high above the earth, the wheels turn not round, even they, from being beside them.

17 In their standing they stand, and in their exaltation they are exalted with them: for the living spirit [is] in them.

18 And go forth doth the honour of Jehovah from off the threshold of the house, and standeth over the cherubs,

19 and the cherubs lift up their wings, and are lifted up from the earth before mine eyes; in their going forth, the wheels also [are] over-against them, and he standeth at the opening of the east gate of the house of Jehovah, and the honour of the God of Israel [is] over them from above.

20 It [is] the living creature that I saw under the God of Israel by the river Chebar, and I know that they are cherubs.

21 Four faces [are] to each, and four wings to each, and the likeness of the hands of man [is] under their wings.

22 As to the likeness of their faces, they [are] the faces that I saw by the river Chebar, their appearances and themselves; each straight forward they go.

Ezekiel 11

1 And lift me up doth a spirit, and it bringeth me in unto the east gate of the house of Jehovah, that is facing the east, and lo, at the opening of the gate twenty and five men, and I see in their midst Jaazaniah son of Azzur, and Pelatiah son of Benaiah, heads of the people.

2 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, these [are] the men who are devising iniquity, and who are giving evil counsel in this city;

3 who are saying, It [is] not near--to build houses, it [is] the pot, and we the flesh.

4 Therefore prophesy concerning them, prophesy, son of man.'

5 And fall upon me doth the Spirit of Jehovah, and He saith unto me, `Say: Thus said Jehovah: Rightly ye have said, O house of Israel, And the steps of your spirit I have known.

6 Ye multiplied your wounded in this city, And filled its out-places with the wounded.

7 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Your wounded whom ye placed in its midst, They [are] the flesh, and it [is] the pot, And you he hath brought out from its midst.

8 A sword ye have feared, And a sword I bring in against you, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

9 And I have brought you out of its midst, And given you into the hand of strangers, And I have done among you judgments.

10 By the sword ye do fall, On the border of Israel I do judge you, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

11 It is not to you for a pot, Nor are ye in its midst for flesh, At the border of Israel I do judge you.

12 And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah, For in My statutes ye have not walked, And My Judgments ye have not done, And according to the judgments of the nations Who are round about you--ye have done!'

13 And it cometh to pass, at my prophesying, that Pelatiah son of Benaiah is dying, and I fall on my face, and cry--a loud voice--and say, `Ah, Lord Jehovah, an end Thou art making of the remnant of Israel.'

14 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

15 `Son of man, thy brethren, thy brethren, men of thy kindred, and all the house of Israel--all of it, [are] they to whom inhabitants of Jerusalem have said, Keep far off from Jehovah;

16 it [is] ours, the land hath been given for an inheritance; therefore say: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because I put them afar off among nations, And because I scattered them through lands, I also am to them for a little sanctuary, In lands whither they have gone in.

17 Therefore say: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: And I have assembled you from the peoples, And I have gathered you from the lands, Into which ye have been scattered, And I have given to you the ground of Israel.

18 And they have gone in thither. And turned aside all its detestable things, And all its abominations--out of it.

19 And I have given to them one heart, And a new spirit I do give in your midst, And I have turned the heart of stone out of their flesh, And I have given to them a heart of flesh.

20 So that in My statutes they walk, And My judgments they keep, and have done them, And they have been to me for a people, And I am to them for God.

21 As to those whose heart is going unto the heart Of their detestable and their abominable things, Their way on their head I have put, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

22 And the cherubs lift up their wings, and the wheels [are] over-against them, and the honour of the God of Israel [is] over them above.

23 And the honour of Jehovah goeth up from off the midst of the city, and standeth on the mountain, that [is] on the east of the city.

24 And a spirit hath lifted me up, and bringeth me in to Chaldea, unto the Removed, in a vision, by the Spirit of God, and go up from off me doth the vision that I have seen;

25 and I speak unto the Removed all the matters of Jehovah that He hath shewed me.

Ezekiel 13

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, prophesy concerning the prophets of Israel who are prophesying, and thou hast said to those prophesying from their own heart: Hear ye a word of Jehovah:

3 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Woe unto the prophets who are foolish, Who are going after their own spirit, And they have seen nothing.

4 As foxes in the wastes, Thy prophets, O Israel, have been.

5 Ye have not gone up into breaches, Nor do ye make a fence for the house of Israel, To stand in battle in a day of Jehovah.

6 They have seen vanity, and lying divination, Who are saying: An affirmation of Jehovah, And Jehovah hath not sent them, And they have hoped to establish a word.

7 A vain vision have ye not seen, And a lying divination spoken, When ye say: An affirmation of Jehovah, And I have not spoken?

8 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because ye have spoken vanity, and seen a lie, Therefore, lo, I [am] against you, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

9 And My hand hath been on the prophets, Who are seeing vanity, and who are divining a lie, In the assembly of My people they are not, And in the writing of the house of Israel they are not written, And unto the ground of Israel they come not,And ye have known that I [am] the Lord Jehovah.

10 Because, even because, they did cause My people to err, Saying, Peace! and there is no peace, And that one is building a wall, And lo, they are daubing it with chalk.

11 Say to those daubing with chalk--It falleth, There hath been an overflowing shower, And ye, O hailstones, do fall, And a tempestuous wind doth rend,

12 And lo, fallen hath the wall! Doth not one say unto you, Where [is] the daubing that ye daubed?

13 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: I have rent with a tempestuous wind in My fury, And an overflowing shower is in Mine anger, And hailstones in My fury--to consume.

14 And I have broken down the wall that ye daubed with chalk, And have caused it to come unto the earth, And revealed hath been its foundation, And it hath fallen, And ye have been consumed in its midst, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

15 And I have completed My wrath on the wall, And on those daubing it with chalk, And I say to you: The wall is not, And those daubing it are not;

16 The prophets of Israel who are prophesying concerning Jerusalem, And who are seeing for her a vision of peace, And there is no peace, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

17 And thou, son of man, set thy face against the daughters of thy people, who are prophesying out of their own heart, and prophesy concerning them,

18 And thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Woe to those sowing pillows for all joints of the arm, And to those making the kerchiefs For the head of every stature--to hunt souls, The souls do ye hunt of My people? And the souls ye have do ye keep alive?

19 Yea, ye pierce Me concerning My people, For handfuls of barley, And for pieces of bread, to put to death Souls that should not die, And to keep alive souls that should not live, By your lying to My people--hearkening to lies.

20 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against your pillows, With which ye are hunting there the souls of the flourishing, And I have rent them from off your arms, And have sent away the souls that ye are hunting, The souls of the flourishing.

21 And I have torn your kerchiefs, And delivered My people out of your hand, And they are no more in your hand for a prey, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

22 Because of paining the heart of the righteous with falsehood, And I have not pained it, And strengthening the hands of the wicked, So as not to turn back from his evil way, To keep him alive,

23 Therefore, vanity ye do not see, And divination ye do not divine again, And I have delivered My people out of your hand, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 16

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, cause Jerusalem to know her abominations, and thou hast said:

3 Thus said the Lord Jehovah to Jerusalem: Thy birth and thy nativity [Are] of the land of the Canaanite, Thy father the Amorite, and thy mother a Hittite.

4 As to thy nativity, in the day thou wast born, Thou--thy navel hath not been cut, And in water thou wast not washed for ease, And thou hast not been salted at all, And thou hast not been swaddled at all.

5 No eye hath had pity on thee, to do to thee any of these, To have compassion on thee, And thou art cast on the face of the field, With loathing of thy person. In the day thou hast been born--thou!

6 And I do pass over by thee, And I see thee trodden down in thy blood, And I say to thee in thy blood, Live, And I say to thee in thy blood, Live.

7 A myriad--as the shoot of the field I have made thee, And thou art multiplied, and art great, And comest in with an excellent adornment, Breasts have been formed, and thy hair hath grown--And thou, naked and bare!

8 And I pass over by thee, and I see thee, And lo, thy time [is] a time of loves, And I spread My skirt over thee, And I cover thy nakedness, And I swear to thee, and come in to a covenant with thee, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, And thou dost become Mine.

9 And I do wash thee with water, And I wash away thy blood from off thee, And I anoint thee with perfume.

10 And I clothe thee with embroidery, And I shoe thee with badger's skin, And I gird thee with fine linen, And I cover thee with figured silk.

11 And I adorn thee with adornments, And I give bracelets for thy hands, And a chain for thy neck.

12 And I give a ring for thy nose, And rings for thine ears, And a crown of beauty on thy head.

13 And thou dost put on gold and silver, And thy clothing [is] fine linen, And figured silk and embroidery, Fine flour, and honey, and oil thou hast eaten, And thou art very very beautiful, And dost go prosperously to the kingdom.

14 And go forth doth thy name among nations, Because of thy beauty--for it [is] complete, In My honour that I have set upon thee, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

15 And thou dost trust in thy beauty, And goest a-whoring because of thy renown, And dost pour out thy whoredoms On every passer by--to him it is.

16 And thou dost take of thy garments, And dost make to thee spotted high-places, And dost go a-whoring upon them, They are not coming in--nor shall it be!

17 And thou dost take thy beauteous vessels Of My gold and My silver that I gave to thee, And dost make to thee images of a male, And dost go a-whoring with them,

18 And dost take the garments of thy embroidery, And thou dost cover them, And My oil and My perfume thou hast set before them.

19 And My bread, that I gave to thee, Fine flour, and oil, and honey, that I caused thee to eat. Thou hast even set it before them, For a sweet fragrance--thus it is, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

20 And thou dost take thy sons and thy daughters Whom thou hast born to Me, And dost sacrifice them to them for food. Is it a little thing because of thy whoredoms,

21 That thou dost slaughter My sons, And dost give them up in causing them to pass over to them?

22 And with all thine abominations and thy whoredoms, Thou hast not remembered the days of thy youth, When thou wast naked and bare, Trodden down in thy blood thou wast!

23 And it cometh to pass, after all thy wickedness, (Woe, woe, to thee--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah),

24 That thou dost build to thee an arch, And dost make to thee a high place in every broad place.

25 At every head of the way thou hast built thy high place, And thou dost make thy beauty abominable, And dost open wide thy feet to every passer by, And dost multiply thy whoredoms,

26 And dost go a-whoring unto sons of Egypt, Thy neighbours--great of appetite! And thou dost multiply thy whoredoms, To provoke Me to anger.

27 And lo, I have stretched out My hand against thee, And I diminish thy portion, And give thee to the desire of those hating thee, The daughters of the Philistines, Who are ashamed of thy wicked way.

28 And thou goest a-whoring unto sons of Asshur, Without thy being satisfied, And thou dost go a-whoring with them, And also--thou hast not been satisfied.

29 And thou dost multiply thy whoredoms On the land of Canaan--toward Chaldea, And even with this thou hast not been satisfied.

30 How weak [is] thy heart, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, In thy doing all these, The work of a domineering whorish woman.

31 In thy building thine arch at the head of every way, Thy high place thou hast made in every broad place, And--hast not been as a whore deriding a gift.

32 The wife who committeth adultery--Under her husband--doth receive strangers.

33 To all whores they give a gift, And--thou hast given thy gifts to all thy lovers, And dost bribe them to come in unto thee, From round about--in thy whoredoms.

34 And the contrary is in thee from women in thy whoredoms, That after thee none doth go a-whoring; And in thy giving a gift, And a gift hath not been given to thee; And thou art become contrary.

35 Therefore, O whore, hear a word of Jehovah,

36 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of thy brass being poured forth, And thy nakedness is revealed in thy whoredoms near thy lovers, And near all the idols of thy abominations, And according to the blood of thy sons, Whom thou hast given tothem;

37 Therefore, lo, I am assembling all thy lovers, To whom thou hast been sweet, And all whom thou hast loved, Besides all whom thou hast hated; And I have assembled them by thee round about, And have revealed thy nakedness to them, And they have seen all thy nakedness.

38 And I have judged thee--judgments of adulteresses, And of women shedding blood, And have given thee blood, fury, and jealousy.

39 And I have given thee into their hand, And they have thrown down thine arch, And they have broken down thy high places, And they have stript thee of thy garments, And they have taken thy beauteous vessels, And they have left thee naked and bare.

40 And have caused an assembly to come up against thee, And stoned thee with stones, And thrust thee through with their swords,

41 And burnt thy houses with fire, And done in thee judgments before the eyes of many women, And I have caused thee to cease from going a-whoring, And also a gift thou givest no more.

42 And I have caused My fury against thee to rest, And My jealousy hath turned aside from thee, And I have been quiet, and I am not angry any more.

43 Because thou hast not remembered the days of thy youth, And dost give trouble to Me in all these, Lo, even I also thy way at first gave up, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, And I did not this thought for all thine abominations.

44 Lo, every one using a simile, Doth use a simile concerning thee, saying: As the mother--her daughter!

45 Thy mother's daughter thou [art], Loathing her husband and her sons, And thy sisters' sister thou [art], Who loathed their husbands and their sons, Your mother [is] a Hittite, and your father an Amorite.

46 And thine elder sister [is] Samaria, she and her daughters, Who is dwelling at thy left hand, And thy younger sister, who is dwelling on thy right hand, [is] Sodom and her daughters.

47 And--in their ways thou hast not walked, And according to their abominations done, As a little thing it hath been loathed, And thou dost more corruptly than they in all thy ways.

48 I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Sodom thy sister hath not done--she and her daughters--As thou hast done--thou and thy daughters.

49 Lo, this hath been the iniquity of Sodom thy sister, Arrogancy, fulness of bread, and quiet ease, Have been to her and to her daughters, And the hand of the afflicted and needy She hath not strengthened.

50 And they are haughty and do abomination before Me, And I turn them aside when I have seen.

51 As to Samaria, as the half of thy sins--she hath not sinned, And thou dost multiply thine abominations more than they, And dost justify thy sisters by all thy abominations that thou hast done.

52 Thou also--bear thy shame, That thou hast adjudged to thy sisters, Because of thy sins that thou hast done more abominably than they, They are more righteous than thou, And thou, also, be ashamed and bear thy shame, In thy justifying thy sisters.

53 And I have turned back [to] their captivity, The captivity of Sodom and her daughters, And the captivity of Samaria and her daughters, And the captivity of thy captives in their midst,

54 So that thou dost bear thy shame, And hast been ashamed of all that thou hast done, In thy comforting them.

55 And thy sisters, Sodom and her daughters, Do turn back to their former state, And Samaria and her daughters Do turn back to their former state, And thou and thy daughters do turn back to your former state.

56 And thy sister Sodom hath not been for a report in thy mouth, In the day of thine arrogancy,

57 Before thy wickedness is revealed, As [at] the time of the reproach of the daughters of Aram, And of all her neighbours, the daughters of the Philistines, Who are despising thee round about.

58 Thy devices and thine abominations, Thou hast borne them, an affirmation of Jehovah.

59 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: I have dealt with thee as thou hast done, In that thou hast despised an oath--to break covenant.

60 And I--I have remembered My covenant with thee, In the days of thy youth, And I have established for thee a covenant age-during.

61 And thou hast remembered thy ways, And thou hast been ashamed, In thy receiving thy sisters--Thine elder with thy younger, And I have given them to thee for daughters, And not by thy covenant.

62 And I--I have established My covenant with thee, And thou hast known that I [am] Jehovah.

63 So that thou dost remember, And thou hast been ashamed, And there is not to thee any more an opening of the mouth because of thy shame, In My receiving atonement for thee, For all that thou hast done, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 18

1 `And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 `What--to you, ye--using this simile Concerning the ground of Israel, saying: Fathers do eat unripe fruit, And the sons' teeth are blunted?

3 I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Ye have no more the use of this simile in Israel.

4 Lo, all the souls are Mine, As the soul of the father, So also the soul of the son--they are Mine, The soul that is sinning--it doth die.

5 And a man, when he is righteous, And hath done judgment and righteousness,

6 On the mountains he hath not eaten, And his eyes he hath not lifted up Unto idols of the house of Israel, And the wife of his neighbour defiled not, And to a separated woman cometh not near,

7 A man--he doth not oppress, His pledge to the debtor he doth return, Plunder he doth not take away, His bread to the hungry he doth give, And the naked doth cover with a garment,

8 In usury he doth not give, and increase taketh not, From perversity he turneth back his hand, True judgment he doth between man and man.

9 In My statutes he doth walk, And My judgments he hath kept--to deal truly, Righteous [is] he, he surely liveth, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

10 And--he hath begotten a son, A burglar--a shedder of blood, And he hath made a brother of one of these,

11 And he all those hath not done, For even on the mountains he hath eaten, And the wife of his neighbour he hath defiled,

12 The afflicted and needy he hath oppressed, Plunder he hath taken violently away, A pledge he doth not return, And unto the idols he hath lifted up his eyes, Abomination he hath done!

13 In usury he hath given, and increase taken, And he liveth: he doth not live, All these abominations he hath done, He doth surely die, his blood is on him.

14 And--lo, he hath begotten a son, And he seeth all the sins of his father, That he hath done, and he feareth, And doth not do like them,

15 On the mountains he hath not eaten, And his eyes he hath not lifted up Unto idols of the house of Israel, The wife of his neighbour he hath not defiled,

16 A man--he hath not oppressed, A pledge he hath not bound, And plunder he hath not taken away, His bread to the hungry he hath given, And the naked he covered with a garment,

17 From the afflicted he hath turned back his hand, Usury and increase he hath not taken, My judgments he hath done, In My statutes he hath walked, He doth not die for the iniquity of his father, He doth surely live.

18 His father--because he used oppression, Did violently Plunder a brother, And that which [is] not good did in the midst of his people, And lo, he is dying in his iniquity.

19 And ye have said, Wherefore hath not the son, Borne of the iniquity of the father? And--the son judgment and righteousness hath done, All My statutes he hath kept, And he doeth them, he surely liveth.

20 The soul that doth sin--it doth die. A son doth not bear of the iniquity of the father, And a father doth not bear of the iniquity of the son, The righteousness of the righteous is on him, And the wickedness of the wicked is on him.

21 And the wicked--when he turneth back From all his sins that he hath done, And he hath kept all My statutes, And hath done judgment and righteousness, He doth surely live, he doth not die.

22 All his transgressions that he hath done Are not remembered to him, In his righteousness that he hath done he liveth.

23 Do I at all desire the death of the wicked? An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Is it not in his turning back from his way--And he hath lived?

24 And in the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, And he hath done perversity, According to all the abominations That the wicked hath done, he doth--thus he liveth, All his righteousnesses that he hath done are not remembered, For his trespass that he hath trespassed, And for his sin that he hath sinned, For them he doth die.

25 And ye have said, Not pondered is the way of the Lord. Hear, I pray you, O house of Israel, My way--is it not pondered? Are not your ways unpondered?

26 In the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, And he hath done perversity, And he is dying by them, for his perversity That he hath done he dieth.

27 And in the turning back of the wicked From his wickedness that he hath done, And he doth judgment and righteousness, He his soul doth keep alive.

28 And he seeth and turneth back, From all his transgressions that he hath done, He doth surely live, he doth not die,

29 And the house of Israel have said, Not pondered is the way of the Lord, My ways-- are they not pondered? O house of Israel--are not your ways unpondered?

30 Therefore, each according to his ways I judge you, O house of Israel? An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Turn ye back, yea, turn yourselves back, From all your transgressions, And iniquity is not to you for a stumbling-block,

31 Cast from off you all your transgressions, By which ye have transgressed, And make to you a new heart, and a new spirit, And why do ye die, O house of Israel?

32 For I have no pleasure in the death of the dying, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, And turn ye back and live!

Ezekiel 19

1 And thou, lift up a lamentation unto princes of Israel,

2 and thou hast said: What [is] thy mother? --a lioness, Among lions she hath crouched down, In the midst of young lions she hath multiplied her whelps.

3 And she bringeth up one of her whelps, A young lion it hath been, And it learneth to tear prey, man it hath devoured.

4 And hear of it do nations, In their pit it hath been caught, And they bring it in with chains unto the land of Egypt.

5 And she seeth, that stayed--perished hath her hope, And she taketh one of her whelps, A young lion she hath made it.

6 And it goeth up and down in the midst of lions, A young lion it hath been, And it learneth to tear prey, man it hath devoured.

7 And it knoweth his forsaken habitations, And their cities it hath laid waste, And desolate is the land and its fulness, Because of the voice of his roaring.

8 And set against it do nations Round about from the provinces. And they spread out for it their net, In their pit it hath been caught.

9 And they put it in prison--in chains, And they bring it unto the king of Babylon, They bring it in unto bulwarks, So that its voice is not heard any more On mountains of Israel.

10 Thy mother [is] as a vine in thy blood by waters planted, Fruitful and full of boughs it hath been, Because of many waters.

11 And it hath strong rods for sceptres of rulers, And high is its stature above thick branches, And it appeareth in its height In the multitude of its thin shoots.

12 And it is plucked up in fury, To the earth it hath been cast, And the east wind hath dried up its fruit, Broken and withered hath been the rod of its strength, Fire hath consumed it.

13 And now--it is planted in a wilderness, In a land dry and thirsty.

14 And go forth doth fire from a rod of its boughs, Its fruit it hath devoured, And it hath no rod of strength--a sceptre to rule, Lamentation it [is] --and it is for a lamentation!'

Ezekiel 20

1 And it cometh to pass, in the seventh year, in the fifth [month], in the tenth of the month, come in have certain of the elders of Israel to seek Jehovah, and they sit before me;

2 and there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

3 `Son of man, speak with the elders of Israel, and thou hast said unto them, Thus said the Lord Jehovah: To seek Me are ye coming in? I live--I am not sought by you--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

4 Dost thou judge them? Dost thou judge, son of man? The abominations of their fathers cause them to know,

5 and thou hast said unto them: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: In the day of My fixing on Israel, I lift up My hand, To the seed of the house of Jacob, And am known to them in the land of Egypt, And I lift up My hand to them, Saying, I [am] Jehovah your God.

6 In that day I did lift up My hand to them, To bring them forth from the land of Egypt, Unto a land that I spied out for them, Flowing with milk and honey, A beauty it [is] to all the lands,

7 And I say unto them, Let each cast away the detestable things of his eyes, And with the idols of Egypt be not defiled, I [am] Jehovah your God.

8 And--they rebel against Me, And have not been willing to hearken to Me, Each, the detestable things of their eyes, They have not cast away, And the idols of Egypt have not forsaken, And I say--to pour out My fury on them, To complete Mine anger against them, In the midst of the land of Egypt.

9 And I do [it] for My name's sake, Not to pollute [it] before the eyes of the nations, In whose midst they [are], Before whose eyes I became known to them, To bring them out from the land of Egypt.

10 And I bring them out of the land of Egypt, And I bring them in unto the wilderness,

11 And I give to them My statutes, And my judgments I caused them to know, Which the man who doth--liveth by them.

12 And also My sabbaths I have given to them, To be for a sign between Me and them, To know that I [am] Jehovah their sanctifier.

13 And--rebel against me do the house of Israel in the wilderness, In My statutes they have not walked, And My judgments they have despised, Which the man who doth--liveth by them. And My sabbaths they have greatly polluted, And I say to pour out My fury on them in the wilderness, to consume them.

14 And I do [it] for My name's sake, Not to pollute [it] before the eyes of the nations, Before whose eyes I brought them forth.

15 And also, I, I have lifted up My hand to them in the wilderness, Not to bring them in to the land that I had given, Flowing with milk and honey, A beauty it [is] to all the lands,

16 Because against My judgments they did kick, And in My statutes they have not walked, And My sabbaths they have polluted, For after their idols their heart is going.

17 And Mine eye hath pity on them--against destroying them, And I have not made of them an end in the wilderness.

18 And I say to their sons in the wilderness: In the statutes of your fathers ye walk not, And their judgments ye do not observe, And with their idols ye are not defiled.

19 I [am] Jehovah your God, in My statutes walk, And My judgments observe, and do them,

20 And My sabbaths sanctify, And they have been for a sign between Me and you, To know that I, Jehovah, [am] your God.

21 And--the sons rebel against Me, In My statutes they have not walked, And My judgments they have not observed--to do them, Which the man who doth--liveth by them. My sabbaths they have polluted, And I say to pour out My fury upon them, To complete Mine anger against them in the wilderness.

22 And I have turned back My hand, And I do [it] for My name's sake, Not to pollute [it] before the eyes of the nations, Before whose eyes I brought them out.

23 I also, I have lifted up My hand to them in the wilderness, To scatter them among nations, And to spread them through lands.

24 Because My judgments they have not done, And My statutes they have despised, And My sabbaths they have polluted, And after idols of their fathers have their eyes been.

25 And I also, I have given to them statutes not good, And judgments by which they do not live.

26 And I defile them by their own gifts, By causing to pass away every opener of a womb, So that I make them desolate, So that they know that I [am] Jehovah.

27 Therefore, speak unto the house of Israel, son of man, and thou hast said unto them, Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Still in this have your fathers reviled Me, In their committing against Me a trespass.

28 And I bring them in unto the land, That I did lift up My hand to give to them, And they see every high hill, and every thick tree, And they sacrifice there their sacrifices, And give there the provocation of their offering, And make there their sweet fragrance, And they pour out there their libations.

29 And I say unto them: What [is] the high place whither ye are going in? And its name is called `high place' to this day.

30 Therefore, say unto the house of Israel: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: In the way of your fathers are ye defiled? And after their detestable things go a-whoring?

31 And in the offering of your gifts, In causing your sons to pass through fire, Ye are defiled by all your idols to this day, And I am sought by you, O house of Israel! I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, I am not sought by you.

32 And that which is going up on your mind, It is not at all--in that ye are saying: We will be as the nations, as the families of the lands, To serve wood and stone.

33 I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Do not I, with a strong hand, And with a stretched-out arm, And with fury poured out--rule over you?

34 And I have brought you forth from the peoples, And assembled you from the lands In which ye have been scattered, With a strong hand and with a stretched-out arm, And with fury poured out.

35 And I have brought you in unto the wilderness of the peoples, And have been judged with you there face to face.

36 As I was judged with your fathers, In the wilderness of the land of Egypt, So I am judged with you, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

37 And I have caused you to pass under the rod, And brought you into the bond of the covenant,

38 And cleared out from you the rebels, And them transgressing against Me, From the land of their sojournings I bring them out, And unto the land of Israel they come not, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

39 And ye, O house of Israel, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Each his idols--go--serve ye, And, afterwards, if ye are not hearkening to me, And My holy name ye do not pollute any more by your gifts, and by your idols.

40 For, in My holy mountain, In the mountain of the height of Israel, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, There serve Me do all the house of Israel, All of it, in the land--there I accept them, And there I do seek your heave-offerings, And with the first-fruit of your gifts, With all your holy things.

41 With sweet fragrance I do accept you, In My bringing you out from the peoples, And I have assembled you from the lands In which ye have been scattered, And I have been sanctified in you Before the eyes of the nations.

42 And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My bringing you to the ground of Israel, Unto the land that I did lift up My hand To give it to your fathers,

43 And ye have remembered there your ways, And all your doings, In which ye have been defiled, And ye have been loathsome in your own faces, For all your evils that ye have done.

44 And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My dealing with you for My name's sake, Not according to your evil ways, And according to your corrupt doings, O house of Israel, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

45 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

46 Son of man, set thy face the way of Teman, and prophesy unto the south, and prophesy unto the forest of the field--the south;

47 and thou hast said to the forest of the south: Hear a word of Jehovah: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am kindling in thee a fire, And it hath devoured in thee every moist tree, and every dry tree, Not quenched is the glowing flames, And burnt by it have been all faces from south to north.

48 And seen have all flesh, that I, Jehovah, have kindled it--it is not quenched.'

49 And I say, `Ah, Lord Jehovah, They are saying of me, Is he not using similes?

Ezekiel 21

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, set thy face unto Jerusalem, and prophesy unto the holy places, and prophesy unto the ground of Israel;

3 and thou hast said unto the ground of Israel: Thus said Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, And have brought out My sword from its scabbard, And have cut off from thee righteous and wicked.

4 Because that I have cut off from thee righteous and wicked, Therefore go out doth My sword from its scabbard, Unto all flesh, from south to north.

5 And known have all flesh that I, Jehovah, Have brought out My sword from its scabbard, It doth not turn back any more.

6 And thou, son of man, sigh with breaking of loins, yea, with bitterness thou dost sigh before their eyes,

7 and it hath come to pass, when they say unto thee, For what art thou sighing? that thou hast said: Because of the report, for it is coming, And melted hath every heart, And feeble hath been all hands, And weak is every spirit, And all knees go--waters, Lo, it is coming, yea, it hath been, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

8 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

9 `Son of man, prophesy, and thou hast said, Thus said Jehovah, say: A sword, a sword is sharpened, and also polished.

10 So as to slaughter a slaughter it is sharpened. So as to have brightness it is polished, Desire hath rejoiced the sceptre of my son, It is despising every tree.

11 And he giveth it for polishing, For laying hold of by the hand. It is sharpened--the sword--and polished, To give it into the hand of a slayer.

12 Cry and howl, son of man, For it hath been among My people, It [is] among all the princes of Israel, Cast unto the sword have been My people. Therefore strike on thy thigh,

13 Because [it is] a trier, And what if even the sceptre it is despising? It shall not be, an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

14 And thou, son of man, prophesy, And smite hand on hand, And bent is the sword a third time, The sword of the wounded! It [is] the sword of the wounded--the great one, That is entering the inner chamber to them.

15 To melt the heart, and to multiply the ruins, By all their gates I have set the point of a sword. Ah, it is made for brightness, Wrapped up for slaughter.

16 Take possession of the right, place thyself at the left, Whither thy face is appointed.

17 And I also, I smite My hand on my hand, And have caused My fury to rest; I, Jehovah, have spoken.'

18 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

19 `And thou, son of man, appoint for thee two ways, for the coming in of the sword of the king of Babylon; from one land they come forth, both of them, and a station prepare thou, at the top of the way of the city prepare [it].

20 A way appoint for the coming of the sword, Unto Rabbath of the sons of Ammon, And to Judah, in Jerusalem--the fenced.

21 For stood hath the king of Babylon at the head of the way, At the top of the two ways, to use divination, He hath moved lightly with the arrows, He hath asked at the teraphim, He hath looked on the liver.

22 At his right hath been the divination--Jerusalem, To place battering-rams, To open the mouth with slaughter, To lift up a voice with shouting, To place battering-rams against the gates, To pour out a mount, to build a fortification.

23 And it hath been to them as a false divination in their eyes, Who have sworn oaths to them, And he is causing iniquity to be remembered to be caught.

24 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of your causing your iniquity to be remembered, In your transgressions being revealed, For your sins being seen, in all your doings, Because of your being remembered, By the hand ye are caught.

25 And thou, wounded, wicked one, Prince of Israel, whose day hath come, In the time of the iniquity of the end!

26 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Turn aside the mitre, and bear away the crown, This-- not this--the low make high, And the high make low.

27 An overturn, overturn, overturn, I make it, Also this hath not been till the coming of Him, Whose [is] the judgment, and I have given it.

28 And thou, son of man, prophesy, and thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah concerning the sons of Ammon, and concerning their reproach: and thou hast said: A sword, a sword, open for slaughter, Polished to the utmost for brightness!

29 In the seeing for thee of a vain thing, In the divining for thee of a lie, To put thee on the necks of the wounded of the wicked, whose day hath come, In the time of the iniquity of the end.

30 Turn [it] back unto its scabbard, In the place where thou wast produced, In the land of thy birth I do judge thee.

31 And I have poured on thee Mine indignation, With fire of My wrath I blow against thee, And have given thee into the hand of brutish men--artificers of destruction.

32 To the fire thou art for fuel, Thy blood is in the midst of the land, Thou art not remembered, For I, Jehovah, have spoken!'

Ezekiel 22

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

2 `And thou, son of man, dost thou judge? dost thou judge the city of blood? then thou hast caused it to know all its abominations,

3 and thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: The city is shedding blood in its midst, For the coming in of its time, And it hath made idols on it for defilement.

4 By thy blood that thou hast shed thou hast been guilty, And by thine idols that thou hast made thou hast been defiled, And thou causest thy days to draw near, And art come in unto thine years, Therefore I have given thee a reproach to nations, And a derision to all the lands.

5 The near and the far-off from thee scoff at thee, O defiled of name--abounding in trouble.

6 Lo, princes of Israel--each according to his arm Have been in thee to shed blood.

7 Father and mother made light of in thee, To a sojourner they dealt oppressively in thy midst, Fatherless and widow they oppressed in thee.

8 My holy things thou hast despised, And My sabbaths thou hast polluted.

9 Men of slander have been in thee to shed blood, And on the mountains they have eaten in thee, Wickedness they have done in thy midst.

10 The nakedness of a father hath one uncovered in thee, The defiled of impurity they humbled in thee.

11 And each with the wife of his neighbour hath done abomination, And each his daughter-in-law hath defiled through wickedness, And each his sister, his father's daughter, hath humbled in thee.

12 A bribe they have taken in thee to shed blood, Usury and increase thou hast taken, And cuttest off thy neighbour by oppression, And Me thou hast forgotten, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah!

13 And lo, I have smitten My hand, Because of thy dishonest gain that thou hast gained, And for thy blood that hath been in thy midst.

14 Doth thy heart stand--are thy hands strong, For the days that I am dealing with thee? I, Jehovah, have spoken and have done [it].

15 And I have scattered thee among nations, And have spread thee out among lands, And consumed thy uncleanness out of thee.

16 And thou hast been polluted in thyself Before the eyes of nations, And thou hast known that I [am] Jehovah.'

17 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying, `Son of man,

18 The house of Israel hath been to Me for dross, All of them [are] brass, and tin, and iron, and lead, In the midst of a furnace--dross hath silver been,

19 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of your all becoming dross, Therefore, lo, I am gathering you unto the midst of Jerusalem,

20 A gathering of silver, and brass, and iron, and lead, and tin, Unto the midst of a furnace--to blow on it fire, to melt it, So do I gather in Mine anger and in My fury, And I have let rest, and have melted you.

21 And I have heaped you up, And blown on you in the fire of My wrath, And ye have been melted in its midst.

22 As the melting of silver in the midst of a furnace, So are ye melted in its midst, And ye have known that I, Jehovah, I have poured out My fury upon you.'

23 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

24 `Son of man, say to it, Thou [art] a land, It [is] not cleansed nor rained on in a day of indignation.

25 A conspiracy of its prophets [is] in its midst, as a roaring lion tearing prey; The soul they have devoured, Wealth and glory they have taken, Its widows have multiplied in its midst.

26 Its priests have wronged My law, And they pollute My holy things, Between holy and common they have not made separation, And between the unclean and the clean they have not made known, And from my sabbaths they have hidden their eyes, And Iam pierced in their midst.

27 Its princes in its midst [are] as wolves, Tearing prey, to shed blood, to destroy souls, For the sake of gaining dishonest gain.

28 And its prophets have daubed for them with chalk, Seeing a vain thing, and divining for them a lie, Saying, `Thus said the Lord Jehovah:' And Jehovah hath not spoken.

29 The people of the land have used oppression, And have taken plunder violently away, And humble and needy have oppressed, And the sojourner oppressed--without judgment.

30 And I seek of them a man making a fence, And standing in the breach before Me, In behalf of the land--not to destroy it, And I have not found.

31 And I pour out on them mine indignation, By fire of My wrath I have consumed them, Their way on their own head I have put, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 23

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying, `Son of man,

2 Two women were daughters of one mother,

3 And they go a-whoring in Egypt, In their youth they have gone a-whoring, There they have bruised their breasts, And there they have dealt with the loves of their virginity.

4 And their names [are] Aholah the elder, And Aholibah her sister, And they are Mine, and bear sons and daughters. As to their names--Samaria [is] Aholah, And Jerusalem [is] Aholibah.

5 And go a-whoring doth Aholah under Me, And she doteth on her lovers, On the neighbouring Assyrians,

6 Clothed with blue--governors and prefects, Desirable young men all of them, Horsemen, riding on horses,

7 And she giveth her whoredoms on them, The choice of the sons of Asshur, All of them--even all on whom she doted, By all their idols she hath been defiled.

8 And her whoredoms out of Egypt she hath not forsaken, For with her they lay in her youth, And they dealt with the loves of her virginity, And they pour out their whoredoms on her.

9 Therefore I have given her into the hand of her lovers, Into the hand of sons of Asshur on whom she doted.

10 They have uncovered her nakedness, Her sons and her daughters they have taken, And her by sword they have slain, And she is a name for women, And judgments they have done with her.

11 And see doth her sister Aholibah, And she maketh her doting love more corrupt than she, And her whoredoms than the whoredoms of her sister.

12 On sons of Asshur she hath doted, Governors and prefects, Neighbouring ones-- clothed in perfection, Horsemen, riding on horses, Desirable young men all of them.

13 And I see that she hath been defiled, One way [is] to them both.

14 And she doth add unto her whoredoms, And she seeth graved men on the wall, Pictures of Chaldeans, graved with red lead,

15 Girded with a girdle on their loins, Dyed attire spread out on their heads, The appearance of rulers--all of them, The likeness of sons of Babylon, Chaldea is the land of their birth.

16 And she doteth on them at the sight of her eyes, And sendeth messengers to them, to Chaldea.

17 And come in unto her do sons of Babylon, To the bed of loves, And they defile her with their whoredoms, And she is defiled with them, And her soul is alienated from them.

18 And she revealeth her whoredoms, And she revealeth her nakedness, And alienated is My soul from off her, As alienated was My soul from off her sister.

19 And she multiplieth her whoredoms, To remember the days of her youth, When she went a-whoring in the land of Egypt.

20 And she doteth on their paramours, Whose flesh [is] the flesh of asses, And the issue of horses--their issue.

21 Thou lookest after the wickedness of thy youth, In dealing out of Egypt thy loves, For the sake of the breasts of thy youth.

22 Therefore, O Aholibah, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am stirring up thy lovers against thee, From whom thy soul hath been alienated, And have brought them in against thee from round about.

23 Sons of Babylon, and of all Chaldea, Pekod, and Shoa, and Koa, All the sons of Asshur with them, Desirable young men, governors and prefects, All of them--rulers and proclaimed ones, Riding on horses, all of them.

24 And they have come in against thee, With arms, rider, and wheel, And with an assembly of peoples; Target, and shield, and helmet, They do set against thee round about, And I have set before them judgment, They have judged thee in their Judgments.

25 And I have set My jealousy against thee, And they have dealt with thee in fury, Thy nose and thine ears they turn aside, And thy posterity by sword falleth, They, thy sons and thy daughters do take away, And thy posterity is devoured by fire.

26 And they have stripped thee of thy garments, And have taken thy beauteous jewels.

27 And I have caused thy wickedness to cease from thee, And thy whoredoms out of the land of Egypt, And thou liftest not up thine eyes unto them, And Egypt thou dost not remember again.

28 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am giving thee into a hand that thou hast hated, Into a hand from which thou wast alienated.

29 And they have dealt with thee in hatred, And they have taken all thy labour, And they have left thee naked and bare, And revealed hath been the nakedness of thy whoredoms, And the wickedness of thy whoredoms.

30 To do these things to thee, In thy going a-whoring after nations, Because thou hast been defiled with their idols,

31 In the way of thy sister thou hast walked, And I have given her cup into thy hand.

32 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: The cup of thy sister thou dost drink, The deep and the wide one, (Thou art for laughter and for scorn,) Abundant to contain.

33 With drunkenness and sorrow thou art filled, A cup of astonishment and desolation, The cup of thy sister Samaria.

34 And thou hast drunk it, and hast drained [it], And its earthen ware thou dost gnaw, And thine own breasts thou pluckest off, For I have spoken, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah,

35 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because thou hast forgotten Me, And thou dost cast Me behind thy back, Even thou also bear thy wickedness and thy whoredoms.'

36 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Son of man, Dost thou judge Aholah and Aholibah? Declare then to them their abominations.

37 For they have committed adultery, And blood [is] in their hands, With their idols they committed adultery, And also their sons whom they bore to Me, They caused to pass over to them for food.

38 Again, this they have done to Me, They defiled My sanctuary in that day, And My sabbaths they have polluted.

39 And in their slaughtering their sons to their idols They also come in unto My sanctuary in that day to pollute it, And lo, thus they have done in the midst of My house,

40 And also that they send to men coming from afar, Unto whom a messenger is sent, And lo, they have come in for whom thou hast washed, Painted thine eyes, and put on adornment.

41 And thou hast sat on a couch of honour, And a table arrayed before it, And My perfume and My oil placed on it.

42 And the voice of a multitude at ease [is] with her, And unto men of the common people are brought in Sabeans from the wilderness, And they put bracelets on their hands, And a beauteous crown on their heads.

43 And I say of the worn-out one in adulteries, Now they commit her whoredoms--she also!

44 And they come in unto her, As the coming in unto a whorish woman, So they have come in unto Aholah, And unto Aholibah--the wicked women.

45 As to righteous men, they judge them with the judgment of adulteresses, And the judgment of women shedding blood, For they [are] adulteresses, And blood [is] in their hands.

46 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: Bring up against them an assembly, And give them to trembling and to spoiling.

47 And they have cast at them the stone of the assembly, And cut them with their swords, Their sons and their daughters they do slay, And their houses with fire they burn.

48 And I have caused wickedness to cease from the land, And instructed have been all the women, And they do not according to your wickedness.

49 And they have put your wickedness on you, And the sins of your idols ye bear, And ye have known that I [am] the Lord Jehovah!

Ezekiel 24

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, in the ninth year, in the tenth month, in the tenth of the month, saying,

2 `Son of man, write for thee the name of the day--this self-same day leaned hath the king of Babylon toward Jerusalem in this self-same day--

3 and use unto the rebellious house a simile, and thou hast said unto them: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: To set on the pot, to set [it] on, and also to pour into it water,

4 To gather its pieces unto it, every good piece, Thigh and shoulder, the choice of the bones to fill in.

5 The choice of the flock to take, And also to pile of the bones under it, Boil it thoroughly, yea, cook its bones in its midst.

6 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Woe [to] the city of blood, A pot whose scum [is] in it, And its scum hath not come out of it, By piece of it, by piece of it bring it out, Not fallen on it hath a lot.

7 For her blood in her midst hath been, On a clear place of a rock she hath set it, She hath not poured it on the earth, To cover it over with dust.

8 To cause fury to come up to take vengeance, I have put her blood on a clear place of a rock--not to be covered.

9 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Woe [to] the city of blood, yea, I--I make great the pile.

10 Make abundant the wood, Kindle the fire, consume the flesh, And make the compound, And let the bones be burnt.

11 And cause it to stand on its coals empty, So that its brass is hot and burning, Melted hath been in its midst its uncleanness, Consumed is its scum.

12 [With] sorrows she hath wearied herself, And the abundance of her scum goeth not out of her, In the fire [is] her scum.

13 In thine uncleanness [is] wickedness, Because I have cleansed thee, And thou hast not been cleansed, From thine uncleanness thou art not cleansed again, Till I have caused My fury to rest on thee.

14 I, Jehovah, hath spoken, It hath come, and I have done [it], I do not free, nor do I spare, nor do I repent, According to thy ways, and according to thine acts, they have judged thee, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

15 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

16 `Son of man, lo, I am taking from thee the desire of thine eyes by a stroke, and thou dost not mourn, nor weep, nor let thy tear come.

17 Cease to groan, [for] the dead thou dost make no mourning, thy bonnet bind on thee, and thy shoes thou dost put on thy feet, and thou dost not cover over the upper lip, and bread of men thou dost not eat.'

18 And I speak unto the people in the morning, and my wife dieth in the evening, and I do in the morning as I have been commanded.

19 And the people say unto me, `Dost thou not declare to us what these [are] to us, that thou art doing?'

20 And I say unto them, `A word of Jehovah hath been unto me, saying:

21 Say to the house of Israel: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am polluting My sanctuary, The excellency of your strength, The desire of your eyes, and the pitied of your soul, And your sons and your daughters whom ye have left, by sword they do fall.

22 And ye have done as I have done, On the upper lip ye are not covered, And bread of men ye do not eat.

23 And your bonnets [are] on your heads, And your shoes [are] on your feet, Ye do not mourn nor do ye weep, And ye have wasted away for your iniquities, And ye have howled one unto another.

24 And Ezekiel hath been to you for a type, According to all that he hath done ye do; In its coming in--ye have known that I [am] the Lord Jehovah.

25 And thou, son of man, Is it not in the day of My taking from them their strength, The joy of their beauty, the desire of their eyes, And the song of their soul, Their sons and their daughters?

26 In that day come doth the escaped one to thee. To cause the ears to hear.

27 In that day opened is thy mouth with the escaped, And thou speakest, and art not silent any more, And thou hast been to them for a type. And they have known that I [am] Jehovah.'

Ezekiel 25

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, set thy face unto the sons of Ammon, and prophesy against them;

3 and thou hast said to the sons of Ammon: Hear ye a word of the Lord Jehovah: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of thy saying, Aha, to My sanctuary, Because it hath been polluted, And unto the ground of Israel, Because it hath been desolate, And unto the house of Judah, Because they have gone into a removal:

4 Therefore, lo, I am giving thee to sons of the east for a possession, And they set their towers in thee, And have placed in thee their tabernacles. They eat thy fruit, and they drink thy milk,

5 And I have given Rabbah for a habitation of camels, And the sons of Ammon for the crouching of a flock, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

6 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of thy clapping the hand, And of thy stamping with the foot, And thou rejoicest with all thy despite in soul Against the ground of Israel,

7 Therefore, lo, I--I have stretched out My hand against thee, And have given thee for a portion to nations, And I have cut thee off from the peoples, And caused thee to perish from the lands; I destroy thee, and thou hast known that I [am] Jehovah.

8 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of the saying of Moab and Seir: Lo, as all the nations [is] the house of Judah;

9 Therefore, lo, I am opening the shoulder of Moab--From the cities--from his cities-- from his frontier, The beauty of the land, Beth-Jeshimoth, Baal-Meon, and Kiriathaim,

10 To the sons of the east, with the sons of Ammon, And I have given it for a possession, So that the sons of Ammon are not remembered among nations.

11 And in Moab I do judgments, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah.

12 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of the doings of Edom, In taking vengeance on the house of Judah, Yea, they are very guilty, And they have taken vengeance on them.

13 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: I have stretched out My hand against Edom, And I have cut off from it man and beast, And given it up--a waste, from Teman even to Dedan, By sword they do fall.

14 And I have given My vengeance on Edom, By the hand of My people Israel, And they have done in Edom, According to My anger, and according to My fury, And they have known My vengeance, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

15 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of the doings of the Philistines in vengeance, And they take vengeance with despite in soul, To destroy--the enmity age-during!

16 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am stretching out My hand against the Philistines, And I have cut off the Cherethim, And destroyed the remnant of the haven of the sea,

17 And done upon them great vengeance with furious reproofs, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My giving out My vengeance on them!

Ezekiel 26

1 And it cometh to pass, in the eleventh year, in the first of the month, there hath been a word of Jehovah unto me, saying: `Son of man,

2 Because that Tyre hath said of Jerusalem: Aha, she hath been broken, the doors of the peoples, She hath turned round unto me, I am filled--she hath been laid waste,

3 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, O Tyre, And have caused to come up against thee many nations, As the sea causeth its billows to come up.

4 And they have destroyed the walls of Tyre, And they have broken down her towers, And I have scraped her dust from her, And made her for a clear place of a rock.

5 A spreading place of nets she is in the midst of the sea, For I--I have spoken--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, And she hath been for a spoil to nations.

6 And her daughters who [are] in the field, by sword they are slain, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah,

7 For, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am bringing in unto Tyre Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, From the north--a king of kings, With horse, and with chariot, and with horsemen, Even an assembly, and a numerous people.

8 Thy daughters in the field by sword he slayeth, And he hath made against thee a fort, And hath poured out against thee a mount, And hath raised against thee a buckler.

9 And a battering-ram before him he placeth against thy walls, And thy towers he breaketh by his weapons.

10 From the abundance of his horses cover thee doth their dust, From the noise of horseman, and wheel, and rider, Shake do thy walls, in his coming in to thy gates, As the coming into a city broken-up.

11 With hoofs of his horses he treadeth all thine out-places, Thy people by sword he doth slay, And the pillars of thy strength to the earth come down.

12 And they have spoiled thy wealth, And they have plundered thy merchandise, And they have thrown down thy walls, And thy desirable houses they break down, And thy stones, and thy wood, and thy dust, In the midst of the waters they place.

13 And I have caused the noise of thy songs to cease, And the voice of thy harps is heard no more.

14 And I have given thee up for a clear place of a rock, A spreading-place of nets thou art, Thou art not built up any more, For I, Jehovah, I have spoken, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

15 Thus said the Lord Jehovah to Tyre: Do not--from the noise of thy fall, In the groaning of the wounded, In the slaying of the slaughter in thy midst, The isles shake?

16 And come down from off their thrones have all princes of the sea, And they have turned aside their robes, And their embroidered garments strip off, Trembling they put on, on the earth they sit, And they have trembled every moment, And they have been astonished at thee,

17 And have lifted up for thee a lamentation, And said to thee: How hast thou perished, That art inhabited from the seas, The praised city, that was strong in the sea, She and her inhabitants, Who put their terror on all her inhabitants!

18 Now they tremble, is it not the day of thy fall? Troubled have been the isles that [are] in the sea, at thine outgoing.

19 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: In my making thee a city wasted, Like cities that have not been inhabited, In bringing up against thee the deep, Then covered thee have the great waters.

20 And I have caused thee to go down, With those going down to the pit, Unto the people of old, And I have caused thee to dwell in the land, The lower parts--in wastes of old, With those going down to the pit, So that thou art not inhabited, And I have given beauty in the land of the living.

21 Wastes I do make thee, and thou art not, And thou art sought, and art not found any more--to the age, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 27

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 `And thou, son of man, lift up concerning Tyre a lamentation, and thou hast said to Tyre:

3 O dweller on the entrances of the sea, Merchant of the peoples unto many isles, Thus said the Lord Jehovah: O Tyre, thou--thou hast said: I [am] the perfection of beauty.

4 In the heart of the seas [are] thy borders, Thy builders have perfected thy beauty.

5 Of firs of Senir they have built to thee all thy double-boarded ships, Of cedars of Lebanon they have taken to make a mast for thee,

6 Of oaks of Bashan they made thine oars, Thy bench they have made of ivory, A branch of Ashurim from isles of Chittim.

7 Of fine linen with embroidery from Egypt hath been thy sail, To be to thee for an ensign, Of blue and purple from isles of Elishah hath been thy covering.

8 Inhabitants of Zidon and Arvad have been rowers to thee, Thy wise men, O Tyre, have been in thee, They [are] thy pilots.

9 Elders of Gebal and its wise men have been in thee, Strengthening thy breach; All ships of the sea and their mariners, Have been in thee, to trade [with] thy merchandise.

10 Persian and Lud and Phut Have been in thy forces--thy men of war. Shield and helmet they hung up in thee, They--they have given out thine honour.

11 The sons of Arvad, and thy force, [Are] on thy walls round about, And short swordsmen in thy towers have been, Their shields they have hung up on thy walls round about, They--they have perfected thy beauty.

12 Tarshish [is] thy merchant, Because of the abundance of all wealth, For silver, iron, tin, and lead, They have given out thy remnants.

13 Javan, Tubal, and Meshech--they [are] thy merchants, For persons of men, and vessels of brass, They have given out thy merchandise.

14 They of the house of Togarmah, [For] horses, and riding steeds, and mules, They have given out thy remnants.

15 Sons of Dedan [are] thy merchants, Many isles [are] the mart of thy hand, Horns of ivory and ebony they sent back thy reward.

16 Aram [is] thy merchant, Because of the abundance of thy works, For emerald, purple, and embroidery, And fine linen, and coral, and agate, They have given out thy remnants.

17 Judah and the land of Israel--they [are] thy merchants, For wheat of Minnith, and Pannag, And honey, and oil, and balm, They have given out thy merchandise.

18 Damascus [is] thy merchant, For the abundance of thy works, Because of the abundance of all wealth, For wine of Helbon, and white wool.

19 Vedan and Javan go about with thy remnants, They have given shining iron, cassia, and cane, In thy merchandise it hath been.

20 Dedan [is] thy merchant, For clothes of freedom for riding.

21 Arabia, and all princes of Kedar, They [are] the traders of thy hand, For lambs, and rams, and he-goats, In these thy merchants.

22 Merchants of Sheba and Raamah--they [are] thy merchants, For the chief of all spices, And for every precious stone, and gold, They have given out thy remnants.

23 Haran, and Canneh, and Eden, merchants of Sheba, Asshur--Chilmad--[are] thy merchants,

24 They [are] thy merchants for perfect things, For wrappings of blue, and embroidery, And for treasuries of rich apparel, With cords bound and girded, for thy merchandise,

25 Ships of Tarshish [are] thy double walls of thy merchandise, And thou art filled and honoured greatly, In the heart of the seas.

26 Into great waters have they brought thee, Those rowing thee, The east wind hath broken thee in the heart of the seas.

27 Thy wealth and thy remnants, Thy merchandise, thy mariners, And thy pilots, strengtheners of thy breach, And the traders of thy merchandise, And all thy men of war, who [are] in thee, And in all thine assembly that [is] in thy midst, Fall into the heart of the seas in the day of thy fall,

28 At the voice of the cry of thy pilots shake do the suburbs.

29 And come down from their ships have all handling an oar, Mariners, all the pilots of the sea, on the land they stand,

30 And have sounded for thee with their voice, And cry bitterly, and cause dust to go up on their heads, In ashes they do roll themselves.

31 And they have made for thee baldness, And they have girded on sackcloth, And they have wept for thee, In bitterness of soul--a bitter mourning.

32 And lifted up for thee have their sons a lamentation, And they have lamented over thee, who [is] as Tyre? As the cut-off one in the midst of the sea?

33 With the outgoing of thy remnants from the seas, Thou hast filled many peoples, With the abundance of thy riches, and thy merchandise, Thou hast made rich things of earth.

34 The time of [thy] being broken by the seas in the depths of the waters, Thy merchandise and all thy assembly in thy midst have fallen.

35 All inhabitants of the isles have been astonished at thee, And their kings have been sore afraid, They have been troubled in countenance.

36 Merchants among the peoples have shrieked for thee, Wastes thou hast been, and thou art not--to the age!'

Ezekiel 28

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 `Son of man, say to the leader of Tyre: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because thy heart hath been high, And thou dost say: A god I [am], The habitation of God I have inhabited, In the heart of the seas, And thou [art] man, and not God, And thou givest out thy heart as the heart of God,

3 Lo, thou [art] wiser than Daniel, No hidden thing have they concealed from thee.

4 By thy wisdom and by thine understanding Thou hast made for thee wealth, And makest gold and silver in thy treasuries.

5 By the abundance of thy wisdom, Through thy merchandise, Thou hast multiplied thy wealth, And high is thy heart through thy wealth.

6 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because of thy giving out thy heart as the heart of God,

7 Therefore, lo, I am bringing in against thee strangers, The terrible of the nations, And they have drawn out their swords Against the beauty of thy wisdom, And they have pierced thy brightness.

8 To destruction they bring thee down, Thou diest by the deaths of the wounded, in the heart of the seas.

9 Dost thou really say, `I [am] God,' Before him who is slaying thee? And thou [art] man, and not God, In the hand of him who is piercing thee.

10 The deaths of the uncircumcised thou diest, By the hand of strangers, for I have spoken, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

11 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

12 `Son of man, lift up a lamentation for the king of Tyre, And thou hast said to him: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Thou art sealing up a measurement, Full of wisdom, and perfect in beauty.

13 In Eden, the garden of God, thou hast been, Every precious stone thy covering, Ruby, topaz, and diamond, beryl, onyx, and jasper, Sapphire, emerald, and carbuncle, and gold, The workmanship of thy tabrets, and of thy pipes, In thee in the day of thy being produced, have been prepared.

14 Thou [art] an anointed cherub who is covering, And I have set thee in the holy mount, God thou hast been, In the midst of stones of fire thou hast walked up and down.

15 Perfect [art] thou in thy ways, From the day of thy being produced, Till perversity hath been found in thee.

16 By the abundance of thy merchandise They have filled thy midst with violence, And thou dost sin, And I thrust thee from the mount of God, And I destroy thee, O covering cherub, From the midst of the stones of fire.

17 High hath been thy heart, because of thy beauty, Thou hast corrupted thy wisdom because of thy brightness, On the earth I have cast thee, Before kings I have set thee, to look on thee,

18 From the abundance of thy iniquity, By the perversity of thy traffic, Thou hast polluted thy sanctuaries, And I bring forth fire from thy midst, It hath devoured thee, And I make thee become ashes on the earth, Before the eyes of all beholding thee.

19 All knowing thee among the peoples Have been astonished at thee, Wastes thou hast been, and thou art not--to the age.'

20 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

21 `Son of man, set thy face unto Zidon, and prophesy concerning it;

22 and thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, O Zidon, And I have been honoured in thy midst, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My doing in her judgments, And I have been sanctified in her.

23 And I have sent into her pestilence, And blood into her out-places, The wounded hath been judged in her midst, By the sword upon her round about, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah.

24 And there is no more to the house of Israel A pricking brier, and paining thorn, Of all round about them--despising them, And they have known that I [am] the Lord Jehovah.

25 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: In My gathering the house of Israel, Out of the peoples among whom they were scattered, I have been sanctified in them, Before the eyes of the nations, And they have dwelt on their ground, That I gave to My servant, to Jacob,

26 And they have dwelt on it confidently, And builded houses, and planted vineyards, And dwelt confidently--in My doing judgments, On all those despising them round about, And they have known that I, Jehovah, [am] their God!'

Ezekiel 29

1 In the tenth year, in the tenth [month], in the twelfth of the month, hath a word of Jehovah been unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, set thy face against Pharaoh king of Egypt, and prophesy concerning him, and concerning Egypt--all of it.

3 Speak, and thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, Pharaoh king of Egypt! The great dragon that is crouching in the midst of his floods, Who hath said, My flood [is] my own, And I--I have made it [for] myself.

4 And I have put hooks in thy jaws, And I have caused the fish of thy floods to cleave to thy scales, And I have caused thee to come up from the midst of thy floods, And every fish of thy floods to thy scales doth cleave.

5 And I have left thee in the wilderness, Thou and every fish of thy floods, On the face of the field thou dost fall, Thou art not gathered nor assembled, To the beast of the earth and to the fowl of the heavens I have given thee for food.

6 And known have all inhabitants of Egypt That I [am] Jehovah, Because of their being a staff of reed to the house of Israel.

7 In their taking hold of thee by thy hand, --thou art crushed, And hast rent to them all the shoulder, And in their leaning on thee thou art broken, And hast caused all their thighs to stand.

8 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am bringing in against thee a sword, And have cut off from thee man and beast.

9 And the land of Egypt hath been for a desolation and a waste, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah. Because he said: The flood [is] mine, and I made [it].

10 Therefore, lo, I [am] against thee, and against thy floods, And have given the land of Egypt for wastes, A waste, a desolation, from Migdol to Syene, And unto the border of Cush.

11 Not pass over into it doth a foot of man, Yea, the foot of beast doth not pass into it, Nor is it inhabited forty years.

12 And I have made the land of Egypt a desolation, In the midst of desolate lands, And its cities, in the midst of waste cities, Are a desolation forty years, And I have scattered the Egyptians among nations, And I have dispersed them through lands.

13 But thus said the Lord Jehovah: At the end of forty years I gather the Egyptians Out of the peoples whither they have been scattered,

14 And I have turned back [to] the captivity of Egypt, And I have brought them back [To] the land of Pathros, to the land of their birth, And they have been there a low kingdom.

15 Of the kingdoms it is lowest, And it lifteth not up itself any more above the nations, And I have made them few, So as not to rule among nations.

16 And it is no more to the house of Israel for a confidence, Bringing iniquity to remembrance, By their turning after them, And they have known that I [am] the Lord Jehovah.'

17 And it cometh to pass, in the twenty and seventh year, in the first [month], in the first of the month, hath a word of Jehovah been unto me, saying:

18 `Son of man, Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon, Hath caused his force to serve a great service against Tyre, Every head [is] bald--every shoulder peeled, And reward he had none, nor his force, out of Tyre, For the service that he served against it.

19 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah, Lo, I am giving to Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon the land of Egypt, And he hath taken away its store, And hath taken its spoil, and taken its prey, And it hath been a reward to his force.

20 His wage for which he laboured I have given to him, The land of Egypt--in that they wrought for Me, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

21 In that day I cause to shoot up a horn to the house of Israel, And to thee I give an opening of the mouth in their midst, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 30

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 `Son of man, prophesy, and thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Howl ye, ha! for the day!

3 For near [is] a day, near [is] a day to Jehovah! A day of clouds, the time of nations it is.

4 And come in hath a sword to Egypt, And there hath been great pain in Cush, In the falling of the wounded in Egypt, And they have taken its store, And broken down have been its foundations.

5 Cush, and Phut, and Lud, and all the mixture, and Chub, And the sons of the land of the covenant with them by sword do fall,

6 Thus said Jehovah: And--fallen have supporters of Egypt, And come down hath the arrogance of her strength, From Migdol to Syene, by sword they fall in her, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

7 And they have been desolated in the midst of desolate lands, And its cities are in the midst of wasted cities.

8 And they have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My giving fire against Egypt, And broken have been all her helpers.

9 In that day go forth do messengers from before Me in ships, To trouble confident Cush, And there hath been great pain among them, As the day of Egypt, for lo, it hath come.

10 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: I have caused the multitude of Egypt to cease, By the hand of Nebuchadrezzar king of Babylon,

11 He and his people with him--the terrible of nations, Are brought in to destroy the land, And they have drawn their swords against Egypt, And have filled the land [with] the wounded.

12 And I have made floods a dry place, And I have sold the land into the hand of evil doers, And I have made desolate the land, And its fulness, by the hand of strangers, I, Jehovah, have spoken.

13 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: And--I have destroyed idols, And caused vain things to cease from Noph, And a prince of the land of Egypt there is no more, And I give fear in the land of Egypt.

14 And I have made Pathros desolate, And I have given fire against Zoan, And I have done judgments in No,

15 And I have poured out My fury on Sin, the stronghold of Egypt, And I have cut off the multitude of No.

16 And I have given fire against Egypt, Greatly pained is Sin, and No is to be rent, And Noph hath daily distresses.

17 The youths of Aven and Pi-Beseth by sword do fall, And these into captivity do go.

18 And in Tehaphnehes hath the day been dark, In My breaking there the yokes of Egypt, And ceased in her hath the excellency of her strength, She--a cloud doth cover her, And her daughters into captivity do go.

19 And I have done judgments in Egypt, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah.'

20 And it cometh to pass, in the eleventh year, in the first [month], in the seventh of the month, hath a word of Jehovah been unto me, saying: `Son of man,

21 The arm of Pharaoh, king of Egypt, I have broken, And lo, it hath not been bound up to give healing, To put a bandage to bind it, To strengthen it--to lay hold on the sword.

22 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against Pharaoh, king of Egypt, And I have broken his arms, The strong one and the broken one, And have caused the sword to fall out of his hand,

23 And scattered the Egyptians among nations, And I have spread them through lands,

24 And strengthened the arms of the king of Babylon, And I have given My sword into his hand, And I have broken the arms of Pharaoh, And he hath groaned the groans of a pierced one- -before him.

25 And I have strengthened the arms of the king of Babylon, And the arms of Pharaoh do fall down, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My giving My sword into the hand of the king of Babylon, And he hath stretched it out toward the landof Egypt.

26 And I have scattered the Egyptians among nations, And I have spread them through lands, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 32

1 And it cometh to pass, in the twelfth year, in the twelfth month, in the first of the month, hath a word of Jehovah been unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, lift up a lamentation for Pharaoh king of Egypt, and thou hast said unto him: A young lion of nations thou hast been like, And thou [art] as a dragon in the seas, And thou comest forth with thy flowings, And dost trouble the waters with thy feet, And thou dost foul their flowings.

3 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: And--I have spread out for thee My net, With an assembly of many peoples, And they have brought thee up in My net.

4 And I have left thee in the land, On the face of the field I do cast thee out, And have caused to dwell upon thee every fowl of the heavens, And have satisfied out of thee the beasts of the whole earth.

5 And I have put thy flesh on the mountains, And filled the valleys [with] thy hugeness,

6 And watered the land with thy flowing, From thy blood--unto the mountains, And streams are filled from thee.

7 And in quenching thee I have covered the heavens, And have made black their stars, The sun with a cloud I do cover, And the moon causeth not its light to shine.

8 All luminaries of light in the heavens, I make black over thee, And I have given darkness over thy land, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah,

9 And I have vexed the heart of many peoples, In My bringing in thy destruction among nations, Unto lands that thou hast not known.

10 And I have made many peoples astonished at thee, And their kings are afraid at thee with trembling, In My brandishing My sword before their faces, And they have trembled every moment, Each for his life--in the day of thy fall.

11 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: A sword of the king of Babylon entereth thee,

12 By swords of the mighty I cause thy multitude to fall, The terrible of nations--all of them, And they have spoiled the excellency of Egypt, And destroyed hath been all her multitude.

13 And I have destroyed all her beasts, From beside many waters, And trouble them not doth a foot of man any more, Yea, the hoofs of beasts trouble them not.

14 Then do I cause their waters to sink, And their rivers as oil I cause to go, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

15 In My making the land of Egypt a desolation, And desolated hath been the land of its fulness, In My smiting all the inhabitants in it, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah.

16 A lamentation it [is], and they have lamented her, Daughters of the nations do lament her, For Egypt, and for all her multitude, they lament her, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

17 And it cometh to pass, in the twelfth year, in the fifteenth of the month, hath a word of Jehovah been unto me, saying,

18 `Son of man, Wail for the multitude of Egypt, And cause it to go down, It--and the daughters of honourable nations, Unto the earth--the lower parts, With those going down to the pit.

19 Than whom hast thou been more pleasant? Go down, and be laid with the uncircumcised.

20 In the midst of the pierced of the sword they fall, [To] the sword she hath been given, They drew her out, and all her multitude.

21 Speak to him do the gods of the mighty out of the midst of sheol, With his helpers-- they have gone down, They have lain with the uncircumcised, The pierced of the sword.

22 There [is] Asshur, and all her assembly, Round about him [are] his graves, All of them [are] wounded, who are falling by sword,

23 Whose graves are appointed in the sides of the pit, And her assembly is round about her grave, All of them wounded, falling by sword, Because they gave terror in the land of the living.

24 There [is] Elam, and all her multitude, Round about [is] her grave, All of them wounded, who are falling by sword, Who have gone down uncircumcised unto the earth--the lower parts, Because they gave their terror in the land of the living, And they bear their shame with those going down to the pit.

25 In the midst of the wounded they have appointed a bed for her with all her multitude, Round about him [are] her graves, All of them uncircumcised, pierced of the sword, For their terror was given in the land of the living, And they bear their shame with those going down to the pit, In the midst of the pierced he hath been put.

26 There [is] Meshech, Tubal, and all her multitude, Round about him [are] her graves, All of them uncircumcised, pierced of the sword, For they gave their terror in the land of the living,

27 And they lie not with the mighty, Who are falling of the uncircumcised, Who have gone down to sheol with their weapons of war, And they put their swords under their heads, And their iniquities are on their bones, For the terror of the mighty [is] in the land of the living.

28 And thou, in the midst of the uncircumcised art broken, And dost lie with the pierced of the sword.

29 There [is] Edom, her kings, and all her princes, Who have been given up in their might, With the pierced of the sword, They with the uncircumcised do lie, And with those going down to the pit.

30 There [are] princes of the north, All of them, and every Zidonian, Who have gone down with the pierced in their terror, Of their might they are ashamed, And they lie uncircumcised with the pierced of the sword, And they bear their shame with those going down to the pit.

31 Then doth Pharaoh see, And he hath been comforted for all his multitude, The pierced of the sword--Pharaoh and all his force, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

32 For I have given his terror in the land of the living, And he hath been laid down in the midst of the uncircumcised, With the pierced of the sword--Pharaoh, and all his multitude, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 33

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, speak unto the sons of thy people, and thou hast said unto them: A land- -when I bring in against it a sword, And the people of the land have taken one man out of their borders, And made him to them for a watchman.

3 And he hath seen the sword coming against the land, And hath blown with a trumpet, and hath warned the people,

4 And the hearer hath heard the voice of the trumpet, and he hath not taken warning, And come in doth the sword, and taketh him away, His blood is on his head.

5 The voice of the trumpet he heard, And he hath not taken warning, his blood is on him, And he who took warning his soul hath delivered.

6 And the watchman, when he seeth the sword coming in, And he hath not blown with a trumpet, And the people hath not been warned, And come in doth a sword, And taketh away of them--a soul, He in his iniquity is taken away, And his blood from the hand of the watchman I require.

7 And thou, son of man, A watchman I gave thee to the house of Israel, And thou hast heard from My mouth a word, And thou hast warned them from Me.

8 In My saying to the wicked, O wicked one--thou dost surely die, And thou hast not spoken to warn the wicked from his way, He--the wicked--in his iniquity doth die, And his blood from thy hand I require.

9 And thou, when thou hast warned the wicked of his way, to turn back from it, And he hath not turned back from his way, He in his iniquity doth die, And thou thy soul hast delivered.

10 And thou, son of man, say unto the house of Israel: Rightly ye have spoken, saying: Surely our transgressions and our sins [are] on us, And in them we are wasting away, How, then, do we live?

11 Say unto them, I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, I delight not in the death of the wicked, But--in the turning of the wicked from his way, And he hath lived, Turn back, turn back, from your evil ways, Yea, why do ye die, O house of Israel?

12 And thou, son of man, say unto the sons of thy people: The righteousness of the righteous doth not deliver him in the day of his transgression, And the wickedness of the wicked, He doth not stumble for it in the day of his turning from his wickedness, And the righteous is not able to live in it in the day of his sinning.

13 In My saying of the righteous: He surely liveth, And--he hath trusted on his righteousness, And he hath done perversity, All his righteous acts are not remembered, And for his perversity that he hath done, For it he doth die.

14 And in My saying to the wicked: Thou surely diest, And--he hath turned back from his sin, And hath done judgment and righteousness,

15 (The pledge the wicked restoreth, plunder he repayeth,) In the statutes of life he hath walked, So as not to do perversity, He surely liveth--he doth not die.

16 None of his sin that he hath sinned is remembered to him, Judgment and righteousness he hath done, He doth surely live.

17 And the sons of thy people have said: The way of the Lord is not pondered, As to them--their way is not pondered.

18 In the turning back of the righteous from his righteousness, And he hath done perversity--he dieth for it.

19 And in the turning back of the wicked from his wickedness, And he hath done judgment and righteousness, by them he liveth.

20 And ye have said: The way of the Lord is not pondered, Each according to his ways do I judge you, O house of Israel.'

21 And it cometh to pass, in the twelfth year--in the tenth [month], in the fifth of the month--of our removal, come in unto me doth one who is escaped from Jerusalem, saying, `The city hath been smitten.'

22 And the hand of Jehovah hath been unto me in the evening, before the coming in of the escaped one, and He openeth my mouth till the coming in unto me in the morning, and opened is my mouth, and I have not been silent again.

23 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

24 `Son of man, the inhabitants of these wastes on the ground of Israel are speaking, saying: Alone hath been Abraham--and he possesseth the land, and we [are] many--to us hath the land been given for a possession.

25 Therefore say unto them: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: With the blood ye do eat, And your eyes ye lift up unto your idols, And blood ye shed, and the land ye inherit!

26 Ye have stood on your sword, Ye have done abomination, Each the wife of his neighbour ye have defiled, And the land ye possess!

27 Thus dost thou say unto them: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: I live--do not they who [are] in the wastes by the sword fall? And they who [are] on the face of the field, To the beast I have given for food, And they who are in strongholds and incaves by pestilence die.

28 And I have made the land a desolation and an astonishment, And ceased hath the excellency of its strength, And desolated have been mountains of Israel, Without any one passing through.

29 And they have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My making the land a desolation and an astonishment, For all their abominations that they have done.

30 And thou, son of man, the sons of thy people who are speaking about thee, By the walls, and in openings of the houses, Have spoken one with another, each with his brother, Saying: Come in, I pray you, And hear what [is] the word that cometh out from Jehovah.

31 And they come in unto thee as the coming in of a people, And they sit before thee-- My people, And have heard thy words, and they do them not, For doting loves with their mouth they are making, After their dishonest gain their heart is going.

32 And lo, thou [art] to them as a singer of doting loves, A pleasant voice, and playing well on an instrument, And they have heard thy words, and they are not doing them.

33 And in its coming in--lo, it hath come, And they have known that a prophet hath been in their midst!'

Ezekiel 34

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

2 `Son of man, prophesy concerning shepherds of Israel, prophesy, and thou hast said unto them: To the shepherds, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Woe [to] the shepherds of Israel, Who have been feeding themselves! The flock do not the shepherds feed?

3 The fat ye do eat, and the wool ye put on, The fed one ye slaughter, the flock ye feed not.

4 The weak ye have not strengthened, And the sick one ye have not healed, And the broken ye have not bound up, And the driven away have not brought back, And the lost ye have not sought, And with might ye have ruled them and with rigour.

5 And they are scattered from want of a shepherd, And are for food to every beast of the field, Yea, they are scattered.

6 Go astray do My flock on all the mountains, And on every high hill, And on all the face of the land have My flock been scattered, And there is none inquiring, and none seeking.

7 Therefore, shepherds, hear a word of Jehovah:

8 I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, If not, because of My flock being for a prey, Yea, My flock is for food to every beast of the field, Because there is no shepherd, And My shepherds have not sought My flock, And the shepherds do feed themselves, And My flock they have not fed.

9 Therefore, O shepherds, hear a word of Jehovah:

10 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against the shepherds, And have required My flock from their hand, And caused them to cease from feeding the flock, And no more do the shepherds feed themselves, And I have delivered My flock from their mouth, And they are not to them for food.

11 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I--even I, have required My flock, And I have sought it out.

12 As a shepherd's searching of his drove, In the day of his being in the midst of his scattered flock, so I do seek My flock, And have delivered them out of all places, Whither they have been scattered, In a day of cloud and thick darkness.

13 And brought them out from the peoples, And have gathered them from the lands, And brought them unto their own ground, And have fed them on mountains of Israel, By streams, and by all dwellings of the land.

14 With good pasture I do feed them, And on mountains of the high place of Israel is their habitation, There do they lie down in a good habitation, And fat pastures they enjoy on mountains of Israel.

15 I feed My flock, and cause them to lie down, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

16 The lost I seek, and the driven away bring back, And the broken I bind up, and the sick I strengthen, And the fat and the strong I destroy, I feed it with judgment.

17 And you, My flock, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am judging between sheep and sheep, Between rams and he-goats.

18 Is it a little thing for you--the good pasture ye enjoy, And the remnant of your pasture ye tread down with your feet, And a depth of waters ye do drink, And the remainder with your feet ye trample,

19 And My flock the trodden thing of your feet consumeth, And the trampled thing of your feet drinketh?

20 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah to them: Lo, I--even I, have judged between fat sheep and lean sheep.

21 Because with side and with shoulder ye thrust away, And with your horns push all the diseased, Till ye have scattered them to the out-place,

22 And I have given safety to My flock, And they are not any more for prey, And I have judged between sheep and sheep.

23 And have raised up over them one shepherd, And he hath fed them--my servant David, He doth feed them, and he is their shepherd,

24 And I, Jehovah, I am their God, And My servant David prince in their midst, I, Jehovah, have spoken.

25 And I have made for them a covenant of peace, And caused evil beasts to cease out of the land, And they have dwelt in a wilderness confidently, And they have slept in forests.

26 And I have given them, and the suburbs of my hill, a blessing, And caused the shower to come down in its season, Showers of blessing they are.

27 And given hath the tree of the field its fruit, And the land doth give her increase, And they have been on their land confident, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My breaking the bands of their yoke, And I have delivered them fromthe hand of those laying service on them.

28 And they are no more a prey to nations, And the beast of the earth devoureth them not, And they have dwelt confidently, And there is none troubling.

29 And I have raised for them a plant for renown, And they are no more consumed by hunger in the land, And they bear no more the shame of the nations.

30 And they have known that I, Jehovah, their God, [am] with them, And they--the house of Israel--My people, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

31 And ye, My flock, the flock of My pasture, Men ye [are] --I [am] your God, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 35

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 `Son of man, set thy face against mount Seir, and prophesy against it,

3 and thou hast said to it: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, O mount Seir, And have stretched out My hand against thee, And made thee a desolation and an astonishment.

4 Thy cities a waste I make, and thou art a desolation, And thou hast known that I [am] Jehovah.

5 Because of thy having an enmity age-during, And thou dost saw the sons of Israel, By the hands of the sword, In the time of their calamity, In the time of the iniquity of the end:

6 Therefore, I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Surely for blood I do appoint thee, And blood doth pursue thee, If blood thou hast not hated, Blood also doth pursue thee.

7 And I have given mount Seir for a desolation and an astonishment, And have cut off from it him who is passing over and him who is returning,

8 And filled his mountains with his wounded, Thy hills, and thy valleys, and all thy streams, The pierced of the sword fall into them.

9 Desolations age-during I make thee, And thy cities do not return, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

10 Because of thy saying: The two nations and the two lands are mine, and we have possessed it, And Jehovah hath been there;

11 Therefore, I live--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, And I have done according to thine anger, And according to thine envy, With which thou hast wrought, Because of thy hatred against them, And I have been known among them when I judge thee.

12 And thou hast known that I--Jehovah, I have heard all thy despisings that thou hast spoken Against mountains of Israel, saying: A desolation, to us they were given for food.

13 And ye magnify yourselves against Me with your mouth, And have made abundant against Me your words, I--I have heard.

14 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: According to the rejoicing of the whole land, A desolation I make of thee.

15 According to thy joy at the inheritance of the house of Israel because of desolation, So I do to thee--a desolation thou art, O mount Seir, and all Edom--all of it, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah!

Ezekiel 36

1 And thou, son of man, prophesy unto mountains of Israel, and thou hast said, O mountains of Israel, hear a word of Jehovah.

2 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because the enemy said against you, Aha, and the high places of old for a possession have been to us,

3 therefore, prophesy, and thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because, even because, of desolating, And of swallowing you up from round about, For your being a possession to the remnant of the nations, And ye are taken up on the tip of the tongue, And [are] an evil report of the people.

4 Therefore, O mountains of Israel, Hear a word of the Lord Jehovah: Thus said the Lord Jehovah, to mountains, and to hills, To streams, and to valleys, And to wastes that [are] desolate, And to cities that are forsaken, That have been for a prey, And for a scorn, to the remnant of the nations who [are] round about.

5 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Have I not, in the fire of My jealousy, Spoken against the remnant of the nations, And against Edom--all of it, Who gave My land to themselves for a possession, With the joy of the whole heart--with despite of soul, For the sake of casting it out for a prey?

6 Therefore, prophesy concerning the ground of Israel, And thou hast said to mountains, and to hills, To streams, and to valleys, Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I, in My jealousy, and in My fury, I have spoken, Because the shame of nations yehave borne.

7 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: I--I have lifted up My hand, Do not--the nations who [are] with you from round about--they their own shame bear?

8 And ye, O mountains of Israel, Your branch ye give out, and your fruits ye bear for My people Israel, For they have drawn near to come.

9 For, lo, I [am] for you, and have turned to you, And ye have been tilled and sown.

10 And I have multiplied on you men, All the house of Israel--all of it, And the cities have been inhabited, And the wastes are built.

11 And I have multiplied on you man and beast, And they have multiplied and been fruitful, And I have caused you to dwell according to your former states, And I have done better than at your beginnings, And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.

12 And I have caused man to walk over you, --My people Israel, And they possess thee, and thou hast been to them for an inheritance, And thou dost add no more to bereave them.

13 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Because they are saying to you: A devourer of men [art] thou, And a bereaver of thy nations thou hast been,

14 Therefore, man thou devourest no more, And thy nations thou causest not to stumble any more, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

15 And I proclaim not unto thee any more the shame of the nations, And the reproach of peoples thou bearest no more, And thy nations stumble not any more, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

16 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

17 `Son of man, The house of Israel are dwelling on their land, And they defile it by their way and by their doings, As the uncleanness of a separated one hath their way been before Me.

18 And I do pour out My fury upon them For the blood that they shed on the land, And with their idols they have defiled it.

19 And I scatter them among nations, And they are spread through lands, According to their way, and according to their doings, I have judged them.

20 And one goeth in unto the nations whither they have gone, And they pollute My holy name by saying to them, The people of Jehovah [are] these, And from His land they have gone forth.

21 And I have pity on My holy name, That the house of Israel have polluted among nations whither they have gone in.

22 Therefore, say to the house of Israel, Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Not for your sake am I working, O house of Israel, But--for My holy name, That ye have polluted among nations whither ye have gone in.

23 And I have sanctified My great name, That is profaned among nations, That ye have polluted in your midst, And known have the nations that I [am] Jehovah, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, In My being sanctified in you before your eyes.

24 And I have taken you out of the nations, And have gathered you out of all the lands, And I have brought you in unto your land,

25 And I have sprinkled over you clean water, And ye have been clean; From all your uncleannesses, and from all your idols, I do cleanse you.

26 And I have given to you a new heart, And a new spirit I give in your midst, And I have turned aside the heart of stone out of your flesh, And I have given to you a heart of flesh.

27 And My Spirit I give in your midst, And I have done this, so that in My statutes ye walk, And My judgments ye keep, and have done them.

28 And ye have dwelt in the land that I have given to your fathers, And ye have been to Me for a people, And I--I am to you for God.

29 And I have saved you from all your uncleannesses, And I have called unto the corn, and multiplied it, And I have put no famine upon you.

30 And I have multiplied the fruit of the tree, And the increase of the field, So that ye receive not any more a reproach of famine among nations.

31 And ye have remembered your ways that [are] evil, And your doings that [are] not good, And have been loathsome in your own faces, For your iniquities, and for your abominations.

32 Not for your sake am I working, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Be it known to you, Be ashamed and confounded, because of your ways, O house of Israel.

33 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: In the day of My cleansing you from all your iniquities, I have caused the cities to be inhabited, And the wastes have been built,

34 And the desolate land is tilled, Instead of which it was a desolation before the eyes of every passer by,

35 And they have said: This land, that was desolated, Hath been as the garden of Eden, And the cities--the wasted, And the desolated, and the broken down, Fenced places have remained.

36 And known have the nations who are left round about you, That I Jehovah have built the thrown down, I have planted the desolated: I Jehovah have spoken, and I have done [it].

37 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Yet this I am required, By the house of Israel to do to them, I multiply them as a flock of men,

38 As a flock of holy ones, as a flock of Jerusalem, In her appointed seasons, So are the waste cities full of flocks of men, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 37

1 There hath been upon me a hand of Jehovah, and He taketh me forth in the Spirit of Jehovah, and doth place me in the midst of the valley, and it is full of bones,

2 and He causeth me to pass over by them, all round about, and lo, very many [are] on the face of the valley, and lo, very dry.

3 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, do these bones live?' And I say, `O Lord Jehovah, Thou--Thou hast known.'

4 And He saith unto me, `Prophesy concerning these bones, and thou hast said unto them: O dry bones, hear a word of Jehovah:

5 Thus said the Lord Jehovah to these bones: Lo, I am bringing into you a spirit, and ye have lived,

6 and I have given on you sinews, and cause flesh to come up upon you, and covered you over with skin, and given in you a spirit, and ye have lived, and ye have known that I [am] Jehovah.'

7 And I have prophesied as I have been commanded, and there is a noise, as I am prophesying, and lo, a rushing, and draw near do the bones, bone unto its bone.

8 And I beheld, and lo, on them [are] sinews, and flesh hath come up, and cover them doth skin over above--and spirit there is none in them.

9 And He saith unto me: `Prophesy unto the Spirit, prophesy, son of man, and thou hast said unto the Spirit: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: From the four winds come in, O Spirit, and breathe on these slain, and they do live.'

10 And I have prophesied as He commanded me, and the Spirit cometh into them, and they live, and stand on their feet--a very very great force.

11 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, these bones are the whole house of Israel; lo, they are saying: Dried up have our bones, And perished hath our hope, We have been cut off by ourselves.

12 Therefore, prophesy, and thou hast said unto them, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am opening your graves, And have brought you up out of your graves, O My people, And brought you in unto the land of Israel.

13 And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah, In My opening your graves, And in My bringing you up out of your graves, O My people.

14 And I have given My Spirit in you, and ye have lived, And I have caused you to rest on your land, And ye have known that I Jehovah, I have spoken, and I have done [it], An affirmation of Jehovah.'

15 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying,

16 `And thou, son of man, take to thee one stick, and write on it, For Judah, and for the sons of Israel, his companions; and take another stick, and write on it, For Joseph, the stick of Ephraim, and all the house of Israel, his companions,

17 and bring them near one unto another, to thee, for one stick, and they have become one in thy hand.

18 `And when sons of thy people speak unto thee, saying, Dost thou not declare to us what these [are] to thee?

19 Speak unto them, Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am taking the stick of Joseph, that [is] in the hand of Ephraim, and the tribes of Israel his companions, and have given them unto him, with the stick of Judah, and have made them become one stick, and they have been one in My hand.

20 And the sticks on which thou writest have been in thy hand before thine eyes,

21 and speak thou unto them: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I am taking the sons of Israel, From among the nations whither they have gone, And have gathered them from round about, And I have brought them in unto their land.

22 And I have made them become one nation in the land, on mountains of Israel, And one king is to them all for king, And they are no more as two nations, Nor are they divided any more into two kingdoms again.

23 Nor are they defiled any more with their idols, And with their abominations, And with any of their transgressions, And I have saved them out of all their dwellings, In which they have sinned, And I have cleansed them, And they have been to Me for a people, And I--I am to them for God.

24 And My servant David [is] king over them, And one shepherd have they all, And in My judgments they go, And My statutes they keep, and have done them.

25 And they have dwelt on the land that I gave to My servant, to Jacob, In which your fathers have dwelt, And they have dwelt on it, they and their sons, And their son's sons--unto the age, And David My servant [is] their prince--to the age.

26 And I have made to them a covenant of peace, A covenant age-during it is with them, And I have placed them, and multiplied them, And placed My sanctuary in their midst--to the age.

27 And My tabernacle hath been over them, And I have been to them for God, And they have been to Me for a people.

28 And known have the nations that I Jehovah am sanctifying Israel, In My sanctuary being in their midst--to the age!'

Ezekiel 38

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto me, saying:

2 `Son of man, set thy face unto Gog, of the land of Magog, prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal, and prophesy concerning him,

3 and thou hast said: Thus saith the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, O Gog, Prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal,

4 And I have turned thee back, And I have put hooks in thy jaws, And have brought thee out, and all thy force, Horses and horsemen, Clothed in perfection all of them, A numerous assembly, [with] buckler and shield, Handling swords--all of them.

5 Persia, Cush, and Phut, with them, All of them [with] shield and helmet.

6 Gomer and all its bands, The house of Togarmah of the sides of the north, And all its bands, many peoples with thee,

7 Be prepared, yea, prepare for thee, Thou and all thine assemblies who are assembled unto thee, And thou hast been to them for a guard.

8 After many days thou art appointed, In the latter end of the years thou comest in unto a land brought back from sword, [A people] gathered out of many peoples, Upon mountains of Israel, That have been for a perpetual waste, And it from the peoples hath been brought out, And dwelt safely have all of them.

9 And thou hast gone up--as wasting thou comest in, As a cloud to cover the land art thou, Thou and all thy bands, and many peoples with thee.

10 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: And it hath come to pass in that day, Come up do things on thy heart, And thou hast thought an evil thought,

11 And thou hast said: I go up against a land of unwalled villages, I go in to those at rest, dwelling confidently, All of them are dwelling without walls, And bar and doors they have not.

12 To take a spoil, and to take a prey, To turn back thy hand on inhabited wastes, And on a people gathered out of nations, Making cattle and substance, Dwelling on a high part of the land.

13 Sheba, and Dedan, and merchants of Tarshish, And all its young lions say to thee: To take a spoil art thou come in? To take a prey assembled thine assembly? To bear away silver and gold? To take away cattle and substance? To take a great spoil?

14 Therefore, prophesy, son of man, and thou hast said to Gog: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: In that day, in the dwelling of My people Israel safely, Dost thou not know?

15 And thou hast come in out of thy place, From the sides of the north, Thou and many peoples with thee, Riding on horses--all of them, A great assembly, and a numerous force.

16 And thou hast come up against My people Israel, As a cloud to cover the land, In the latter end of the days it is, And I have brought thee in against My land, In order that the nations may know Me, In My being sanctified in thee before their eyes, O Gog.

17 Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Art thou he of whom I spake in former days, By the hand of My servants, prophets of Israel, Who are prophesying in those days--years, To bring thee in against them?

18 And it hath come to pass, in that day, In the day of the coming in of Gog against the land of Israel, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Come up doth My fury in My face,

19 And in My zeal, in the fire of My wrath, I have spoken: Is there not in that day a great rushing on the land of Israel?

20 And rushed from My presence have fishes of the sea, And the fowl of the heavens, And the beast of the field, And every creeping thing that is creeping on the ground, And all men who [are] on the face of the ground, And thrown down have beenthe mountains, And fallen have the ascents, And every wall to the earth falleth.

21 And I have called against him, to all My mountains a sword, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, The sword of each is against his brother.

22 And I have been judged with him, With pestilence and with blood, And an overflowing rain and hailstones, Fire and brimstone I rain on him, and on his bands, And on many peoples who [are] with him.

23 And I have magnified Myself, and sanctified Myself, And I have been known before the eyes of many nations, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah!

Ezekiel 39

1 And thou, son of man, prophesy concerning Gog, and thou hast said: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Lo, I [am] against thee, O Gog, Prince of Rosh, Meshech, and Tubal,

2 And have turned thee back, and enticed thee, And caused thee to come up from the sides of the north, And brought thee in against mountains of Israel,

3 And have smitten thy bow out of thy left hand, Yea, thine arrows out of thy right I cause to fall.

4 On mountains of Israel thou fallest, Thou, and all thy bands, and the peoples who [are] with thee, To ravenous fowl--a bird of every wing, And [to] a beast of the field, I have given thee for food.

5 On the face of the field thou fallest, for I have spoken, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

6 And I have sent a fire against Magog, And against the confident inhabitants of the isles, And they have known that I [am] Jehovah.

7 And My holy name I make known in the midst of My people Israel, And I pollute not My holy name any more, And known have the nations that I, Jehovah, the Holy One, [am] in Israel.

8 Lo, it hath come, and it hath been done, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, It [is] the day of which I spake.

9 And gone out have the inhabitants of cities of Israel, And they have burned and kindled [a fire], With armour, and shield, and buckler, With bow, and with arrows, And with handstaves, and with javelins, And they have caused a fire to burn with them seven years,

10 And they do not take wood out of the field, Nor do they hew out of the forests, For with armour they cause the fire to burn, And they have spoiled their spoilers, And they have plundered their plunderers, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

11 And it hath come to pass, in that day, I give to Gog a place there--a grave in Israel, the valley of those passing by, east of the sea, and it is stopping those passing by, and they have buried there Gog, and all his multitude, and have cried, O valley of the multitude of Gog!

12 And the house of Israel have buried them--in order to cleanse the land--seven months.

13 Yea, all the people of the land have buried them, and it hath been to them for a name--the day of My being honoured--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

14 And men for continual employment they separate, passing on through the land, burying with those passing by those who are left on the face of the earth, to cleanse it: at the end of seven months they search.

15 And those passing by have passed through the land, and seen a bone of man, and one hath constructed near it a sign till those burying have buried it in the valley of the multitude of Gog.

16 And also the name of the city [is] The multitude; and they have cleansed the land.

17 And thou, son of man, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Say to the bird--every wing, and to every beast of the field: Be assembled and come in, Be gathered from round about, For My sacrifice that I am sacrificing for you, A great sacrifice on mountains of Israel, And ye have eaten flesh, and drunk blood.

18 Flesh of the mighty ye do eat, And blood of princes of the earth ye drink, Of rams, of lambs, and of he-goats, Of calves, fatlings of Bashan--all of them.

19 And ye have eaten fat to satiety, And ye have drunk blood--to drunkenness, Of My sacrifice that I sacrificed for you.

20 And ye have been satisfied at My table with horse and rider, Mighty man, and every man of war, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

21 And I have given My honour among nations, And seen have all the nations My Judgment that I have done, And My hand that I have laid on them.

22 And known have the house of Israel that I [am] Jehovah their God, From that day and henceforth.

23 And known have the nations that for their iniquity, Removed have the house of Israel, Because they have trespassed against Me, And I do hide My face from them, And give them into the hand of their adversaries, And they fall by sword--all of them.

24 According to their uncleanness, And according to their transgressions, I have done with them, And I do hide My face from them.

25 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: Now do I bring back the captivity of Jacob, And I have pitied all the house of Israel, And have been zealous for My holy name.

26 And they have forgotten their shame, And all their trespass that they trespassed against Me, In their dwelling on their land confidently and none troubling.

27 In My bringing them back from the peoples, I have assembled them from the lands of their enemies, And I have been sanctified in them before the eyes of the many nations,

28 And they have known that I [am] Jehovah their God, In My removing them unto the nations, And I have gathered them unto their land, And I leave none of them any more there.

29 And I hide not any more My face from them, In that I have poured out My spirit on the house of Israel, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah!'

Ezekiel 41

1 And he bringeth me in unto the temple, and he measureth the posts, six cubits the breadth on this side, and six cubits the breadth on that side--the breadth of the tent.

2 And the breadth of the opening [is] ten cubits; and the sides of the opening [are] five cubits on this side, and five cubits on that side; and he measureth its length forty cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits.

3 And he hath gone inward, and measureth the post of the opening two cubits, and the opening six cubits, and the breadth of the opening seven cubits.

4 And he measureth its length twenty cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits, unto the front of the temple, and he saith unto me, `This [is] the holy of holies.'

5 And he measureth the wall of the house six cubits, and the breadth of the sidechamber four cubits, all round the house round about.

6 And the side-chambers [are] side-chamber by side-chamber, three and thirty times; and they are entering into the wall--which the house hath for the side-chambers all round about--to be taken hold of, and they are not taken hold of by the wall of the house.

7 And a broad place and a turning place still upwards [are] to the side-chambers, for the turning round of the house [is] still upwards all round about the house: therefore the breadth of the house [is] upwards, and so the lower one goeth up unto the higher by the midst.

8 And I have looked at the house, the height all round about: the foundations of the side-chambers [are] the fulness of the reed, six cubits by the joining.

9 The breadth of the wall that [is] to the side-chamber at the outside [is] five cubits; and that which is left [is] the place of the side-chambers that [are] to the house.

10 And between the chambers [is] a breadth of twenty cubits round about the house, all round about.

11 And the opening of the side-chamber [is] to the place left, one opening northward, and one opening southward, and the breadth of the place that is left [is] five cubits all round about.

12 As to the building that [is] at the front of the separate place [at] the corner westward, the breadth [is] seventy cubits, and the wall of the building five cubits broad all round about, and its length ninety cubits.

13 And he hath measured the house, the length [is] a hundred cubits; and the separate place, and the building, and its walls, the length [is] a hundred cubits;

14 and the breadth of the front of the house, and of the separate place eastward, a hundred cubits.

15 And he hath measured the length of the building unto the front of the separate place that [is] at its hinder part, and its galleries on this side and on that side, a hundred cubits, and the inner temple and the porches of the court,

16 the thresholds, and the narrow windows, and the galleries round about them three, over-against the threshold, a ceiling of wood all round about, and the ground unto the windows and the covered windows,

17 over above the opening, and unto the inner-house, and at the outside, and by all the wall all round about within and without [by] measure.

18 And it is made [with] cherubs and palm-trees, and a palm-tree [is] between cherub and cherub, and two faces [are] to the cherub;

19 and the face of man [is] unto the palm-tree on this side, and the face of a young lion unto the palm-tree on that side; it is made unto all the house all round about.

20 from the earth unto above the opening [are] the cherubs and the palm-trees made, and [on] the wall of the temple.

21 Of the temple the side post [is] square, and of the front of the sanctuary, the appearance [is] as the appearance.

22 Of the altar, the wood [is] three cubits in height, and its length two cubits; and its corners [are] to it, and its length, and its walls [are] of wood, and he speaketh unto me, `This [is] the table that [is] before Jehovah.'

23 And two doors [are] to the temple and to the sanctuary;

24 and two leaves [are] to the doors, two turning leaves [are] to the doors, two to the one door, and two leaves to the other.

25 And made on them, on the doors of the temple, [are] cherubs and palm-trees as are made on the walls, and a thickness of wood [is] at the front of the porch on the outside.

26 And narrow windows and palm-trees [are] on this side, and on that side, at the sides of the porch, and the side-chambers of the house, and the thick places.

Ezekiel 42

1 And he bringeth me forth unto the outer court, the way northward, and he bringeth me in unto the chamber that [is] over-against the separate place, and that [is] over-against the building at the north.

2 At the front of the length [is] a hundred cubits [at] the north opening, and the breadth fifty cubits.

3 Over-against the twenty [cubits] that are to the inner court, and over-against the pavement that [is] to the outer court, [is] gallery over-against gallery, in the three [storeys].

4 And at the front of the chambers [is] a walk of ten cubits in breadth unto the inner part, a way of one cubit, and their openings [are] at the north.

5 And the upper chambers [are] short, for the galleries contain more than these, than the lower, and than the middle one, of the building;

6 for they [are] threefold, and they have no pillars as the pillars of the court, therefore it hath been kept back--more than the lower and than the middle one--from the ground.

7 As to the wall that [is] at the outside, over-against the chambers, the way of the outercourt at the front of the chambers, its length [is] fifty cubits;

8 for the length of the chambers that [are] to the outer court [is] fifty cubits, and of those on the front of the temple a hundred cubits.

9 And under these chambers [is] the entrance from the east, in one's going into them from the outer court.

10 In the breadth of the wall of the court eastward, unto the front of the separate place, and unto the front of the building, [are] chambers.

11 And the way before them [is] as the appearance of the chambers that [are] northward, according to their length so [is] their breadth, and all their outlets, and according to their fashions, and according to their openings.

12 And according to the openings of the chambers that [are] southward [is] an opening at the head of the way, the way directly in the front of the wall eastward in entering them.

13 And he saith unto me, `The north chambers, the south chambers, that [are] at the front of the separate place, they [are] holy chambers, where the priests (who [are] near to Jehovah) eat the most holy things, there they place the most holy things, and the present, and the sin-offering, and the guilt-offering, for the place [is] holy.

14 In the priests' going in, they come not out from the sanctuary unto the outer court, and there they place their garments with which they minister, for they [are] holy, and have put on other garments, and have drawn near unto that which [is]for the people.'

15 And he hath finished the measurements of the inner house, and hath brought me forth the way of the gate whose front [is] eastward, and he hath measured it all round about.

16 He hath measured the east side with the measuring-reed, five hundred reeds, with the measuring-reed round about.

17 He hath measured the north side, five hundred reeds, with the measuring reed round about.

18 The south side he hath measured, five hundred reeds, with the measuring-reed.

19 He hath turned round unto the west side, he hath measured five hundred reeds with the measuring-reed.

20 At the four sides he hath measured it, a wall [is] to it all round about, the length five hundred, and the breadth five hundred, to separate between the holy and the profane place.

Ezekiel 43

1 And he causeth me to go to the gate, the gate that is looking eastward.

2 And lo, the honour of the God of Israel hath come from the way of the east, and His voice [is] as the noise of many waters, and the earth hath shone from His honour.

3 And according to the appearance [is] the appearance that I saw, as the appearance that I saw in my coming in to destroy the city, and the appearances [are] as the appearance that I saw at the river Chebar, and I fall on my face.

4 And the honour of Jehovah hath come in unto the house, the way of the gate whose face [is] eastward.

5 And take me up doth the Spirit, and bringeth me in unto the inner court, and lo, the honour of Jehovah hath filled the house.

6 And I hear one speaking unto me from the house, and a man hath been standing near me,

7 and He saith unto me: `Son of man, the place of My throne, And the place of the soles of My feet, Where I dwell in the midst of the sons of Israel to the age, Defile no more do the house of Israel My holy name, They, and their kings, by their whoredom, And by the carcases of their kings--their high places.

8 In their putting their threshold with My threshold, And their door-post near My doorpost, And the wall between Me and them, And they have defiled My holy name, By their abominations that they have done, And I consume them in Mine anger.

9 Now do they put far off their whoredom, And the carcases of their kings--from Me, And I have dwelt in their midst to the age.

10 Thou, son of man, Shew the house of Israel the house, And they are ashamed of their iniquities, And they have measured the measurement.

11 And since they have been ashamed of all that they have done, The form of the house, and its measurement, And its outlets, and its inlets, and all its forms, And all its statutes, even all its forms, And all its laws cause them to know, And write [it] before their eyes, And they observe all its forms, And all its statutes, and have done them.

12 This [is] a law of the house: on the top of the mountain, all its border all round about [is] most holy; lo, this [is] a law of the house.

13 `And these [are] measures of the altar by cubits: The cubit [is] a cubit and a handbreadth, and the centre [is] a cubit, and a cubit the breadth; and its border on its edge round about [is] one span, and this [is] the upper part of the altar.

14 And from the centre of the ground unto the lower border [is] two cubits, and the breadth one cubit, and from the lesser border unto the greater border four cubits, and the breadth a cubit.

15 `And the altar [is] four cubits, and from the altar and upward [are] four horns.

16 And the altar [is] twelve long by twelve broad, square in its four squares.

17 And the border [is] fourteen long by fourteen broad, at its four squares, and the border round about it [is] half a cubit, and the centre to it [is] a cubit round about, and its steps are looking eastward.'

18 And He saith unto me, `Son of man, Thus said the Lord Jehovah: These [are] statutes of the altar in the day of its being made to cause burnt-offering to go up on it, and to sprinkle on it blood.

19 And thou hast given unto the priests, the Levites, who [are] of the seed of Zadok-- who are near unto Me, an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, to serve Me--a calf from the herd, for a sin-offering.

20 And thou hast taken of its blood, and hast put it on its four horns, and on the four corners of its border, and on the border round about, and hast cleansed it, and purified it.

21 And thou hast taken the bullock of the sin-offering, and hast burnt it in the appointed place of the house at the outside of the sanctuary.

22 And on the second day thou dost bring near a kid of the goats, a perfect one, for a sin-offering, and they have cleansed the altar, as they cleansed [it] for the bullock.

23 In thy finishing cleansing, thou dost bring near a calf, a son of the herd, a perfect one, and a ram out of the flock, a perfect one.

24 And thou hast brought them near before Jehovah, and the priests have cast upon them salt, and have caused them to go up, a burnt-offering to Jehovah.

25 Seven days thou dost prepare a goat for a sin-offering daily, and a bullock, a son of the herd, and a ram out of the flock, perfect ones, do they prepare.

26 Seven days they purify the altar, and have cleansed it, and filled their hand.

27 And the days are completed, and it hath come to pass on the eighth day, and henceforth, the priests prepare on the altar your burnt-offerings and your peace-offerings, and I have accepted you--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.'

Ezekiel 44

1 And he causeth me to turn back the way of the gate of the outer sanctuary that is looking eastward, and it is shut.

2 And Jehovah saith unto me, `This gate is shut, it is not opened, and none doth go in by it, for Jehovah, God of Israel, hath come in by it, and it hath been shut.

3 The prince, who [is] prince, he sitteth by it to eat bread before Jehovah, by the way of the porch of the gate he cometh in, and by its way he goeth out.'

4 And he bringeth me in the way of the north gate unto the front of the house, and I look, and lo, filled hath the honour of Jehovah the house of Jehovah, and I fall on my face.

5 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Son of man, set thy heart, and see with thine eyes, and with thine ears hear, all that I am speaking with thee, of all the statutes of the house of Jehovah, and of all its laws; and thou hast set thy heart to the entrance of the house, with all the outlets of the sanctuary,

6 and hast said unto the rebellious, unto the house of Israel: Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Enough to you--of all your abominations, O house of Israel.

7 In your bringing in sons of a stranger, uncircumcised of heart, and uncircumcised of flesh, to be in My sanctuary, to pollute it, even My house, in your bringing near My bread, fat, and blood, and they break My covenant by all your abominations,

8 and ye have not kept the charge of My holy things, and ye set [them] for keepers of My charge in My sanctuary for you.

9 `Thus said the Lord Jehovah: No son of a stranger, uncircumcised of heart, and uncircumcised of flesh, cometh in unto My sanctuary, even any son of a stranger, who [is] in the midst of the sons of Israel,

10 but--the Levites who have gone far off from me, in the wandering of Israel when they went astray from Me after their idols, and they have borne their iniquity.

11 And they have been in My sanctuary ministrants, overseers at the gates of the house, and ministrants at the house; they slay the burnt-offering and the sacrifice for the people, and they stand before them to serve them.

12 Because that they serve them before their idols, and have been to the house of Israel for a stumbling-block of iniquity, therefore I have lifted up my hand against them--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah--and they have borne their iniquity.

13 And they draw not nigh unto Me to act as My priest, and to draw nigh unto any of My holy things, unto the holy of holies, and they have borne their shame and their abominations that they have done,

14 and I made them keepers of the charge of the house, for all its service and for all that is done in it.

15 `And the priests, the Levites, sons of Zadok, who have kept the charge of My sanctuary in the wandering of the sons of Israel from off Me, they draw near unto Me to serve Me, and have stood before Me, to bring near to Me fat and blood--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah:

16 they come in unto My sanctuary, and they draw near unto My table to serve Me, and they have kept My charge.

17 And it hath come to pass, in their going in unto the gates of the inner court, linen garments they put on; and no wool cometh up on them in their ministering in the gates of the inner court and within.

18 Linen bonnets are on their head, and linen trousers are on their loins, they are not restrained with sweat.

19 And in their going forth unto the outer court--unto the outer court unto the people-- they strip off their garments, in which they are ministering, and have placed them in the holy chambers, and have put on other garments; and they do not sanctify the people in their own garments.

20 And their head they do not shave, and the lock they do not send forth; they certainly poll their heads.

21 And no priest doth drink wine in their coming in unto the inner court.

22 And a widow and divorced woman they do not take to them for wives: but--virgins of the seed of the house of Israel, and the widow who is widow of a priest, do they take.

23 `And My people they direct between holy and common, and between unclean and clean they cause them to discern.

24 And concerning controversy, they stand up for judgment; with My judgments they judge it; and My law and My statutes in all My appointed places they keep; and My sabbaths they sanctify.

25 And unto any dead man they come not for uncleanness, but for father, and for mother, and for son, and for daughter, for brother, for sister who hath not been to a man, they defile themselves.

26 `And after his cleansing, seven days they number to him.

27 And in the day of his coming in unto the sanctuary, unto the inner court, to minister in the sanctuary, he bringeth near his sin-offering--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

28 And it hath been to them for an inheritance; I [am] their inheritance: and a possession ye do not give to them in Israel; I [am] their possession.

29 The present, and the sin-offering, and the guilt-offering, they do eat, and every devoted thing in Israel is theirs.

30 And the first of all the first-fruits of all, and every heave-offering of all, of all your heave-offerings, are the priests': and the first of your dough ye give to the priest, to cause a blessing to rest on thy house.

31 Any carcase and torn thing, of the fowl, and of the beasts, the priests do not eat.

Ezekiel 45

1 And in your causing the land to fall in inheritance, ye lift up a heave-offering to Jehovah, a holy [portion] of the land: the length--five and twenty thousand [is] the length, and the breadth ten thousand; it [is] holy in all its border round about.

2 There is of this for the sanctuary five hundred by five hundred, square, round about; and fifty cubits of suburb [is] to it round about.

3 And by this measure thou dost measure: the length [is] five and twenty thousand, and the breadth ten thousand: and in it is the sanctuary, the holy of holies.

4 The holy [portion] of the land it [is]; for priests, ministrants of the sanctuary, it is, who are drawing near to serve Jehovah; and it hath been to them a place for houses, and a holy place for a sanctuary.

5 `And of the five and twenty thousand of length, and of the ten thousand of breadth, there is to the Levites, ministrants of the house, for them--for a possession--twenty chambers.

6 `And of the possession of the city ye give five thousand of breadth, and of length five and twenty thousand, over-against the heave-offering of the holy [portion]: to all the house of Israel it is.

7 As to the prince, on this side, and on that side, of the heave-offering of the holy place, and of the possession of the city, at the front of the heave-offering of the holy place, and at the front of the possession of the city, from the westcorner westward, and from the east corner eastward--and the length [is] over-against one of the portions from the west border unto the east border--

8 of the land there is to him for a possession in Israel, and My princes do not oppress any more My people, and the land they give to the house of Israel according to their tribes.

9 `Thus said the Lord Jehovah: Enough to you--princes of Israel; violence and spoil turn aside, and judgment and righteousness do; lift up your exactions from off My people--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

10 Just balances, and a just ephah, and a just bath--ye have.

11 The ephah and the bath is of one measure, for the bath to bear a tenth of the homer, and the ephah a tenth of the homer: according to the homer is its measurement.

12 And, the shekel [is] twenty gerah: twenty shekels, five and twenty shekels, fifteen shekels--is your maneh.

13 `This [is] the heave-offering that ye lift up; a sixth part of the ephah of a homer of wheat, also ye have given a sixth part of the ephah of a homer of barley,

14 and the portion of oil, the bath of oil, a tenth part of the bath out of the cor, a homer of ten baths--for ten baths [are] a homer;

15 and one lamb out of the flock, out of two hundred, out of the watered country of Israel, for a present, and for a burnt-offering, and for peace-offerings, to make atonement by them-- an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

16 All the people of the land are at this heave-offering for the prince in Israel.

17 And on the prince are the burnt-offerings, and the present, and the libation, in feasts, and in new moons, and in sabbaths, in all appointed times of the house of Israel: he doth make the sin-offering, and the present, and the burnt-offering, and the peace-offerings, to make atonement for the house of Israel.

18 `Thus said the Lord Jehovah: In the first [month], in the first of the month, thou dost take a bullock, a son of the herd, a perfect one, and hast cleansed the sanctuary:

19 and the priest hath taken of the blood of the sin offering, and hath put on the doorpost of the house, and on the four corners of the border of the altar, and on the post of the gate of the inner court.

20 And so thou dost do on the seventh of the month, because of each erring one, and because of the simple one--and ye have purified the house.

21 `In the first [month], in the fourteenth day of the month, ye have the passover, a feast of seven days, unleavened food is eaten.

22 And the prince hath prepared on that day, for himself, and for all the people of the land, a bullock, a sin-offering.

23 And the seven days of the feast he prepareth a burnt-offering to Jehovah, seven bullocks, and seven rams, perfect ones, daily seven days, and a sin-offering, a kid of the goats, daily.

24 And a present of an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, he doth prepare, and of oil a hin for an ephah.

25 In the seventh [month], in the fifteenth day of the month, in the feast, he doth according to these things seven days; as the sin-offering so the burnt-offering, and as the present so also the oil.

Ezekiel 46

1 `Thus said the Lord Jehovah: The gate of the inner court that is looking eastward is shut the six days of work, and on the day of rest it is opened, and in the day of the new moon it is opened;

2 and come in hath the prince the way of the porch of the gate at the outside, and he hath stood by the post of the gate, and the priests have made his burnt-offering, and his peaceofferings, and he hath bowed himself by the opening of the gate, and hath gone forth, and the gate is not shut till the evening.

3 And bowed themselves have the people of the land at the opening of that gate, on sabbaths, and on new moons, before Jehovah.

4 `And the burnt-offering that the prince bringeth near to Jehovah on the day of rest [is] six lambs, perfect ones, and a ram, a perfect one.

5 And the present [is] an ephah for a ram, and for the lambs a present, the gift of his hand, and of oil a hin for an ephah.

6 And on the day of the new moon a bullock, a son of the herd, a perfect one, and six lambs and a ram, they are perfect.

7 And with an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, he prepareth a present, and for the lambs as his hand attaineth, and of oil a hin for an ephah.

8 `And in the coming in of the prince, the way of the porch of the gate he cometh in, and by its way he goeth out.

9 And in the coming in of the people of the land before Jehovah at appointed times, he who hath come in the way of the north gate to bow himself, goeth out the way of the south gate, and he who hath come in the way of the south gate, goeth outby the way of the north gate: he doth not turn back the way of the gate by which he came in, but over-against it he goeth out.

10 And the prince in their midst in their coming in cometh in, and in their going out he goeth out.

11 `And in feasts, and in appointed times, the present is an ephah for a bullock, and an ephah for a ram, and for lambs the gift of his hand, and of oil a hin for an ephah.

12 And when the prince maketh a free-will burnt-offering, or free-will peace-offerings, to Jehovah, then he hath opened for himself the gate that is looking eastward, and he hath made his burnt-offering and his peace-offerings as he doth in the day of rest, and he hath gone out, and he hath shut the gate after his going out.

13 `And a lamb, son of a year, a perfect one, thou dost make a burnt-offering daily to Jehovah; morning by morning thou dost make it.

14 And a present thou dost make for it morning by morning, a sixth part of the ephah, and of oil a third part of the hin, to temper with the fine flour, a present to Jehovah, by a statute age-during--continually;

15 and prepare ye the lamb, and the present, and the oil, morning by morning, a continual burnt-offering.

16 `Thus said the Lord Jehovah: When the prince giveth a gift to any of his sons, his inheritance it [is], to his sons it [is]; their possession it [is] by inheritance.

17 And when he giveth a gift out of his inheritance to one of his servants, then it hath been to him till the year of freedom, and it hath turned back to the prince, only the inheritance of his sons is theirs.

18 And the prince doth not take of the inheritance of the people to oppress them, out of their possession, out of his own possession he doth cause his sons to inherit, so that My people are not scattered each from his possession.'

19 And he bringeth me in through the entrance that [is] by the side of the gate, unto the holy chambers, unto the priests, that are looking northward, and lo, there [is] a place in their two sides westward.

20 And he saith unto me, `This [is] the place where the priests do boil the guilt-offering and the sin-offering, where they bake the present, so as not to bring [it] out unto the outer court, to sanctify the people.'

21 And he bringeth me out unto the outer court, and causeth me to pass over unto the four corners of the court, and lo, a court in a corner of the court, a court in a corner of the corner.

22 In the four corners of the court [are] perfume courts, forty long, and thirty broad, one measure [is] to the four corners.

23 And a row [is] round about in them, round about to them four, and made with boilers under the rows round about.

24 And he saith unto me, `These [are] the houses of those boiling where the ministrants of the house boil the sacrifice of the people.'

Ezekiel 47

1 And he causeth me to turn back unto the opening of the house; and lo, water is coming forth from under the threshold of the house eastward, for the front of the house [is] eastward, and the water is coming down from beneath, from the right side of the house, from the south of the altar.

2 And he causeth me to go out the way of the gate northward, and causeth me to turn round the way without, unto the gate that [is] without, the way that is looking eastward, and lo, water is coming forth from the right side.

3 In the going out of the man eastward, and a line in his hand, then he measureth a thousand by the cubit, and he causeth me to pass over into water--water to the ankles.

4 And he measureth a thousand, and causeth me to pass over into water--water to the knees. And he measureth a thousand, and causeth me to pass over--water to the loins.

5 And he measureth a thousand--a stream that I am not able to pass over; for risen have the waters--waters to swim in--a stream that is not passed over.

6 And he saith unto me, `Hast thou seen, son of man?' and he leadeth me, and bringeth me back unto the edge of the stream.

7 In my turning back, then, lo, at the edge of the stream [are] very many trees, on this side and on that side.

8 And he saith unto me, `These waters are going forth unto the east circuit, and have gone down unto the desert, and have entered the sea; unto the sea they are brought forth, and the waters have been healed.

9 And it hath come to pass, every living creature that teemeth, whithersoever the streams come, doth live: and there hath been great abundance of fish, for these waters have come thither, and they are healed; and every thing whither the streamcometh hath lived.

10 And it hath come to pass, fishers do stand by it, from En-Gedi even unto En-Eglaim; a spreading place of nets they are; according to their own kind is their fish, as the fish of the great sea, very many.

11 Its miry and its marshy places--they are not healed; to salt they have been given up.

12 And by the stream there cometh up on its edge, on this side and on that side, every [kind of] fruit-tree whose leaf fadeth not, and not consumed is its fruit, according to its months it yieldeth first-fruits, because its waters from the sanctuary are coming forth; and its fruits hath been for food, and its leaf for medicine.

13 `Thus said the Lord Jehovah: This [is] the border whereby ye inherit the land, according to the twelve tribes of Israel; Joseph [hath] portions.

14 And ye have inherited it, one as well as another, in that I have lifted up My hand to give it to your fathers; and this land hath fallen to you in inheritance.

15 `And this [is] the border of the land at the north quarter; from the great sea, the way of Hethlon, at the coming in to Zedad:

16 Hamath, Berothah, Sibraim, that [is] between the border of Damascus and the border of Hamath; Hazar-Hatticon, that [is] at the coast of Havran.

17 And the border from the sea hath been Hazar-Enan, the border of Damascus, and Zaphon at the north, and the border of Hamath: and [this is] the north quarter.

18 `And the east quarter [is] from between Havran, and Damascus, and Gilead, and the land of Israel, [to] the Jordan; from the border over-against the eastern sea ye measure: and [this is] the east quarter.

19 `And the south quarter southward [is] from Tamar unto the waters of Meriboth- Kadesh, the stream unto the great sea: and [this is] the south quarter southward.

20 `And the west quarter [is] the great sea, from the border till over-against the coming in to Hamath: this [is] the west quarter.

21 `And ye have divided this land to you, according to the tribes of Israel;

22 and it hath come to pass, ye separate it for an inheritance to yourselves, and to the sojourners who are sojourning in your midst, who have begotten sons in your midst, and they have been to you as native, with the sons of Israel, with you they are separated for an inheritance in the midst of the tribes of Israel.

23 And it hath come to pass, in the tribe with which the sojourner sojourneth, there ye give his inheritance--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

Ezekiel 48

1 And these [are] the names of the tribes: From the north end unto the side of the way of Hethlon, at the coming in to Hamath, Hazar-Enan, the border of Damascus northward, unto the side of Hamath, and they have been his--side east and west, Dan one,

2 and by the border of Dan, from the east side unto the west side, Asher one,

3 and by the border of Asher, from the east side even unto the west side, Naphtali one,

4 and by the border of Naphtali, from the east side unto the west side, Manasseh one,

5 and by the border of Manasseh, from the east side unto the west side, Ephraim one,

6 and by the border of Ephraim, from the east side even unto the west side, Reuben one,

7 and by the border of Reuben, from the east side unto the west side, Judah one,

8 and by the border of Judah, from the east side unto the west side is the heave-offering that ye lift up, five and twenty thousand broad and long, as one of the parts, from the east side unto the west side: and the sanctuary hath been in its midst.

9 The heave-offering that ye lift up to Jehovah [is] five and twenty thousand long, and broad ten thousand.

10 And of these is the holy heave-offering for the priests, northward five and twenty thousand, and westward [in] breadth ten thousand, and eastward [in] breadth ten thousand, and southward [in] length five and twenty thousand: and the sanctuary of Jehovah hath been in its midst.

11 For the priests who are sanctified of the sons of Zadok, who have kept My charge, who erred not in the erring of the sons of Israel, as the Levites erred,

12 even the heave-offering hath been to them, out of the heave-offering of the land, most holy, by the border of the Levites.

13 `And [to] the Levites over-against the border of the priests [are] five and twenty thousand [in] length, and [in] breadth ten thousand, all the length [is] five and twenty thousand, and the breadth ten thousand.

14 And they do not sell of it, nor exchange, nor cause to pass away the first-fruit of the land: for [it is] holy to Jehovah.

15 And the five thousand that is left in the breadth, on the front of the five and twenty thousand, is common--for the city, for dwelling, and for suburb, and the city hath been in its midst.

16 And these [are] its measures: the north side five hundred, and four thousand, and the south side five hundred, and four thousand, and on the east side five hundred, and four thousand, and the west side five hundred, and four thousand.

17 And the suburb to the city hath been northward, fifty and two hundred, and southward, fifty and two hundred, and eastward, fifty and two hundred, and westward, fifty and two hundred.

18 `And the residue in length over-against the heave-offering of the holy [portion is] ten thousand eastward, and ten thousand westward, and it hath been over-against the heave-offering of the holy [portion], and its increase hath been for food to the servants of the city,

19 even [to] him who is serving the city, they serve it out of all the tribes of Israel.

20 All the heave-offering [is] five and twenty thousand by five and twenty thousand, square do ye lift up the heave-offering of the holy [portion] with the possession of the city.

21 `And the residue [is] for the prince, on this side and on that side of the heaveoffering of the holy [portion], and of the possession of the city, on the front of the five and twenty thousand of the heave-offering unto the east border, andwestward, on the front of the five and twenty thousand on the west border, over-against the portions of the prince; and the heave-offering of the holy [portion], and the sanctuary of the house, hath been in its midst.

22 And from the possession of the Levites, from the possession of the city, in the midst of that which is to the prince, between the border of Judah and the border of Benjamin, there is to the prince.

23 `As to the rest of the tribes, from the east side unto the west side, Benjamin one,

24 and by the border of Benjamin, from the east side unto the west side, Simeon one,

25 and by the border of Simeon, from the east side unto the west side, Issachar one,

26 and by the border of Issachar, from the east side unto the west side, Zebulun one,

27 and by the border of Zebulun, from the east side unto the west side, Gad one,

28 and by the border of Gad, at the south side southward, the border hath been from Tamar [to] the waters of Meriboth-Kadesh, the stream by the great sea.

29 This [is] the land that ye separate by inheritance to the tribes of Israel, and these [are] their portions--an affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

30 `And these [are] the outgoings of the city on the north side, five hundred, and four thousand measures.

31 And the gates of the city [are] according to the names of the tribes of Israel; three gates northward: the gate of Reuben one, the gate of Judah one, the gate of Levi one.

32 And on the east side five hundred, and four thousand, and three gates: the gate of Joseph one, the gate of Benjamin one, the gate of Dan one.

33 And the south side five hundred, and four thousand measures, and three gates: the gate of Simeon one, the gate of Issachar one, the gate of Zebulun one.

34 The west side five hundred, and four thousand, their gates three: the gate of Gad one, the gate of Asher one, the gate of Naphtali one.

35 Round about [is] eighteen thousand, and the renown of the city [is] from the day Jehovah [is] there.'

Daniel 1

1 In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah, come hath Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon to Jerusalem, and layeth siege against it;

2 and the Lord giveth into his hand Jehoiakim king of Judah, and some of the vessels of the house of God, and he bringeth them in [to] the land of Shinar, [to] the house of his god, and the vessels he hath brought in [to] the treasure-house of his god.

3 And the king saith, to Ashpenaz master of his eunuchs, to bring in out of the sons of Israel, (even of the royal seed, and of the chiefs,)

4 lads in whom there is no blemish, and of good appearance, and skilful in all wisdom, and possessing knowledge, and teaching thought, and who have ability to stand in the palace of the king, and to teach them the literature and language of the Chaldeans.

5 And the king doth appoint for them a rate, day by day, of the king's portion of food, and of the wine of his drinking, so as to nourish them three years, that at the end thereof they may stand before the king.

6 And there are among them out of the sons of Judah, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah,

7 and the chief of the eunuchs setteth names on them, and he setteth on Daniel, Belteshazzar; and on Hananiah, Shadrach; and on Mishael, Meshach; and on Azariah, Abed-Nego.

8 And Daniel purposeth in his heart that he will not pollute himself with the king's portion of food, and with the wine of his drinking, and he seeketh of the chief of the eunuchs that he may not pollute himself.

9 And God giveth Daniel for kindness and for mercies before the chief of the eunuchs;

10 and the chief of the eunuchs saith to Daniel, `I am fearing my lord the king, who hath appointed your food and your drink, for why doth he see your faces sadder than [those of] the lads which [are] of your circle? then ye have made my head indebted to the king,'

11 And Daniel saith unto the Meltzar, whom the chief of the eunuchs hath appointed over

12 `Try, I pray thee, thy servants, ten days; and they give to us of the vegetables, and we eat, and water, and we drink;

13 and our appearance is seen before thee, and the appearance of the lads who are eating the king's portion of food, and as thou seest--deal with thy servants.'

14 And he hearkeneth to them, to this word, and trieth them ten days:

15 and at the end of ten days their appearance hath appeared better and fatter in flesh then any of the lads who are eating the king's portion of food.

16 And the Meltzar is taking away their portion of food, and the wine of their drink, and is giving to them vegetables.

17 As to these four lads, God hath given to them knowledge and understanding in every [kind of] literature, and wisdom; and Daniel hath given instruction about every [kind of] vision and dreams.

18 And at the end of the days that the king had said to bring them in, bring them in doth the chief of the eunuchs before Nebuchadnezzar.

19 And the king speaketh with them, and there hath none been found among them all like

20 and [in] any matter of wisdom [and] understanding that the king hath sought of them, he findeth them ten hands above all the scribes, the enchanters, who [are] in all his kingdom.

21 And Daniel is unto the first year of Cyrus the king.

Daniel 3

1 Nebuchadnezzar the king hath made an image of gold, its height sixty cubits, its breadth six cubits; he hath raised it up in the valley of Dura, in the province of Babylon;

2 and Nebuchadnezzar the king hath sent to gather the satraps, the prefects, and the governors, the honourable judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the province, to come to the dedication of the image thatNebuchadnezzar the king hath raised up.

3 Then are gathered the satraps, the prefects, and the governors, the honourable judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the province, to the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath raised up: and they are standing before the image that Nebuchadnezzar hath raised up.

4 And a crier is calling mightily: `To you they are saying: O peoples, nations, and languages!

5 at the time that ye hear the voice of the cornet, the flute, the harp, the sackbut, the psaltery, the symphony, and all kinds of music, ye fall down and do obeisance to the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath raised up:

6 and whoso doth not fall down and do obeisance, in that hour he is cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.'

7 Therefore at that time, when all the peoples are hearing the voice of the cornet, the flute, the harp, the sackbut, the psaltery, and all kinds of music, falling down are all the peoples, nations and languages, doing obeisance to the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath raised up.

8 Therefore at that time drawn near have certain Chaldeans, and accused the Jews;

9 they have answered, yea, they are saying to Nebuchadnezzar the king, `O king, to the ages live!

10 Thou, O king, hast made a decree that every man who doth hear the voice of the cornet, the flute, the harp, the sackbut, the psaltery, and the symphony, and all kinds of music, doth fall down and do obeisance to the golden image;

11 and whoso doth not fall down and do obeisance, is cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace.

12 There are certain Jews whom thou hast appointed over the work of the province of Babylon--Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, these men have not made of thee, O king, [any] regard; thy gods they are not serving, and to the golden image thou hast raised up--are not making obeisance.'

13 Then Nebuchadnezzar, in anger and fury, hath said to bring in Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego. Then these men have been brought in before the king.

14 Nebuchadnezzar hath answered and said to them, `Is [it] a laid plan, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego--my gods ye are not serving, and to the golden image that I have raised up ye are not doing obeisance?

15 Now, lo, ye are ready, so that at the time that ye hear the voice of the cornet, the flute, the harp, the sackbut, the psaltery, and the symphony, and all kinds of music, ye fall down and do obeisance to the image that I have made! --and lo, ye do no obeisance--in that hour ye are cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace; who is that God who doth deliver you out of my hands?'

16 Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego have answered, yea, they are saying to the king Nebuchadnezzar, `We have no need concerning this matter to answer thee.

17 Lo, it is; our God whom we are serving, is able to deliver us from a burning fiery furnace; and from thy hand, O king, He doth deliver.

18 And lo--not! be it known to thee, O king, that thy gods we are not serving, and to the golden image thou hast raised up we do no obeisance.'

19 Then Nebuchadnezzar hath been full of fury, and the expression of his face hath been changed concerning Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego; he answered and said to heat the furnace seven times above that which it is seen to be heated;

20 and to certain mighty men who [are] in his force he hath said to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, to cast into the burning fiery furnace.

21 Then these men have been bound in their coats, their tunics, and their turbans, and their clothing, and have been cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace.

22 Therefore, because that the word of the king is urgent, and the furnace heated exceedingly, those men who have taken up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego--killed them hath the spark of the fire.

23 And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, have fallen down in the midst of the burning fiery furnace--bound.

24 Then Nebuchadnezzar the king hath been astonished, and hath risen in haste; he hath answered and said to his counsellors, `Have we not cast three men into the midst of the fire-- bound?' They have answered and are saying to the king, `Certainly, O king.'

25 He answered and hath said, `Lo, I am seeing four men loose, walking in the midst of the fire, and they have no hurt; and the appearance of the fourth [is] like to a son of the gods.'

26 Then Nebuchadnezzar hath drawn near to the gate of the burning fiery furnace; he hath answered and said, `Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, servants of God Most High come forth, yea, come;' then come forth do Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego,from the midst of the fire;

27 and gathered together, the satraps, the prefects, and the governors, and the counsellors of the king, are seeing these men, that the fire hath no power over their bodies, and the hair of their head hath not been singed, and their coats have not changed, and the smell of fire hath not passed on them.

28 Nebuchadnezzar hath answered and hath said, `Blessed [is] the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, who hath sent His messenger, and hath delivered His servants who trusted on Him, and the word of the king changed, and gave up their bodies that they might not serve nor do obeisance to any god except to their own God.

29 And by me a decree is made, that any people, nation, and language, that doth speak erroneously concerning the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, pieces he is made, and its house is made a dunghill, because that there is no other god whois able thus to deliver.'

30 Then the king hath caused Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, to prosper in the province of Babylon.

Daniel 4

1 `Nebuchadnezzar the king to all peoples, nations, and languages, who are dwelling in all the earth: Your peace be great!

2 The signs and wonders that God Most High hath done with me, it is good before me to shew.

3 His signs how great! and His wonders how mighty! His kingdom [is] a kingdom ageduring, and His rule [is] with generation and generation.

4 `I, Nebuchadnezzar, have been at rest in my house, and flourishing in my palace:

5 a dream I have seen, and it maketh me afraid, and the conceptions on my bed, and the visions of my head, do trouble me.

6 And by me a decree is made, to cause all the wise men of Babylon to come up before me, that the interpretation of the dream they may cause me to know.

7 Then coming up are the scribes, the enchanters, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers, and the dream I have told before them, and its interpretation they are not making known to me.

8 And at last come up before me hath Daniel, whose name [is] Belteshazzar--according to the name of my god--and in whom [is] the spirit of the holy gods, and the dream before him I have told:

9 `O Belteshazzar, master of the scribes, as I have known that the spirit of the holy gods [is] in thee, and no secret doth press thee, the visions of my dream that I have seen, and its interpretation, tell.

10 As to the visions of my head on my bed, I was looking, and lo, a tree in the midst of the earth, and its height [is] great:

11 become great hath the tree, yea, strong, and its height doth reach to the heavens, and its vision to the end of the whole land;

12 its leaves [are] fair, and its budding great, and food for all [is] in it: under it take shade doth the beast of the field, and in its boughs dwell do the birds of the heavens, and of it fed are all flesh.

13 `I was looking, in the visions of my head on my bed, and lo, a sifter, even a holy one, from the heavens is coming down.

14 He is calling mightily, and thus hath said, Cut down the tree, and cut off its branches, shake off its leaves, and scatter its budding, move away let the beast from under it, and the birds from off its branches;

15 but the stump of its roots leave in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field, and with the dew of the heavens is it wet, and with the beasts [is] his portion in the herb of the earth;

16 his heart from man's is changed, and the heart of a beast is given to him, and seven times pass over him;

17 by the decree of the sifters [is] the sentence, and by the saying of the holy ones the requirement, to the intent that the living may know that the Most High is ruler in the kingdom of men, and to whom He willeth He giveth it, and the lowest of men He doth raise up over it.

18 `This dream I have seen, I king Nebuchadnezzar; and thou, O Belteshazzar, the interpretation tell, because that all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to cause me to know the interpretation, and thou [art] able, for the spirit of the holy gods [is] in thee.

19 `Then Daniel, whose name [is] Belteshazzar, hath been astonished about one hour, and his thoughts do trouble him; the king hath answered and said, O Belteshazzar, let not the dream and its interpretation trouble thee. Belteshazzar hath answered and said, My lord, the dream--to those hating thee, and its interpretation--to thine enemies!

20 The tree that thou hast seen, that hath become great and strong, and its height doth reach to the heavens, and its vision to all the land,

21 and its leaves [are] fair, and its budding great, and food for all [is] in it, under it dwell doth the beast of the field, and on its boughs sit do the birds of the heavens.

22 `Thou it [is], O king, for thou hast become great and mighty, and thy greatness hath become great, and hath reached to the heavens, and thy dominion to the end of the earth;

23 and that which the king hath seen--a sifter, even a holy one, coming down from the heavens, and he hath said, Cut down the tree, and destroy it; but the stump of its roots leave in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field, and with the dew of the heavens it is wet, and with the beast of the field [is] his portion, till that seven times pass over him.

24 `This [is] the interpretation, O king, and the decree of the Most High it [is] that hath come against my lord the king:

25 and they are driving thee away from men, and with the beast of the field is thy dwelling, and the herb as oxen they do cause thee to eat, and by the dew of the heavens they are wetting thee, and seven times do pass over thee, till that thou knowest that the Most High is ruler in the kingdom of men, and to whom He willeth He giveth it.

26 And that which they said--to leave the stump of the roots of the tree; thy kingdom for thee abideth, after that thou knowest that the heavens are ruling.

27 `Therefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable unto thee, and thy sins by righteousness break off, and thy perversity by pitying the poor, lo, it is a lengthening of thine ease.

28 `All--hath come on Nebuchadnezzar the king.

29 `At the end of twelve months, on the palace of the kingdom of Babylon he hath been walking;

30 the king hath answered and said, Is not this that great Babylon that I have built, for the house of the kingdom, in the might of my strength, and for the glory of mine honour?

31 `While the word is [in] the king's mouth a voice from the heavens hath fallen: To thee they are saying: O Nebuchadnezzar the king, the kingdom hath passed from thee,

32 and from men they are driving thee away, and with the beast of the field [is] thy dwelling, the herb as oxen they do cause thee to eat, and seven times do pass over thee, till that thou knowest that the Most High is ruler in the kingdom of men, and to whom He willeth He giveth it.

33 `In that hour the thing hath been fulfilled on Nebuchadnezzar, and from men he is driven, and the herb as oxen he eateth, and by the dew of the heavens his body is wet, till that his hair as eagles' hath become great, and his nails as birds.'

34 `And at the end of the days I, Nebuchadnezzar, mine eyes to the heavens have lifted up, and mine understanding unto me returneth, and the Most High I have blessed, and the Ageduring Living One I have praised and honoured, whose dominion [is] a dominion age-during, and His kingdom with generation and generation;

35 and all who are dwelling on the earth as nothing are reckoned, and according to his will He is doing among the forces of the heavens and those dwelling on the earth, and there is none that doth clap with his hand, and saith to Him, What hast Thou done?

36 `At that time my understanding doth return unto me, and for the glory of my kingdom, my honour and my brightness doth return unto me, and to me my counsellors and my great men do seek, and over my kingdom I have been made right, and abundant greatness hath been added to me.

37 `Now, I, Nebuchadnezzar, am praising and exalting and honouring the King of the heavens, for all His works [are] truth, and His paths judgment, and those walking in pride He is able to humble.'

Daniel 7

1 In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon, Daniel hath seen a dream, and the visions of his head on his bed, then the dream he hath written, the chief of the things he hath said.

2 Answered hath Daniel and said, `I was seeing in my vision by night, and lo, the four winds of the heavens are coming forth to the great sea;

3 and four great beasts are coming up from the sea, diverse one from another.

4 The first [is] like a lion, and it hath an eagle's wings. I was seeing till that its wings have been plucked, and it hath been lifted up from the earth, and on feet as a man it hath been caused to stand, and a heart of man is given to it.

5 And lo, another beast, a second, like to a bear, and to the same authority it hath been raised, and three ribs [are] in its mouth, between its teeth, and thus they are saying to it, Rise, consume much flesh.

6 `After this I was seeing, and lo, another like a leopard, and it hath four wings of a fowl on its back, and four heads hath the beast, and dominion is given to it.

7 `After this I was seeing in the visions of the night, and lo, a fourth beast, terrible and fearful, and exceedingly strong; and it hath iron teeth very great, it hath consumed, yea, it doth break small, and the remnant with its feet it hath trampled; and it [is] diverse from all the beasts that [are] before it; and it hath ten horns.

8 `I was considering about the horns, and lo, another horn, a little one, hath come up between them, and three of the first horns have been eradicated from before it, and lo, eyes as the eyes of man [are] in this horn, and a mouth speaking greatthings.

9 `I was seeing till that thrones have been thrown down, and the Ancient of Days is seated, His garment as snow [is] white, and the hair of his head [is] as pure wool, His throne flames of fire, its wheels burning fire.

10 A flood of fire is proceeding and coming forth from before Him, a thousand thousands do serve Him, and a myriad of myriads before Him do rise up, the Judge is seated, and the books have been opened.

11 `I was seeing, then, because of the voice of the great words that the horn is speaking, I was seeing till that the beast is slain, and his body hath been destroyed, and given to the burning fire;

12 and the rest of the beasts have caused their dominion to pass away, and a prolongation in life is given to them, till a season and a time.

13 `I was seeing in the visions of the night, and lo, with the clouds of the heavens as a son of man was [one] coming, and unto the Ancient of Days he hath come, and before Him they have brought him near.

14 And to him is given dominion, and glory, and a kingdom, and all peoples, nations, and languages do serve him, his dominion [is] a dominion age-during, that passeth not away, and his kingdom that which is not destroyed.

15 `Pierced hath been my spirit--I, Daniel--in the midst of the sheath, and the visions of my head trouble me;

16 I have drawn near unto one of those standing, and the certainty I seek from him of all this; and he hath said to me, yea, the interpretation of the things he hath caused me to know:

17 `These great beasts, that [are] four, [are] four kings, they rise up from the earth;

18 and receive the kingdom do the saints of the Most High, and they strengthen the kingdom unto the age, even unto the age of the ages.

19 `Then I wished for certainty concerning the fourth beast, that was diverse from them all, fearful exceedingly; its teeth of iron, and its nails of brass, it hath devoured, it doth break small, and the remnant with its feet it hath trampled;

20 and concerning the ten horns that [are] in its heads, and of the other that came up, and before which three have fallen, even of that horn that hath eyes, and a mouth speaking great things, and whose appearance [is] great above its companions.

21 `I was seeing, and this horn is making war with the saints, and hath prevailed over them,

22 till that the Ancient of Days hath come, and judgment is given to the saints of the Most High, and the time hath come, and the saints have strengthened the kingdom.

23 `Thus he said: The fourth beast is the fourth kingdom in the earth, that is diverse from all kingdoms, and it consumeth all the earth, and treadeth it down, and breaketh it small.

24 And the ten horns out of the kingdom [are] ten kings, they rise, and another doth rise after them, and it is diverse from the former, and three kings it humbleth;

25 and words as an adversary of the Most High it doth speak, and the saints of the Most High it doth wear out, and it hopeth to change seasons and law; and they are given into its hand, till a time, and times, and a division of a time.

26 `And the Judge is seated, and its dominion they cause to pass away, to cut off, and to destroy--unto the end;

27 and the kingdom, and the dominion, even the greatness of the kingdom under the whole heavens, is given to the people--the saints of the Most High, His kingdom [is] a kingdom age-during, and all dominions do serve and obey Him.

28 `Hitherto [is] the end of the matter. I, Daniel, greatly do my thoughts trouble me, and my countenance is changed on me, and the matter in my heart I have kept.

Daniel 8

1 `In the third year of the reign of Belshazzar the king, a vision hath appeared unto me--I

2 And I see in a vision, and it cometh to pass, in my seeing, and I [am] in Shushan the palace that [is] in Elam the province, and I see in a vision, and I have been by the stream Ulai.

3 And I lift up mine eyes, and look, and lo, a certain ram is standing before the stream, and it hath two horns, and the two horns [are] high; and the one [is] higher than the other, and the high one is coming up last.

4 I have seen the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward, and no living creatures do stand before it, and there is none delivering out of its hand, and it hath done according to its pleasure, and hath exerted itself.

5 `And I have been considering, and lo, a young he-goat hath come from the west, over the face of the whole earth, whom none is touching in the earth; as to the young he-goat, a conspicuous horn [is] between its eyes.

6 And it cometh unto the ram possessing the two horns, that I had seen standing before the stream, and runneth unto it in the fury of its power.

7 And I have seen it coming near the ram, and it becometh embittered at it, and smiteth the ram, and breaketh its two horns, and there hath been no power in the ram to stand before it, and it casteth it to the earth, and trampleth it down, and there hath been no deliverer to the ram out of its power.

8 `And the young he-goat hath exerted itself very much, and when it is strong, broken hath been the great horn; and come up doth a vision of four in its place, at the four winds of the heavens.

9 And from the one of them come forth hath a little horn, and it exerteth itself greatly toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the beauteous [land];

10 yea, it exerteth unto the host of the heavens, and causeth to fall to the earth of the host, and of the stars, and trampleth them down.

11 And unto the prince of the host it exerteth itself, and by it taken away hath been the continual [sacrifice], and thrown down the base of his sanctuary.

12 And the host is given up, with the continual [sacrifice], through transgression, and it throweth down truth to the earth, and it hath worked, and prospered.

13 `And I hear a certain holy one speaking, and a certain holy one saith to the wonderful numberer who is speaking: Till when [is] the vision of the continual [sacrifice], and of the transgression, an astonishment, to make both sanctuary and host a treading down?

14 And he saith unto me, Till evening--morning two thousand and three hundred, then is the holy place declared right.

15 `And it cometh to pass in my seeing--I, Daniel--the vision, that I require understanding, and lo, standing over-against me [is] as the appearance of a mighty one.

16 And I hear a voice of man between [the banks of] Ulai, and he calleth and saith: Gabriel, cause this [one] to understand the appearance.

17 And he cometh in near my station, and at his coming in I have been afraid, and I fall on my face, and he saith unto me: Understand, son of man, for at the time of the end [is] the vision.

18 And in his speaking with me, I have been in a trance on my face, on the earth; and he cometh against me, and causeth me to stand on my station,

19 and saith: Lo, I--I am causing thee to know that which is in the latter end of the indignation; for, at the appointed time [is] the end.

20 `The ram that thou hast seen possessing two horns, [are] the kings of Media and Persia.

21 And the young he-goat, the hairy one, [is] the king of Javan; and the great horn that [is] between its eyes is the first king;

22 and that being broken, stand up do four in its place, four kingdoms from the nation do stand up, and not in its power.

23 `And in the latter end of their kingdom, about the perfecting of the transgressors, stand up doth a king, fierce of face, and understanding hidden things;

24 and his power hath been mighty, and not by his own power; and wonderful things he destroyeth, and he hath prospered, and wrought, and destroyed mighty ones, and the people of the Holy Ones.

25 `And by his understanding he hath also caused deceit to prosper in his hand, and in his heart he exerteth himself, and by ease he destroyeth many; and against the prince of princes he standeth--and without hand he is broken.

26 And the appearance of the evening and of the morning, that is told, is true; and thou, hide thou the vision, for [it is] after many days.'

27 And I, Daniel, have been, yea, I became sick [for] days, and I rise, and do the king's work, and am astonished at the appearance, and there is none understanding.

Daniel 10

1 In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia, a thing is revealed to Daniel, whose name is called Belteshazzar, and the thing [is] true, and the warfare [is] great: and he hath understood the thing, and hath understanding about the appearance.

2 `In those days, I, Daniel, have been mourning three weeks of days;

3 desirable bread I have not eaten, and flesh and wine hath not come in unto my mouth, and I have not anointed myself at all, till the completion of three weeks of days.

4 `And in the twenty and fourth day of the first month, I have been by the side of the great river, that [is] Hiddekel:

5 and I lift up mine eyes, and look, and lo, a certain one clothed in linen, and his loins girt with pure gold of Uphaz,

6 and his body as a beryl, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as lamps of fire, and his arms and his feet as the aspect of bright brass, and the voice of his words as the voice of a multitude.

7 `And I have seen--I, Daniel, by myself--the appearance: and the men who have been with me have not seen the appearance, but a great trembling hath fallen on them, and they flee to be hidden;

8 and I have been left by myself, and I see this great appearance, and there hath been no power left in me, and my honour hath been turned in me to corruption, yea, I have not retained power.

9 `And I hear the voice of his words, and when I hear the voice of his words, then I have been in a trance on my face, and my face [is] to the earth;

10 and lo, a hand hath come against me, and shaketh me on my knees and the palms of my hands.

11 `And he saith unto me: Daniel, man greatly desired, attend to the words that I am speaking unto thee, and stand on thy station, for now I have been sent unto thee. `And when he speaketh with me this word, I have stood trembling.

12 And he saith unto me: Do not fear, Daniel, for from the first day that thou didst give thy heart to understand, and to humble thyself before thy God, thy words have been heard, and I have come because of thy words.

13 `And the head of the kingdom of Persia is standing over-against me twenty and one days, and lo, Michael, first of the chief heads, hath come in to help me, and I have remained there near the kings of Persia;

14 and I have come to cause thee to understand that which doth happen to thy people in the latter end of the days, for yet the vision [is] after days.

15 `And when he speaketh with me about these things, I have set my face toward the earth, and have been silent;

16 and lo, as the manner of the sons of men, he is striking against my lips, and I open my mouth, and I speak, and say unto him who is standing over-against me: My lord, by the appearance turned have been my pangs against me, and I have retained no power.

17 And how is the servant of this my lord able to speak with this my lord? as for me, henceforth there remaineth in me no power, yea, breath hath not been left in me.

18 `And he addeth, and striketh against me, as the appearance of a man, and strengtheneth me,

19 and he saith: Do not fear, O man greatly desired, peace to thee, be strong, yea, be strong; and when he speaketh with me, I have strengthened myself, and I say, Let my lord speak, for thou hast strengthened me.

20 And he saith, Hast thou known why I have come unto thee? and now I turn back to fight with the head of Persia; yea, I am going forth, and lo, the head of Javan hath come;

21 but I declare to thee that which is noted down in the Writing of Truth, and there is not one strengthening himself with me, concerning these, except Michael your head.

Daniel 11

1 `And I, in the first year of Darius the Mede, my standing [is] for a strengthener, and for a stronghold to him;

2 and, now, truth I declare to thee, Lo, yet three kings are standing for Persia, and the fourth doth become far richer than all, and according to his strength by his riches he stirreth up the whole, with the kingdom of Javan.

3 And a mighty king hath stood, and he hath ruled a great dominion, and hath done according to his will;

4 and according to his standing is his kingdom broken, and divided to the four winds of the heavens, and not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion that he ruled, for his kingdom is plucked up--and for others apart from these.

5 `And a king of the south--even of his princes--doth become strong, and doth prevail against him, and hath ruled; a great dominion [is] his dominion.

6 `And at the end of years they do join themselves together, and a daughter of the king of the south doth come in unto the king of the north to do upright things; and she doth not retain the power of the arm; and he doth not stand, nor his arm;and she is given up, she, and those bringing her in, and her child, and he who is strengthening her in [these] times.

7 `And [one] hath stood up from a branch of her roots, [in] his station, and he cometh in unto the bulwark, yea, he cometh into a stronghold of the king of the south, and hath wrought against them, and hath done mightily;

8 and also their gods, with their princes, with their desirable vessels of silver and gold, into captivity he bringeth [into] Egypt; and he doth stand more years than the king of the north.

9 `And the king of the south hath come into the kingdom, and turned back unto his own land;

10 and his sons stir themselves up, and have gathered a multitude of great forces, and he hath certainly come in, and overflowed, and passed through, and he turneth back, and they stir themselves up unto his stronghold.

11 And the king of the south doth become embittered, and hath gone forth and fought with him, with the king of the north, and hath caused a great multitude to stand, and the multitude hath been given into his hand,

12 and he hath carried away the multitude, his heart is high, and he hath caused myriads to fall, and he doth not become strong.

13 `And the king of the north hath turned back, and hath caused a multitude to stand, greater than the first, and at the end of the times a second time he doth certainly come in with a great force, and with much substance;

14 and in those times many do stand up against the king of the south, and sons of the destroyers of thy people do lift themselves up to establish the vision--and they have stumbled.

15 `And the king of the north cometh in, and poureth out a mount, and hath captured fenced cities; and the arms of the south do not stand, nor the people of his choice, yea, there is no power to stand.

16 And he who is coming unto him doth according to his will, and there is none standing before him; and he standeth in the desirable land, and [it is] wholly in his hand.

17 And he setteth his face to go in with the strength of his whole kingdom, and upright ones with him; and he hath wrought, and the daughter of women he giveth to him, to corrupt her; and she doth not stand, nor is for him.

18 `And he turneth back his face to the isles, and hath captured many; and a prince hath caused his reproach of himself to cease; without his reproach he turneth [it] back to him.

19 And he turneth back his face to the strongholds of his land, and hath stumbled and fallen, and is not found.

20 `And stood up on his station hath [one] causing an exactor to pass over the honour of the kingdom, and in a few days he is destroyed, and not in anger, nor in battle.

21 `And stood up on his station hath a despicable one, and they have not given unto him the honour of the kingdom, and he hath come in quietly, and hath strengthened the kingdom by flatteries.

22 And the arms of the flood are overflowed from before him, and are broken; and also the leader of the covenant.

23 And after they join themselves unto him, he worketh deceit, and hath increased, and hath been strong by a few of the nation.

24 Peaceably even into the fertile places of the province He cometh, and he hath done that which his fathers did not, nor his fathers' fathers; prey, and spoil, and substance, to them he scattereth, and against fenced places he deviseth his devices, even for a time.

25 `And he stirreth up his power and his heart against the king of the south with a great force, and the king of the south stirreth himself up to battle with a very great and mighty force, and standeth not, for they devise devices against him,

26 and those eating his portion of food destroy him, and his force overfloweth, and fallen have many wounded.

27 `And both of the kings' hearts [are] to do evil, and at one table they speak lies, and it doth not prosper, for yet the end [is] at a time appointed.

28 And he turneth back [to] his land with great substance, and his heart [is] against the holy covenant, and he hath wrought, and turned back to his land.

29 At the appointed time he turneth back, and hath come against the south, and it is not as the former, and as the latter.

30 And ships of Chittim have come in against him, and he hath been pained, and hath turned back, and hath been insolent toward the holy covenant, and hath wrought, and turned back, and he understandeth concerning those forsaking the holy covenant.

31 And strong ones out of him stand up, and have polluted the sanctuary, the stronghold, and have turned aside the continual [sacrifice], and appointed the desolating abomination.

32 And those acting wickedly [against] the covenant, he defileth by flatteries; and the people knowing their God are strong, and have wrought.

33 And the teachers of the people give understanding to many; and they have stumbled by sword, and by flame, by captivity, and by spoil--days.

34 And in their stumbling, they are helped--a little help, and joined to them have been many with flatteries.

35 And some of the teachers do stumble for refining by them, and for purifying, and for making white--till the end of the time, for [it is] yet for a time appointed.

36 `And the king hath done according to his will, and exalteth himself, and magnifieth himself against every god, and against the God of gods he speaketh wonderful things, and hath prospered till the indignation hath been completed, for that which is determined hath been done.

37 And unto the God of his fathers he doth not attend, nor to the desire of women, yea, to any god he doth not attend, for against all he magnifieth himself.

38 And to the god of strongholds, on his station, he giveth honour; yea, to a god whom his fathers knew not he giveth honour, with gold, and with silver, and with precious stone, and with desirable things.

39 And he hath dealt in the fortresses of the strongholds with a strange god whom he hath acknowledged; he multiplieth honour, and hath caused them to rule over many, and the ground he apportioneth at a price.

40 `And at the time of the end, push himself forward with him doth a king of the south, and storm against him doth a king of the north, with chariot, and with horsemen, and with many ships; and he hath come in to the lands, and hath overflowed,and passed over,

41 and hath come into the desirable land, and many do stumble, and these escape from his hand: Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the sons of Ammon.

42 `And he sendeth forth his hand upon the lands, and the land of Egypt is not for an escape;

43 and he hath ruled over treasures of gold and of silver, and over all the desirable things of Egypt, and Lubim and Cushim [are] at his steps.

44 `And reports trouble him out of the east and out of the north, and he hath gone forth in great fury to destroy, and to devote many to destruction;

45 and he planteth the tents of his palace between the seas and the holy desirable mountain, and hath come unto his end, and there is no helper to him.

Hosea 2

1 `Say ye to your brethren--Ammi, And to your sisters--Ruhamah.

2 Plead ye with your mother--plead, (For she [is] not My wife, and I [am] not her husband,) And she turneth her whoredoms from before her, And her adulteries from between her breasts,

3 Lest I strip her naked. And have set her up as [in] the day of her birth, And have made her as a wilderness, And have set her as a dry land, And have put her to death with thirst.

4 And her sons I do not pity, For sons of whoredoms [are] they,

5 For gone a-whoring hath their mother, Acted shamefully hath their conceiver, For she hath said, I go after my lovers, Those giving my bread and my water, My wool and my flax, my oil and my drink.

6 Therefore, lo, I am hedging up thy way with thorns, And I have made for her a wall, And her paths she doth not find.

7 And she hath pursued her lovers, And she doth not overtake them, And hath sought them, and doth not find, And she hath said: I go, and I turn back unto My first husband, For--better to me then than now.

8 And she knew not that I had given to her, The corn, and the new wine, and the oil. Yea, silver I did multiply to her, And the gold they prepared for Baal.

9 Therefore do I turn back, And I have taken My corn in its season, And My new wine in its appointed time, And I have taken away My wool and My flax, covering her nakedness.

10 And now do I reveal her dishonour before the eyes of her lovers, And none doth deliver her out of My hand.

11 And I have caused to cease all her joy, Her festival, her new moon, and her sabbath, Even all her appointed times,

12 And made desolate her vine and her fig-tree, Of which she said, A gift they [are] to me, That my lovers have given to me, And I have made them for a forest, And consumed them hath a beast of the field.

13 And I have charged on her the days of the Baalim, To whom she maketh perfume, And putteth on her ring and her ornament, And goeth after her lovers, And Me forgat--an affirmation of Jehovah.

14 Therefore, lo, I am enticing her, And have caused her to go to the wilderness, And I have spoken unto her heart,

15 And given to her her vineyards from thence, And the valley of Achor for an opening of hope, And she hath responded there as in the days of her youth, And as in the day of her coming up out of the land of Egypt.

16 And it hath come to pass, in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah, Thou dost call Me-- My husband, And dost not call Me any more--My lord.

17 And I have turned aside the names of the lords from her mouth, And they are not remembered any more by their name.

18 And I have made to them a covenant in that day, with the beast of the field, And with the fowl of the heavens, And the creeping thing of the ground, And bow, and sword, and war I break from off the land, And have caused them to lie down confidently.

19 And I have betrothed thee to Me to the age, And betrothed thee to Me in righteousness, And in judgment, and kindness, and mercies,

20 And betrothed thee to Me in faithfulness, And thou hast known Jehovah.

21 And it hath come to pass in that day, I answer--an affirmation of Jehovah, I answer the heavens, and they answer the earth.

22 And the earth doth answer the corn, And the new wine, and the oil, And they answer Jezreel.

23 And I have sowed her to Me in the land, And I have pitied Lo-Ruhamah, And I have said to Lo-Ammi, My people thou [art], and it saith, My God!'

Hosea 4

1 `Hear a word of Jehovah, sons of Israel, For a strife [is] to Jehovah with inhabitants of the land, For there is no truth, nor kindness, Nor knowledge of God, in the land,

2 Swearing, and lying, and murdering, And stealing, and committing adultery--have increased, And blood against blood hath touched.

3 Therefore mourn doth the land, And weak is every dweller in it, With the beast of the field, And with the fowl of the heavens, And the fishes of the sea--they are removed.

4 Only, let no one strive, nor reprove a man, And thy people [are] as those striving with a priest.

5 And thou hast stumbled in the day, And stumbled hath also a prophet with thee in the night, And I have cut off thy mother.

6 Cut off have been My people for lack of knowledge, Because thou knowledge hast rejected, I reject thee from being priest to Me, And thou forgettest the law of thy God, I forget thy sons, I also!

7 According to their abundance so they sinned against Me, Their honour into shame I change.

8 The sin of My people they do eat, And unto their iniquity lift up their soul.

9 And it hath been, like people, like priest, And I have charged on it its ways, And its habitual doings I return to it.

10 And they have eaten, and are not satisfied, They have gone a-whoring, and increase not, For they have left off taking heed to Jehovah.

11 Whoredom, and wine, and new wine, take the heart,

12 My people at its staff asketh and its rod declareth to it, For a spirit of whoredoms hath caused to err, And they go a-whoring from under their God.

13 On tops of the mountains they do sacrifice, And on the hills they make perfume, Under oak, and poplar, and terebinth, For good [is] its shade.

14 Therefore commit whoredom do your daughters, And your spouses commit adultery, I do not see after your daughters when they commit whoredom, And after your spouses when they commit adultery, For they with the harlots are separated, And with thewhores they do sacrifice, A people that doth not understand kicketh.

15 Though a harlot thou [art], O Israel, Let not Judah become guilty, And come not ye in to Gilgal, nor go up to Beth-Aven, Nor swear ye, Jehovah liveth.

16 For as a refractory heifer hath Israel turned aside, Now doth Jehovah feed them as a lamb in a large place.

17 Joined to idols [is] Ephraim, let him alone.

18 Sour [is] their drink, They have gone diligently a-whoring, Her protectors have loved shame thoroughly.

19 Distressed her hath wind with its wings, And they are ashamed of their sacrifices!

Hosea 5

1 `Hear this, O priests, and attend, O house of Israel, And, O house of the king, give ear, For the judgment [is] for you, For, a snare ye have been on Mizpah, And a net spread out on Tabor.

2 And to slaughter sinners have gone deep, And I [am] a fetter to them all.

3 I have known Ephraim, And Israel hath not been hid from me, For now thou hast gone a-whoring, Ephraim, Defiled is Israel.

4 They give not up their habitual doings, To turn back unto their God, For a spirit of whoredoms [is] in their midst, And Jehovah they have not known.

5 And humbled hath been the excellency of Israel to his face, And Israel and Ephraim stumble by their iniquity, Stumbled also hath Judah with them.

6 With their flock and with their herd, They go to seek Jehovah, and do not find, He hath withdrawn from them.

7 Against Jehovah they dealt treacherously, For strange sons they have begotten, Now consume them doth a month [with] their portions.

8 Blow ye a cornet in Gibeah, a trumpet in Ramah, Shout, O Beth-Aven, after thee, O Benjamin.

9 Ephraim is for a desolation in a day of reproof, Among the tribes of Israel I have made known a sure thing.

10 Princes of Judah have been as those removing a border, On them I do pour out as water My wrath.

11 Oppressed is Ephraim, broken in judgment, When he pleased he went after the command.

12 And I [am] as a moth to Ephraim, And as a rotten thing to the house of Judah.

13 And see doth Ephraim his sickness, and Judah his wound, And Ephraim goeth unto Asshur, And sendeth unto a warlike king, And he is not able to give healing to you, Nor doth he remove from you a scar.

14 For I [am] as a lion to Ephraim, And as a young lion to the house of Judah, I--I tear and go, I bear away, and there is no deliverer.

15 I go--I turn back unto My place, Till that they are desolate, and have sought My face. In their distress they do seek Me speedily!'

Hosea 6

1 `Come, and we turn back unto Jehovah, For He hath torn, and He doth heal us, He doth smite, and He bindeth us up.

2 He doth revive us after two days, In the third day He doth raise us up, And we live before Him.

3 And we know--we pursue to know Jehovah, As the dawn prepared is His going forth, And He cometh in as a shower to us, As gathered rain--sprinkling earth.'

4 What do I do to thee, O Ephraim? What do I do to thee, O Judah? Your goodness [is] as a cloud of the morning, And as dew rising early--going.

5 Therefore I have hewed by prophets, I have slain them by sayings of My mouth, And My judgments to the light goeth forth.

6 For kindness I desired, and not sacrifice, And a knowledge of God above burntofferings.

7 And they, as Adam, transgressed a covenant, There they dealt treacherously against me.

8 Gilead [is] a city of workers of iniquity, Slippery from blood.

9 And as bands do wait for a man, A company of priests do murder--the way to Shechem, For wickedness they have done.

10 In the house of Israel I have seen a horrible thing, There [is] the whoredom of Ephraim--defiled is Israel.

11 Also, O Judah, appointed is a harvest to thee, In My turning back [to] the captivity of My people!

Hosea 7

1 `When I give healing to Israel, Then revealed is the iniquity of Ephraim, And the wickedness of Samaria, For they have wrought falsehood, And a thief doth come in, Stript off hath a troop in the street,

2 And they do not say to their heart, [That] all their evil I have remembered, Now compassed them have their doings, Over-against My face they have been.

3 With their wickedness they make glad a king, And with their lies--princes.

4 All of them [are] adulterers, Like a burning oven of a baker, He ceaseth from stirring up after kneading the dough, till its leavening.

5 A day of our king! Princes have polluted themselves [with] the poison of wine, He hath drawn out his hand with scorners.

6 For they have drawn near, As an oven [is] their heart, In their lying in wait all the night sleep doth their baker, Morning! he is burning as a flaming fire.

7 All of them are warm as an oven, And they have devoured their judges, All their kings have fallen, There is none calling unto Me among them.

8 Ephraim! among peoples he mixeth himself, Ephraim hath been a cake unturned.

9 Devoured have strangers his power, And he hath not known, Also old age hath sprinkled [itself] on him, And he hath not known.

10 And humbled hath been the excellency of Israel to his face, And they have not turned back unto Jehovah their God, Nor have they sought Him for all this.

11 And Ephraim is as a simple dove without heart, Egypt they called on--[to] Asshur they have gone.

12 When they go I spread over them My net, As the fowl of the heavens I bring them down, I chastise them as their company hath heard.

13 Woe to them, for they wandered from Me, Destruction to them, for they transgressed against Me, And I--I ransom them, and they have spoken lies against Me,

14 And have not cried unto Me with their heart, but howl on their beds, For corn and new wine they assemble themselves, They turn aside against Me.

15 And I instructed--I strengthened their arms, And concerning Me they think evil!

16 They turn back--not to the Most High, They have been as a deceitful bow, Fall by sword do their princes, From the insolence of their tongue, This [is] their derision in the land of Egypt!

Hosea 8

1 `Unto thy mouth--a trumpet, As an eagle against the house of Jehovah, Because they transgressed My covenant, And against My law they have rebelled.

2 To Me they cry, `My God, we--Israel--have known Thee.'

3 Cast off good hath Israel, an enemy pursueth him.

4 They have made kings, and not by Me, They have made princes, and I have not known, Their silver and their gold they have made to them idols, So that they are cut off.

5 Cast off hath thy calf, O Samaria, Burned hath Mine anger against them, Till when are they not capable of purity?

6 For even it [is] of Israel; an artificer made it, And it [is] not God, For the calf of Samaria is fragments!

7 For wind they sow, and a hurricane they reap, Stalk it hath none--a shoot not yielding grain, If so be it yield--strangers do swallow it up.

8 Israel hath been swallowed up, Now they have been among nations, As a vessel in which is no delight.

9 For they--they have gone up [to] Asshur, A wild ass alone by himself [is] Ephraim, They have hired lovers!

10 Also though they hire among nations, Now I gather them, and they are pained a little, From the burden of a king of princes.

11 Because Ephraim did multiply altars to sin, They have been to him altars to sin.

12 I write for him numerous things of My law, As a strange thing they have been reckoned.

13 The sacrifices of Mine offerings! They sacrifice flesh, and they eat, Jehovah hath not accepted them, Now doth He remember their iniquity, And inspect their sin, They--[to] Egypt they turn back.

14 And forget doth Israel his Maker, and buildeth temples, And Judah hath multiplied cities of defence, And I have sent a fire into his cities, And it hath consumed their palaces!

Hosea 9

1 `Rejoice not, O Israel, be not joyful like the peoples, For thou hast gone a-whoring from thy God, Thou hast loved a gift near all floors of corn.

2 Floor and wine-press do not delight them, And new wine doth fail in her,

3 They do not abide in the land of Jehovah, And turned back hath Ephraim [to] Egypt, And in Asshur an unclean thing they eat.

4 They pour not out wine to Jehovah, Nor are they sweet to Him, Their sacrifices [are] as bread of mourners to them, All eating it are unclean: For their bread [is] for themselves, It doth not come into the house of Jehovah.

5 What do ye at the day appointed? And at the day of Jehovah's festival?

6 For, lo, they have gone because of destruction, Egypt gathereth them, Moph burieth them, The desirable things of their silver, Nettles possess them--a thorn [is] in their tents.

7 Come in have the days of inspection, Come in have the days of recompence, Israel doth know! a fool [is] the prophet, Mad [is] the man of the Spirit, Because of the abundance of thine iniquity, And great [is] the hatred.

8 Ephraim is looking [away] from My God, The prophet! a snare of a fowler [is] over all his ways, Hatred [is] in the house of his God.

9 They have gone deep--have done corruptly, As [in] the days of Gibeah, He doth remember their iniquity, He doth inspect their sins.

10 As grapes in a wilderness I found Israel, As the first-fruit in a fig-tree, at its beginning, I have seen your fathers, They--they have gone in [to] Baal-Peor, And are separated to a shameful thing, And are become abominable like their love.

11 Ephraim [is] as a fowl, Fly away doth their honour, without birth, And without womb, and without conception.

12 For though they nourish their sons, I have made them childless--without man, Surely also, woe to them, when I turn aside from them.

13 Ephraim! when I have looked to the rock, Is planted in comeliness, And Ephraim [is] to bring out unto a slayer his sons.

14 Give to them, Jehovah--what dost Thou give? Give to them miscarrying womb, and dry breasts.

15 All their evil [is] in Gilgal, Surely there I have hated them, Because of the evil of their doings, Out of My house I do drive them, I add not to love them, all their heads [are] apostates.

16 Ephraim hath been smitten, Their root hath dried up, fruit they yield not, Yea, though they bring forth, I have put to death the desired of their womb.

17 Reject them doth my God, Because they have not hearkened to Him, And they are wanderers among nations!

Hosea 10

1 `An empty vine [is] Israel, Fruit he maketh like to himself, According to the abundance of his fruit, He hath multiplied for the altars, According to the goodness of his land, They have made goodly standing-pillars.

2 Their heart hath been divided, now they are guilty, He doth break down their altars, He doth destroy their standing-pillars.

3 For now they say: We have no king, Because we have not feared Jehovah, And the king--what doth he for us?

4 They have spoken words, To swear falsehood in making a covenant, And flourished as a poisonous herb hath judgment, on the furrows of a field.

5 For the calves of Beth-Aven fear do inhabitants of Samaria, Surely mourned on account of it hath its people, And its priests on account of it leap about, Because of its honour, for it hath removed from it,

6 Also it to Asshur is carried, a present to a warlike king, Shame doth Ephraim receive, And ashamed is Israel of its own counsel.

7 Cut off is Samaria! Its king [is] as a chip on the face of the waters.

8 And destroyed have been high places of Aven, the sin of Israel. Thorn and bramble go up on their altars, And they have said to hills, Cover us, And to heights, Fall upon us.

9 From the days of Gibeah thou hast sinned, O Israel, There they have stood, Not overtake them in Gibeah doth battle, Because of sons of perverseness.

10 When I desire, then I do bind them, And gathered against them have peoples, When they bind themselves to their two iniquities.

11 And Ephraim [is] a trained heifer--loving to thresh, And I--I have passed over on the goodness of its neck, I cause [one] to ride Ephraim, Plough doth Judah, harrow for him doth Jacob.

12 Sow for yourselves in righteousness, Reap according to loving-kindness, Till for yourselves tillage of knowledge, To seek Jehovah, Till he come and shew righteousness to you.

13 Ye have ploughed wickedness, Perversity ye have reaped, Ye have eaten the fruit of lying, For thou hast trusted in thy way, In the abundance of thy might.

14 And rise doth a tumult among thy people, And all thy fortresses are spoiled, As the spoiling of Shalman of Beth-Arbel, In a day of battle, Mother against sons dashed in pieces.

15 Thus hath Beth-El done to you, Because of the evil of your wickedness, In the dawn cut off utterly is a king of Israel!

Hosea 11

1 Because Israel [is] a youth, and I love him, Out of Egypt I have called for My Son.

2 They have called to them rightly, They have gone from before them, To lords they do sacrifice, And to graven images they make perfume.

3 And I have caused Ephraim to go on foot, Taking them by their arms, And they have not known that I strengthened them.

4 With cords of man I do draw them, With thick cords of love, And I am to them as a raiser up of a yoke on their jaws, And I incline unto him--I feed [him].

5 He turneth not back unto the land of Egypt, And Asshur--he [is] his king, For they have refused to return.

6 Grievous hath been the sword in his cities, And it hath ended his bars, and consumed-- from their own counsels.

7 And My people are hanging in suspense, about My returning, And unto the Most High they do call, Together they exalt not.

8 How do I give thee up, O Ephraim? Do I deliver thee up, O Israel? How do I make thee as Admah? Do I set thee as Zeboim? Turned in Me is My heart, kindled together have been My repentings.

9 I do not the fierceness of My anger, I turn not back to destroy Ephraim, For God I [am], and not a man. In thy midst the Holy One, and I enter not in enmity,

10 After Jehovah they go--as a lion He roareth, When He doth roar, then tremble do the sons from the west.

11 They tremble as a sparrow out of Egypt, And as a dove out of the land of Asshur, And I have caused them to dwell in their own houses, An affirmation of Jehovah.

12 Compassed Me with feigning hath Ephraim, And with deceit the house of Israel. And Judah again is ruling with God, And with the Holy Ones [is] faithful!

Hosea 12

1 Ephraim is enjoying wind, And is pursuing an east wind, All the day lying and spoiling he multiplieth, And a covenant with Asshur they make, And oil to Egypt is carried.

2 And a controversy hath Jehovah with Judah, To lay a charge on Jacob according to his ways, According to his doings He returneth to him.

3 In the womb he took his brother by the heel, And by his strength he was a prince with God,

4 Yea, he is a prince unto the Messenger, And he overcometh [by] weeping, And he maketh supplication to Him, At Bethel He doth find him, And there He doth speak with us,

5 Even Jehovah, God of the Hosts, Jehovah [is] His memorial.

6 And thou, through thy God, dost turn, Kindness and judgment keep thou, And wait on thy God continually.

7 Canaan! in his hand [are] balances of deceit! To oppress he hath loved.

8 And Ephraim saith: `Surely I have become rich, I have found wealth for myself, All my labours--they find not against me iniquity that [is] sin.'

9 And I--Jehovah thy God from the land of Egypt, Again do I turn thee back into tents, As in the days of the appointed time.

10 And I have spoken unto the prophets, And I have multiplied vision, And by the hand of the prophets I use similes.

11 Surely Gilead [is] iniquity, Only, vanity they have been, In Gilead bullocks they have sacrificed, Also their altars [are] as heaps, on the furrows of a field.

12 And Jacob doth flee to the country of Aram, And Israel doth serve for a wife, Yea, for a wife he hath kept watch.

13 And by a prophet hath Jehovah brought up Israel out of Egypt, And by a prophet it hath been watched.

14 Ephraim hath provoked most bitterly, And his blood on himself he leaveth, And his reproach turn back to him doth his Lord!

Hosea 13

1 When Ephraim speaketh tremblingly, He hath been lifted up in Israel, When he becometh guilty in Baal he dieth.

2 And now do they add to sin, And make to them a molten image of their silver, By their own understanding--idols, A work of artisans--all of it, Of them they say, who [are] sacrificers among men, `The calves let them kiss.'

3 Therefore they are as a cloud of the morning, And as dew, rising early, going away, As chaff tossed about out of a floor, And as smoke out of a window.

4 And I [am] Jehovah thy God from the land of Egypt, And a God besides Me thou dost not know, And a Saviour--there is none save Me.

5 I--I have known thee in a wilderness, In a land of droughts.

6 According to their feedings they are satiated, They have been satiated, And their heart is lifted up, Therefore they have forgotten Me,

7 And I am to them as a lion, As a leopard by the way I look out.

8 I do meet them as a bereaved bear, And I rend the enclosure of their heart.

9 And I consume them there as a lioness, A beast of the field doth rend them.

10 Thou hast destroyed thyself, O Israel, But in Me [is] thy help, Where [is] thy king now--And he doth save thee in all thy cities? And thy judges of whom thou didst say, `Give to me a king and heads?'

11 I give to thee a king in Mine anger, And I take away in My wrath.

12 Bound up [is] the iniquity of Ephraim, Hidden [is] his sin,

13 Pangs of a travailing woman come to him, He [is] a son not wise, For he remaineth not the time for the breaking forth of sons.

14 From the hand of Sheol I do ransom them, From death I redeem them, Where [is] thy plague, O death? Where thy destruction, O Sheol? Repentance is hid from Mine eyes.

15 Though he among brethren produceth fruit, Come in doth an east wind, a wind of Jehovah, From a wilderness it is coming up, And it drieth up his fountain, And become dry doth his spring, It--it spoileth a treasure--every desirable vessel.

16 Become desolate doth Samaria, Because she hath rebelled against her God, By sword they do fall, Their sucklings are dashed in pieces, And its pregnant ones are ripped up!

Hosea 14

1 Turn back, O Israel, unto Jehovah thy God, For thou hast stumbled by thine iniquity.

2 Take with you words, and turn to Jehovah, Say ye unto Him: `Take away all iniquity, and give good, And we do render the fruit of our lips.

3 Asshur doth not save us, on a horse we ride not, Nor do we say any more, Our God, to the work of our hands, For in Thee find mercy doth the fatherless.'

4 I heal their backsliding, I love them freely, For turned back hath Mine anger from him.

5 I am as dew to Israel, he flourisheth as a lily, And he striketh forth his roots as Lebanon.

6 Go on do his sucklings, And his beauty is as an olive, And he hath fragrance as Lebanon.

7 Return do the dwellers under his shadow, They revive [as] corn, and flourish as a vine, His memorial [is] as wine of Lebanon.

8 O Ephraim, what to Me any more with idols? I--I afflicted, and I cause him to sing: `I [am] as a green fir-tree,' From Me is thy fruit found.

9 Who [is] wise, and doth understand these? Prudent, and knoweth them? For upright are the ways of Jehovah, And the righteous go on in them, And the transgressors stumble therein!

Joel 1

1 A word of Jehovah that hath been unto Joel, son of Pethuel:

2 Hear this, ye aged ones, And give ear, all ye inhabitants of the land, Hath this been in your days? Or in the days of your fathers?

3 Concerning it to your sons talk ye, And your sons to their sons, And their sons to another generation.

4 What is left of the palmer-worm, eaten hath the locust, And what is left of the locust, Eaten hath the cankerworm, And what is left of the cankerworm, Eaten hath the caterpillar.

5 Awake, ye drunkards, and weep, And howl all drinking wine, because of the juice, For it hath been cut off from your mouth.

6 For a nation hath come up on my land, Strong, and there is no number, Its teeth [are] the teeth of a lion, And it hath the jaw-teeth of a lioness.

7 It hath made my vine become a desolation, And my fig-tree become a chip, It hath made it thoroughly bare, and hath cast down, Made white have been its branches.

8 Wail, as a virgin girdeth with sackcloth, For the husband of her youth.

9 Cut off hath been present and libation from the house of Jehovah, Mourned have the priests, ministrants of Jehovah.

10 Spoiled is the field, mourned hath the ground, For spoiled is the corn, Dried up hath been new wine, languish doth oil.

11 Be ashamed, ye husbandmen, Howl, vine-dressers, for wheat and for barley, For perished hath the harvest of the field.

12 The vine hath been dried up, And the fig-tree doth languish, Pomegranate, also palm, and apple-tree, All trees of the field have withered, For dried up hath been joy from the sons of men.

13 Gird, and lament, ye priests, Howl, ye ministrants of the altar, Come in, lodge in sackcloth, ministrants of my God, For withheld from the house of your God hath been present and libation.

14 Sanctify a fast, proclaim a restraint, Gather the elders--all the inhabitants of the land, [Into] the house of Jehovah your God,

15 And cry unto Jehovah, `Alas for the day! For near [is] a day of Jehovah, And as destruction from the mighty it cometh.

16 Is not before our eyes food cut off? From the house of our God joy and rejoicing?

17 Rotted have scattered things under their clods, Desolated have been storehouses, Broken down have been granaries, For withered hath the corn.

18 How have cattle sighed! Perplexed have been droves of oxen, For there is no pasture for them, Also droves of sheep have been desolated.

19 Unto Thee, O Jehovah, I do call, For fire hath consumed comely places of a wilderness, And a flame hath set on fire all trees of the field.

20 Also the cattle of the field long for Thee, For dried up have been streams of water, And fire hath consumed comely places of a wilderness!'

Joel 2

1 Blow ye a trumpet in Zion, And shout ye in My holy hill, Tremble do all inhabitants of the earth, For coming is the day of Jehovah, for [it is] near!

2 A day of darkness and thick darkness, A day of cloud and thick darkness, As darkness spread on the mountains, A people numerous and mighty, Like it there hath not been from of old, And after it there is not again--till the years of generation and generation.

3 Before it consumed hath fire, And after it burn doth a flame, As the garden of Eden [is] the land before it, And after it a wilderness--a desolation! And also an escape there hath not been to it,

4 As the appearance of horses [is] its appearance, And as horsemen, so they run.

5 As the noise of chariots, on the tops of the mountains they skip, As the noise of a flame of fire devouring stubble, As a mighty people set in array for battle.

6 From its face pained are peoples, All faces have gathered paleness.

7 As mighty ones they run, As men of war they go up a wall, And each in his own ways they do go, And they embarrass not their paths.

8 And each his brother they press not, Each in his way they go on, If by the missile they fall, they are not cut off.

9 In the city they run to and fro, On the wall they run, Into houses they go up by the windows, They go in as a thief.

10 At their face trembled hath the earth, Shaken have the heavens, Sun and moon have been black, And stars have gathered up their shining.

11 And Jehovah hath given forth His voice before His force, For very great [is] His camp, For mighty [is] the doer of His word, For great [is] the day of Jehovah--very fearful, And who doth bear it?

12 And also now--an affirmation of Jehovah, Turn ye back unto Me with all your heart, And with fasting, and with weeping, And with lamentation.

13 And rend your heart, and not your garments, And turn back unto Jehovah your God, For gracious and merciful [is] He, Slow to anger, and abundant in kindness, And He hath repented concerning the evil.

14 Who knoweth--He doth turn back, Yea--He hath repented, And He hath left behind Him a blessing, A present and libation of Jehovah your God?

15 Blow ye a trumpet in Zion, Sanctify a fast--proclaim a restraint.

16 Gather the people, sanctify an assembly, Assemble the aged, Gather infants and sucklings of the breasts, Go out let a bridegroom from his inner chamber, And a bride out of her closet.

17 Between the porch and the altar weep let the priests, ministrants of Jehovah, And let them say: `Have pity, O Jehovah, on Thy people, And give not Thy inheritance to reproach, To the ruling over them of nations, Why do they say among peoples, Where [is] their God?'

18 And let Jehovah be zealous for His land, And have pity on His people.

19 Let Jehovah answer and say to His people, `Lo, I am sending to you the corn, And the new wine, and the oil, And ye have been satisfied with it, And I make you no more a reproach among nations,

20 And the northern I put far off from you, And have driven him unto a land dry and desolate, With his face unto the eastern sea, And his rear unto the western sea, And come up hath his stink, And come up doth his stench, For he hath exerted himself to work.

21 Do not fear, O land! joy and rejoice, For Jehovah hath exerted Himself to work.

22 Do not fear, O cattle of the field! For sprung forth have pastures of a wilderness, For the tree hath borne its fruit, Fig-tree and vine have given their strength!

23 And ye sons of Zion, joy and rejoice, In Jehovah your God, For He hath given to you the Teacher for righteousness, And causeth to come down to you a shower, Sprinkling and gathered--in the beginning.

24 And full have been the floors [with] pure corn, And overflown have the presses [with] new wine and oil.

25 And I have recompensed to you the years That consume did the locust, the cankerworm, And the caterpillar, and the palmer-worm, My great force that I did send against you.

26 And ye have eaten, eating and being satisfied, And have praised the name of Jehovah your God, Who hath dealt with you wonderfully, And not ashamed are My people to the age.

27 And ye have known that in the midst of Israel [am] I, And I [am] Jehovah your God, and there is none else, And not ashamed are My people to the age.

28 And it hath come to pass afterwards, I do pour out My Spirit on all flesh, And prophesied have your sons and your daughters, Your old men do dream dreams, Your young men do see visions.

29 And also on the men-servants, and on the maid-servants, In those days I do pour out My Spirit.

30 And I have given wonders in the heavens, and in the earth, Blood and fire, and columns of smoke.

31 The sun is turned to darkness, and the moon to blood, Before the coming of the day of Jehovah, The great and the fearful.

32 And it hath come to pass, Every one who calleth in the name of Jehovah is delivered, For in mount Zion and in Jerusalem there is an escape, As Jehovah hath said, And among the remnants whom Jehovah is calling!

Joel 3

1 For lo, in those days, and in that time, When I turn back [to] the captivity of Judah and Jerusalem,

2 Then I have gathered all the nations, And caused them to go down unto the valley of Jehoshaphat, And I have been judged with them there, Concerning My people and Mine inheritance--Israel, Whom they scattered among nations, And My land they have apportioned.

3 And for My people they do cast a lot, And they give the young man for an harlot, And the young woman have sold for wine, That they may drink.

4 And also, what [are] ye to Me, O Tyre and Zidon, And all circuits of Philistia? Recompence are ye rendering unto Me? And if ye are giving recompence to Me, Swiftly, hastily, I turn back your recompence on your head.

5 In that My silver and My gold ye took, And My desirable things that are good, Ye have brought in to your temples.

6 And sons of Judah, and sons of Jerusalem, Ye have sold to the sons of Javan, To put them far off from their border.

7 Lo, I am stirring them up out of the place Whither ye have sold them, And I have turned back your recompence on your head,

8 And have sold your sons and your daughters Into the hand of the sons of Judah, And they have sold them to Shabeans, Unto a nation far off, for Jehovah hath spoken.

9 Proclaim ye this among nations, Sanctify a war, stir up the mighty ones, Come nigh, come up, let all the men of war.

10 Beat your ploughshares to swords, And your pruning-hooks to javelins, Let the weak say, `I [am] mighty.'

11 Haste, and come in, all ye nations round, And be gathered together, Thither cause to come down, O Jehovah, Thy mighty ones.

12 Wake and come up let the nations unto the valley of Jehoshaphat, For there I sit to judge all the nations around.

13 Send ye forth a sickle, For ripened hath harvest, Come in, come down, for filled hath been the press, Overflowed hath wine-presses, For great [is] their wickedness.

14 Multitudes, multitudes [are] in the valley of decision, For near [is] the day of Jehovah in the valley of decision.

15 Sun and moon have been black, And stars have gathered up their shining.

16 And Jehovah from Zion doth roar, And from Jerusalem giveth forth His voice, And shaken have the heavens and earth, And Jehovah [is] a refuge to his people, And a stronghold to sons of Israel.

17 And ye have known that I [am] Jehovah your God, Dwelling in Zion, My holy mountain, And Jerusalem hath been holy, And strangers do not pass over into it again.

18 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Drop down do the mountains juice, And the hills do flow [with] milk, And all streams of Judah do go [with] water, And a fountain from the house of Jehovah goeth forth, And hath watered the valley of Shittim.

19 Egypt a desolation becometh, And Edom a desolation, a wilderness, becometh, For violence [to] sons of Judah, Whose innocent blood they shed in their land.

20 And Judah to the age doth dwell, And Jerusalem to generation and generation.

21 And I have declared their blood innocent, [That] I did not declare innocent, And Jehovah is dwelling in Zion!

Amos 2

1 Thus said Jehovah: For three transgressions of Moab, And for four, I do not reverse it, Because of his burning the bones of the king of Edom to lime,

2 And I have sent a fire against Moab, And it hath consumed the palaces of Kerioth, And dying with noise is Moab, With shouting, with voice of a trumpet.

3 And I have cut off a judge from her midst, And all its heads I slay with him, said Jehovah.

4 Thus said Jehovah: For three transgressions of Judah, And for four, I do not reserve it, Because of their loathing the law of Jehovah, And His statutes they have not kept, And their lies do cause them to err, After which their fathers did walk,

5 And I have sent a fire against Judah, And it hath consumed palaces of Jerusalem.

6 Thus said Jehovah: For three transgressions of Israel, And for four, I do not reverse it, Because of their selling for silver the righteous, And the needy for a pair of sandals.

7 Who are panting for the dust of the earth on the head of the poor, And the way of the humble they turn aside, And a man and his father go unto the damsel, So as to pollute My holy name.

8 And on pledged garments they stretch themselves near every altar, And the wine of fined ones they drink [in] the house of their gods.

9 And I--I have destroyed the Amorite from before them, Whose height [is] as the height of cedars, And strong he [is] as the oaks, And I destroy his fruit from above, And his roots from beneath.

10 And I--I have brought you up from the land of Egypt, And cause you to go in a wilderness forty years, To possess the land of the Amorite.

11 And I raise of your sons for prophets, And of your choice ones for Nazarites, Is not this true, O sons of Israel? An affirmation of Jehovah.

12 And ye cause the Nazarites to drink wine, And on the prophets ye have laid a charge, Saying, `Do not prophecy!'

13 Lo, I am pressing you under, As the full cart doth press for itself a sheaf.

14 And perished hath refuge from the swift, And the strong strengtheneth not his power, And the mighty delivereth not his soul.

15 And the handler of the bow standeth not, And the swift with his feet delivereth not [himself], And the rider of the horse delivereth not his soul.

16 And the courageous of heart among the mighty, Naked doth flee in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah!

Amos 3

1 Hear ye this word that Jehovah hath spoken concerning you, O sons of Israel, concerning all the family that I brought up from the land of Egypt, saying:

2 Only you I have known of all families of the land, Therefore I charge on you all your iniquities.

3 Do two walk together if they have not met?

4 Roar doth a lion in a forest and prey he hath none? Give out doth a young lion his voice from his habitation, If he hath not caught?

5 Doth a bird fall into a snare of the earth, And there is no gin for it? Doth a snare go up from the ground, And prey it captureth not?

6 Is a trumpet blown in a city, And do people not tremble? Is there affliction in a city, And Jehovah hath not done [it]?

7 For the Lord Jehovah doth nothing, Except He hath revealed His counsel unto His servants the prophets.

8 A lion hath roared--who doth not fear? The Lord Jehovah hath spoken--who doth not prophesy?

9 Sound ye unto palaces in Ashdod, And to palaces in the land of Egypt, and say: Be ye gathered on mountains of Samaria, And see many troubles within her, And oppressed ones in her midst.

10 And they have not known to act straightforwardly, An affirmation of Jehovah, Who are treasuring up violence and spoil in their palaces.

11 Therefore, thus said the Lord Jehovah: An adversary--and surrounding the land, And he hath brought down from thee thy strength, And spoiled have been thy palaces.

12 Thus said Jehovah: As the shepherd delivereth from the lion's mouth Two legs, or a piece of an ear, So delivered are the sons of Israel, Who are sitting in Samaria on the corner of a bed, And in Damascus [on that of] a couch.

13 Hear ye and testify to the house of Jacob, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, God of Hosts.

14 For in the day of My charging the transgressions of Israel on him, I have laid a charge on the altars of Beth-El, And cut off have been the horns of the altar, And they have fallen to the earth.

15 And I have smitten the winter-house with the summer-house, And perished have houses of ivory, And consumed have been many houses, An affirmation of Jehovah!

Amos 4

1 Hear this word, ye kine of Bashan, Who [are] in the mountain of Samaria, Who are oppressing the poor, Who are bruising the needy, Who are saying to their lords: `Bring in, and we do drink.'

2 Sworn hath the Lord Jehovah by His holiness, That lo, days are coming upon you, And he hath taken you away with hooks, And your posterity with fish-hooks.

3 And [by] breaches ye go forth, A woman [at that] over-against her, And ye have cast down the high place, An affirmation of Jehovah.

4 Enter ye Beth-El, and transgress, At Gilgal multiply transgression, And bring in every morning your sacrifices, Every third year your tithes.

5 And perfume with leaven a thank-offering, And proclaim willing gifts, sound ye! For so ye have loved, O sons of Israel, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah.

6 And I also--I have given to you cleanness of teeth in all your cities, And lack of bread in all your places, And ye have not turned back unto Me, an affirmation of Jehovah.

7 And I also--I have withheld from you the rain. While yet three months to harvest, And I have sent rain on one city, And on another city I do not send rain, One portion is rained on, And the portion on which it raineth not withereth.

8 And wandered have two or three cities, Unto the same city to drink water, And they are not satisfied, And ye have not turned back unto Me, An affirmation of Jehovah.

9 I have smitten you with blasting and with mildew, The abundance of your gardens and of your vineyards, And of your figs, and of your olives, Eat doth the palmer-worm, And ye have not turned back unto Me, An affirmation of Jehovah.

10 I have sent among you pestilence by the way of Egypt, I have slain by sword your choice ones, With your captive horses, And I cause the stink of your camps to come up--even into your nostrils, And ye have not turned back unto Me, An affirmationof Jehovah.

11 I have overturned among you, Like the overturn by God of Sodom and Gomorrah, And ye are as a brand delivered from a burning, And ye have not turned back unto Me, An affirmation of Jehovah.

12 Therefore, thus I do to thee, O Israel, at last, Because this I do to thee, Prepare to meet thy God, O Israel.

13 For, lo, the former of mountains, and creator of wind, And the declarer to man what [is] His thought, He is making dawn obscurity, And is treading on high places of earth, Jehovah, God of Hosts, [is] His name!

Amos 5

1 Hear this word that I am bearing to you, A lamentation, O house of Israel:

2 `Fallen, not again to rise, hath the virgin of Israel, Left on her land--she hath no raiser up.'

3 For thus said the Lord Jehovah: The city that is going out a thousand, Doth leave an hundred, And that which is going out an hundred, Doth leave ten to the house of Israel.

4 For thus said Jehovah to the house of Israel: Seek ye Me, and live,

5 And seek not Beth-El, and Gilgal enter not, And Beer-Sheba pass not through, For Gilgal doth utterly remove, And Beth-El doth become vanity.

6 Seek ye Jehovah, and live, Lest He prosper as fire [against] the house of Joseph, And it hath consumed, And there is no quencher for Beth-El.

7 Ye who are turning to wormwood judgment, And righteousness to the earth have put down,

8 The maker of Kimah and Kesil, And the turner to morning of death-shade, And day [as] night He hath made dark, Who is calling to the waters of the sea, And poureth them on the face of the earth, Jehovah [is] His name;

9 Who is brightening up the spoiled against the strong, And the spoiled against a fortress cometh.

10 They have hated a reprover in the gate, And a plain speaker they abominate.

11 Therefore, because of your trampling on the poor, And the tribute of corn ye take from him, Houses of hewn work ye have built, And ye do not dwell in them, Desirable vineyards ye have planted, And ye do not drink their wine.

12 For I have known--many [are] your transgressions, And mighty your sins, Adversaries of the righteous, taking ransoms, And the needy in the gate ye turned aside.

13 Therefore is the wise at that time silent, For an evil time it [is].

14 Seek good, and not evil, that ye may live, And it is so; Jehovah, God of Hosts, [is] with you, as ye said.

15 Hate evil, and love good, And set up judgment in the gate, It may be Jehovah, God of Hosts, doth pity the remnant of Joseph.

16 Therefore, thus said Jehovah, God of Hosts, the Lord, In all broad places [is] lamentation, And in all out-places they say, `Alas, alas,' And called the husbandman to mourning, And to lamentation the skilful of wailing.

17 And in all vineyards [is] lamentation, For I pass into thy midst, said Jehovah.

18 Ho, ye who are desiring the day of Jehovah, Why [is] this to you--the day of Jehovah? It is darkness, and not light,

19 As [when] one fleeth from the face of the lion, And the bear hath met him, And he hath come in to the house, And hath leant his hand on the wall, And the serpent hath bitten him.

20 Is not the day of Jehovah darkness and not light, Even thick darkness that hath no brightness?

21 I have hated--I have loathed your festivals, And I am not refreshed by your restraints.

22 For though ye cause burnt-offerings and your presents to ascend to Me, I am not pleased, And the peace-offering of your fatlings I behold not.

23 Turn aside from Me the noise of thy songs, Yea, the praise of thy psaltery I hear not.

24 And roll on as waters doth judgment, And righteousness as a perennial stream.

25 Sacrifices and offering did ye bring nigh to Me, In a wilderness forty years, O house of Israel?

26 And ye bare Succoth your king, and Chiun your images, The star of your god, that ye made for yourselves.

27 And I removed you beyond Damascus, Said Jehovah, God of Hosts [is] His name.

Amos 6

1 Woe [to] those secure in Zion, And those confident in the mount of Samaria, The marked of the chief of the nations, And come to them have the house of Israel.

2 Pass ye over [to] Calneh and see, And go thence [to] Hamath the great, And go down [to] Gath of the Philistines, Are [they] better than these kingdoms? Greater [is] their border than your border?

3 Who are putting away the day of evil, And ye bring nigh the seat of violence,

4 Who are lying down on beds of ivory, And are spread out on their couches, And are eating lambs from the flock, And calves from the midst of the stall,

5 Who are taking part according to the psaltery, Like David they invented for themselves instruments of music;

6 Who are drinking with bowls of wine, And [with] chief perfumes anoint [themselves], And have not been pained for the breach of Joseph.

7 Therefore now they remove at the head of the captives, And turned aside is the mourning-feast of stretched-out ones.

8 Sworn hath the Lord Jehovah by Himself, An affirmation of Jehovah, God of Hosts: I am abominating the excellency of Jacob, And his high places I have hated, And I have delivered up the city and its fulness.

9 And if there are left ten persons in one house, It hath come to pass--that they have died.

10 And lifted him up hath his loved one, even his burner, To bring forth the bones from the house, And he said to him who [is] in the sides of the house, `Is there yet with thee?' And he said, `None,' then he said, `Hush! Save to make mention of the name of Jehovah.'

11 For lo, Jehovah is commanding, And He hath smitten the great house [with] breaches, And the little house [with] clefts.

12 Do horses run on a rock? Doth one plough [it] with oxen? For ye have turned to gall judgment, And the fruit of righteousness to wormwood.

13 O ye who are rejoicing at nothing, Who are saying, `Have we not by our strength taken to ourselves horns?'

14 Surely, lo, I am raising against you a nation, O house of Israel, An affirmation of Jehovah, God of Hosts, And they have oppressed you from the coming in to Hamath, Unto the stream of the desert.

Amos 8

1 Thus hath the Lord Jehovah shewed me, and, lo, a basket of summer-fruit.

2 And He saith, `What art thou seeing, Amos?' and I say, `A basket of summer-fruit.' And Jehovah saith unto me: `The end hath come unto My people Israel, I do not add any more to pass over to it.

3 And howled have songstresses of a palace in that day, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, Many [are] the carcases, into any place throw--hush!

4 Hear this, ye who are swallowing up the needy, To cause to cease the poor of the land,

5 Saying, When doth the new moon pass, And we sell ground corn? And the sabbath, and we open out pure corn? To make little the ephah, And to make great the shekel, And to use perversely balances of deceit.

6 To purchase with money the poor, And the needy for a pair of sandals, Yea, the refuse of the pure corn we sell.

7 Sworn hath Jehovah by the excellency of Jacob: `I forget not for ever any of their works.

8 For this doth not the land tremble, And mourned hath every dweller in it? And come up as a flood hath all of it. And it hath been cast out, and hath sunk, Like the flood of Egypt.

9 And it hath come to pass in that day, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, I have caused the sun to go in at noon, And caused darkness on the land in a day of light,

10 And have turned your festivals to mourning, And all your songs to lamentation, And caused sackcloth to come up on all loins, And on every head--baldness, And made it as a mourning [of] an only one, And its latter end as a day of bitterness.

11 Lo, days are coming, An affirmation of the Lord Jehovah, And I have sent a famine into the land, Not a famine of bread, nor a thirst of water But of hearing the words of Jehovah.

12 And they have wandered from sea unto sea, And from north even unto east, They go to and fro to seek the word of Jehovah, And they do not find.

13 In that day faint do the fair virgins, And the young men, with thirst.

14 Those swearing by the guilt of Samaria, And have said, Live doth thy god, O Dan, And, Live doth the way of Beer-Sheba, And they have fallen--and rise not again!'

Amos 9

1 I have seen the Lord standing by the altar, and He saith: `Smite the knob, and the thresholds shake, And cut them off by the head--all of them, And their posterity with a sword I do slay, Not flee to them doth the fleer, Nor escape to them dotha fugitive.

2 If they dig through into sheol, From thence doth My hand take them, And if they go up the heavens, From thence I cause them to come down.

3 And if they be hid in the top of Carmel, From thence I search out, and have taken them, And if they be hid from Mine eyes in the bottom of the sea, From thence I command the serpent, And it hath bitten them.

4 And if they go into captivity before their enemies, From thence I command the sword, And it hath slain them, And I have set Mine eye on them for evil, And not for good.

5 And [it is] the Lord, Jehovah of Hosts, Who is striking against the land, and it melteth, And mourned have all the inhabitants in it, And come up as a flood hath all of it, And it hath sunk-- like the flood of Egypt.

6 Who is building in the heavens His upper chambers; As to His troop, Upon earth He hath founded it, Who is calling for the waters of the sea, And poureth them out on the face of the land, Jehovah [is] His name.

7 As sons of Cushim are ye not to Me? O sons of Israel--an affirmation of Jehovah. Israel did I not bring up out of the land of Egypt? And the Philistines from Caphtor, and Aram from Kir?

8 Lo, the eyes of the Lord Jehovah [are] on the sinful kingdom, And I have destroyed it from off the face of the ground, Only, I destroy not utterly the house of Jacob, An affirmation of Jehovah.

9 For lo, I am commanding, And I have shaken among all the nations the house of Israel, As [one] doth shake with a sieve, And there falleth not a grain [to] the earth.

10 By sword die do all sinners of My people, Who are saying, `Not overtake, or go before, For our sakes, doth evil.'

11 In that day I raise the tabernacle of David, that is fallen, And I have repaired their breaches, And its ruins I do raise up, And I have built it up as in days of old.

12 So that they possess the remnant of Edom, And all the nations on whom My name is called, An affirmation of Jehovah--doer of this.

13 Lo, days are coming--an affirmation of Jehovah, And come nigh hath the ploughman to the reaper, And the treader of grapes to the scatterer of seed, And the mountains have dropped juice, And all the hills do melt.

14 And I have turned back [to] the captivity of My people Israel, And they have built desolate cities, and inhabited, And have planted vineyards, and drunk their wine, And made gardens, and eaten their fruit.

15 And I have planted them on their own ground, And they are not plucked up any more from off their own ground, That I have given to them, said Jehovah thy God!

Obadiah 1

1 Thus said the Lord Jehovah to Edom, A report we have heard from Jehovah, And an ambassador among nations was sent, `Rise, yea, let us rise against her for battle.'

2 Lo, little I have made thee among nations, Despised [art] thou exceedingly.

3 The pride of thy heart hath lifted thee up, O dweller in clifts of a rock, (A high place [is] his habitation, He is saying in his heart, `Who doth bring me down [to] earth?')

4 If thou dost go up high as an eagle, And if between stars thou dost set thy nest, From thence I bring thee down, An affirmation of Jehovah.

5 If thieves have come in to thee, If spoilers of the night, How hast thou been cut off! Do they not steal their sufficiency? If gatherers have come in to thee, Do they not leave gleanings?

6 How hath Esau been searched out! Flowed out have his hidden things,

7 Unto the border sent thee have all thine allies, Forgotten thee, prevailed over thee, have thy friends, Thy bread they make a snare under thee, There is no understanding in him!

8 Is it not in that day--an affirmation of Jehovah, That I have destroyed the wise out of Edom, And understanding out of the mount of Esau?

9 And broken down have been thy mighty ones, O Teman, So that every one of the mount of Esau is cut off.

10 For slaughter, for violence [to] thy brother Jacob, Cover thee doth shame, And thou hast been cut off--to the age.

11 In the day of thy standing over-against, In the day of strangers taking captive his force, And foreigners have entered his gates, And for Jerusalem have cast a lot, Even thou [art] as one of them!

12 And--thou dost not look on the day of thy brother, On the day of his alienation, Nor dost thou rejoice over sons of Judah, In the day of their destruction, Nor make great thy mouth in a day of distress.

13 Nor come into a gate of My people in a day of their calamity, Nor look, even thou, on its misfortune in a day of its calamity, Nor send forth against its force in a day of its calamity,

14 Nor stand by the breach to cut off its escaped, Nor deliver up its remnant in a day of distress.

15 For near [is] the day of Jehovah, on all the nations, As thou hast done, it is done to thee, Thy deed doth turn back on thine own head.

16 For--as ye have drunk on My holy mount, Drink do all the nations continually, And they have drunk and have swallowed, And they have been as they have not been.

17 And in mount Zion there is an escape, And it hath been holy, And the house of Jacob have possessed their possessions.

18 And the house of Jacob hath been a fire, And the house of Joseph a flame, And the house of Esau for stubble, And they have burned among them, And they have consumed them, And there is not a remnant to the house of Esau, For Jehovah hath spoken.

19 And they have possessed the south with the mount of Esau, And the low country with the Philistines, And they have possessed the field of Ephraim, And the field of Samaria, And Benjamin with Gilead.

20 And the removed of this force of the sons of Israel, That [is with] the Canaanites unto Zarephat, And the removed of Jerusalem that [is] with the Sepharad, Possess the cities of the south.

21 And gone up have saviours on mount Zion, To judge the mount of Esau, And the kingdom hath been to Jehovah!'

Jonah 1

1 And there is a word of Jehovah unto Jonah son of Amittai, saying:

2 `Rise, go unto Nineveh, the great city, and proclaim against it that their wickedness hath come up before Me.'

3 And Jonah riseth to flee to Tarshish from the face of Jehovah, and goeth down [to] Joppa, and findeth a ship going [to] Tarshish, and he giveth its fare, and goeth down into it, to go with them to Tarshish from the face of Jehovah.

4 And Jehovah hath cast a great wind on the sea, and there is a great tempest in the sea, and the ship hath reckoned to be broken;

5 and the mariners are afraid, and cry each unto his god, and cast the goods that [are] in the ship into the sea, to make [it] light of them; and Jonah hath gone down unto the sides of the vessel, and he lieth down, and is fast asleep.

6 And the chief of the company draweth near to him, and saith to him, `What--to thee, O sleeper? rise, call unto thy God, it may be God doth bethink himself of us, and we do not perish.'

7 And they say each unto his neighbour, `Come, and we cast lots, and we know on whose account this evil [is] on us.' And they cast lots, and the lot falleth on Jonah.

8 And they say unto him, `Declare to us, we pray thee, on what account this evil [is] on us? what [is] thine occupation, and whence comest thou? what [is] thy country, seeing thou art not of this people?'

9 And he saith unto them, `A Hebrew I [am], and Jehovah, God of the heavens, I am reverencing, who made the sea and the dry land.'

10 And the men fear a great fear, and say unto him, `What [is] this thou hast done!' for the men have known that from the face of Jehovah he is fleeing, for he hath told them.

11 And they say unto him, `What do we do to thee that the sea may cease from us, for the sea is more and more tempestuous?'

12 And he saith unto them, `Lift me up, and cast me into the sea, and the sea doth cease from you; for I know that on my account this great tempest [is] upon you.'

13 And the men row to turn back unto the dry land, and are not able, for the sea is more and more tempestuous against them.

14 And they cry unto Jehovah, and say, `We pray Thee, O Jehovah, let us not, we pray Thee, perish for this man's life, and do not lay on us innocent blood, for Thou, Jehovah, as Thou hast pleased, Thou hast done.'

15 And they lift up Jonah, and cast him into the sea, and the sea ceaseth from its raging;

16 and the men fear Jehovah--a great fear, and sacrifice a sacrifice to Jehovah, and vow vows.

17 And Jehovah appointeth a great fish to swallow up Jonah, and Jonah is in the bowels of the fish three days and three nights.

Jonah 2

1 And Jonah prayeth unto Jehovah his God from the bowels of the fish.

2 And he saith: I called, because of my distress, to Jehovah, And He doth answer me, From the belly of sheol I have cried, Thou hast heard my voice.

3 When Thou dost cast me [into] the deep, Into the heart of the seas, Then the flood doth compass me, All Thy breakers and Thy billows have passed over me.

4 And I--I said: I have been cast out from before Thine eyes, (Yet I add to look unto Thy holy temple!)

5 Compassed me have waters unto the soul, The deep doth compass me, The weed is bound to my head.

6 To the cuttings of mountains I have come down, The earth, her bars [are] behind me to the age. And Thou bringest up from the pit my life, O Jehovah my God.

7 In the feebleness within me of my soul Jehovah I have remembered, And come in unto Thee doth my prayer, Unto Thy holy temple.

8 Those observing lying vanities their own mercy forsake.

9 And I--with a voice of thanksgiving--I sacrifice to Thee, That which I have vowed I complete, Salvation [is] of Jehovah.

10 And Jehovah saith to the fish, and it vomiteth out Jonah on the dry land.

Micah 1

1 A word of Jehovah that hath been unto Micah the Morashite in the days of Jotham, Ahaz, Hezekiah, kings of Judah, that he hath seen concerning Samaria and Jerusalem:

2 Hear, O peoples, all of them! Attend, O earth, and its fulness, And the Lord Jehovah is against you for a witness, The Lord from His holy temple.

3 For lo, Jehovah is going out from His place, And He hath come down, And hath trodden on high places of earth.

4 Melted have been the mountains under Him, And the valleys do rend themselves, As wax from the presence of fire, As waters cast down by a slope.

5 For the transgression of Jacob [is] all this, And for the sins of the house of Israel. What [is] the transgression of Jacob? Is it not Samaria? And what the high places of Judah? Is it not Jerusalem?

6 And I have set Samaria for a heap of the field, For plantations of a vineyard, And poured out into a valley her stones, And her foundations I uncover.

7 And all her graven images are beaten down, And all her gifts are burnt with fire, And all her idols I make a desolation, For, from the hire of a harlot she gathered, and unto the hire of a harlot they return.

8 For this I lament and howl, I go spoiled and naked, I make a lamentation like dragons, And a mourning like daughters of an ostrich.

9 For mortal [are] her wounds, For it hath come unto Judah, It hath come to a gate of My people--to Jerusalem.

10 In Gath tell ye not--in Acco weep not, In Beth-Aphrah, in dust roll thyself.

11 Pass over for thee, O inhabitant of Shaphir, Naked one of shame. Not gone out hath the inhabitant of Zaanan, The lamentation of Beth-Ezel doth take from you its standing.

12 For stayed for good hath the inhabitant of Maroth, For evil hath come down from Jehovah to the gate of Jerusalem.

13 Bind the chariot to a swift beast, O inhabitant of Lachish, The beginning of sin [is] she to the daughter of Zion, For in thee have been found the transgressions of Israel.

14 Therefore thou givest presents to Moresheth-Gath, The houses of Achzib become a lying thing to the kings of Israel.

15 Yet the possessor I do bring in to thee, O inhabitant of Mareshah, To Adullam come in doth the honour of Israel.

16 Make bald and shave, for thy delightful sons, Enlarge thy baldness as an eagle, For they have removed from thee!

Micah 2

1 Woe [to] those devising iniquity, And working evil on their beds, In the light of the morning they do it, For their hand is--to God.

2 And they have desired fields, And they have taken violently, And houses, and they have taken away, And have oppressed a man and his house, Even a man and his inheritance.

3 Therefore, thus said Jehovah: Lo, I am devising against this family evil, From which ye do not remove your necks, Nor walk loftily, for a time of evil it [is].

4 In that day doth [one] take up for you a simile, And he hath wailed a wailing of woe, He hath said, We have been utterly spoiled, The portion of my people He doth change, How doth He move toward me! To the backslider our fields He apportioneth.

5 Therefore, thou hast no caster of a line by lot In the assembly of Jehovah.

6 Ye do not prophesy--they do prophesy, They do not prophesy to these, It doth not remove shame.

7 Doth the house of Jacob say, `Hath the Spirit of Jehovah been shortened? Are these His doings?' Do not My words benefit the people that is walking uprightly?

8 And yesterday My people for an enemy doth raise himself up, From the outer garment the honourable ornament ye strip off, From the confident passers by, Ye who are turning back from war.

9 The women of My people ye cast out from its delightful house, From its sucklings ye take away My honour to the age.

10 Rise and go, for this [is] not the rest, Because of uncleanness it doth corrupt, And corruption is powerful.

11 If one is going [with] the wind, And [with] falsehood hath lied: `I prophesy to thee of wine, and of strong drink,' He hath been the prophet of this people!

12 I do surely gather thee, O Jacob, all of thee, I surely bring together the remnant of Israel, Together I do set it as the flock of Bozrah, As a drove in the midst of its pasture, It maketh a noise because of man.

13 Gone up hath the breaker before them, They have broken through, Yea, they pass through the gate, Yea, they go out through it, And pass on doth their king before them, And Jehovah at their head!

Micah 3

1 And I say, `Hear, I pray you, heads of Jacob, And ye judges of the house of Israel, Is it not for you to know the judgment?

2 Ye who are hating good, and loving evil, Taking violently their skin from off them, And their flesh from off their bones,

3 And who have eaten the flesh of My people, And their skin from off them have stript, And their bones they have broken, And they have spread [them] out as in a pot, And as flesh in the midst of a caldron.

4 Then do they cry unto Jehovah, And He doth not answer them, And hideth His face from them at that time, As they have made evil their doings.

5 Thus said Jehovah concerning the prophets Who are causing My people to err, Who are biting with their teeth, And have cried `Peace,' And he who doth not give unto their mouth, They have sanctified against him war.

6 Therefore a night ye have without vision, And darkness ye have without divination, And gone in hath the sun on the prophets, And black over them hath been the day.

7 And ashamed have been the seers, And confounded have been the diviners, And covered their lip have all of them, For their is no answer, O God.

8 And yet I have been full of power by the Spirit of Jehovah, And of judgment, and of might, To declare to Jacob his transgression, And to Israel his sin.

9 Hear this, I pray you, heads of the house of Jacob, And ye judges of the house of Israel, Who are making judgment abominable, And all uprightness do pervert.

10 Building up Zion with blood, And Jerusalem with iniquity.

11 Her heads for a bribe do judge, And her priests for hire do teach, And her prophets for silver divine, And on Jehovah they lean, saying, `Is not Jehovah in our midst? Evil doth not come in upon us.'

12 Therefore, for your sake, Zion is ploughed a field, and Jerusalem is heaps, And the mount of the house [is] for high places of a forest!

Micah 4

1 And it hath come to pass, In the latter end of the days, The mount of the house of Jehovah Is established above the top of the mounts, And it hath been lifted up above the hills, And flowed unto it have peoples.

2 And gone have many nations and said, Come and we go up to the mount of Jehovah, And unto the house of the God of Jacob, And He doth teach us of His ways, And we do walk in His paths, For from Zion doth go forth a law, And a word of Jehovah fromJerusalem.

3 And He hath judged between many peoples, And given a decision to mighty nations afar off, They have beaten their swords to ploughshares, And their spears to pruning-hooks, Nation lifteth not up sword unto nation, Nor do they learn war any more.

4 And they have sat each under his vine, And under his fig-tree, And there is none troubling, For the mouth of Jehovah of Hosts hath spoken.

5 For all the peoples do walk, Each in the name of its god--and we, We do walk in the name of Jehovah our God, To the age and for ever.

6 In that day--an affirmation of Jehovah, I do gather the halting one, And the driven away one I bring together, And she whom I have afflicted.

7 And I have set the halting for a remnant, And the far-off for a mighty nation, And reigned hath Jehovah over them in mount Zion, From henceforth, and unto the age.

8 And thou, O tower of Eder, Fort of the daughter of Zion, unto thee it cometh, Yea, come in hath the former rule, The kingdom to the daughter of Jerusalem.

9 Now, why dost thou shout aloud? A king--is there none in thee? Hath thy counsellor perished, That taken hold of thee hath pain as a travailing woman?

10 Be pained, and bring forth, O daughter of Zion, As a travailing woman, For now, thou goest forth from the city, And thou hast dwelt in the field, And thou hast gone unto Babylon, There thou art delivered, There redeem thee doth Jehovah from the hand of thine enemies.

11 And now, gathered against thee have been many nations, who are saying: `Let her be defiled, and our eyes look on Zion.'

12 They have not known the thoughts of Jehovah, Nor have they understood His counsel, For He hath gathered them as a sheaf [into] a threshing-floor.

13 Arise, and thresh, O daughter of Zion, For thy horn I make iron, And thy hoofs I make brass, And thou hast beaten small many peoples, And I have devoted to Jehovah their gain, And their wealth to the Lord of the whole earth!

Micah 5

1 Now gather thyself together, O daughter of troops, A siege he hath laid against us, With a rod they smite on the cheek the judge of Israel.

2 And thou, Beth-Lehem Ephratah, Little to be among the chiefs of Judah! From thee to Me he cometh forth--to be ruler in Israel, And his comings forth [are] of old, From the days of antiquity.

3 Therefore he doth give them out till the time She who bringeth forth hath brought forth, And the remnant of his brethren return to the sons of Israel.

4 And he hath stood and delighted in the strength of Jehovah, In the excellency of the name of Jehovah his God, And they have remained, For now he is great unto the ends of earth.

5 And this [one] hath been peace, Asshur! when he doth come into our land, And when he doth tread in our palaces, We have raised against him seven shepherds, And eight anointed of man.

6 And they have afflicted the land of Asshur with the sword, And the land of Nimrod at its openings, And he hath delivered from Asshur when he doth come into our land, And when he treadeth in our borders.

7 And the remnant of Jacob hath been in the midst of many peoples, As dew from Jehovah--as showers on the herb, That waiteth not for man, nor stayeth for the sons of men.

8 Yea, the remnant of Jacob hath been among nations, In the midst of many peoples, As a lion among beasts of a forest, As a young lion among ranks of a flock, Which if it hath passed through, Hath both trodden down and hath torn, And there is no deliverer.

9 High is thy hand above thine adversaries, And all thine enemies are cut off.

10 And it hath come to pass in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah, I have cut off thy horses from thy midst, And I have destroyed thy chariots,

11 And I have cut off the cities of thy land, And I have thrown down all thy fortresses,

12 And have cut off sorcerers out of thy hand, And observers of clouds thou hast none.

13 And I have cut off thy graven images, And thy standing-pillars out of thy midst, And thou dost not bow thyself any more To the work of thy hands.

14 And I have plucked up thy shrines out of thy midst, And I have destroyed thine enemies.

15 And I have done vengeance in anger and in fury, With the nations who have not hearkened!

Micah 6

1 Hear, I pray you, that which Jehovah is saying: `Rise--strive thou with the mountains, And cause thou the hills to hear thy voice.'

2 Hear, O mountains, the strife of Jehovah, Ye strong ones--foundations of earth! For a strife [is] to Jehovah, with His people, And with Israel He doth reason.

3 O My people, what have I done to thee? And what--have I wearied thee? Testify against Me.

4 For I brought thee up from the land of Egypt, And from the house of servants I have ransomed thee, And I send before thee Moses, Aaron, and Miriam.

5 O My people, remember, I pray you, What counsel did Balak king of Moab, What answer him did Balaam son of Beor, (From Shittim unto Gilgal,) In order to know the righteous acts of Jehovah.'

6 With what do I come before Jehovah? Do I bow to God Most High? Do I come before Him with burnt-offerings? With calves--sons of a year?

7 Is Jehovah pleased with thousands of rams? With myriads of streams of oil? Do I give my first-born [for] my transgression? The fruit of my body [for] the sin of my soul?

8 He hath declared to thee, O man, what [is] good; Yea, what is Jehovah requiring of thee, Except--to do judgment, and love kindness, And lowly to walk with thy God?

9 A voice of Jehovah to the city calleth, And wisdom doth fear Thy name, Hear ye the rod, and Him who appointed it.

10 Are there yet [in] the house of the wicked Treasures of wickedness, And the abhorred scanty ephah?

11 Do I reckon [it] pure with balances of wickedness? And with a bag of deceitful stones?

12 Whose rich ones have been full of violence, And its inhabitants have spoken falsehood, And their tongue [is] deceitful in their mouth.

13 And I also, I have begun to smite thee, To make desolate, because of thy sins.

14 Thou--thou eatest, and thou art not satisfied, And thy pit [is] in thy midst, And thou removest, and dost not deliver, And that which thou deliverest, to a sword I give.

15 Thou--thou sowest, and thou dost not reap, Thou--thou treadest the olive, And thou pourest not out oil, And new wine--and thou drinkest not wine.

16 And kept habitually are the statutes of Omri, And all the work of the house of Ahab, And ye do walk in their counsels, For My giving thee for a desolation, And its inhabitants for a hissing, And the reproach of My people ye do bear!

Micah 7

1 My woe [is] to me, for I have been As gatherings of summer-fruit, As gleanings of harvest, There is no cluster to eat, The first-ripe fruit desired hath my soul.

2 Perished hath the kind out of the land, And upright among men--there are none, All of them for blood lie in wait, Each his brother they hunt [with] a net.

3 On the evil [are] both hands to do [it] well, The prince is asking--also the judge--for recompence, And the great--he is speaking the mischief of his soul, And they wrap it up.

4 Their best one [is] as a brier, The upright one--than a thorn-hedge, The day of thy watchmen--Thy visitation--hath come. Now is their perplexity.

5 Believe not in a friend, trust not in a leader, From her who is lying in thy bosom keep the openings of thy mouth.

6 For a son is dishonouring a father, A daughter hath stood against her mother, A daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law, The enemies of each [are] the men of his house.

7 And I--in Jehovah I do watch, I do wait for the God of my salvation, Hear me doth my God.

8 Thou dost not rejoice over me, O mine enemy, When I have fallen, I have risen, When I sit in darkness Jehovah is a light to me.

9 The indignation of Jehovah I do bear, For I have sinned against Him, Till that He doth plead my cause, And hath executed my judgment, He doth bring me forth to the light, I look on His righteousness.

10 And see doth mine enemy, And cover her doth shame, Who saith unto me, `Where [is] Jehovah thy God?' Mine eyes do look on her, Now she is for a treading-place, As mire of the outplaces.

11 The day to build thy walls! That day--removed is the limit.

12 That day--even unto thee it doth come in, From Asshur and the cities of the fortress, And from the fortress even unto the river, And from sea to sea, and mount to mount.

13 And the land hath been for a desolation, Because of its inhabitants, Because of the fruit of their doings.

14 Rule Thou Thy people with Thy rod, The flock of Thine inheritance, Dwelling alone [in] a forest in the midst of Carmel, They enjoy Bashan and Gilead as in days of old.

15 According to the days of thy coming forth out of the land of Egypt, I do shew it wonderful things.

16 See do nations, and they are ashamed of all their might, They lay a hand on the mouth, their ears are deaf.

17 They lick dust as a serpent, as fearful things of earth, They tremble from their enclosures, Of Jehovah our God they are afraid, Yea, they are afraid of Thee.

18 Who [is] a God like Thee? taking away iniquity, And passing by the transgression of the remnant of His inheritance, He hath not retained for ever His anger, Because He--He delighteth [in] kindness.

19 He doth turn back, He pitieth us, He doth subdue our iniquities, And Thou castest into the depths of the sea all their sins.

20 Thou givest truth to Jacob, kindness to Abraham, That thou hast sworn to our fathers, from the days of antiquity!

Nahum 1

1 Burden of Nineveh. The Book of the Vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.

2 A God zealous and avenging [is] Jehovah, An avenger [is] Jehovah, and possessing fury. An avenger [is] Jehovah on His adversaries, And He is watching for His enemies.

3 Jehovah [is] slow to anger, and great in power, And Jehovah doth not entirely acquit, In a hurricane and in a tempest [is] His way, And a cloud [is] the dust of His feet.

4 He is pushing against a sea, and drieth it up, Yea, all the floods He hath made dry, Languishing [are] Bashan and Carmel, Yea, the flower of Lebanon [is] languishing.

5 Mountains have shaken because of Him, And the hills have been melted; And lifted up [is] the earth at His presence, And the world and all dwelling in it.

6 Before His indignation who doth stand? And who riseth up in the heat of His anger? His fury hath been poured out like fire, And the rocks have been broken by Him.

7 Good [is] Jehovah for a strong place in a day of distress. And He knoweth those trusting in Him.

8 And with a flood passing over, An end He maketh of its place, And His enemies doth darkness pursue.

9 What do we devise against Jehovah? An end He is making, arise not twice doth distress.

10 For while princes [are] perplexed, And with their drink are drunken, They have been consumed as stubble fully dried.

11 From thee hath come forth a deviser of evil Against Jehovah--a worthless counsellor.

12 Thus said Jehovah: Though complete, and thus many, Yet thus they have been cut off, And he hath passed away. And I afflicted thee, I afflict thee no more.

13 And now I break his rod from off thee, And thy bands I do draw away.

14 And commanded concerning thee hath Jehovah, `No more of thy name doth spread abroad, From the house of thy gods I cut off graven and molten image, I appoint thy grave, for thou hast been vile.

15 Lo, on the mountains the feet of one proclaiming tidings, sounding peace! Celebrate, O Judah, thy festivals, complete thy vows, For add no more to pass over into thee doth the worthless, He hath been completely cut off!

Nahum 2

1 Come up hath a scatterer to thy face, Keep the bulwark, watch the way, Strengthen the loins, strengthen power mightily.

2 For turned back hath Jehovah to the excellency of Jacob, As [to] the excellency of Israel, For emptied them out have emptiers, And their branches they have marred.

3 The shield of his mighty ones is become red, Men of might [are in] scarlet, With fiery torches [is] the chariot in a day of his preparation, And the firs have been caused to tremble.

4 In out-places shine do the chariots, They go to and fro in broad places, Their appearances [are] like torches, As lightnings they run.

5 He doth remember his honourable ones, They stumble in their goings, They hasten [to] its wall, and prepared is the covering.

6 Gates of the rivers have been opened, And the palace is dissolved.

7 And it is established--she hath removed, She hath been brought up, And her handmaids are leading as the voice of doves, Tabering on their hearts.

8 And Nineveh [is] as a pool of waters, From of old it [is] --and they are fleeing! `Stand ye, stand;' and none is turning!

9 Seize ye silver, seize ye gold, And there is no end to the prepared things, [To] the abundance of all desirable vessels.

10 She is empty, yea, emptiness and waste, And the heart hath melted, And the knees have smitten together, And great pain [is] in all loins, And the faces of all of them have gathered paleness.

11 Where [is] the habitation of lionesses? And a feeding-place it [is] for young lions Where walked hath a lion, an old lion, A lion's whelp, and there is none troubling.

12 The lion is tearing parts [for] his whelps, And is strangling for his lionesses, And he doth fill [with] prey his holes, And his habitations [with] rapine.

13 Lo, I [am] against thee, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, And I have burned in smoke its chariot, And thy young lions consume doth a sword, And I have cut off from the land thy prey, And not heard any more is the voice of thy messengers!

Nahum 3

1 Woe [to] the city of blood, She is all with lies--burglary--full, Prey doth not depart.

2 The sound of a whip, And the sound of the rattling of a wheel, And of a prancing horse, and of a bounding chariot, Of a horseman mounting.

3 And the flame of a sword, and the lightning of a spear, And the abundance of the wounded, And the weight of carcases, Yea, there is no end to the bodies, They stumble over their bodies.

4 Because of the abundance of the fornications of an harlot, The goodness of the grace of the lady of witchcrafts, Who is selling nations by her fornications, And families by her witchcrafts.

5 Lo, I [am] against thee, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, And have removed thy skirts before thy face, And have shewed nations thy nakedness, And kingdoms thy shame,

6 And I have cast upon thee abominations, And dishonoured thee, and made thee as a sight.

7 And it hath come to pass, Each of thy beholders fleeth from thee, And hath said: `Spoiled is Nineveh, Who doth bemoan for her?' Whence do I seek comforters for thee?

8 Art thou better than No-Ammon, That is dwelling among brooks? Waters she hath round about her, Whose bulwark [is] the sea, waters her wall.

9 Cush her might, and Egypt, and there is no end. Put and Lubim have been for thy help.

10 Even she doth become an exile, She hath gone into captivity, Even her sucklings are dashed to pieces At the top of all out-places, And for her honoured ones they cast a lot, And all her great ones have been bound in fetters.

11 Even thou art drunken, thou art hidden, Even thou dost seek a strong place, because of an enemy.

12 All thy fortresses [are] fig-trees with first-fruits, If they are shaken, They have fallen into the mouth of the eater.

13 Lo, thy people [are] women in thy midst, To thine enemies thoroughly opened Have been the gates of thy land, Consumed hath fire thy bars.

14 Waters of a siege draw for thyself, Strengthen thy fortresses, Enter into mire, and tread on clay, Make strong a brick-kiln.

15 There consume thee doth a fire, Cut thee off doth a sword, It doth consume thee as a cankerworm! Make thyself heavy as the cankerworm, Make thyself heavy as the locust.

16 Multiply thy merchants above the stars of the heavens, The cankerworm hath stripped off, and doth flee away.

17 Thy crowned ones [are] as a locust, And thy princes as great grasshoppers, That encamp in hedges in a day of cold, The sun hath risen, and it doth flee away, And not known is its place where they are.

18 Slumbered have thy friends, king of Asshur, Rest do thine honourable ones, Scattered have been thy people on the mountains, And there is none gathering.

19 There is no weakening of thy destruction, Grievous [is] thy smiting, All hearing thy fame have clapped the hand at thee, For over whom did not thy wickedness pass continually?

Habakkuk 1

1 The burden that Habakkuk the prophet hath seen:

2 Till when, O Jehovah, have I cried, And Thou dost not hear? I cry unto Thee-- `Violence,' and Thou dost not save.

3 Why dost Thou shew me iniquity, And perversity dost cause to behold? And spoiling and violence [are] before me, And there is strife, and contention doth lift [itself] up,

4 Therefore doth law cease, And judgment doth not go forth for ever, For the wicked is compassing the righteous, Therefore wrong judgment goeth forth.

5 Look ye on nations, and behold and marvel greatly. For a work He is working in your days, Ye do not believe though it is declared.

6 For, lo, I am raising up the Chaldeans, The bitter and hasty nation, That is going to the broad places of earth, To occupy tabernacles not its own.

7 Terrible and fearful it [is], From itself its judgment and its excellency go forth.

8 Swifter than leopards have been its horses, And sharper than evening wolves, And increased have its horsemen, Even its horsemen from afar come in, They fly as an eagle, hasting to consume.

9 Wholly for violence it doth come in, Their faces swallowing up the east wind, And it doth gather as the sand a captivity.

10 And at kings it doth scoff, And princes [are] a laughter to it, At every fenced place it doth laugh, And it heapeth up dust, and captureth it.

11 Then passed on hath the spirit, Yea, he doth transgress, And doth ascribe this his power to his god.

12 Art not Thou of old, O Jehovah, my God, my Holy One? We do not die, O Jehovah, For judgment Thou hast appointed it, And, O Rock, for reproof Thou hast founded it.

13 Purer of eyes than to behold evil, To look on perverseness Thou art not able, Why dost Thou behold the treacherous? Thou keepest silent when the wicked Doth swallow the more righteous than he,

14 And Thou makest man as fishes of the sea, As a creeping thing--none ruling over him.

15 Each of them with a hook he hath brought up, He doth catch it in his net, and gathereth it in his drag, Therefore he doth joy and rejoice.

16 Therefore he doth sacrifice to his net, And doth make perfume to his drag, For by them [is] his portion fertile, and his food fat.

17 Doth he therefore empty his net, And continually to slay nations spare not?

Habakkuk 2

1 On my charge I stand, and I station myself on a bulwark, and I watch to see what He doth speak against me, and what I do reply to my reproof.

2 And Jehovah answereth me and saith: `Write a vision, and explain on the tables, That he may run who is reading it.

3 For yet the vision [is] for a season, And it breatheth for the end, and doth not lie, If it tarry, wait for it, For surely it cometh, it is not late.

4 Lo, a presumptuous one! Not upright is his soul within him, And the righteous by his stedfastness liveth.

5 And also, because the wine [is] treacherous, A man is haughty, and remaineth not at home, Who hath enlarged as sheol his soul, And is as death that is not satisfied, And doth gather unto itself all the nations, And doth assemble unto itselfall the peoples,

6 Do not these--all of them--against him a simile taken up, And a moral of acute sayings for him, And say, Woe [to] him who is multiplying [what is] not his? Till when also is he multiplying to himself heavy pledges?

7 Do not thy usurers instantly rise up, And those shaking thee awake up, And thou hast been for a spoil to them?

8 Because thou hast spoiled many nations, Spoil thee do all the remnant of the peoples, Because of man's blood, and of violence [to] the land, [To] the city, and [to] all dwelling in it.

9 Woe [to] him who is gaining evil gain for his house, To set on high his nest, To be delivered from the hand of evil,

10 Thou hast counselled a shameful thing to thy house, To cut off many peoples, and sinful [is] thy soul.

11 For a stone from the wall doth cry out, And a holdfast from the wood answereth it.

12 Woe [to] him who is building a city by blood, And establishing a city by iniquity.

13 Lo, is it not from Jehovah of Hosts And peoples are fatigued for fire, And nations for vanity are weary?

14 For full is the earth of the knowledge of the honour of Jehovah, As waters cover [the bottom of] a sea.

15 Woe [to] him who is giving drink to his neighbour, Pouring out thy bottle, and also making drunk, In order to look on their nakedness.

16 Thou hast been filled--shame without honour, Drink thou also, and be uncircumcised, Turn round unto thee doth the cup of the right hand of Jehovah, And shameful spewing [is] on thine honour.

17 For violence [to] Lebanon doth cover thee, And spoil of beasts doth affright them, Because of man's blood, and of violence [to] the land, [To] the city, and [to] all dwelling in it.

18 What profit hath a graven image given That its former hath graven it? A molten image and teacher of falsehood, That trusted hath the former on his own formation--to make dumb idols?

19 Woe [to] him who is saying to wood, `Awake,' `Stir up,' to a dumb stone, It a teacher! lo, it is overlaid--gold and silver, And there is no spirit in its midst.

20 And Jehovah [is] in His holy temple, Be silent before Him, all the earth!

Habakkuk 3

1 A prayer of Habakkuk the prophet concerning erring ones:

2 O Jehovah, I heard thy report, I have been afraid, O Jehovah, Thy work! in midst of years revive it, In the midst of years Thou makest known In anger Thou dost remember mercy.

3 God from Teman doth come, The Holy One from mount Paran. Pause! Covered the heavens hath His majesty, And His praise hath filled the earth.

4 And the brightness is as the light, He hath rays out of His hand, And there--the hiding of His strength.

5 Before Him goeth pestilence, And a burning flame goeth forth at His feet.

6 He hath stood, and He measureth earth, He hath seen, and He shaketh off nations, And scatter themselves do mountains of antiquity, Bowed have the hills of old, The ways of old [are] His.

7 Under sorrow I have seen tents of Cushan, Tremble do curtains of the land of Midian.

8 Against rivers hath Jehovah been wroth? Against rivers [is] Thine anger? Against the sea [is] Thy wrath? For Thou dost ride on Thy horses--Thy chariots of salvation?

9 Utterly naked Thou dost make Thy bow, Sworn are the tribes--saying, `Pause!' [With] rivers Thou dost cleave the earth.

10 Seen thee--pained are mountains, An inundation of waters hath passed over, Given forth hath the deep its voice, High its hands it hath lifted up.

11 Sun--moon--hath stood--a habitation, At the light thine arrows go on, At the brightness, the glittering of thy spear.

12 In indignation Thou dost tread earth, In anger Thou dost thresh nations.

13 Thou hast gone forth for the salvation of Thy people, For salvation with Thine anointed, Thou hast smitten the head of the house of the wicked, Laying bare the foundation unto the neck. Pause!

14 Thou hast pierced with his staves the head of his leaders, They are tempestuous to scatter me, Their exultation [is] as to consume the poor in secret.

15 Thou hast proceeded through the sea with Thy horses--the clay of many waters.

16 I have heard, and my belly trembleth, At the noise have my lips quivered, Rottenness doth come into my bones, And in my place I do tremble, That I rest for a day of distress, At the coming up of the people, he overcometh it.

17 Though the fig-tree doth not flourish, And there is no produce among vines, Failed hath the work of the olive, And fields have not yielded food, Cut off from the fold hath been the flock, And there is no herd in the stalls.

18 Yet I, in Jehovah I exult, I do joy in the God of my salvation.

19 Jehovah the Lord [is] my strength, And He doth make my feet like hinds, And on my high-places causeth me to tread. To the overseer with my stringed instruments!

Zephaniah 1

1 A word of Jehovah that hath been unto Zephaniah son of Cushi, son of Gedaliah, son of Amariah, son of Hezikiah, in the days of Josiah son of Amoz, king of Judah:

2 I utterly consume all from off the face of the ground, An affirmation of Jehovah.

3 I consume man and beast, I consume fowl of the heavens, and fishes of the sea, And the stumbling-blocks--the wicked, And I have cut off man from the face of the ground, An affirmation of Jehovah,

4 And stretched out My hand against Judah, And against all inhabiting Jerusalem, And cut off from this place the remnant of Baal, The name of the idolatrous priests, with the priests,

5 And those bowing themselves On the roofs to the host of the heavens, And those bowing themselves, Swearing to Jehovah, and swearing by Malcham,

6 And those removing from after Jehovah, And who have not sought Jehovah, nor besought Him.

7 Hush! because of the Lord Jehovah, For near [is] a day of Jehovah, For prepared hath Jehovah a sacrifice, He hath sanctified His invited ones.

8 And it hath come to pass, In the day of the sacrifice of Jehovah, That I have laid a charge on the heads, And on sons of the king, And on all putting on strange clothing.

9 And I have laid a charge on every one Who is leaping over the threshold in that day, Who are filling the house of their masters [With] violence and deceit.

10 And there hath been in that day, An affirmation of Jehovah, The noise of a cry from the fish-gate, And of a howling from the Second, And of great destruction from the hills.

11 Howl, ye inhabitants of the hollow place, For cut off hath been all the merchant people, Cut off have been all bearing silver.

12 And it hath come to pass, at that time, I search Jerusalem with lights, And I have laid a charge on the men Who are hardened on their preserved things, Who are saying in their heart: Jehovah doth no good, nor doth He evil.

13 And their wealth hath been for a spoil, And their houses for desolation, And they have built houses, and do not inhabit, And they have planted vineyards, And they do not drink their wine.

14 Near [is] the great day of Jehovah, Near, and hasting exceedingly, The noise of the day of Jehovah, Bitterly shriek there doth a mighty one.

15 A day of wrath [is] that day, A day of adversity and distress, A day of waste and desolation, A day of darkness and gloominess, A day of cloud and thick darkness.

16 A day of trumpet and shouting against the fenced cities, And against the high corners.

17 And I have sent distress to men, And they have walked as the blind, For against Jehovah they have sinned, And poured out is their blood as dust, And their flesh [is] as dung.

18 Even their silver, even their gold, Is not able to deliver them in a day of the wrath of Jehovah, And in the fire of His jealousy consumed is the whole land, For only a hastened end doth He make Of all the inhabitants of the land!

Zephaniah 2

1 Bend yourselves, yea, bend ye, O nation not desired,

2 Before the bringing forth of a statute, As chaff hath the day passed on, While yet not come in upon you doth the heat of the anger of Jehovah, While yet not come in upon you doth a day of the anger of Jehovah,

3 Seek Jehovah, all ye humble of the land, Who His judgment have done, Seek ye righteousness, seek humility, It may be ye are hidden in a day of the anger of Jehovah.

4 For Gaza is forsaken, And Ashkelon [is] for a desolation, Ashdod! at noon they do cast her forth, And Ekron is rooted up.

5 Ho! O inhabitants of the sea-coast, Nation of the Cherethites, A word of Jehovah [is] against you, Canaan, land of the Philistines, And I have destroyed thee without an inhabitant.

6 And the sea-coast hath been habitations, Cottages [for] shepherds, and folds [for] a flock.

7 And the coast hath been for the remnant of the house of Judah, By them they have pleasure, In houses of Ashkelon at even they lie down, For inspect them doth Jehovah their God, And He hath turned back [to] their captivity.

8 I have heard the reproach of Moab, And the revilings of the sons of Ammon, Wherewith they reproached My people, And magnify [themselves] against their border.

9 Therefore, I live, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, God of Israel, Surely, Moab is as Sodom, And the sons of Ammon as Gomorrah, An overrunning of nettles and salt-pits, And a desolation--unto the age. A residue of My people do seize them, And a remnant of My nation inherit them.

10 This [is] to them for their arrogancy, Because they have reproached, And they magnify [themselves] against the people of Jehovah of Hosts.

11 Fearful [is] Jehovah against them, For He made bare all gods of the land, And bow themselves to Him, each from his place, Do all islanders of the nations.

12 Also ye, O Cushim, pierced of My sword [are] they.

13 And He stretcheth His hand against the north, And doth destroy Asshur, And he setteth Nineveh for a desolation, A dry land like a wilderness.

14 And crouched in her midst have droves, Every beast of the nation, Both pelican and hedge-hog in her knobs lodge, A voice doth sing at the window, `Destruction [is] at the threshold, For the cedar-work is exposed.'

15 This [is] the exulting city that is dwelling confidently, That is saying in her heart, `I [am], and beside me there is none,' How hath she been for a desolation, A crouching-place for beasts, Every one passing by her doth hiss, He doth shake his hand!

Zephaniah 3

1 Woe [to] the rebellious and polluted, The oppressing city!

2 She hath not hearkened to the voice, She hath not accepted instruction, In Jehovah she hath not trusted, Unto her God she hath not drawn near.

3 Her heads in her midst [are] roaring lions, Her judges [are] evening wolves, They have not gnawn the bone in the morning.

4 Her prophets unstable--men of treachery, Her priests have polluted the sanctuary, They have violated the law.

5 Jehovah [is] righteous in her midst, He doth not do perverseness, Morning by morning His judgment he giveth to the light, It hath not been lacking, And the perverse doth not know shame.

6 I have cut off nations, Desolated have been their chief ones, I have laid waste their out-places without any passing by, Destroyed have been their cities, Without man, without inhabitant.

7 I have said: Only, ye do fear Me, Ye do accept instruction, And her habitation is not cut off, All that I have appointed for her, But they have risen early, They have corrupted all their doings.

8 Therefore, wait for Me--an affirmation of Jehovah, For the day of My rising for prey, For My judgment [is] to gather nations, To assemble kingdoms, To pour out on them Mine indignation, All the heat of Mine anger, For by the fire of My jealousy consumed is all the earth.

9 For then do I turn unto peoples a pure lip, To call all of them by the name of Jehovah, To serve Him [with] one shoulder.

10 From beyond the rivers of Cush, my supplicants, The daughter of My scattered ones, Do bring My present.

11 In that day thou art not ashamed because of any of thine actions, Wherewith thou hast transgressed against Me, For then do I turn aside from thy midst The exulting ones of thine excellency, And thou dost add no more to be haughty, In My holy mountain.

12 And I have left in thy midst a people humble and poor, And they have trusted in the name of Jehovah.

13 The remnant of Israel do no perversity, nor speak lies, Nor found in their mouth is a deceitful tongue, For they have delight, and have lain down, And there is none troubling.

14 Cry aloud, O daughter of Zion, shout, O Israel, Rejoice and exult with the whole heart, O daughter of Jerusalem.

15 Jehovah hath turned aside thy judgments, He hath faced thine enemy, The king of Israel, Jehovah, [is] in thy midst, Thou seest evil no more.

16 In that day it is said to Jerusalem, `Fear not, O Zion, let not thy hands be feeble.

17 Jehovah thy God [is] in thy midst, A mighty one doth save, He rejoiceth over thee with joy, He doth work in His love, He joyeth over thee with singing.'

18 Mine afflicted from the appointed place I have gathered, from thee they have been, Bearing for her sake reproach.

19 Lo, I am dealing with all afflicting thee at that time, And I have saved the halting one, And the driven out ones I do gather, And have set them for a praise and for a name, In all the land of their shame.

20 At that time I bring you in, Even at the time of My assembling you, For I give you for a name, and for a praise, Among all peoples of the land, In My turning back [to] your captivity before your eyes, said Jehovah!

Haggai 1

1 In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in the first day of the month, hath a word of Jehovah been by the hand of Haggai the prophet, unto Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and unto Joshua son of Josedech, thehigh priest, saying:

2 Thus spake Jehovah of Hosts, saying: This people! --they have said, `The time hath not come, The time the house of Jehovah [is] to be built.'

3 And there is a word of Jehovah by the hand of Haggai the prophet, saying:

4 Is it time for you--you! To dwell in your covered houses, And this house to lie waste?

5 And now, thus said Jehovah of Hosts, Set your heart to your ways.

6 Ye have sown much, and brought in little, To eat, and not to satiety, To drink, and not to drunkenness, To clothe, and none hath heat, And he who is hiring himself out, Is hiring himself for a bag pierced through.

7 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Set your heart to your ways.

8 Go up the mountain, and ye have brought in wood, And build the house, and I am pleased with it. And I am honoured, said Jehovah.

9 Looking for much, and lo, little, And ye brought [it] home, and I blew on it, Wherefore? --an affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, Because of My house that is waste, And ye are running--each to his house,

10 Therefore, over you refrained have the heavens from dew, And the land hath refrained its increase.

11 And I proclaim draught on the land, And on the mountains, and on the corn, And on the new wine, and on the oil, And on what the ground doth bring forth, And on man, and on beast, And on all labour of the hands.'

12 And Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, and Joshua son of Josedech, the high priest, and all the remnant of the people, do hearken to the voice of Jehovah their God, and unto the words of

13 And Haggai, messenger of Jehovah, in messages of Jehovah, speaketh to the people, saying: `I [am] with you, an affirmation of Jehovah.'

14 And Jehovah doth stir up the spirit of Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua son of Josedech, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people, and they come in, and do work in the house of Jehovah of Hosts their God,

15 in the twenty and fourth day of the sixth month, in the second year of Darius the king.

Haggai 2

1 In the seventh [month], in the twenty and first of the month, hath a word of Jehovah been by the hand of Haggai the prophet, saying:

2 `Speak, I pray thee, unto Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and unto

3 Who among you hath been left that saw this house in its former honour? And what are ye seeing it now? Is it not, compared with it, as nothing in your eyes?

4 And now, be strong, O Zerubbabel, An affirmation of Jehovah, And be strong, O

5 The thing that I covenanted with you, In your coming forth from Egypt, And My Spirit is remaining in your midst, fear not.

6 For thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Yet once more--it [is] a little, And I am shaking the heavens and the earth, And the sea, and the dry land,

7 And I have shaken all the nations, And they have come [to] the desire of all the nations, And I have filled this house [with] honour, Said Jehovah of Hosts.

8 Mine [is] the silver, and Mine the gold, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts.

9 Greater is the honour of this latter house, Than of the former, said Jehovah of Hosts, And in this place do I give peace, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts.'

10 On the twenty and fourth of the ninth [month], in the second year of Darius, hath a word of Jehovah been by the hand of Haggai the prophet, saying:

11 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: `Ask, I pray thee, the priests [of] the law, saying:

12 Lo, one doth carry holy flesh in the skirt of his garment, and he hath come with his skirt against the bread, or against the pottage, or against the wine, or against the oil, or against any food--is it holy?' And the priests answer and say, `No.'

13 And Haggai saith, `If the unclean of body doth come against any of these, is it unclean?' And the priests answer and say, `It is unclean.'

14 And Haggai answereth and saith, `So [is] this people, and so [is] this nation before Me--an affirmation of Jehovah--and so [is] every work of their hands, and that which they bring near there--it is unclean.

15 And now, lay [it], I pray you, to your heart, From this day, and onwards, Before the laying of stone to stone in the temple of Jehovah.

16 From that time [one] hath come to a heap of twenty, And it hath been ten, He hath come unto the wine-fat to draw out fifty purahs, And it hath been twenty.

17 I have smitten you with blasting, And with mildew, and with hail--All the work of your hands, And there is none of you with Me, An affirmation of Jehovah.

18 Set [it], I pray you, to your heart, from this day and onwards, from the twenty and fourth day of the ninth [month], even from the day that the temple of Jehovah hath been founded, set [it] to your heart.

19 Is the seed yet in the barn? And hitherto the vine and the fig, And the pomegranate, and the olive-tree, Have not borne--from this day I bless.'

20 And there is a word of Jehovah a second time unto Haggai, on the twenty and fourth of the month, saying:

21 `Speak unto Zerubbabel governor of Judah, saying: I am shaking the heavens and the earth,

22 And have overturned the throne of kingdoms, And I have destroyed the strength of kingdoms of the nations, And overturned chariot and its charioteers, And come down have horses and their riders, Each by the sword of his brother.

23 In that day--an affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, I take thee, Zerubbabel, son of Shealtiel, My servant--an affirmation of Jehovah, And have set thee as a signet, for on thee I have fixed, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts!

Zechariah 1

1 In the eighth month, in the second year of Darius, hath a word of Jehovah been unto Zechariah, son of Berechiah, son of Iddo, the prophet, saying:

2 `Jehovah was wroth against your fathers--wrath!

3 And thou hast said unto them, Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, turn back unto Me, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, And I turn back unto you, said Jehovah of Hosts.

4 Ye shall not be as your fathers, To whom the former prophets called, saying: Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, Turn back I pray you, From your evil ways and from your evil doings, And they did not hearken, Nor attend to Me--an affirmation of Jehovah.

5 Your fathers--where [are] they? And the prophets--to the age do they live?

6 Only, My words, and My statutes, That I commanded My servants the prophets, Have they not overtaken your fathers, And they turn back and say: As Jehovah of Hosts designed to do to us, According to our ways, and according to our doings, So He hath done to us?'

7 On the twenty and fourth day of the eleventh month, (it [is] the month of Sebat,) in the second year of Darius, hath a word of Jehovah been unto Zechariah, son of Berechiah, son of Iddo, the prophet, saying:

8 I have seen by night, and lo, one riding on a red horse, and he is standing between the myrtles that [are] in the shade, and behind him [are] horses, red, bay, and white.

9 And I say, `What [are] these, my lord?' And the messenger who is speaking with me saith unto me, `I--I do shew thee what these [are].'

10 And the one who is standing between the myrtles doth answer and say, `These [are] they whom Jehovah hath sent to walk up and down in the land.'

11 And they answer the messenger of Jehovah who is standing between the myrtles, and say, `We have walked up and down in the land, and lo, all the land is sitting still, and at rest.'

12 And the messenger of Jehovah answereth and saith, `Jehovah of Hosts! till when dost Thou not pity Jerusalem, and the cities of Judah, that Thou hast abhorred these seventy years?'

13 And Jehovah answereth the messenger, who is speaking with me, good words, comfortable words.

14 And the messenger who is speaking with me, saith unto me, `Call, saying: Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: I have been zealous for Jerusalem, and for Zion [with] great zeal.

15 And [with] great wrath I am wroth against the nations who are at ease, For I was a little wroth, and they assisted--for evil.

16 Therefore, thus said Jehovah: I have turned to Jerusalem with mercies, My house is built in it, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts, And a line is stretched over Jerusalem.

17 Again call, saying: Thus said Jehovah of Hosts, Again do my cities overflow from good, And Jehovah hath again comforted Zion, And He hath fixed again on Jerusalem.'

18 And I lift up mine eyes, and look, and lo, four horns.

19 And I say unto the messenger who is speaking with me, `What [are] these?' And he saith unto me, `These [are] the horns that have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem.'

20 And Jehovah doth shew me four artisans.

21 And I say, `What [are] these coming in to do?' And He speaketh, saying: `These [are] the horns that have scattered Judah, so that no one hath lifted up his head, and these come in to trouble them, to cast down the horns of the nations who are lifting up a horn against the land of Judah--to scatter it.'

Zechariah 2

1 And I lift up mine eyes, and look, and lo, a man, and in his hand a measuring line.

2 And I say, `Whither are thou going?' And he saith unto me, `To measure Jerusalem, to see how much [is] its breadth, and how much its length.'

3 And lo, the messenger who is speaking with me is going out, and another messenger is going out to meet him,

4 and he saith unto him, `Run, speak unto this young man, saying: Unwalled villages inhabit doth Jerusalem, From the abundance of man and beast in her midst.

5 And I--I am to her--an affirmation of Jehovah, A wall of fire round about, And for honour I am in her midst.

6 Ho, ho, and flee from the land of the north, An affirmation of Jehovah, For, as the four winds of the heavens, I have spread you abroad, An affirmation of Jehovah.

7 Ho, Zion, be delivered who art dwelling [with] the daughter of Babylon.

8 For thus said Jehovah of Hosts: After honour He hath sent me unto the nations who are spoiling you, For he who is coming against you, Is coming against the daughter of His eye.

9 For lo, I am waving my hand against them, And they have been a spoil to their servants. And ye have known that Jehovah of Hosts hath sent me.

10 Singe, and rejoice, O daughter of Zion, For lo, I am coming, and have dwelt in thy midst, An affirmation of Jehovah.

11 And joined have been many nations unto Jehovah in that day, And they have been to Me for a people, And I have dwelt in thy midst, And thou hast known that Jehovah of Hosts hath sent me unto thee.

12 And Jehovah hath inherited Judah, His portion on the holy ground, And He hath fixed again on Jerusalem.

13 Hush, all flesh, because of Jehovah, For He hath been roused up from His holy habitation!'

Zechariah 7

1 And it cometh to pass, in the fourth year of Darius the king hath a word of Jehovah been unto Zechariah, in the fourth of the ninth month, in Chisleu.

2 And Beth-El sendeth Sherezer and Regem-Melech, and its men, to appease the face of Jehovah,

3 speaking unto the priests who [are] at the house of Jehovah of Hosts, and unto the prophets, saying, `Do I weep in the fifth month--being separated--as I have done these so many years?'

4 And there is a word of Jehovah of Hosts unto me, saying:

5 `Speak unto all the people of the land, and unto the priests, saying:

6 When ye fasted with mourning in the fifth and in the seventh [months] --even these seventy years--did ye keep the fast [to] Me--Me? And when ye eat, and when ye drink, is it not ye who are eating, and ye who are drinking?

7 `Are not [these] the words that Jehovah proclaimed by the hand of the former prophets, in Jerusalem's being inhabited, and [in] safety, and its cities round about it, and the south and the plain--abiding?'

8 And there is a word of Jehovah unto Zechariah, saying:

9 `Thus spake Jehovah of Hosts, saying: True judgment judge ye, And kindness and mercy do one with another.

10 And widow, and fatherless, Sojourner, and poor, ye do not oppress, And the calamity of one another ye do not devise in your heart.

11 And they refuse to attend, And they give a refractory shoulder, And their ears have made heavy against hearing.

12 And their heart they have made adamant, Against hearing the law, and the words, That Jehovah of Hosts sent by His Spirit, By the hand of the former prophets, And their is great wrath from Jehovah of Hosts.

13 And it cometh to pass, as He called, And they have not hearkened, So do they call, and I do not hearken, Said Jehovah of Hosts.

14 And I toss them on all the nations, That they have not known, The land hath been desolate behind them, Of any passing by and turning back, And they set a desirable land for a desolation!

Zechariah 8

1 And there is a word of Jehovah of Hosts, saying:

2 `Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: I have been zealous for Zion with great zeal, With great heat I have been zealous for her.

3 Thus said Jehovah: I have turned back unto Zion, And I have dwelt in the midst of Jerusalem, And Jerusalem hath been called `The city of truth,' And the mountain of Jehovah of Hosts, `The holy mountain.'

4 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Again dwell do old men and old women, In broad places of Jerusalem, And each his staff in his hand, Because of abundance of days.

5 And broad places of the city are full of boys and girls, Playing in its broad places.

6 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Surely it is wonderful in the eyes of the remnant of this people in those days, Also in Mine eyes it is wonderful, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts.

7 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Lo, I am saving My people from the land of the rising, And from the land of the going in, of the sun,

8 And I have brought them in, They have dwelt in the midst of Jerusalem, And they have been to Me for a people, And I am to them for God, In truth and in righteousness.

9 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Let your hands be strong, Ye who are hearing in these days these words from the mouth of the prophets, That in the day the house of Jehovah of Hosts Hath been founded, the temple [is] to be built.

10 For, before those days there hath been no hiring of man, Yea, a hiring of beasts there is none; And to him who is going out, And to him who is coming in, There is no peace because of the adversary, And I send all men--each against his neighbour.

11 And now, not as [in] the former days [am] I to the remnant of this people, An affirmation of Jehovah of Hosts.

12 Because of the sowing of peace, The vine doth give her fruit, And the earth doth give her increase, And the heavens do give their dew, And I have caused the remnant of this people To inherit all these.

13 And it hath come to pass, As ye have been a reviling among nations, O house of Judah, and house of Israel, So I save you, and ye have been a blessing, Do not fear, let your hands be strong.

14 For, thus said Jehovah of Hosts, As I did purpose to do evil to you, When your fathers made Me wroth, Said Jehovah of Hosts, and I did not repent,

15 So I have turned back, I have purposed, in these days, To do good with Jerusalem, And with the house of Judah--fear not!

16 These [are] the things that ye do: Speak ye truth each with his neighbour, Truth and peaceful judgment judge in your gates,

17 And each the evil of his neighbour ye do not devise in your heart, And a false oath ye do not love, For all these [are] things that I have hated, An affirmation of Jehovah.'

18 And there is a word of Jehovah of Hosts unto me, saying:

19 `Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: The fast of the fourth, and the fast of the fifth, and the fast of the seventh, and the fast of the tenth [months], are to the house of Judah for joy and for rejoicing, and for pleasant appointed seasons, and the truth and the peace they have loved.

20 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: Yet come do peoples, and inhabitants of many cities,

21 Yea, gone have inhabitants of one To another, saying: We go diligently, To appease the face of Jehovah, To seek Jehovah of Hosts--I go, even I.

22 Yea, come in have many peoples, and mighty nations, To seek Jehovah of Hosts in Jerusalem, And to appease the face of Jehovah.

23 Thus said Jehovah of Hosts: In those days take hold do ten men of all languages of the nations, Yea, they have taken hold on the skirt of a man, a Jew, saying: We go with you, for we heard God [is] with you!

Zechariah 9

1 The burden of a word of Jehovah against the land of Hadrach, and Demmeseh--his place of rest: (When to Jehovah [is] the eye of man, And of all the tribes of Israel.)

2 And also Hamath doth border thereon, Tyre and Zidon, for--very wise!

3 And Tyre doth build a bulwark to herself, And doth heap silver as dust, And gold as mire of out-places.

4 Lo, the Lord doth dispossess her, And He hath smitten in the sea her force, And she with fire is consumed.

5 See doth Ashkelon and fear, Also Gaza, and she is exceedingly pained, Also Ekron- -for her expectation dried up, And perished hath a king from Gaza, And Ashkelon doth not remain,

6 And dwelt hath a foreigner in Ashdod, And I have cut off the excellency of the Philistines.

7 And turned aside his blood from his mouth, His abominations from between his teeth, And he hath remained, even he, to our God, And he hath been as a leader in Judah, And Ekron as a Jebusite.

8 And I have pitched for My house a camp, Because of the passer through, and of the returner, And pass not through against them again doth an exactor, For, now, I have seen with My eyes.

9 Rejoice exceedingly, O daughter of Zion, Shout, O daughter of Jerusalem, Lo, thy King doth come to thee, Righteous--and saved is He, Afflicted--and riding on an ass, And on a colt- -a son of she-asses.

10 And I have cut off the chariot from Ephraim, And the horse from Jerusalem, Yea, cut off hath been the bow of battle, And he hath spoken peace to nations, And his rule [is] from sea unto sea, And from the river unto the ends of earth.

11 Also thou--by the blood of thy covenant, I have sent thy prisoners out of the pit, There is no water in it.

12 Turn back to a fenced place, Ye prisoners of the hope, Even to-day a second announcer I restore to thee.

13 For I have trodden for Me Judah, A bow I have filled [with] Ephraim, And I have stirred up thy sons, O Zion, Against thy sons, O Javan, And I have set thee as the sword of a hero.

14 And Jehovah doth appear for them, And gone forth as lightning hath His arrow, And the Lord Jehovah with a trumpet bloweth, And He hath gone with whirlwinds of the south.

15 Jehovah of Hosts doth cover them over, And they consumed, and subdued slingstones, Yea, they have drunk, They have made a noise as wine, And they have been full as a bowl, As corners of an altar.

16 And saved them hath Jehovah their God In that day, as a flock of His people, For stones of a crown are displaying themselves over His ground.

17 For what His goodness! and what His beauty! Corn the young men, And new wine the virgins--make fruitful!

Zechariah 10

1 They asked of Jehovah rain in a time of latter rain, Jehovah is making lightnings, And rain [in] showers He doth give to them. To each--the herb in the field.

2 Because the teraphim did speak iniquity, And the diviners have seen a falsehood, And dreams of the vanity they speak, [With] vanity they give comfort, Therefore they have journeyed as a flock, They are afflicted, for there is no shepherd.

3 Against the shepherds did Mine anger burn, And against the he-goats I lay a charge, For inspected hath Jehovah of Hosts His flock, the house of Judah, And set them as His beauteous horse in battle.

4 From him [is] a corner-stone, From him a nail, from him a battle-bow, From him goeth forth every exactor together.

5 And they have been as heroes, Treading in mire of out-places in battle, And they have fought, for Jehovah [is] with them, And have put to shame riders of horses.

6 And I have made mighty the house of Judah, And the house of Joseph I do save, And I have caused them to dwell, for I have loved them, And they have been as [if] I had not cast them off, For I [am] Jehovah their God, And I answer them.

7 And Ephraim hath been as a hero, And rejoiced hath their heart as wine, And their sons see, and they have rejoiced, Rejoice doth their heart in Jehovah.

8 I hist for them, and I gather them, For I have redeemed them, And they have multiplied as they did multiply.

9 And I sow them among peoples, And in far-off places they remember Me, And they have lived with their sons, And they have turned back.

10 And I have brought them back from the land of Egypt, And from Asshur I do gather them, And unto the land of Gilead and Lebanon I do bring them in, And there is not found for them [space].

11 And He hath passed over through the sea, And hath pressed and smitten billows in the sea, And dried up have been all depths of a flood, And brought down hath been the excellency of Asshur, And the rod of Egypt doth turn aside.

12 And I have made them mighty in Jehovah, And in His name they walk up and down, An affirmation of Jehovah!

Zechariah 11

1 Open, O Lebanon, thy doors, And fire doth devour among thy cedars.

2 Howl, O fir, for fallen hath the cedar, For their honourable ones were destroyed, Howl, ye oaks of Bashan, For come down hath the fenced forest,

3 A voice of the howling of the shepherds! For destroyed was their robe of honour, A voice of the roaring of young lions! For destroyed was the excellency of Jordan.

4 Thus said Jehovah my God: `Feed the flock of the slaughter,

5 Whose buyers slay them, and are not guilty, And their sellers say, Blessed [is] Jehovah, And I am rich, And their shepherds have no pity on them.

6 For I have pity no more on inhabitants of the land, An affirmation of Jehovah, And lo, I am causing man to come forth, Each into the hand of his neighbour, And into the hand of his king, And they have beaten down the land, And I do not deliver out of their hand.'

7 And I feed the flock of slaughter, even you, ye afflicted of the flock; and I take to me two staves, the one I have called Pleasantness, and the other I have called Bands, and I feed the flock.

8 And I cut off the three shepherds in one month, and my soul is grieved with them, and also their soul hath abhorred me.

9 And I say, `I do not feed you, the dying, let die; and the cut off, let be cut off; and the remaining ones, let each eat the flesh of its neighbour.'

10 And I take My staff Pleasantness, and cut it asunder, to make void My covenant that I had made with all the peoples:

11 and it is broken in that day, and know well do the afflicted of the flock who are observing me, that it [is] a word of Jehovah.

12 And I say unto them: `If good in your eyes, give my hire, and if not, forbear;' and they weigh out my hire--thirty silverlings.

13 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Cast it unto the potter;' the goodly price that I have been prized at by them, and I take the thirty silverlings, and cast them [to] the house of Jehovah, unto the potter.

14 And I cut asunder my second staff, Bands, to break the unity between Judah and Israel.

15 And Jehovah saith unto me, `Again take to thee the instrument of a foolish shepherd.

16 For lo, I am raising up a shepherd in the land, The cut off he doth not inspect, The shaken off he doth not seek, And the broken he doth not heal, The standing he doth not sustain, And the flesh of the fat he doth eat, And their hoofs he doth break off.

17 Woe [to] the worthless shepherd, forsaking the flock, A sword [is] on his arm, and on his right eye, His arm is utterly dried up, And his right eye is very dim!'

Zechariah 12

1 The burden of a word of Jehovah on Israel. An affirmation of Jehovah, Stretching out heaven, and founding earth, And forming the spirit of man in his midst.

2 Lo, I am making Jerusalem a cup of reeling To all the peoples round about, And also against Judah it is, In the siege against Jerusalem.

3 And it hath come to pass, in that day, I make Jerusalem a burdensome stone to all the peoples, All loading it are completely pressed down, And gathered against it have been all nations of the earth.

4 In that day--an affirmation of Jehovah, I do smite every horse with astonishment, And its rider with madness, And on the house of Judah I open My eyes, And every horse of the peoples I smite with blindness.

5 And leaders of Judah have said in their heart, `Strength to me [are] the inhabitants of Jerusalem, In Jehovah of Hosts their God.'

6 In that day I make the leaders of Judah As a hearth of fire among trees, And as a torch of fire in a sheaf, And they have consumed--on the right and on the left--all the peoples round about, And Jerusalem hath inhabited again her place in Jerusalem.

7 And saved hath Jehovah the tents of Judah first, So that become not great against Judah Doth the beauty of the house of David, And the beauty of the inhabitant of Jerusalem.

8 In that day cover over doth Jehovah the inhabitant of Jerusalem, And the stumbling among them hath been in that day as David, And the house of David as God--As a messenger of Jehovah--before them.

9 And it hath come to pass, in that day, I seek to destroy all the nations Who are coming in against Jerusalem,

10 And I have poured on the house of David, And on the inhabitant of Jerusalem, A spirit of grace and supplications, And they have looked unto Me whom they pierced, And they have mourned over it, Like a mourning over the only one, And they have been in bitterness for it, Like a bitterness over the first-born.

11 In that day, great is the mourning of Jerusalem, As the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the valley of Megiddon,

12 And mourned hath the land--every family apart, The family of the house of David apart, And their women apart; The family of the house of Nathan apart, And their women apart;

13 The family of the house of Levi apart, And their women apart; The family of Shimei apart, And their women apart,

14 All the families that are left, Every family apart, and their women apart!

Zechariah 14

1 Lo, a day hath come to Jehovah, And divided hath been thy spoil in thy midst.

2 And I have gathered all the nations unto Jerusalem to battle, And captured hath been the city, And spoiled have been the houses, And the women are lain with, Gone forth hath half the city in a removal, And the remnant of the people are notcut off from the city.

3 And gone forth hath Jehovah, And He hath fought against those nations, As in the day of His fighting in a day of conflict.

4 And stood have His feet, in that day, On the mount of Olives, That [is] before Jerusalem eastward, And cleft hath been the mount of Olives at its midst, To the east, and to the west, a very great valley, And removed hath the half of the mount towards the north. And its half towards the south.

5 And ye have fled [to] the valley of My mountains, For join doth the valley of the mountains to Azal, And ye have fled as ye fled before the shaking, In the days of Uzziah king of Judah, And come in hath Jehovah my God, All holy ones [are] with Thee.

6 And it hath come to pass, in that day, The precious light is not, it is dense darkness,

7 And there hath been one day, It is known to Jehovah, not day nor night, And it hath been at evening-time--there is light.

8 And it hath come to pass, in that day, Go forth do living waters from Jerusalem, Half of them unto the eastern sea, And half of them unto the western sea, In summer and in winter it is.

9 And Jehovah hath become king over all the land, In that day there is one Jehovah, and His name one.

10 Changed is all the land as a plain, From Gebo to Rimmon, south of Jerusalem, And she hath been high, and hath dwelt in her place, Even from the gate of Benjamin To the place of the first gate, unto the front gate, And from the tower of Hananeel, Unto the wine-vats of the king.

11 And they have dwelt in her, And destruction is no more, And Jerusalem hath dwelt confidently.

12 And this is the plague with which Jehovah Doth plague all the peoples who have warred against Jerusalem, He hath consumed away its flesh, And it is standing on its feet, And its eyes are consumed in their holes, And its tongue is consumedin their mouth.

13 And it hath come to pass, in that day, A great destruction [from] Jehovah is among them, And they have seized each the hand of his neighbour, And gone up hath his hand against the hand of his neighbour.

14 And also Judah is fought with in Jerusalem, And gathered hath been the force of all the nations round about, Gold, and silver, and apparel, in great abundance.

15 And so is the plague of the horse, of the mule, Of the camel, and of the ass, And of all the cattle that are in these camps, As this plague.

16 And it hath come to pass, Every one who hath been left of all the nations, Who are coming in against Jerusalem, They have also gone up from year to year, To bow themselves to the King, Jehovah of Hosts, And to celebrate the feast of the booths.

17 And it hath come to pass, That he who doth not go up of the families of the land unto Jerusalem, To bow himself to the King, Jehovah of Hosts, Even on them there is no shower.

18 And if the family of Egypt go not up, nor come in, Then not on them is the plague With which Jehovah doth plague the nations That go not up to celebrate the feast of booths.

19 This is the punishment of the sin of Egypt, And the punishment of the sin of all the nations, That go not up to celebrate the feast of booths.

20 In that day there is on bells of the horse, `Holy to Jehovah,' And the pots in the house of Jehovah Have been as bowls before the altar.

21 And every pot in Jerusalem, and in Judah, Have been holy to Jehovah of Hosts, And all those sacrificing have come in, And have taken of them, and boiled in them, And there is no merchant any more in the house of Jehovah of Hosts in that day!

Malachi 2

1 And now, to you [is] this charge, O priests,

2 If ye hearken not, and if ye lay [it] not to heart, To give honour to My name, said Jehovah of Hosts, I have sent against you the curse, And I have cursed your blessings, Yea, I have also cursed it, Because ye are not laying [it] to heart.

3 Lo, I am pushing away before you the seed, And have scattered dung before your faces, Dung of your festivals, And it hath taken you away with it.

4 And ye have known that I have sent unto you this charge, For My covenant being with Levi, Said Jehovah of Hosts.

5 My covenant hath been with him of life and of peace, And I make them to him a fear, and he doth fear Me, And because of My name he hath been affrighted.

6 The law of truth hath been in his mouth, And perverseness hath not been found in his lips, In peace and in uprightness he walked with Me, And many he brought back from iniquity.

7 For the lips of a priest preserve knowledge, And law they do seek from his mouth, For a messenger of Jehovah of Hosts he [is].

8 And ye, ye have turned from the way, Ye have caused many to stumble in the law, Ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi, Said Jehovah of Hosts.

9 And I also, I have made you despised and low before all the people, Because ye are not keeping My ways, And are accepting persons in the law.

10 Have we not all one father? Hath not our God prepared us? Wherefore do we deal treacherously, Each against his brother, To pollute the covenant of our fathers?

11 Dealt treacherously hath Judah, And abomination hath been done in Israel, and in Jerusalem, For polluted hath Judah the holy thing of Jehovah, That He hath loved, and hath married the daughter of a strange god.

12 Cut off doth Jehovah the man who doth it, Tempter and tempted--from the tents of Jacob, Even he who is bringing nigh a present to Jehovah of Hosts.

13 And this a second time ye do, Covering with tears the altar of Jehovah, With weeping and groaning, Because there is no more turning unto the present, Or receiving of a pleasing thing from your hand.

14 And ye have said, `Wherefore?' Because Jehovah hath testified between thee And the wife of thy youth, That thou hast dealt treacherously against her, And she thy companion, and thy covenant-wife.

15 And He did not make one [only], And He hath the remnant of the Spirit. And what [is] the one [alone]! He is seeking a godly seed. And ye have been watchful over your spirit, And with the wife of thy youth, None doth deal treacherously.

16 For [I] hate sending away, said Jehovah, God of Israel, And He [who] hath covered violence with his clothing, said Jehovah of Hosts, And ye have been watchful over your spirit, And ye do not deal treacherously.

17 Ye have wearied Jehovah with your words, And ye have said: `In what have we wearied Him?' In your saying: `Every evil-doer [is] good in the eyes of Jehovah, And in them He is delighting,' Or, `Where [is] the God of judgment?'

Malachi 3

1 Lo, I am sending My messenger, And he hath prepared a way before Me, And suddenly come in unto his temple Doth the Lord whom ye are seeking, Even the messenger of the covenant, Whom ye are desiring, Lo, he is coming, said Jehovah of Hosts.

2 And who is bearing the day of his coming? And who is standing in his appearing? For he [is] as fire of a refiner, And as soap of a fuller.

3 And he hath sat, a refiner and purifier of silver, And he hath purified the sons of Levi, And hath refined them as gold and as silver, And they have been to Jehovah bringing nigh a present in righteousness.

4 And sweet to Jehovah hath been the present of Judah and Jerusalem, As in days of old, and as in former years.

5 And I have drawn near to you for judgment, And I have been a witness, Making haste against sorcerers, And against adulterers, And against swearers to a falsehood, And against oppressors of the hire of an hireling, Of a widow, and of a fatherless one, And those turning aside a sojourner, And who fear Me not, said Jehovah of Hosts.

6 For I [am] Jehovah, I have not changed, And ye, the sons of Jacob, Ye have not been consumed.

7 Even from the days of your fathers Ye have turned aside from My statutes, And ye have not taken heed. Turn back unto Me, and I turn back to you, Said Jehovah of Hosts. And ye have said, `In what do we turn back?'

8 Doth man deceive God? but ye are deceiving Me, And ye have said: `In what have we deceived Thee?' The tithe and the heave-offering!

9 With a curse ye are cursed! And Me ye are deceiving--this nation--all of it.

10 Bring in all the tithe unto the treasure-house, And there is food in My house; When ye have tried Me, now, with this, Said Jehovah of Hosts, Do not I open to you the windows of heaven? Yea, I have emptied on you a blessing till there is no space.

11 And I have pushed for you against the consumer, And He doth not destroy to you the fruit of the ground, Nor miscarry to you doth the vine in the field, Said Jehovah of Hosts.

12 And declared you happy have all the nations, For ye are a delightful land, said Jehovah of Hosts.

13 Hard against Me have been your words, Said Jehovah, and ye have said: `What have we spoken against Thee?'

14 Ye have said, `A vain thing to serve God! And what gain when we kept His charge? And when we have gone in black, Because of Jehovah of Hosts?

15 And now, we are declaring the proud happy, Yea, built up have been those doing wickedness, Yea they have tempted God, and escape.'

16 Then have those fearing Jehovah spoken one to another, And Jehovah doth attend and hear, And written is a book of memorial before Him Of those fearing Jehovah, And of those esteeming His name.

17 And they have been to Me, said Jehovah of Hosts, In the day that I am appointing--a peculiar treasure, And I have had pity on them, As one hath pity on his son who is serving him.

18 And ye have turned back and considered, Between the righteous and the wicked, Between the servant of God and him who is not His servant.

Matthew 5

1 And having seen the multitudes, he went up to the mount, and he having sat down, his disciples came to him,

2 and having opened his mouth, he was teaching them, saying:

3 `Happy the poor in spirit--because theirs is the reign of the heavens.

4 `Happy the mourning--because they shall be comforted.

5 `Happy the meek--because they shall inherit the land.

6 `Happy those hungering and thirsting for righteousness--because they shall be filled.

7 `Happy the kind--because they shall find kindness.

8 `Happy the clean in heart--because they shall see God.

9 `Happy the peacemakers--because they shall be called Sons of God.

10 `Happy those persecuted for righteousness' sake--because theirs is the reign of the heavens.

11 `Happy are ye whenever they may reproach you, and may persecute, and may say any evil thing against you falsely for my sake--

12 rejoice ye and be glad, because your reward [is] great in the heavens, for thus did they persecute the prophets who were before you.

13 `Ye are the salt of the land, but if the salt may lose savour, in what shall it be salted? for nothing is it good henceforth, except to be cast without, and to be trodden down by men.

14 `Ye are the light of the world, a city set upon a mount is not able to be hid;

15 nor do they light a lamp, and put it under the measure, but on the lamp-stand, and it shineth to all those in the house;

16 so let your light shine before men, that they may see your good works, and may glorify your Father who [is] in the heavens.

17 `Do not suppose that I came to throw down the law or the prophets--I did not come to throw down, but to fulfil;

18 for, verily I say to you, till that the heaven and the earth may pass away, one iota or one tittle may not pass away from the law, till that all may come to pass.

19 `Whoever therefore may loose one of these commands--the least--and may teach men so, least he shall be called in the reign of the heavens, but whoever may do and may teach [them], he shall be called great in the reign of the heavens.

20 `For I say to you, that if your righteousness may not abound above that of the scribes and Pharisees, ye may not enter to the reign of the heavens.

21 `Ye heard that it was said to the ancients: Thou shalt not kill, and whoever may kill shall be in danger of the judgment;

22 but I--I say to you, that every one who is angry at his brother without cause, shall be in danger of the judgment, and whoever may say to his brother, Empty fellow! shall be in danger of the sanhedrim, and whoever may say, Rebel! shall be indanger of the gehenna of the fire.

23 `If, therefore, thou mayest bring thy gift to the altar, and there mayest remember that thy brother hath anything against thee,

24 leave there thy gift before the altar, and go--first be reconciled to thy brother, and then having come bring thy gift.

25 `Be agreeing with thy opponent quickly, while thou art in the way with him, that the opponent may not deliver thee to the judge, and the judge may deliver thee to the officer, and to prison thou mayest be cast,

26 verily I say to thee, thou mayest not come forth thence till that thou mayest pay the last farthing.

27 `Ye heard that it was said to the ancients: Thou shalt not commit adultery;

28 but I--I say to you, that every one who is looking on a woman to desire her, did already commit adultery with her in his heart.

29 `But, if thy right eye doth cause thee to stumble, pluck it out and cast from thee, for it is good to thee that one of thy members may perish, and not thy whole body be cast to gehenna.

30 `And, if thy right hand doth cause thee to stumble, cut it off, and cast from thee, for it is good to thee that one of thy members may perish, and not thy whole body be cast to gehenna.

31 `And it was said, That whoever may put away his wife, let him give to her a writing of divorce;

32 but I--I say to you, that whoever may put away his wife, save for the matter of whoredom, doth make her to commit adultery; and whoever may marry her who hath been put away doth commit adultery.

33 `Again, ye heard that it was said to the ancients: Thou shalt not swear falsely, but thou shalt pay to the Lord thine oaths;

34 but I--I say to you, not to swear at all; neither by the heaven, because it is the throne of God,

35 nor by the earth, because it is His footstool, nor by Jerusalem, because it is a city of a great king,

36 nor by thy head mayest thou swear, because thou art not able one hair to make white or black;

37 but let your word be, Yes, Yes, No, No, and that which is more than these is of the evil.

38 `Ye heard that it was said: Eye for eye, and tooth for tooth;

39 but I--I say to you, not to resist the evil, but whoever shall slap thee on thy right cheek, turn to him also the other;

40 and whoever is willing to take thee to law, and thy coat to take--suffer to him also the cloak.

41 `And whoever shall impress thee one mile, go with him two,

42 to him who is asking of thee be giving, and him who is willing to borrow from thee thou mayest not turn away.

43 `Ye heard that it was said: Thou shalt love thy neighbour, and shalt hate thine enemy;

44 but I--I say to you, Love your enemies, bless those cursing you, do good to those hating you, and pray for those accusing you falsely, and persecuting you,

45 that ye may be sons of your Father in the heavens, because His sun He doth cause to rise on evil and good, and He doth send rain on righteous and unrighteous.

46 `For, if ye may love those loving you, what reward have ye? do not also the taxgatherers the same?

47 and if ye may salute your brethren only, what do ye abundant? do not also the taxgatherers so?

48 ye shall therefore be perfect, as your Father who [is] in the heavens is perfect.

Matthew 6

1 `Take heed your kindness not to do before men, to be seen by them, and if not-- reward ye have not from your Father who [is] in the heavens;

2 whenever, therefore, thou mayest do kindness, thou mayest not sound a trumpet before thee as the hypocrites do, in the synagogues, and in the streets, that they may have glory from men; verily I say to you--they have their reward!

3 `But thou, doing kindness, let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doth,

4 that thy kindness may be in secret, and thy Father who is seeing in secret Himself shall reward thee manifestly.

5 `And when thou mayest pray, thou shalt not be as the hypocrites, because they love in the synagogues, and in the corners of the broad places--standing--to pray, that they may be seen of men; verily I say to you, that they have their reward.

6 `But thou, when thou mayest pray, go into thy chamber, and having shut thy door, pray to thy Father who [is] in secret, and thy Father who is seeing in secret, shall reward thee manifestly.

7 `And--praying--ye may not use vain repetitions like the nations, for they think that in their much speaking they shall be heard,

8 be ye not therefore like to them, for your Father doth know those things that ye have need of before your asking him;

9 thus therefore pray ye: `Our Father who [art] in the heavens! hallowed be Thy name.

10 `Thy reign come: Thy will come to pass, as in heaven also on the earth.

11 `Our appointed bread give us to-day.

12 `And forgive us our debts, as also we forgive our debtors.

13 `And mayest Thou not lead us to temptation, but deliver us from the evil, because Thine is the reign, and the power, and the glory--to the ages. Amen.

14 `For, if ye may forgive men their trespasses He also will forgive you--your Father who [is] in the heavens;

15 but if ye may not forgive men their trespasses, neither will your Father forgive your trespasses.

16 `And when ye may fast, be ye not as the hypocrites, of sour countenances, for they disfigure their faces, that they may appear to men fasting; verily I say to you, that they have their reward.

17 `But thou, fasting, anoint thy head, and wash thy face,

18 that thou mayest not appear to men fasting, but to thy Father who [is] in secret, and thy Father, who is seeing in secret, shall reward thee manifestly.

19 `Treasure not up to yourselves treasures on the earth, where moth and rust disfigure, and where thieves break through and steal,

20 but treasure up to yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust doth disfigure, and where thieves do not break through nor steal,

21 for where your treasure is, there will be also your heart.

22 `The lamp of the body is the eye, if, therefore, thine eye may be perfect, all thy body shall be enlightened,

23 but if thine eye may be evil, all thy body shall be dark; if, therefore, the light that [is] in thee is darkness--the darkness, how great!

24 `None is able to serve two lords, for either he will hate the one and love the other, or he will hold to the one, and despise the other; ye are not able to serve God and Mammon.

25 `Because of this I say to you, be not anxious for your life, what ye may eat, and what ye may drink, nor for your body, what ye may put on. Is not the life more than the nourishment, and the body than the clothing?

26 look to the fowls of the heaven, for they do not sow, nor reap, nor gather into storehouses, and your heavenly Father doth nourish them; are not ye much better than they?

27 `And who of you, being anxious, is able to add to his age one cubit?

28 and about clothing why are ye anxious? consider well the lilies of the field; how do they grow? they do not labour, nor do they spin;

29 and I say to you, that not even Solomon in all his glory was arrayed as one of these.

30 `And if the herb of the field, that to-day is, and to-morrow is cast to the furnace, God doth so clothe--not much more you, O ye of little faith?

31 therefore ye may not be anxious, saying, What may we eat? or, What may we drink? or, What may we put round?

32 for all these do the nations seek for, for your heavenly Father doth know that ye have need of all these;

33 but seek ye first the reign of God and His righteousness, and all these shall be added to you.

34 Be not therefore anxious for the morrow, for the morrow shall be anxious for its own things; sufficient for the day [is] the evil of it.

Matthew 7

1 `Judge not, that ye may not be judged,

2 for in what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged, and in what measure ye measure, it shall be measured to you.

3 `And why dost thou behold the mote that [is] in thy brother's eye, and the beam that [is] in thine own eye dost not consider?

4 or, how wilt thou say to thy brother, Suffer I may cast out the mote from thine eye, and lo, the beam [is] in thine own eye?

5 Hypocrite, cast out first the beam out of thine own eye, and then thou shalt see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother's eye.

6 `Ye may not give that which is [holy] to the dogs, nor cast your pearls before the swine, that they may not trample them among their feet, and having turned--may rend you.

7 `Ask, and it shall be given to you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened to you;

8 for every one who is asking doth receive, and he who is seeking doth find, and to him who is knocking it shall be opened.

9 `Or what man is of you, of whom, if his son may ask a loaf--a stone will he present to him?

10 and if a fish he may ask--a serpent will he present to him?

11 if, therefore, ye being evil, have known good gifts to give to your children, how much more shall your Father who [is] in the heavens give good things to those asking him?

12 `All things, therefore, whatever ye may will that men may be doing to you, so also do to them, for this is the law and the prophets.

13 `Go ye in through the strait gate, because wide [is] the gate, and broad the way that is leading to the destruction, and many are those going in through it;

14 how strait [is] the gate, and compressed the way that is leading to the life, and few are those finding it!

15 `But, take heed of the false prophets, who come unto you in sheep's clothing, and inwardly are ravening wolves.

16 From their fruits ye shall know them; do [men] gather from thorns grapes? or from thistles figs?

17 so every good tree doth yield good fruits, but the bad tree doth yield evil fruits.

18 A good tree is not able to yield evil fruits, nor a bad tree to yield good fruits.

19 Every tree not yielding good fruit is cut down and is cast to fire:

20 therefore from their fruits ye shall know them.

21 `Not every one who is saying to me Lord, lord, shall come into the reign of the heavens; but he who is doing the will of my Father who is in the heavens.

22 Many will say to me in that day, Lord, lord, have we not in thy name prophesied? and in thy name cast out demons? and in thy name done many mighty things?

23 and then I will acknowledge to them, that--I never knew you, depart from me ye who are working lawlessness.

24 `Therefore, every one who doth hear of me these words, and doth do them, I will liken him to a wise man who built his house upon the rock;

25 and the rain did descend, and the streams came, and the winds blew, and they beat on that house, and it fell not, for it had been founded on the rock.

26 `And every one who is hearing of me these words, and is not doing them, shall be likened to a foolish man who built his house upon the sand;

27 and the rain did descend, and the streams came, and the winds blew, and they beat on that house, and it fell, and its fall was great.'

28 And it came to pass, when Jesus ended these words, the multitudes were astonished at his teaching,

29 for he was teaching them as having authority, and not as the scribes.

Matthew 10

1 And having called to him his twelve disciples, he gave to them power over unclean spirits, so as to be casting them out, and to be healing every sickness, and every malady.

2 And of the twelve apostles the names are these: first, Simon, who is called Peter, and Andrew his brother; James of Zebedee, and John his brother;

3 Philip, and Bartholomew; Thomas, and Matthew the tax-gatherer; James of Alpheus, and Lebbeus who was surnamed Thaddeus;

4 Simon the Cananite, and Judas Iscariot, who did also deliver him up.

5 These twelve did Jesus send forth, having given command to them, saying, `To the way of the nations go not away, and into a city of the Samaritans go not in,

6 and be going rather unto the lost sheep of the house of Israel.

7 `And, going on, proclaim saying that, the reign of the heavens hath come nigh;

8 infirm ones be healing, lepers be cleansing, dead be raising, demons be casting out-- freely ye did receive, freely give.

9 `Provide not gold, nor silver, nor brass in your girdles,

10 nor scrip for the way, nor two coats, nor sandals, nor staff--for the workman is worthy of his nourishment.

11 `And into whatever city or village ye may enter, inquire ye who in it is worthy, and there abide, till ye may go forth.

12 And coming to the house salute it,

13 and if indeed the house be worthy, let your peace come upon it; and if it be not worthy, let your peace turn back to you.

14 `And whoever may not receive you nor hear your words, coming forth from that house or city, shake off the dust of your feet,

15 verily I say to you, It shall be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment than for that city.

16 `Lo, I do send you forth as sheep in the midst of wolves, be ye therefore wise as the serpents, and simple as the doves.

17 And, take ye heed of men, for they will give you up to sanhedrims, and in their synagogues they will scourge you,

18 and before governors and kings ye shall be brought for my sake, for a testimony to them and to the nations.

19 `And whenever they may deliver you up, be not anxious how or what ye may speak, for it shall be given you in that hour what ye shall speak;

20 for ye are not the speakers, but the Spirit of your Father that is speaking in you.

21 `And brother shall deliver up brother to death, and father child, and children shall rise up against parents, and shall put them to death,

22 and ye shall be hated by all because of my name, but he who hath endured to the end, he shall be saved.

23 `And whenever they may persecute you in this city, flee to the other, for verily I say to you, ye may not have completed the cities of Israel till the Son of Man may come.

24 `A disciple is not above the teacher, nor a servant above his lord;

25 sufficient to the disciple that he may be as his teacher, and the servant as his lord; if the master of the house they did call Beelzeboul, how much more those of his household?

26 `Ye may not, therefore, fear them, for there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed, and hid, that shall not be known;

27 that which I tell you in the darkness, speak in the light, and that which you hear at the ear, proclaim on the house-tops.

28 `And be not afraid of those killing the body, and are not able to kill the soul, but fear rather Him who is able both soul and body to destroy in gehenna.

29 `Are not two sparrows sold for an assar? and one of them shall not fall on the ground without your Father;

30 and of you--even the hairs of the head are all numbered;

31 be not therefore afraid, than many sparrows ye are better.

32 `Every one, therefore, who shall confess in me before men, I also will confess in him before my Father who is in the heavens;

33 and whoever shall deny me before men, I also will deny him before my Father who is in the heavens.

34 `Ye may not suppose that I came to put peace on the earth; I did not come to put peace, but a sword;

35 for I came to set a man at variance against his father, and a daughter against her mother, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law,

36 and the enemies of a man are those of his household.

37 `He who is loving father or mother above me, is not worthy of me, and he who is loving son or daughter above me, is not worthy of me,

38 and whoever doth not receive his cross and follow after me, is not worthy of me.

39 `He who found his life shall lose it, and he who lost his life for my sake shall find it.

40 `He who is receiving you doth receive me, and he who is receiving me doth receive Him who sent me,

41 he who is receiving a prophet in the name of a prophet, shall receive a prophet's reward, and he who is receiving a righteous man in the name of a righteous man, shall receive a righteous man's reward,

42 and whoever may give to drink to one of these little ones a cup of cold water only in the name of a disciple, verily I say to you, he may not lose his reward.'

Matthew 11

1 And it came to pass, when Jesus ended directing his twelve disciples, he departed thence to teach and to preach in their cities.

2 And John having heard in the prison the works of the Christ, having sent two of his disciples,

3 said to him, `Art thou He who is coming, or for another do we look?'

4 And Jesus answering said to them, `Having gone, declare to John the things that ye hear and see,

5 blind receive sight, and lame walk, lepers are cleansed, and deaf hear, dead are raised, and poor have good news proclaimed,

6 and happy is he who may not be stumbled in me.'

7 And as they are going, Jesus began to say to the multitudes concerning John, `What went ye out to the wilderness to view? --a reed shaken by the wind?

8 `But what went ye out to see? --a man clothed in soft garments? lo, those wearing the soft things are in the kings' houses.

9 `But what went ye out to see? --a prophet? yes, I say to you, and more than a prophet,

10 for this is he of whom it hath been written, Lo, I do send My messenger before thy face, who shall prepare thy way before thee.

11 Verily I say to you, there hath not risen, among those born of women, a greater than John the Baptist, but he who is least in the reign of the heavens is greater than he.

12 `And, from the days of John the Baptist till now, the reign of the heavens doth suffer violence, and violent men do take it by force,

13 for all the prophets and the law till John did prophesy,

14 and if ye are willing to receive [it], he is Elijah who was about to come;

15 he who is having ears to hear--let him hear.

16 `And to what shall I liken this generation? it is like little children in market-places, sitting and calling to their comrades,

17 and saying, We piped unto you, and ye did not dance, we lamented to you, and ye did not smite the breast.

18 `For John came neither eating nor drinking, and they say, He hath a demon;

19 the Son of Man came eating and drinking, and they say, Lo, a man, a glutton, and a wine-drinker, a friend of tax-gatherers and sinners, and wisdom was justified of her children.'

20 Then began he to reproach the cities in which were done most of his mighty works, because they did not reform.

21 `Woe to thee, Chorazin! woe to thee, Bethsaida! because, if in Tyre and Sidon had been done the mighty works that were done in you, long ago in sackcloth and ashes they had reformed;

22 but I say to you, to Tyre and Sidon it shall be more tolerable in a day of judgment than for you.

23 `And thou, Capernaum, which unto the heaven wast exalted, unto hades shalt be brought down, because if in Sodom had been done the mighty works that were done in thee, it had remained unto this day;

24 but I say to you, to the land of Sodom it shall be more tolerable in a day of judgment than to thee.'

25 At that time Jesus answering said, `I do confess to Thee, Father, Lord of the heavens and of the earth, that thou didst hide these things from wise and understanding ones, and didst reveal them to babes.

26 Yes, Father, because so it was good pleasure before Thee.

27 `All things were delivered to me by my Father, and none doth know the Son, except the Father, nor doth any know the Father, except the Son, and he to whom the Son may wish to reveal [Him].

28 `Come unto me, all ye labouring and burdened ones, and I will give you rest,

29 take up my yoke upon you, and learn from me, because I am meek and humble in heart, and ye shall find rest to your souls,

30 for my yoke [is] easy, and my burden is light.'

Matthew 12

1 At that time did Jesus go on the sabbaths through the corn, and his disciples were hungry, and they began to pluck ears, and to eat,

2 and the Pharisees having seen, said to him, `Lo, thy disciples do that which it is not lawful to do on a sabbath.'

3 And he said to them, `Did ye not read what David did, when he was hungry, himself and those with him--

4 how he went into the house of God, and the loaves of the presentation did eat, which it is not lawful to him to eat, nor to those with him, except to the priests alone?

5 `Or did ye not read in the Law, that on the sabbaths the priests in the temple do profane the sabbath, and are blameless?

6 and I say to you, that a greater than the temple is here;

7 and if ye had known what is: Kindness I will, and not sacrifice--ye had not condemned the blameless,

8 for the son of man is lord even of the sabbath.'

9 And having departed thence, he went to their synagogue,

10 and lo, there was a man having the hand withered, and they questioned him, saying, `Is it lawful to heal on the sabbaths?' that they might accuse him.

11 And he said to them, `What man shall be of you, who shall have one sheep, and if this may fall on the sabbaths into a ditch, will not lay hold on it and raise [it]?

12 How much better, therefore, is a man than a sheep? --so that it is lawful on the sabbaths to do good.'

13 Then saith he to the man, `Stretch forth thy hand,' and he stretched [it] forth, and it was restored whole as the other.

14 And the Pharisees having gone forth, held a consultation against him, how they might destroy him,

15 and Jesus having known, withdrew thence, and there followed him great multitudes, and he healed them all,

16 and did charge them that they might not make him manifest,

17 that it might be fulfilled that was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying,

18 `Lo, My servant, whom I did choose, My beloved, in whom My soul did delight, I will put My Spirit upon him, and judgment to the nations he shall declare,

19 he shall not strive nor cry, nor shall any hear in the broad places his voice,

20 a bruised reed he shall not break, and smoking flax he shall not quench, till he may put forth judgment to victory,

21 and in his name shall nations hope.'

22 Then was brought to him a demoniac, blind and dumb, and he healed him, so that the blind and dumb both spake and saw.

23 And all the multitudes were amazed, and said, `Is this the Son of David?'

24 but the Pharisees having heard, said, `This one doth not cast out demons, except by Beelzeboul, ruler of the demons.'

25 And Jesus, knowing their thoughts, said to them, `Every kingdom having been divided against itself is desolated, and no city or house having been divided against itself, doth stand,

26 and if the Adversary doth cast out the Adversary, against himself he was divided, how then doth his kingdom stand?

27 `And if I, by Beelzeboul, do cast out the demons, your sons--by whom do they cast out? because of this they--they shall be your judges.

28 `But if I, by the Spirit of God, do cast out the demons, then come already unto you did the reign of God.

29 `Or how is one able to go into the house of the strong man, and to plunder his goods, if first he may not bind the strong man? and then his house he will plunder.

30 `He who is not with me is against me, and he who is not gathering with me, doth scatter.

31 Because of this I say to you, all sin and evil speaking shall be forgiven to men, but the evil speaking of the Spirit shall not be forgiven to men.

32 And whoever may speak a word against the Son of Man it shall be forgiven to him, but whoever may speak against the Holy Spirit, it shall not be forgiven him, neither in this age, nor in that which is coming.

33 `Either make the tree good, and its fruit good, or make the tree bad, and its fruit bad, for from the fruit is the tree known.

34 `Brood of vipers! how are ye able to speak good things--being evil? for out of the abundance of the heart doth the mouth speak.

35 The good man out of the good treasure of the heart doth put forth the good things, and the evil man out of the evil treasure doth put forth evil things.

36 `And I say to you, that every idle word that men may speak, they shall give for it a reckoning in a day of judgment;

37 for from thy words thou shalt be declared righteous, and from thy words thou shalt be declared unrighteous.'

38 Then answered certain of the scribes and Pharisees, saying, `Teacher, we will to see a sign from thee.'

39 And he answering said to them, `A generation, evil and adulterous, doth seek a sign, and a sign shall not be given to it, except the sign of Jonah the prophet;

40 for, as Jonah was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights, so shall the Son of Man be in the heart of the earth three days and three nights.

41 `Men of Nineveh shall stand up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it, for they reformed at the proclamation of Jonah, and lo, a greater than Jonah here!

42 `A queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it, for she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon, and lo, a greater than Solomon here!

43 `And, when the unclean spirit may go forth from the man, it doth walk through dry places seeking rest, and doth not find;

44 then it saith, I will turn back to my house whence I came forth; and having come, it findeth [it] unoccupied, swept, and adorned:

45 then doth it go, and take with itself seven other spirits more evil than itself, and having gone in they dwell there, and the last of that man doth become worse than the first; so shall it be also to this evil generation.'

46 And while he was yet speaking to the multitudes, lo, his mother and brethren had stood without, seeking to speak to him,

47 and one said to him, `Lo, thy mother and thy brethren do stand without, seeking to speak to thee.'

48 And he answering said to him who spake to him, `Who is my mother? and who are my brethren?'

49 And having stretched forth his hand toward his disciples, he said, `Lo, my mother and my brethren!

50 for whoever may do the will of my Father who is in the heavens, he is my brother, and sister, and mother.'

Matthew 16

1 And the Pharisees and Sadducees having come, tempting, did question him, to shew to them a sign from the heaven,

2 and he answering said to them, `Evening having come, ye say, Fair weather, for the heaven is red,

3 and at morning, Foul weather to-day, for the heaven is red--gloomy; hypocrites, the face of the heavens indeed ye do know to discern, but the signs of the times ye are not able!

4 `A generation evil and adulterous doth seek a sign, and a sign shall not be given to it, except the sign of Jonah the prophet;' and having left them he went away.

5 And his disciples having come to the other side, forgot to take loaves,

6 and Jesus said to them, `Beware, and take heed of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees;'

7 and they were reasoning in themselves, saying, `Because we took no loaves.'

8 And Jesus having known, said to them, `Why reason ye in yourselves, ye of little faith, because ye took no loaves?

9 do ye not yet understand, nor remember the five loaves of the five thousand, and how many hand-baskets ye took up?

10 nor the seven loaves of the four thousand, and how many baskets ye took up?

11 how do ye not understand that I did not speak to you of bread--to take heed of the leaven of the Pharisees and Sadducees?'

12 Then they understood that he did not say to take heed of the leaven of the bread, but of the teaching, of the Pharisees and Sadducees.

13 And Jesus, having come to the parts of Caesarea Philippi, was asking his disciples, saying, `Who do men say me to be--the Son of Man?'

14 and they said, `Some, John the Baptist, and others, Elijah, and others, Jeremiah, or one of the prophets.'

15 He saith to them, `And ye--who do ye say me to be?'

16 and Simon Peter answering said, `Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.'

17 And Jesus answering said to him, `Happy art thou, Simon Bar-Jona, because flesh and blood did not reveal [it] to thee, but my Father who is in the heavens.

18 `And I also say to thee, that thou art a rock, and upon this rock I will build my assembly, and gates of Hades shall not prevail against it;

19 and I will give to thee the keys of the reign of the heavens, and whatever thou mayest bind upon the earth shall be having been bound in the heavens, and whatever thou mayest loose upon the earth shall be having been loosed in the heavens.'

20 Then did he charge his disciples that they may say to no one that he is Jesus the Christ.

21 From that time began Jesus to shew to his disciples that it is necessary for him to go away to Jerusalem, and to suffer many things from the elders, and chief priests, and scribes, and to be put to death, and the third day to rise.

22 And having taken him aside, Peter began to rebuke him, saying, `Be kind to thyself, sir; this shall not be to thee;'

23 and he having turned, said to Peter, `Get thee behind me, adversary! thou art a stumbling-block to me, for thou dost not mind the things of God, but the things of men.'

24 Then said Jesus to his disciples, `If any one doth will to come after me, let him disown himself, and take up his cross, and follow me,

25 for whoever may will to save his life, shall lose it, and whoever may lose his life for my sake shall find it,

26 for what is a man profited if he may gain the whole world, but of his life suffer loss? or what shall a man give as an exchange for his life?

27 `For, the Son of Man is about to come in the glory of his Father, with his messengers, and then he will reward each, according to his work.

28 Verily I say to you, there are certain of those standing here who shall not taste of death till they may see the Son of Man coming in his reign.'

Matthew 20

1 `For the reign of the heavens is like to a man, a householder, who went forth with the morning to hire workmen for his vineyard,

2 and having agreed with the workmen for a denary a day, he sent them into his vineyard.

3 `And having gone forth about the third hour, he saw others standing in the marketplace idle,

4 and to these he said, Go ye--also ye--to the vineyard, and whatever may be righteous I will give you;

5 and they went away. `Again, having gone forth about the sixth and the ninth hour, he did in like manner.

6 And about the eleventh hour, having gone forth, he found others standing idle, and saith to them, Why here have ye stood all the day idle?

7 they say to him, Because no one did hire us; he saith to them, Go ye--ye also--to the vineyard, and whatever may be righteous ye shall receive.

8 `And evening having come, the lord of the vineyard saith to his steward, Call the workmen, and pay them the reward, having begun from the last--unto the first.

9 And they of about the eleventh hour having come, did receive each a denary.

10 `And the first having come, did suppose that they shall receive more, and they received, they also, each a denary,

11 and having received [it], they were murmuring against the householder, saying,

12 that These, the last, wrought one hour, and thou didst make them equal to us, who were bearing the burden of the day--and the heat.

13 `And he answering said to one of them, Comrade, I do no unrighteousness to thee; for a denary didst not thou agree with me?

14 take that which is thine, and go; and I will to give to this, the last, also as to thee;

15 is it not lawful to me to do what I will in mine own? is thine eye evil because I am good?

16 So the last shall be first, and the first last, for many are called, and few chosen.'

17 And Jesus going up to Jerusalem, took the twelve disciples by themselves in the way, and said to them,

18 `Lo, we go up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man shall be delivered to the chief priests and scribes,

19 and they shall condemn him to death, and shall deliver him to the nations to mock, and to scourge, and to crucify, and the third day he will rise again.'

20 Then came near to him the mother of the sons of Zebedee, with her sons, bowing and asking something from him,

21 and he said to her, `What wilt thou?' She saith to him, `Say, that they may sit-- these my two sons--one on thy right hand, and one on the left, in thy reign.'

22 And Jesus answering said, `Ye have not known what ye ask for yourselves; are ye able to drink of the cup that I am about to drink? and with the baptism that I am baptized with, to be baptized?' They say to him, `We are able.'

23 And he saith to them, `Of my cup indeed ye shall drink, and with the baptism that I am baptized with ye shall be baptized; but to sit on my right hand and on my left is not mine to give, but--to those for whom it hath been prepared by my father.'

24 And the ten having heard, were much displeased with the two brothers,

25 and Jesus having called them near, said, `Ye have known that the rulers of the nations do exercise lordship over them, and those great do exercise authority over them,

26 but not so shall it be among you, but whoever may will among you to become great, let him be your ministrant;

27 and whoever may will among you to be first, let him be your servant;

28 even as the Son of Man did not come to be ministered to, but to minister, and to give his life a ransom for many.'

29 And they going forth from Jericho, there followed him a great multitude,

30 and lo, two blind men sitting by the way, having heard that Jesus doth pass by, cried, saying, `Deal kindly with us, sir--Son of David.'

31 And the multitude charged them that they might be silent, and they cried out the more, saying, `Deal kindly with us sir--Son of David.'

32 And having stood, Jesus called them, and said, `What will ye [that] I may do to you?'

33 they say to him, `Sir, that our eyes may be opened;'

34 and having been moved with compassion, Jesus touched their eyes, and immediately their eyes received sight, and they followed him.

Matthew 23

1 Then Jesus spake to the multitudes, and to his disciples,

2 saying, `On the seat of Moses sat down the scribes and the Pharisees;

3 all, then, as much as they may say to you to observe, observe and do, but according to their works do not, for they say, and do not;

4 for they bind together burdens heavy and grievous to be borne, and lay upon the shoulders of men, but with their finger they will not move them.

5 `And all their works they do to be seen by men, and they make broad their phylacteries, and enlarge the fringes of their garments,

6 they love also the chief couches in the supper, and the chief seats in the synagogues,

7 and the salutations in the market-places, and to be called by men, Rabbi, Rabbi.

8 `And ye--ye may not be called Rabbi, for one is your director--the Christ, and all ye are brethren;

9 and ye may not call [any] your father on the earth, for one is your Father, who is in the heavens,

10 nor may ye be called directors, for one is your director--the Christ.

11 And the greater of you shall be your ministrant,

12 and whoever shall exalt himself shall be humbled, and whoever shall humble himself shall be exalted.

13 `Woe to you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye shut up the reign of the heavens before men, for ye do not go in, nor those going in do ye suffer to enter.

14 `Woe to you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye eat up the houses of the widows, and for a pretence make long prayers, because of this ye shall receive more abundant judgment.

15 `Woe to you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye go round the sea and the dry land to make one proselyte, and whenever it may happen--ye make him a son of gehenna twofold more than yourselves.

16 `Woe to you, blind guides, who are saying, Whoever may swear by the sanctuary, it is nothing, but whoever may swear by the gold of the sanctuary--is debtor!

17 Fools and blind! for which [is] greater, the gold, or the sanctuary that is sanctifying the gold?

18 `And, whoever may swear by the altar, it is nothing; but whoever may swear by the gift that is upon it--is debtor!

19 Fools and blind! for which [is] greater, the gift, or the altar that is sanctifying the gift?

20 `He therefore who did swear by the altar, doth swear by it, and by all things on it;

21 and he who did swear by the sanctuary, doth swear by it, and by Him who is dwelling in it;

22 and he who did swear by the heaven, doth swear by the throne of God, and by Him who is sitting upon it.

23 `Woe to you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye give tithe of the mint, and the dill, and the cumin, and did neglect the weightier things of the Law--the judgment, and the kindness, and the faith; these it behoved [you] to do, and those not to neglect.

24 `Blind guides! who are straining out the gnat, and the camel are swallowing.

25 `Woe to you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye make clean the outside of the cup and the plate, and within they are full of rapine and incontinence.

26 `Blind Pharisee! cleanse first the inside of the cup and the plate, that the outside of them also may become clean.

27 `Woe to you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye are like to whitewashed sepulchres, which outwardly indeed do appear beautiful, and within are full of bones of dead men, and of all uncleanness;

28 so also ye outwardly indeed do appear to men righteous, and within ye are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness.

29 `Woe to you, Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! because ye build the sepulchres of the prophets, and adorn the tombs of the righteous,

30 and say, If we had been in the days of our fathers, we would not have been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets.

31 So that ye testify to yourselves, that ye are sons of them who did murder the prophets;

32 and ye--ye fill up the measure of your fathers.

33 `Serpents! brood of vipers! how may ye escape from the judgment of the gehenna?

34 `Because of this, lo, I send to you prophets, and wise men, and scribes, and of them ye will kill and crucify, and of them ye will scourge in your synagogues, and will pursue from city to city;

35 that on you may come all the righteous blood being poured out on the earth from the blood of Abel the righteous, unto the blood of Zacharias son of Barachias, whom ye slew between the sanctuary and the altar:

36 verily I say to you, all these things shall come upon this generation.

37 `Jerusalem, Jerusalem, that art killing the prophets, and stoning those sent unto thee, how often did I will to gather thy children together, as a hen doth gather her own chickens under the wings, and ye did not will.

38 Lo, left desolate to you is your house;

39 for I say to you, ye may not see me henceforth, till ye may say, Blessed [is] he who is coming in the name of the Lord.'

Matthew 24

1 And having gone forth, Jesus departed from the temple, and his disciples came near to show him the buildings of the temple,

2 and Jesus said to them, `Do ye not see all these? verily I say to you, There may not be left here a stone upon a stone, that shall not be thrown down.'

3 And when he is sitting on the mount of the Olives, the disciples came near to him by himself, saying, `Tell us, when shall these be? and what [is] the sign of thy presence, and of the full end of the age?'

4 And Jesus answering said to them, `Take heed that no one may lead you astray,

5 for many shall come in my name, saying, I am the Christ, and they shall lead many astray,

6 and ye shall begin to hear of wars, and reports of wars; see, be not troubled, for it behoveth all [these] to come to pass, but the end is not yet.

7 `For nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom, and there shall be famines, and pestilences, and earthquakes, in divers places;

8 and all these [are] the beginning of sorrows;

9 then they shall deliver you up to tribulation, and shall kill you, and ye shall be hated by all the nations because of my name;

10 and then shall many be stumbled, and they shall deliver up one another, and shall hate one another.

11 `And many false prophets shall arise, and shall lead many astray;

12 and because of the abounding of the lawlessness, the love of the many shall become cold;

13 but he who did endure to the end, he shall be saved;

14 and this good news of the reign shall be proclaimed in all the world, for a testimony to all the nations; and then shall the end arrive.

15 `Whenever, therefore, ye may see the abomination of the desolation, that was spoken of through Daniel the prophet, standing in the holy place (whoever is reading let him observe)

16 then those in Judea--let them flee to the mounts;

17 he on the house-top--let him not come down to take up any thing out of his house;

18 and he in the field--let him not turn back to take his garments.

19 `And woe to those with child, and to those giving suck in those days;

20 and pray ye that your flight may not be in winter, nor on a sabbath;

21 for there shall be then great tribulation, such as was not from the beginning of the world till now, no, nor may be.

22 And if those days were not shortened, no flesh would have been saved; but because of the chosen, shall those days be shortened.

23 `Then if any one may say to you, Lo, here [is] the Christ! or here! ye may not believe;

24 for there shall arise false Christs, and false prophets, and they shall give great signs and wonders, so as to lead astray, if possible, also the chosen.

25 Lo, I did tell you beforehand.

26 `If therefore they may say to you, Lo, in the wilderness he is, ye may not go forth; lo, in the inner chambers, ye may not believe;

27 for as the lightning doth come forth from the east, and doth appear unto the west, so shall be also the presence of the Son of Man;

28 for wherever the carcase may be, there shall the eagles be gathered together.

29 `And immediately after the tribulation of those days, the sun shall be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light, and the stars shall fall from the heaven, and the powers of the heavens shall be shaken;

30 and then shall appear the sign of the Son of Man in the heaven; and then shall all the tribes of the earth smite the breast, and they shall see the Son of Man coming upon the clouds of the heaven, with power and much glory;

31 and he shall send his messengers with a great sound of a trumpet, and they shall gather together his chosen from the four winds, from the ends of the heavens unto the ends thereof.

32 `And from the fig-tree learn ye the simile: When already its branch may have become tender, and the leaves it may put forth, ye know that summer [is] nigh,

33 so also ye, when ye may see all these, ye know that it is nigh--at the doors.

34 Verily I say to you, this generation may not pass away till all these may come to pass.

35 The heaven and the earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away.

36 `And concerning that day and the hour no one hath known--not even the messengers of the heavens--except my Father only;

37 and as the days of Noah--so shall be also the presence of the Son of Man;

38 for as they were, in the days before the flood, eating, and drinking, marrying, and giving in marriage, till the day Noah entered into the ark,

39 and they did not know till the flood came and took all away; so shall be also the presence of the Son of Man.

40 Then two men shall be in the field, the one is received, and the one is left;

41 two women shall be grinding in the mill, one is received, and one is left.

42 `Watch ye therefore, because ye have not known in what hour your Lord doth come;

43 and this know, that if the master of the house had known in what watch the thief doth come, he had watched, and not suffered his house to be broken through;

44 because of this also ye, become ye ready, because in what hour ye do not think, the Son of Man doth come.

45 `Who, then, is the servant, faithful and wise, whom his lord did set over his household, to give them the nourishment in season?

46 Happy that servant, whom his lord, having come, shall find doing so;

47 verily I say to you, that over all his substance he will set him.

48 `And, if that evil servant may say in his heart, My Lord doth delay to come,

49 and may begin to beat the fellow-servants, and to eat and to drink with the drunken,

50 the lord of that servant will arrive in a day when he doth not expect, and in an hour of which he doth not know,

51 and will cut him off, and his portion with the hypocrites will appoint; there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth.

Matthew 25

1 `Then shall the reign of the heavens be likened to ten virgins, who, having taken their lamps, went forth to meet the bridegroom;

2 and five of them were prudent, and five foolish;

3 they who were foolish having taken their lamps, did not take with themselves oil;

4 and the prudent took oil in their vessels, with their lamps.

5 `And the bridegroom tarrying, they all nodded and were sleeping,

6 and in the middle of the night a cry was made, Lo, the bridegroom doth come; go ye forth to meet him.

7 `Then rose all those virgins, and trimmed their lamps,

8 and the foolish said to the prudent, Give us of your oil, because our lamps are going out;

9 and the prudent answered, saying--Lest there may not be sufficient for us and you, go ye rather unto those selling, and buy for yourselves.

10 `And while they are going away to buy, the bridegroom came, and those ready went in with him to the marriage-feasts, and the door was shut;

11 and afterwards come also do the rest of the virgins, saying, Sir, sir, open to us;

12 and he answering said, Verily I say to you, I have not known you.

13 `Watch therefore, for ye have not known the day nor the hour in which the Son of Man doth come.

14 `For--as a man going abroad did call his own servants, and did deliver to them his substance,

15 and to one he gave five talents, and to another two, and to another one, to each according to his several ability, went abroad immediately.

16 `And he who did receive the five talents, having gone, wrought with them, and made other five talents;

17 in like manner also he who [received] the two, he gained, also he, other two;

18 and he who did receive the one, having gone away, digged in the earth, and hid his lord's money.

19 `And after a long time cometh the lord of those servants, and taketh reckoning with them;

20 and he who did receive the five talents having come, brought other five talents, saying, `Sir, five talents thou didst deliver to me; lo, other five talents did I gain besides them.

21 `And his lord said to him, Well done, servant, good and faithful, over a few things thou wast faithful, over many things I will set thee; enter into the joy of thy lord.

22 `And he who also did receive the two talents having come, said, Sir, two talents thou didst deliver to me; lo, other two talents I did gain besides them.

23 `His lord said to him, Well done, servant, good and faithful, over a few things thou wast faithful, over many things I will set thee; enter into the joy of thy lord.

24 `And he also who hath received the one talent having come, said, Sir, I knew thee, that thou art a hard man, reaping where thou didst not sow, and gathering from whence thou didst not scatter;

25 and having been afraid, having gone away, I hid thy talent in the earth; lo, thou hast thine own!

26 `And his lord answering said to him, Evil servant, and slothful, thou hadst known that I reap where I did not sow, and I gather whence I did not scatter!

27 it behoved thee then to put my money to the money-lenders, and having come I had received mine own with increase.

28 `Take therefore from him the talent, and give to him having the ten talents,

29 for to every one having shall be given, and he shall have overabundance, and from him who is not having, even that which he hath shall be taken from him;

30 and the unprofitable servant cast ye forth to the outer darkness; there shall be the weeping and the gnashing of the teeth.

31 `And whenever the Son of Man may come in his glory, and all the holy messengers with him, then he shall sit upon a throne of his glory;

32 and gathered together before him shall be all the nations, and he shall separate them from one another, as the shepherd doth separate the sheep from the goats,

33 and he shall set the sheep indeed on his right hand, and the goats on the left.

34 `Then shall the king say to those on his right hand, Come ye, the blessed of my Father, inherit the reign that hath been prepared for you from the foundation of the world;

35 for I did hunger, and ye gave me to eat; I did thirst, and ye gave me to drink; I was a stranger, and ye received me;

36 naked, and ye put around me; I was infirm, and ye looked after me; in prison I was, and ye came unto me.

37 `Then shall the righteous answer him, saying, Lord, when did we see thee hungering, and we nourished? or thirsting, and we gave to drink?

38 and when did we see thee a stranger, and we received? or naked, and we put around?

39 and when did we see thee infirm, or in prison, and we came unto thee?

40 `And the king answering, shall say to them, Verily I say to you, Inasmuch as ye did [it] to one of these my brethren--the least--to me ye did [it].

41 Then shall he say also to those on the left hand, Go ye from me, the cursed, to the fire, the age-during, that hath been prepared for the Devil and his messengers;

42 for I did hunger, and ye gave me not to eat; I did thirst, and ye gave me not to drink;

43 a stranger I was, and ye did not receive me; naked, and ye put not around me; infirm, and in prison, and ye did not look after me.

44 `Then shall they answer, they also, saying, Lord, when did we see thee hungering, or thirsting, or a stranger, or naked, or infirm, or in prison, and we did not minister to thee?

45 `Then shall he answer them, saying, Verily I say to you, Inasmuch as ye did [it] not to one of these, the least, ye did [it] not to me.

46 And these shall go away to punishment age-during, but the righteous to life ageduring.'

Mark 3

1 And he entered again into the synagogue, and there was there a man having the hand withered,

2 and they were watching him, whether on the sabbaths he will heal him, that they might accuse him.

3 And he saith to the man having the hand withered, `Rise up in the midst.'

4 And he saith to them, `Is it lawful on the sabbaths to do good, or to do evil? life to save, or to kill?' but they were silent.

5 And having looked round upon them with anger, being grieved for the hardness of their heart, he saith to the man, `Stretch forth thy hand;' and he stretched forth, and his hand was restored whole as the other;

6 and the Pharisees having gone forth, immediately, with the Herodians, were taking counsel against him how they might destroy him.

7 And Jesus withdrew with his disciples unto the sea, and a great multitude from Galilee followed him, and from Judea,

8 and from Jerusalem, and from Idumea and beyond the Jordan; and they about Tyre and Sidon--a great multitude--having heard how great things he was doing, came unto him.

9 And he said to his disciples that a little boat may wait on him, because of the multitude, that they may not press upon him,

10 for he did heal many, so that they threw themselves on him, in order to touch him--as many as had plagues;

11 and the unclean spirits, when they were seeing him, were falling down before him, and were crying, saying--`Thou art the Son of God;'

12 and many times he was charging them that they might not make him manifest.

13 And he goeth up to the mountain, and doth call near whom he willed, and they went away to him;

14 and he appointed twelve, that they may be with him, and that he may send them forth to preach,

15 and to have power to heal the sicknesses, and to cast out the demons.

16 And he put on Simon the name Peter;

17 and James of Zebedee, and John the brother of James, and he put on them names-- Boanerges, that is, `Sons of thunder;'

18 and Andrew, and Philip, and Bartholomew, and Matthew, and Thomas, and James of Alpheus, and Thaddeus, and Simon the Cananite,

19 and Judas Iscariot, who did also deliver him up; and they come into a house.

20 And come together again doth a multitude, so that they are not able even to eat bread;

21 and his friends having heard, went forth to lay hold on him, for they said that he was beside himself,

22 and the scribes who [are] from Jerusalem having come down, said--`He hath Beelzeboul,' and--`By the ruler of the demons he doth cast out the demons.'

23 And, having called them near, in similes he said to them, `How is the Adversary able to cast out the Adversary?

24 and if a kingdom against itself be divided, that kingdom cannot be made to stand;

25 and if a house against itself be divided, that house cannot be made to stand;

26 and if the Adversary did rise against himself, and hath been divided, he cannot be made to stand, but hath an end.

27 `No one is able the vessels of the strong man--having entered into his house--to spoil, if first he may not bind the strong man, and then his house he will spoil.

28 `Verily I say to you, that all the sins shall be forgiven to the sons of men, and evil speakings with which they might speak evil,

29 but whoever may speak evil in regard to the Holy Spirit hath not forgiveness--to the age, but is in danger of age-during judgment;'

30 because they said, `He hath an unclean spirit.'

31 Then come do his brethren and mother, and standing without, they sent unto him, calling him,

32 and a multitude was sitting about him, and they said to him, `Lo, thy mother and thy brethren without do seek thee.'

33 And he answered them, saying, `Who is my mother, or my brethren?'

34 And having looked round in a circle to those sitting about him, he saith, `Lo, my mother and my brethren!

35 for whoever may do the will of God, he is my brother, and my sister, and mother.'

Mark 11

1 And when they come nigh to Jerusalem, to Bethphage, and Bethany, unto the mount of the Olives, he sendeth forth two of his disciples,

2 and saith to them, `Go away to the village that is over-against you, and immediately, entering into it, ye shall find a colt tied, on which no one of men hath sat, having loosed it, bring [it]:

3 and if any one may say to you, Why do ye this? say ye that the lord hath need of it, and immediately he will send it hither.'

4 And they went away, and found the colt tied at the door without, by the two ways, and they loose it,

5 and certain of those standing there said to them, `What do ye--loosing the colt?'

6 and they said to them as Jesus commanded, and they suffered them.

7 And they brought the colt unto Jesus, and did cast upon it their garments, and he sat upon it,

8 and many did spread their garments in the way, and others were cutting down branches from the trees, and were strewing in the way.

9 And those going before and those following were crying out, saying, `Hosanna! blessed [is] he who is coming in the name of the Lord;

10 blessed is the coming reign, in the name of the Lord, of our father David; Hosanna in the highest.'

11 And Jesus entered into Jerusalem, and into the temple, and having looked round on all things, it being now evening, he went forth to Bethany with the twelve.

12 And on the morrow, they having come forth from Bethany, he hungered,

13 and having seen a fig-tree afar off having leaves, he came, if perhaps he shall find anything in it, and having come to it, he found nothing except leaves, for it was not a time of figs,

14 and Jesus answering said to it, `No more from thee--to the age--may any eat fruit;' and his disciples were hearing.

15 And they come to Jerusalem, and Jesus having gone into the temple, began to cast forth those selling and buying in the temple, and the tables of the money-changers and the seats of those selling the doves, he overthrew,

16 and he did not suffer that any might bear a vessel through the temple,

17 and he was teaching, saying to them, `Hath it not been written--My house a house of prayer shall be called for all the nations, and ye did make it a den of robbers?'

18 And the scribes and the chief priests heard, and they were seeking how they shall destroy him, for they were afraid of him, because all the multitude was astonished at his teaching;

19 and when evening came, he was going forth without the city.

20 And in the morning, passing by, they saw the fig-tree having been dried up from the roots,

21 and Peter having remembered saith to him, `Rabbi, lo, the fig-tree that thou didst curse is dried up.'

22 And Jesus answering saith to them, `Have faith of God;

23 for verily I say to you, that whoever may say to this mount, Be taken up, and be cast into the sea, and may not doubt in his heart, but may believe that the things that he saith do come to pass, it shall be to him whatever he may say.

24 Because of this I say to you, all whatever--praying--ye do ask, believe that ye receive, and it shall be to you.

25 `And whenever ye may stand praying, forgive, if ye have anything against any one, that your Father also who is in the heavens may forgive you your trespasses;

26 and, if ye do not forgive, neither will your Father who is in the heavens forgive your trespasses.'

27 And they come again to Jerusalem, and in the temple, as he is walking, there come unto him the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders,

28 and they say to him, `By what authority dost thou these things? and who gave thee this authority that these things thou mayest do?'

29 And Jesus answering said to them, `I will question you--I also--one word; and answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things;

30 the baptism of John--from heaven was it? or from men? answer me.'

31 And they were reasoning with themselves, saying, `If we may say, From heaven, he will say, Wherefore, then, did ye not believe him?

32 But if we may say, From men,' --they were fearing the people, for all were holding

33 and answering they say to Jesus, `We have not known;' and Jesus answering saith to them, `Neither do I tell you by what authority I do these things.'

Mark 13

1 And as he is going forth out of the temple, one of his disciples saith to him, `Teacher, see! what stones! and what buildings!'

2 and Jesus answering said to him, `Seest thou these great buildings? there may not be left a stone upon a stone, that may not be thrown down.'

3 And as he is sitting at the mount of the Olives, over-against the temple, Peter, and

4 `Tell us when these things shall be? and what [is] the sign when all these may be about to be fulfilled?'

5 And Jesus answering them, began to say, `Take heed lest any one may lead you astray,

6 for many shall come in my name, saying--I am [he], and many they shall lead astray;

7 and when ye may hear of wars and reports of wars, be not troubled, for these behove to be, but the end [is] not yet;

8 for nation shall rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom, and there shall be earthquakes in divers places, and there shall be famines and troubles; beginnings of sorrows [are] these.

9 `And take ye heed to yourselves, for they shall deliver you up to sanhedrims, and to synagogues, ye shall be beaten, and before governors and kings ye shall be set for my sake, for a testimony to them;

10 and to all the nations it behoveth first that the good news be proclaimed.

11 `And when they may lead you, delivering up, be not anxious beforehand what ye may speak, nor premeditate, but whatever may be given to you in that hour, that speak ye, for it is not ye who are speaking, but the Holy Spirit.

12 `And brother shall deliver up brother to death, and father child, and children shall rise up against parents, and shall put them to death,

13 and ye shall be hated by all because of my name, but he who hath endured to the end-- he shall be saved.

14 `And when ye may see the abomination of the desolation, that was spoken of by

15 and he upon the house-top, let him not come down to the house, nor come in to take anything out of his house;

16 and he who is in the field, let him not turn to the things behind, to take up his garment.

17 `And woe to those with child, and to those giving suck, in those days;

18 and pray ye that your flight may not be in winter,

19 for those days shall be tribulation, such as hath not been from the beginning of the creation that God created, till now, and may not be;

20 and if the Lord did not shorten the days, no flesh had been saved; but because of the chosen, whom He did choose to Himself, He did shorten the days.

21 `And then, if any may say to you, Lo, here [is] the Christ, or, Lo, there, ye may not believe;

22 for there shall rise false Christs and false prophets, and they shall give signs and wonders, to seduce, if possible, also the chosen;

23 and ye, take heed; lo, I have foretold you all things.

24 `But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun shall be darkened, and the moon shall not give her light,

25 and the stars of the heaven shall be falling, and the powers that are in the heavens shall be shaken.

26 `And then they shall see the Son of Man coming in clouds with much power and glory,

27 and then he shall send his messengers, and gather together his chosen from the four winds, from the end of the earth unto the end of heaven.

28 `And from the fig-tree learn ye the simile: when the branch may already become tender, and may put forth the leaves, ye know that nigh is the summer;

29 so ye, also, when these ye may see coming to pass, ye know that it is nigh, at the doors.

30 Verily I say to you, that this generation may not pass away till all these things may come to pass;

31 the heaven and the earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away.

32 `And concerning that day and the hour no one hath known--not even the messengers who are in the heaven, not even the Son--except the Father.

33 Take heed, watch and pray, for ye have not known when the time is;

34 as a man who is gone abroad, having left his house, and given to his servants the authority, and to each one his work, did command also the porter that he may watch;

35 watch ye, therefore, for ye have not known when the lord of the house doth come, at even, or at midnight, or at cock-crowing, or at the morning;

36 lest, having come suddenly, he may find you sleeping;

37 and what I say to you, I say to all, Watch.'

Mark 16

1 And the sabbath having past, Mary the Magdalene, and Mary of James, and Salome, bought spices, that having come, they may anoint him,

2 and early in the morning of the first of the sabbaths, they come unto the sepulchre, at the rising of the sun,

3 and they said among themselves, `Who shall roll away for us the stone out of the door of the sepulchre?'

4 And having looked, they see that the stone hath been rolled away--for it was very great,

5 and having entered into the sepulchre, they saw a young man sitting on the right hand, arrayed in a long white robe, and they were amazed.

6 And he saith to them, `Be not amazed, ye seek Jesus the Nazarene, the crucified: he did rise--he is not here; lo, the place where they laid him!

7 and go, say to his disciples, and Peter, that he doth go before you to Galilee; there ye shall see him, as he said to you.'

8 And, having come forth quickly, they fled from the sepulchre, and trembling and amazement had seized them, and to no one said they anything, for they were afraid.

9 And he, having risen in the morning of the first of the sabbaths, did appear first to Mary the Magdalene, out of whom he had cast seven demons;

10 she having gone, told those who had been with him, mourning and weeping;

11 and they, having heard that he is alive, and was seen by her, did not believe.

12 And after these things, to two of them, as they are going into a field, walking, he was manifested in another form,

13 and they having gone, told to the rest; not even them did they believe.

14 Afterwards, as they are reclining (at meat), he was manifested to the eleven, and did reproach their unbelief and stiffness of heart, because they believed not those having seen him being raised;

15 and he said to them, `Having gone to all the world, proclaim the good news to all the creation;

16 he who hath believed, and hath been baptized, shall be saved; and he who hath not believed, shall be condemned.

17 `And signs shall accompany those believing these things; in my name demons they shall cast out; with new tongues they shall speak;

18 serpents they shall take up; and if any deadly thing they may drink, it shall not hurt them; on the ailing they shall lay hands, and they shall be well.'

19 The Lord, then, indeed, after speaking to them, was received up to the heaven, and sat on the right hand of God;

20 and they, having gone forth, did preach everywhere, the Lord working with [them], and confirming the word, through the signs following. Amen.

Luke 6

1 And it came to pass, on the second-first sabbath, as he is going through the corn fields, that his disciples were plucking the ears, and were eating, rubbing with the hands,

2 and certain of the Pharisees said to them, `Why do ye that which is not lawful to do on the sabbaths?'

3 And Jesus answering said unto them, `Did ye not read even this that David did, when he hungered, himself and those who are with him,

4 how he went into the house of God, and the loaves of the presentation did take, and did eat, and gave also to those with him, which it is not lawful to eat, except only to the priests?'

5 and he said to them, --`The Son of Man is lord also of the sabbath.'

6 And it came to pass also, on another sabbath, that he goeth into the synagogue, and teacheth, and there was there a man, and his right hand was withered,

7 and the scribes and the Pharisees were watching him, if on the sabbath he will heal, that they might find an accusation against him.

8 And he himself had known their reasonings, and said to the man having the withered hand, `Rise, and stand in the midst;' and he having risen, stood.

9 Then said Jesus unto them, `I will question you something: Is it lawful on the sabbaths to do good, or to do evil? life to save or to kill?'

10 And having looked round on them all, he said to the man, `Stretch forth thy hand;' and he did so, and his hand was restored whole as the other;

11 and they were filled with madness, and were speaking with one another what they might do to Jesus.

12 And it came to pass in those days, he went forth to the mountain to pray, and was passing the night in the prayer of God,

13 and when it became day, he called near his disciples, and having chosen from them twelve, whom also he named apostles,

14 (Simon, whom also he named Peter, and Andrew his brother, James and John, Philip and Bartholomew,

15 Matthew and Thomas, James of Alphaeus, and Simon called Zelotes,

16 Judas of James, and Judas Iscariot, who also became betrayer;)

17 and having come down with them, he stood upon a level spot, and a crowd of his disciples, and a great multitude of the people from all Judea, and Jerusalem, and the maritime Tyre and Sidon, who came to hear him, and to be healed of their sicknesses,

18 and those harassed by unclean spirits, and they were healed,

19 and all the multitude were seeking to touch him, because power from him was going forth, and he was healing all.

20 And he, having lifted up his eyes to his disciples, said: `Happy the poor--because yours is the reign of God.

21 `Happy those hungering now--because ye shall be filled. `Happy those weeping now-- because ye shall laugh.

22 `Happy are ye when men shall hate you, and when they shall separate you, and shall reproach, and shall cast forth your name as evil, for the Son of Man's sake--

23 rejoice in that day, and leap, for lo, your reward [is] great in the heaven, for according to these things were their fathers doing to the prophets.

24 `But woe to you--the rich, because ye have got your comfort.

25 `Woe to you who have been filled--because ye shall hunger. `Woe to you who are laughing now--because ye shall mourn and weep.

26 `Woe to you when all men shall speak well of you--for according to these things were their fathers doing to false prophets.

27 `But I say to you who are hearing, Love your enemies, do good to those hating you,

28 bless those cursing you, and pray for those accusing you falsely;

29 and to him smiting thee upon the cheek, give also the other, and from him taking away from thee the mantle, also the coat thou mayest not keep back.

30 `And to every one who is asking of thee, be giving; and from him who is taking away thy goods, be not asking again;

31 and as ye wish that men may do to you, do ye also to them in like manner;

32 and--if ye love those loving you, what grace have ye? for also the sinful love those loving them;

33 and if ye do good to those doing good to you, what grace have ye? for also the sinful do the same;

34 and if ye lend [to those] of whom ye hope to receive back, what grace have ye? for also the sinful lend to sinners--that they may receive again as much.

35 `But love your enemies, and do good, and lend, hoping for nothing again, and your reward will be great, and ye shall be sons of the Highest, because He is kind unto the ungracious and evil;

36 be ye therefore merciful, as also your Father is merciful.

37 `And judge not, and ye may not be judged; condemn not, and ye may not be condemned; release, and ye shall be released.

38 `Give, and it shall be given to you; good measure, pressed, and shaken, and running over, they shall give into your bosom; for with that measure with which ye measure, it shall be measured to you again.'

39 And he spake a simile to them, `Is blind able to lead blind? shall they not both fall into a pit?

40 A disciple is not above his teacher, but every one perfected shall be as his teacher.

41 `And why dost thou behold the mote that is in thy brother's eye, and the beam that [is] in thine own eye dost not consider?

42 or how art thou able to say to thy brother, Brother, suffer, I may take out the mote that [is] in thine eye--thyself the beam in thine own eye not beholding? Hypocrite, take first the beam out of thine own eye, and then thou shalt see clearly to take out the mote that [is] in thy brother's eye.

43 `For there is not a good tree making bad fruit, nor a bad tree making good fruit;

44 for each tree from its own fruit is known, for not from thorns do they gather figs, nor from a bramble do they crop a grape.

45 `The good man out of the good treasure of his heart doth bring forth that which [is] good; and the evil man out of the evil treasure of his heart doth bring forth that which [is] evil; for out of the abounding of the heart doth his mouth speak.

46 `And why do ye call me, Lord, Lord, and do not what I say?

47 Every one who is coming unto me, and is hearing my words, and is doing them, I will shew you to whom he is like;

48 he is like to a man building a house, who did dig, and deepen, and laid a foundation upon the rock, and a flood having come, the stream broke forth on that house, and was not able to shake it, for it had been founded upon the rock.

49 `And he who heard and did not, is like to a man having builded a house upon the earth, without a foundation, against which the stream brake forth, and immediately it fell, and the ruin of that house became great.'

Luke 11

1 And it came to pass, in his being in a certain place praying, as he ceased, a certain one of his disciples said unto him, `Sir, teach us to pray, as also John taught his disciples.'

2 And he said to them, `When ye may pray, say ye: Our Father who art in the heavens; hallowed be Thy name: Thy reign come; Thy will come to pass, as in heaven also on earth;

3 our appointed bread be giving us daily;

4 and forgive us our sins, for also we ourselves forgive every one indebted to us; and mayest Thou not bring us into temptation; but do Thou deliver us from the evil.'

5 And he said unto them, `Who of you shall have a friend, and shall go on unto him at midnight, and may say to him, Friend, lend me three loaves,

6 seeing a friend of mine came out of the way unto me, and I have not what I shall set before him,

7 and he from within answering may say, Do not give me trouble, already the door hath been shut, and my children with me are in the bed, I am not able, having risen, to give to thee.

8 `I say to you, even if he will not give to him, having risen, because of his being his friend, yet because of his importunity, having risen, he will give him as many as he doth need;

9 and I say to you, Ask, and it shall be given to you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened to you;

10 for every one who is asking doth receive; and he who is seeking doth find; and to him who is knocking it shall be opened.

11 `And of which of you--the father--if the son shall ask a loaf, a stone will he present to him? and if a fish, will he instead of a fish, a serpent present to him?

12 and if he may ask an egg, will he present to him a scorpion?

13 If, then, ye, being evil, have known good gifts to be giving to your children, how much more shall the Father who is from heaven give the Holy Spirit to those asking Him!'

14 And he was casting forth a demon, and it was dumb, and it came to pass, the demon having gone forth, the dumb man spake, and the multitudes wondered,

15 and certain of them said, `By Beelzeboul, ruler of the demons, he doth cast forth the demons;'

16 and others, tempting, a sign out of heaven from him were asking.

17 And he, knowing their thoughts, said to them, `Every kingdom having been divided against itself is desolated; and house against house doth fall;

18 and if also the Adversary against himself was divided, how shall his kingdom be made to stand? for ye say, by Beelzeboul is my casting forth the demons.

19 `But if I by Beelzeboul cast forth the demons--your sons, by whom do they cast forth? because of this your judges they shall be;

20 but if by the finger of God I cast forth the demons, then come unawares upon you did the reign of God.

21 `When the strong man armed may keep his hall, in peace are his goods;

22 but when the stronger than he, having come upon [him], may overcome him, his whole-armour he doth take away in which he had trusted, and his spoils he distributeth;

23 he who is not with me is against me, and he who is not gathering with me doth scatter.

24 `When the unclean spirit may go forth from the man it walketh through waterless places seeking rest, and not finding, it saith, I will turn back to my house whence I came forth;

25 and having come, it findeth [it] swept and adorned;

26 then doth it go, and take to it seven other spirits more evil than itself, and having entered, they dwell there, and the last of that man becometh worst than the first.'

27 And it came to pass, in his saying these things, a certain woman having lifted up the voice out of the multitude, said to him, `Happy the womb that carried thee, and the paps that thou didst suck!'

28 And he said, `Yea, rather, happy those hearing the word of God, and keeping [it]!'

29 And the multitudes crowding together upon him, he began to say, `This generation is evil, a sign it doth seek after, and a sign shall not be given to it, except the sign of Jonah the prophet,

30 for as Jonah became a sign to the Ninevites, so also shall the Son of Man be to this generation.

31 `A queen of the south shall rise up in the judgment with the men of this generation, and shall condemn them, because she came from the ends of the earth to hear the wisdom of Solomon; and lo, greater than Solomon here!

32 `Men of Nineveh shall stand up in the judgment with this generation, and shall condemn it, because they reformed at the proclamation of Jonah; and lo, greater than Jonah here!

33 `And no one having lighted a lamp, doth put [it] in a secret place, nor under the measure, but on the lamp-stand, that those coming in may behold the light.

34 `The lamp of the body is the eye, when then thine eye may be simple, thy whole body also is lightened; and when it may be evil, thy body also is darkened;

35 take heed, then, lest the light that [is] in thee be darkness;

36 if then thy whole body is lightened, not having any part darkened, the whole shall be lightened, as when the lamp by the brightness may give thee light.'

37 And in [his] speaking, a certain Pharisee was asking him that he might dine with him, and having gone in, he reclined (at meat),

38 and the Pharisee having seen, did wonder that he did not first baptize himself before the dinner.

39 And the Lord said unto him, `Now do ye, the Pharisees, the outside of the cup and of the plate make clean, but your inward part is full of rapine and wickedness;

40 unthinking! did not He who made the outside also the inside make?

41 But what ye have give ye [as] alms, and, lo, all things are clean to you.

42 `But woe to you, the Pharisees, because ye tithe the mint, and the rue, and every herb, and ye pass by the judgment, and the love of God; these things it behoveth to do, and those not to be neglecting.

43 `Woe to you, the Pharisees, because ye love the first seats in the synagogues, and the salutations in the market-places.

44 `Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites, because ye are as the unseen tombs, and the men walking above have not known.'

45 And one of the lawyers answering, saith to him, `Teacher, these things saying, us also thou dost insult;'

46 and he said, `And to you, the lawyers, woe! because ye burden men with burdens grievous to be borne, and ye yourselves with one of your fingers do not touch the burdens.

47 `Woe to you, because ye build the tombs of the prophets, and your fathers killed them.

48 Then do ye testify, and are well pleased with the works of your fathers, because they indeed killed them, and ye do build their tombs;

49 because of this also the wisdom of God said: I will send to them prophets, and apostles, and some of them they shall kill and persecute,

50 that the blood of all the prophets, that is being poured forth from the foundation of the world, may be required from this generation;

51 from the blood of Abel unto the blood of Zacharias, who perished between the altar and the house; yes, I say to you, It shall be required from this generation.

52 `Woe to you, the lawyers, because ye took away the key of the knowledge; yourselves ye did not enter; and those coming in, ye did hinder.'

53 And in his speaking these things unto them, the scribes and the Pharisees began fearfully to urge and to press him to speak about many things,

54 laying wait for him, and seeking to catch something out of his mouth, that they might accuse him.

Luke 12

1 At which time the myriads of the multitude having been gathered together, so as to tread upon one another, he began to say unto his disciples, first, `Take heed to yourselves of the leaven of the Pharisees, which is hypocrisy;

2 and there is nothing covered, that shall not be revealed; and hid, that shall not be known;

3 because whatever in the darkness ye said, in the light shall be heard: and what to the ear ye spake in the inner-chambers, shall be proclaimed upon the house-tops.

4 `And I say to you, my friends, be not afraid of those killing the body, and after these things are not having anything over to do;

5 but I will show to you, whom ye may fear; Fear him who, after the killing, is having authority to cast to the gehenna; yes, I say to you, Fear ye Him.

6 `Are not five sparrows sold for two assars? and one of them is not forgotten before God,

7 but even the hairs of your head have been all numbered; therefore fear ye not, than many sparrows ye are of more value.

8 `And I say to you, Every one--whoever may confess with me before men, the Son of Man also shall confess with him before the messengers of God,

9 and he who hath denied me before men, shall be denied before the messengers of God,

10 and every one whoever shall say a word to the Son of Man, it shall be forgiven to him, but to him who to the Holy Spirit did speak evil, it shall not be forgiven.

11 `And when they bring you before the synagogues, and the rulers, and the authorities, be not anxious how or what ye may reply, or what ye may say,

12 for the Holy Spirit shall teach you in that hour what it behoveth [you] to say.'

13 And a certain one said to him, out of the multitude, `Teacher, say to my brother to divide with me the inheritance.'

14 And he said to him, `Man, who set me a judge or a divider over you?'

15 And he said unto them, `Observe, and beware of the covetousness, because not in the abundance of one's goods is his life.'

16 And he spake a simile unto them, saying, `Of a certain rich man the field brought forth well;

17 and he was reasoning within himself, saying, What shall I do, because I have not where I shall gather together my fruits?

18 and he said, This I will do, I will take down my storehouses, and greater ones I will build, and I will gather together there all my products and my good things,

19 and I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast many good things laid up for many years, be resting, eat, drink, be merry.

20 `And God said to him, Unthinking one! this night thy soul they shall require from thee, and what things thou didst prepare--to whom shall they be?

21 so [is] he who is treasuring up to himself, and is not rich toward God.'

22 And he said unto his disciples, `Because of this, to you I say, Be not anxious for your life, what ye may eat; nor for the body, what ye may put on;

23 the life is more than the nourishment, and the body than the clothing.

24 `Consider the ravens, that they sow not, nor reap, to which there is no barn nor storehouse, and God doth nourish them; how much better are ye than the fowls?

25 and who of you, being anxious, is able to add to his age one cubit?

26 If, then, ye are not able for the least--why for the rest are ye anxious?

27 `Consider the lilies, how do they grow? they labour not, nor do they spin, and I say to you, not even Solomon in all his glory was arrayed as one of these;

28 and if the herbage in the field, that to-day is, and to-morrow into an oven is cast, God doth so clothe, how much more you--ye of little faith?

29 `And ye--seek not what ye may eat, or what ye may drink, and be not in suspense,

30 for all these things do the nations of the world seek after, and your Father hath known that ye have need of these things;

31 but, seek ye the reign of God, and all these things shall be added to you.

32 `Fear not, little flock, because your Father did delight to give you the reign;

33 sell your goods, and give alms, make to yourselves bags that become not old, a treasure unfailing in the heavens, where thief doth not come near, nor moth destroy;

34 for where your treasure is, there also your heart will be.

35 `Let your loins be girded, and the lamps burning,

36 and ye like to men waiting for their lord, when he shall return out of the wedding feasts, that he having come and knocked, immediately they may open to him.

37 `Happy those servants, whom the lord, having come, shall find watching; verily I say to you, that he will gird himself, and will cause them to recline (at meat), and having come near, will minister to them;

38 and if he may come in the second watch, and in the third watch he may come, and may find [it] so, happy are those servants.

39 `And this know, that if the master of the house had known what hour the thief doth come, he would have watched, and would not have suffered his house to be broken through;

40 and ye, then, become ye ready, because at the hour ye think not, the Son of Man doth come.'

41 And Peter said to him, `Sir, unto us this simile dost thou speak, or also unto all?'

42 And the Lord said, `Who, then, is the faithful and prudent steward whom the lord shall set over his household, to give in season the wheat measure?

43 Happy that servant, whom his lord, having come, shall find doing so;

44 truly I say to you, that over all his goods he will set him.

45 `And if that servant may say in his heart, My lord doth delay to come, and may begin to beat the men-servants and the maid-servants, to eat also, and to drink, and to be drunken;

46 the lord of that servant will come in a day in which he doth not look for [him], and in an hour that he doth not know, and will cut him off, and his portion with the unfaithful he will appoint.

47 `And that servant, who having known his lord's will, and not having prepared, nor having gone according to his will, shall be beaten with many stripes,

48 and he who, not having known, and having done things worthy of stripes, shall be beaten with few; and to every one to whom much was given, much shall be required from him; and to whom they did commit much, more abundantly they will ask of him.

49 `Fire I came to cast to the earth, and what will I if already it was kindled?

50 but I have a baptism to be baptized with, and how am I pressed till it may be completed!

51 `Think ye that peace I came to give in the earth? no, I say to you, but rather division;

52 for there shall be henceforth five in one house divided--three against two, and two against three;

53 a father shall be divided against a son, and a son against a father, a mother against a daughter, and a daughter against a mother, a mother-in-law against her daughter-in-law, and a daughter-in-law against her mother-in-law.'

54 And he said also to the multitudes, `When ye may see the cloud rising from the west, immediately ye say, A shower doth come, and it is so;

55 and when--a south wind blowing, ye say, that there will be heat, and it is;

56 hypocrites! the face of the earth and of the heaven ye have known to make proof of, but this time--how do ye not make proof of [it]?

57 `And why, also, of yourselves, judge ye not what is righteous?

58 for, as thou art going away with thy opponent to the ruler, in the way give diligence to be released from him, lest he may drag thee unto the judge, and the judge may deliver thee to the officer, and the officer may cast thee into prison;

59 I say to thee, thou mayest not come forth thence till even the last mite thou mayest give back.'

Luke 14

1 And it came to pass, on his going into the house of a certain one of the chiefs of the Pharisees, on a sabbath, to eat bread, that they were watching him,

2 and lo, there was a certain dropsical man before him;

3 and Jesus answering spake to the lawyers and Pharisees, saying, `Is it lawful on the sabbath-day to heal?'

4 and they were silent, and having taken hold of [him], he healed him, and let [him] go;

5 and answering them he said, `Of which of you shall an ass or ox fall into a pit, and he will not immediately draw it up on the sabbath-day?'

6 and they were not able to answer him again unto these things.

7 And he spake a simile unto those called, marking how they were choosing out the first couches, saying unto them,

8 `When thou mayest be called by any one to marriage-feasts, thou mayest not recline on the first couch, lest a more honourable than thou may have been called by him,

9 and he who did call thee and him having come shall say to thee, Give to this one place, and then thou mayest begin with shame to occupy the last place.

10 `But, when thou mayest be called, having gone on, recline in the last place, that when he who called thee may come, he may say to thee, Friend, come up higher; then thou shalt have glory before those reclining with thee;

11 because every one who is exalting himself shall be humbled, and he who is humbling himself shall be exalted.'

12 And he said also to him who did call him, `When thou mayest make a dinner or a supper, be not calling thy friends, nor thy brethren, nor thy kindred, nor rich neighbours, lest they may also call thee again, and a recompense may come to thee;

13 but when thou mayest make a feast, be calling poor, maimed, lame, blind,

14 and happy thou shalt be, because they have not to recompense thee, for it shall be recompensed to thee in the rising again of the righteous.'

15 And one of those reclining with him, having heard these things, said to him, `Happy [is] he who shall eat bread in the reign of God;'

16 and he said to him, `A certain man made a great supper, and called many,

17 and he sent his servant at the hour of the supper to say to those having been called, Be coming, because now are all things ready.

18 `And they began with one consent all to excuse themselves: The first said to him, A field I bought, and I have need to go forth and see it; I beg of thee, have me excused.

19 `And another said, Five yoke of oxen I bought, and I go on to prove them; I beg of thee, have me excused:

20 and another said, A wife I married, and because of this I am not able to come.

21 `And that servant having come, told to his lord these things, then the master of the house, having been angry, said to his servant, Go forth quickly to the broad places and lanes of the city, and the poor, and maimed, and lame, and blind, bring in hither.

22 `And the servant said, Sir, it hath been done as thou didst command, and still there is room.

23 `And the lord said unto the servant, Go forth to the ways and hedges, and constrain to come in, that my house may be filled;

24 for I say to you, that none of those men who have been called shall taste of my supper.'

25 And there were going on with him great multitudes, and having turned, he said unto them,

26 `If any one doth come unto me, and doth not hate his own father, and mother, and wife, and children, and brothers, and sisters, and yet even his own life, he is not able to be my disciple;

27 and whoever doth not bear his cross, and come after me, is not able to be my disciple.

28 `For who of you, willing to build a tower, doth not first, having sat down, count the expence, whether he have the things for completing?

29 lest that he having laid a foundation, and not being able to finish, all who are beholding may begin to mock him,

30 saying--This man began to build, and was not able to finish.

31 `Or what king going on to engage with another king in war, doth not, having sat down, first consult if he be able with ten thousand to meet him who with twenty thousand is coming against him?

32 and if not so--he being yet a long way off--having sent an embassy, he doth ask the things for peace.

33 `So, then, every one of you who doth not take leave of all that he himself hath, is not able to be my disciple.

34 `The salt [is] good, but if the salt doth become tasteless, with what shall it be seasoned?

35 neither for land nor for manure is it fit--they cast it without. He who is having ears to hear--let him hear.'

Luke 15

1 And all the tax-gatherers and the sinners were coming nigh to him, to hear him,

2 and the Pharisees and the scribes were murmuring, saying--This one doth receive sinners, and doth eat with them.'

3 And he spake unto them this simile, saying,

4 `What man of you having a hundred sheep, and having lost one out of them, doth not leave behind the ninety-nine in the wilderness, and go on after the lost one, till he may find it?

5 and having found, he doth lay [it] on his shoulders rejoicing,

6 and having come to the house, he doth call together the friends and the neighbours, saying to them, Rejoice with me, because I found my sheep--the lost one.

7 `I say to you, that so joy shall be in the heaven over one sinner reforming, rather than over ninety-nine righteous men, who have no need of reformation.

8 `Or what woman having ten drachms, if she may lose one drachm, doth not light a lamp, and sweep the house, and seek carefully till that she may find?

9 and having found, she doth call together the female friends and the neighbours, saying, Rejoice with me, for I found the drachm that I lost.

10 `So I say to you, joy doth come before the messengers of God over one sinner reforming.'

11 And he said, `A certain man had two sons,

12 and the younger of them said to the father, Father, give me the portion of the substance falling to [me], and he divided to them the living.

13 `And not many days after, having gathered all together, the younger son went abroad to a far country, and there he scattered his substance, living riotously;

14 and he having spent all, there came a mighty famine on that country, and himself began to be in want;

15 and having gone on, he joined himself to one of the citizens of that country, and he sent him to the fields to feed swine,

16 and he was desirous to fill his belly from the husks that the swine were eating, and no one was giving to him.

17 `And having come to himself, he said, How many hirelings of my father have a superabundance of bread, and I here with hunger am perishing!

18 having risen, I will go on unto my father, and will say to him, Father, I did sin--to the heaven, and before thee,

19 and no more am I worthy to be called thy son; make me as one of thy hirelings.

20 `And having risen, he went unto his own father, and he being yet far distant, his father saw him, and was moved with compassion, and having ran he fell upon his neck and kissed him;

21 and the son said to him, Father, I did sin--to the heaven, and before thee, and no more am I worthy to be called thy son.

22 `And the father said unto his servants, Bring forth the first robe, and clothe him, and give a ring for his hand, and sandals for the feet;

23 and having brought the fatted calf, kill [it], and having eaten, we may be merry,

24 because this my son was dead, and did live again, and he was lost, and was found; and they began to be merry.

25 `And his elder son was in a field, and as, coming, he drew nigh to the house, he heard music and dancing,

26 and having called near one of the young men, he was inquiring what these things might be,

27 and he said to him--Thy brother is arrived, and thy father did kill the fatted calf, because in health he did receive him back.

28 `And he was angry, and would not go in, therefore his father, having come forth, was entreating him;

29 and he answering said to the father, Lo, so many years I do serve thee, and never thy command did I transgress, and to me thou didst never give a kid, that with my friends I might make merry;

30 but when thy son--this one who did devour thy living with harlots--came, thou didst kill to him the fatted calf.

31 `And he said to him, Child, thou art always with me, and all my things are thine;

32 but to be merry, and to be glad, it was needful, because this thy brother was dead, and did live again, he was lost, and was found.'

Luke 16

1 And he said also unto his disciples, `A certain man was rich, who had a steward, and he was accused to him as scattering his goods;

2 and having called him, he said to him, What [is] this I hear about thee? render the account of thy stewardship, for thou mayest not any longer be steward.

3 `And the steward said in himself, What shall I do, because my lord doth take away the stewardship from me? to dig I am not able, to beg I am ashamed: --

4 I have known what I shall do, that, when I may be removed from the stewardship, they may receive me to their houses.

5 `And having called near each one of his lord's debtors, he said to the first, How much dost thou owe to my lord?

6 and he said, A hundred baths of oil; and he said to him, Take thy bill, and having sat down write fifty.

7 `Afterward to another he said, And thou, how much dost thou owe? and he said, A hundred cors of wheat; and he saith to him, Take thy bill, and write eighty.

8 `And the lord commended the unrighteous steward that he did prudently, because the sons of this age are more prudent than the sons of the light, in respect to their generation.

9 and I say to you, Make to yourselves friends out of the mammon of unrighteousness, that when ye may fail, they may receive you to the age-during tabernacles.

10 `He who is faithful in the least, [is] also faithful in much; and he who in the least [is] unrighteous, is also unrighteous in much;

11 if, then, in the unrighteous mammon ye became not faithful--the true who will entrust to you?

12 and if in the other's ye became not faithful--your own, who shall give to you?

13 `No domestic is able to serve two lords, for either the one he will hate, and the other he will love; or one he will hold to, and of the other he will be heedless; ye are not able to serve God and mammon.'

14 And also the Pharisees, being lovers of money, were hearing all these things, and were deriding him,

15 and he said to them, `Ye are those declaring yourselves righteous before men, but God doth know your hearts; because that which among men is high, [is] abomination before God;

16 the law and the prophets [are] till John; since then the reign of God is proclaimed good news, and every one doth press into it;

17 and it is easier to the heaven and the earth to pass away, than of the law one tittle to fall.

18 `Every one who is sending away his wife, and marrying another, doth commit adultery; and every one who is marrying her sent away from a husband doth commit adultery.

19 `And--a certain man was rich, and was clothed in purple and fine linen, making merry sumptuously every day,

20 and there was a certain poor man, by name Lazarus, who was laid at his porch, full of sores,

21 and desiring to be filled from the crumbs that are falling from the table of the rich man; yea, also the dogs, coming, were licking his sores.

22 `And it came to pass, that the poor man died, and that he was carried away by the messengers to the bosom of Abraham--and the rich man also died, and was buried;

23 and in the hades having lifted up his eyes, being in torments, he doth see Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his bosom,

24 and having cried, he said, Father Abraham, deal kindly with me, and send Lazarus, that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and may cool my tongue, because I am distressed in this flame.

25 `And Abraham said, Child, remember that thou did receive--thou--thy good things in thy life, and Lazarus in like manner the evil things, and now he is comforted, and thou art distressed;

26 and besides all these things, between us and you a great chasm is fixed, so that they who are willing to go over from hence unto you are not able, nor do they from thence to us pass through.

27 `And he said, I pray thee, then, father, that thou mayest send him to the house of my father,

28 for I have five brothers, so that he may thoroughly testify to them, that they also may not come to this place of torment.

29 `Abraham saith to him, They have Moses and the prophets, let them hear them;

30 and he said, No, father Abraham, but if any one from the dead may go unto them, they will reform.

31 And he said to him, If Moses and the prophets they do not hear, neither if one may rise out of the dead will they be persuaded.'

John 7

1 And Jesus was walking after these things in Galilee, for he did not wish to walk in Judea, because the Jews were seeking to kill him,

2 and the feast of the Jews was nigh--that of tabernacles--

3 his brethren, therefore, said unto him, `Remove hence, and go away to Judea, that thy disciples also may behold thy works that thou dost;

4 for no one in secret doth anything, and himself seeketh to be in public; if thou dost these things--manifest thyself to the world;'

5 for not even were his brethren believing in him.

6 Jesus, therefore, saith to them, `My time is not yet present, but your time is always ready;

7 the world is not able to hate you, but me it doth hate, because I testify concerning it that its works are evil.

8 Ye--go ye up to this feast; I do not yet go up to this feast, because my time hath not yet been fulfilled;'

9 and saying these things to them, he remained in Galilee.

10 And when his brethren went up, then also he himself went up to the feast, not manifestly, but as in secret;

11 the Jews, therefore, were seeking him, in the feast, and said, `Where is that one?'

12 and there was much murmuring about him among the multitudes, some indeed said--`He is good;' and others said, `No, but he leadeth astray the multitude;'

13 no one, however, was speaking freely about him, through fear of the Jews.

14 And it being now the middle of the feast, Jesus went up to the temple, and he was teaching,

15 and the Jews were wondering, saying, `How hath this one known letters--not having learned?'

16 Jesus answered them and said, `My teaching is not mine, but His who sent me;

17 if any one may will to do His will, he shall know concerning the teaching, whether it is of God, or--I do speak from myself.

18 `He who is speaking from himself his own glory doth seek, but he who is seeking the glory of him who sent him, this one is true, and unrighteousness is not in him;

19 hath not Moses given you the law? and none of you doth the law; why me do ye seek to kill?'

20 The multitude answered and said, `Thou hast a demon, who doth seek to kill thee?'

21 Jesus answered and said to them, `One work I did, and ye all wonder,

22 because of this, Moses hath given you the circumcision--not that it is of Moses, but of the fathers--and on a sabbath ye circumcise a man;

23 if a man doth receive circumcision on a sabbath that the law of Moses may not be broken, are ye wroth with me that I made a man all whole on a sabbath?

24 judge not according to appearance, but the righteous judgment judge.'

25 Certain, therefore, of the Jerusalemites said, `Is not this he whom they are seeking to kill?

26 and, lo, he doth speak freely, and they say nothing to him; did the rulers at all know truly that this is truly the Christ?

27 but this one--we have known whence he is; and the Christ, when he doth come, no one doth know whence he is.'

28 Jesus cried, therefore, in the temple, teaching and saying, `Ye have both known me, and ye have known whence I am; and I have not come of myself, but He who sent me is true, whom ye have not known;

29 and I have known Him, because I am from Him, and He did send me.'

30 They were seeking, therefore, to seize him, and no one laid the hand on him, because his hour had not yet come,

31 and many out of the multitude did believe in him, and said--`The Christ--when he may come--will he do more signs than these that this one did?'

32 The Pharisees heard the multitude murmuring these things concerning him, and the Pharisees and the chief priests sent officers that they may take him;

33 Jesus, therefore, said to them, `Yet a little time I am with you, and I go away unto Him who sent me;

34 ye will seek me, and ye shall not find; and where I am, ye are not able to come.'

35 The Jews, therefore, said among themselves, `Whither is this one about to go that we shall not find him? --to the dispersion of the Greeks is he about to go? and to teach the Greeks;

36 what is this word that he said, Ye will seek me, and ye shall not find? and, Where I am, ye are not able to come?'

37 And in the last, the great day of the feast, Jesus stood and cried, saying, `If any one doth thirst, let him come unto me and drink;

38 he who is believing in me, according as the Writing said, Rivers out of his belly shall flow of living water;'

39 and this he said of the Spirit, which those believing in him were about to receive; for not yet was the Holy Spirit, because Jesus was not yet glorified.

40 Many, therefore out of the multitude, having heard the word, said, `This is truly the Prophet;'

41 others said, `This is the Christ;' and others said, `Why, out of Galilee doth the Christ come?

42 Did not the Writing say, that out of the seed of David, and from Bethlehem--the village where David was--the Christ doth come?'

43 A division, therefore, arose among the multitude because of him.

44 And certain of them were willing to seize him, but no one laid hands on him;

45 the officers came, therefore, unto the chief priests and Pharisees, and they said to them, `Wherefore did ye not bring him?'

46 The officers answered, `Never so spake man--as this man.'

47 The Pharisees, therefore, answered them, `Have ye also been led astray?

48 did any one out of the rulers believe in him? or out of the Pharisees?

49 but this multitude, that is not knowing the law, is accursed.'

50 Nicodemus saith unto them--he who came by night unto him--being one of them,

51 `Doth our law judge the man, if it may not hear from him first, and know what he doth?'

52 They answered and said to him, `Art thou also out of Galilee? search and see, that a prophet out of Galilee hath not risen;'

53 and each one went on to his house, but Jesus went on to the mount of the Olives.

John 15

1 `I am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman;

2 every branch in me not bearing fruit, He doth take it away, and every one bearing fruit, He doth cleanse by pruning it, that it may bear more fruit;

3 already ye are clean, because of the word that I have spoken to you;

4 remain in me, and I in you, as the branch is not able to bear fruit of itself, if it may not remain in the vine, so neither ye, if ye may not remain in me.

5 `I am the vine, ye the branches; he who is remaining in me, and I in him, this one doth bear much fruit, because apart from me ye are not able to do anything;

6 if any one may not remain in me, he was cast forth without as the branch, and was withered, and they gather them, and cast to fire, and they are burned;

7 if ye may remain in me, and my sayings in you may remain, whatever ye may wish ye shall ask, and it shall be done to you.

8 `In this was my Father glorified, that ye may bear much fruit, and ye shall become my disciples.

9 According as the Father did love me, I also loved you, remain in my love;

10 if my commandments ye may keep, ye shall remain in my love, according as I the commands of my Father have kept, and do remain in His love;

11 these things I have spoken to you, that my joy in you may remain, and your joy may be full.

12 `This is my command, that ye love one another, according as I did love you;

13 greater love than this hath no one, that any one his life may lay down for his friends;

14 ye are my friends, if ye may do whatever I command you;

15 no more do I call you servants, because the servant hath not known what his lord doth, and you I have called friends, because all things that I heard from my Father, I did make known to you.

16 `Ye did not choose out me, but I chose out you, and did appoint you, that ye might go away, and might bear fruit, and your fruit might remain, that whatever ye may ask of the Father in my name, He may give you.

17 `These things I command you, that ye love one another;

18 if the world doth hate you, ye know that it hath hated me before you;

19 if of the world ye were, the world its own would have been loving, and because of the world ye are not--but I chose out of the world--because of this the world hateth you.

20 `Remember the word that I said to you, A servant is not greater than his lord; if me they did persecute, you also they will persecute; if my word they did keep, yours also they will keep;

21 but all these things will they do to you, because of my name, because they have not known Him who sent me;

22 if I had not come and spoken to them, they were not having sin; but now pretext they have not for their sin.

23 `He who is hating me, doth hate also my Father;

24 if I did not do among them the works that no other hath done, they were not having sin, and now they have both seen and hated both me and my Father;

25 but--that the word may be fulfilled that was written in their law--They hated me without a cause.

26 `And when the Comforter may come, whom I will send to you from the Father--the Spirit of truth, who from the Father doth come forth, he will testify of me;

27 and ye also do testify, because from the beginning ye are with me.

Acts 7

1 And the chief priest said, `Are then these things so?'

2 and he said, `Men, brethren, and fathers, hearken: The God of the glory did appear to our father Abraham, being in Mesopotamia, before his dwelling in Haran,

3 and He said to him, Go forth out of thy land, and out of thy kindred, and come to a land that I shall shew thee.

4 `Then having come forth out of the land of the Chaldeans, he dwelt in Haran, and from thence, after the death of his father, He did remove him to this land wherein ye now dwell,

5 and He gave him no inheritance in it, not even a footstep, and did promise to give it to him for a possession, and to his seed after him--he having no child.

6 `And God spake thus, That his seed shall be sojourning in a strange land, and they shall cause it to serve, and shall do it evil four hundred years,

7 and the nation whom they shall serve I will judge, said God; and after these things they shall come forth and shall do Me service in this place.

8 `And He gave to him a covenant of circumcision, and so he begat Isaac, and did circumcise him on the eighth day, and Isaac [begat] Jacob, and Jacob--the twelve patriarchs;

9 and the patriarchs, having been moved with jealousy, sold Joseph to Egypt, and God was with him,

10 and did deliver him out of all his tribulations, and gave him favour and wisdom before Pharaoh king of Egypt, and he did set him--governor over Egypt and all his house.

11 `And there came a dearth upon all the land of Egypt and Canaan, and great tribulation, and our fathers were not finding sustenance,

12 and Jacob having heard that there was corn in Egypt, sent forth our fathers a first time;

13 and at the second time was Joseph made known to his brethren, and Joseph's kindred became manifest to Pharaoh,

14 and Joseph having sent, did call for his father Jacob, and all his kindred--with seventy and five souls--

15 and Jacob went down to Egypt, and died, himself and our fathers,

16 and they were carried over into Sychem, and were laid in the tomb that Abraham bought for a price in money from the sons of Emmor, of Sychem.

17 `And according as the time of the promise was drawing nigh, which God did swear to Abraham, the people increased and multiplied in Egypt,

18 till another king rose, who had not known Joseph;

19 this one, having dealt subtilely with our kindred, did evil to our fathers, causing to expose their babes, that they might not live;

20 in which time Moses was born, and he was fair to God, and he was brought up three months in the house of his father;

21 and he having been exposed, the daughter of Pharaoh took him up, and did rear him to herself for a son;

22 and Moses was taught in all wisdom of the Egyptians, and he was powerful in words and in works.

23 `And when forty years were fulfilled to him, it came upon his heart to look after his brethren, the sons of Israel;

24 and having seen a certain one suffering injustice, he did defend, and did justice to the oppressed, having smitten the Egyptian;

25 and he was supposing his brethren to understand that God through his hand doth give salvation; and they did not understand.

26 `On the succeeding day, also, he shewed himself to them as they are striving, and urged them to peace, saying, Men, brethren are ye, wherefore do ye injustice to one another?

27 and he who is doing injustice to the neighbour, did thrust him away, saying, Who set thee a ruler and a judge over us?

28 to kill me dost thou wish, as thou didst kill yesterday the Egyptian?

29 `And Moses fled at this word, and became a sojourner in the land of Midian, where he begat two sons,

30 and forty years having been fulfilled, there appeared to him in the wilderness of mount Sinai a messenger of the Lord, in a flame of fire of a bush,

31 and Moses having seen did wonder at the sight; and he drawing near to behold, there came a voice of the Lord unto him,

32 I [am] the God of thy fathers; the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob. `And Moses having become terrified, durst not behold,

33 and the Lord said to him, Loose the sandal of thy feet, for the place in which thou hast stood is holy ground;

34 seeing I have seen the affliction of My people that [is] in Egypt, and their groaning I did hear, and came down to deliver them; and now come, I will send thee to Egypt.

35 `This Moses, whom they did refuse, saying, Who did set thee a ruler and a judge? this one God a ruler and a redeemer did send, in the hand of a messenger who appeared to him in the bush;

36 this one did bring them forth, having done wonders and signs in the land of Egypt, and in the Red Sea, and in the wilderness forty years;

37 this is the Moses who did say to the sons of Israel: A prophet to you shall the Lord your God raise up out of your brethren, like to me, him shall ye hear.

38 `This is he who was in the assembly in the wilderness, with the messenger who is speaking to him in the mount Sinai, and with our fathers who did receive the living oracles to give to us;

39 to whom our fathers did not wish to become obedient, but did thrust away, and turned back in their hearts to Egypt,

40 saying to Aaron, Make to us gods who shall go on before us, for this Moses, who brought us forth out of the land of Egypt, we have not known what hath happened to him.

41 `And they made a calf in those days, and brought a sacrifice to the idol, and were rejoicing in the works of their hands,

42 and God did turn, and did give them up to do service to the host of the heaven, according as it hath been written in the scroll of the prophets: Slain beasts and sacrifices did ye offer to Me forty years in the wilderness, O house of Israel?

43 and ye took up the tabernacle of Moloch, and the star of your god Remphan--the figures that ye made to bow before them, and I will remove your dwelling beyond Babylon.

44 `The tabernacle of the testimony was among our fathers in the wilderness, according as He did direct, who is speaking to Moses, to make it according to the figure that he had seen;

45 which also our fathers having in succession received, did bring in with Joshua, into the possession of the nations whom God did drive out from the presence of our fathers, till the days of David,

46 who found favour before God, and requested to find a tabernacle for the God of Jacob;

47 and Solomon built Him an house.

48 `But the Most High in sanctuaries made with hands doth not dwell, according as the prophet saith:

49 The heaven [is] My throne, and the earth My footstool; what house will ye build to Me? saith the Lord, or what [is] the place of My rest?

50 hath not My hand made all these things?

51 `Ye stiff-necked and uncircumcised in heart and in ears! ye do always the Holy Spirit resist; as your fathers--also ye;

52 which of the prophets did not your fathers persecute? and they killed those who declared before about the coming of the Righteous One, of whom now ye betrayers and murderers have become,

53 who received the law by arrangement of messengers, and did not keep [it].'

54 And hearing these things, they were cut to the hearts, and did gnash the teeth at him;

55 and being full of the Holy Spirit, having looked stedfastly to the heaven, he saw the glory of God, and Jesus standing on the right hand of God,

56 and he said, `Lo, I see the heavens having been opened, and the Son of Man standing on the right hand of God.'

57 And they, having cried out with a loud voice, stopped their ears, and did rush with one accord upon him,

58 and having cast him forth outside of the city, they were stoning [him] --and the witnesses did put down their garments at the feet of a young man called Saul--

59 and they were stoning Stephen, calling and saying, `Lord Jesus, receive my spirit;'

60 and having bowed the knees, he cried with a loud voice, `Lord, mayest thou not lay to them this sin;' and this having said, he fell asleep.

Romans 2

1 Therefore, thou art inexcusable, O man--every one who is judging--for in that in which thou dost judge the other, thyself thou dost condemn, for the same things thou dost practise who art judging,

2 and we have known that the judgment of God is according to truth, upon those practising such things.

3 And dost thou think this, O man, who art judging those who such things are practising, and art doing them, that thou shalt escape the judgment of God?

4 or the riches of His goodness, and forbearance, and long-suffering, dost thou despise? --not knowing that the goodness of God doth lead thee to reformation!

5 but, according to thy hardness and impenitent heart, thou dost treasure up to thyself wrath, in a day of wrath and of the revelation of the righteous judgment of God,

6 who shall render to each according to his works;

7 to those, indeed, who in continuance of a good work, do seek glory, and honour, and incorruptibility--life age-during;

8 and to those contentious, and disobedient, indeed, to the truth, and obeying the unrighteousness--indignation and wrath,

9 tribulation and distress, upon every soul of man that is working the evil, both of Jew first, and of Greek;

10 and glory, and honour, and peace, to every one who is working the good, both to Jew first, and to Greek.

11 For there is no acceptance of faces with God,

12 for as many as without law did sin, without law also shall perish, and as many as did sin in law, through law shall be judged,

13 for not the hearers of the law [are] righteous before God, but the doers of the law shall be declared righteous: --

14 For, when nations that have not a law, by nature may do the things of the law, these not having a law--to themselves are a law;

15 who do shew the work of the law written in their hearts, their conscience also witnessing with them, and between one another the thoughts accusing or else defending,

16 in the day when God shall judge the secrets of men, according to my good news, through Jesus Christ.

17 Lo, thou art named a Jew, and dost rest upon the law, and dost boast in God,

18 and dost know the will, and dost approve the distinctions, being instructed out of the law,

19 and hast confidence that thou thyself art a leader of blind ones, a light of those in darkness,

20 an instructor of foolish ones, a teacher of babes, having the form of the knowledge and of the truth in the law.

21 Thou, then, who art teaching another, thyself dost thou not teach?

22 thou who art preaching not to steal, dost thou steal? thou who art saying not to commit adultery, dost thou commit adultery? thou who art abhorring the idols, dost thou rob temples?

23 thou who in the law dost boast, through the transgression of the law God dost thou dishonour?

24 for the name of God because of you is evil spoken of among the nations, according as it hath been written.

25 For circumcision, indeed, doth profit, if law thou mayest practise, but if a transgressor of law thou mayest be, thy circumcision hath become uncircumcision.

26 If, therefore the uncircumcision the righteousness of the law may keep, shall not his uncircumcision for circumcision be reckoned?

27 and the uncircumcision, by nature, fulfilling the law, shall judge thee who, through letter and circumcision, [art] a transgressor of law.

28 For he is not a Jew who is [so] outwardly, neither [is] circumcision that which is outward in flesh;

29 but a Jew [is] he who is [so] inwardly, and circumcision [is] of the heart, in spirit, not in letter, of which the praise is not of men, but of God.

Romans 3

1 What, then, [is] the superiority of the Jew? or what the profit of the circumcision?

2 much in every way; for first, indeed, that they were intrusted with the oracles of God;

3 for what, if certain were faithless? shall their faithlessness the faithfulness of god make useless?

4 let it not be! and let God become true, and every man false, according as it hath been written, `That Thou mayest be declared righteous in Thy words, and mayest overcome in Thy being judged.'

5 And, if our unrighteousness God's righteousness doth establish, what shall we say? is God unrighteous who is inflicting the wrath? (after the manner of a man I speak)

6 let it not be! since how shall God judge the world?

7 for if the truth of God in my falsehood did more abound to His glory, why yet am I also as a sinner judged?

8 and not, as we are evil spoken of, and as certain affirm us to say--`We may do the evil things, that the good ones may come?' whose judgment is righteous.

9 What, then? are we better? not at all! for we did before charge both Jews and Greeks with being all under sin,

10 according as it hath been written--`There is none righteous, not even one;

11 There is none who is understanding, there is none who is seeking after God.

12 All did go out of the way, together they became unprofitable, there is none doing good, there is not even one.

13 A sepulchre opened [is] their throat; with their tongues they used deceit; poison of asps [is] under their lips.

14 Whose mouth is full of cursing and bitterness.

15 Swift [are] their feet to shed blood.

16 Ruin and misery [are] in their ways.

17 And a way of peace they did not know.

18 There is no fear of God before their eyes.'

19 And we have known that as many things as the law saith, to those in the law it doth speak, that every mouth may be stopped, and all the world may come under judgment to God;

20 wherefore by works of law shall no flesh be declared righteous before Him, for through law is a knowledge of sin.

21 And now apart from law hath the righteousness of God been manifested, testified to by the law and the prophets,

22 and the righteousness of God [is] through the faith of Jesus Christ to all, and upon all those believing, --for there is no difference,

23 for all did sin, and are come short of the glory of God--

24 being declared righteous freely by His grace through the redemption that [is] in Christ Jesus,

25 whom God did set forth a mercy seat, through the faith in his blood, for the shewing forth of His righteousness, because of the passing over of the bygone sins in the forbearance of God--

26 for the shewing forth of His righteousness in the present time, for His being righteous, and declaring him righteous who [is] of the faith of Jesus.

27 Where then [is] the boasting? it was excluded; by what law? of works? no, but by a law of faith:

28 therefore do we reckon a man to be declared righteous by faith, apart from works of law.

29 The God of Jews only [is He], and not also of nations?

30 yes, also of nations; since one [is] God who shall declare righteous the circumcision by faith, and the uncircumcision through the faith.

31 Law then do we make useless through the faith? let it not be! yea, we do establish law.

Romans 4

1 What, then, shall we say Abraham our father, to have found, according to flesh?

2 for if Abraham by works was declared righteous, he hath to boast--but not before god;

3 for what doth the writing say? `And Abraham did believe God, and it was reckoned to him--to righteousness;'

4 and to him who is working, the reward is not reckoned of grace, but of debt;

5 and to him who is not working, and is believing upon Him who is declaring righteous the impious, his faith is reckoned--to righteousness:

6 even as David also doth speak of the happiness of the man to whom God doth reckon righteousness apart from works:

7 `Happy they whose lawless acts were forgiven, and whose sins were covered;

8 happy the man to whom the Lord may not reckon sin.'

9 [Is] this happiness, then, upon the circumcision, or also upon the uncircumcision--for we say that the faith was reckoned to Abraham--to righteousness?

10 how then was it reckoned? he being in circumcision, or in uncircumcision? not in circumcision, but in uncircumcision;

11 and a sign he did receive of circumcision, a seal of the righteousness of the faith in the uncircumcision, for his being father of all those believing through uncircumcision, for the righteousness also being reckoned to them,

12 and father of circumcision to those not of circumcision only, but who also walk in the steps of the faith, that [is] in the uncircumcision of our father Abraham.

13 For not through law [is] the promise to Abraham, or to his seed, of his being heir of the world, but through the righteousness of faith;

14 for if they who are of law [are] heirs, the faith hath been made void, and the promise hath been made useless;

15 for the law doth work wrath; for where law is not, neither [is] transgression.

16 Because of this [it is] of faith, that [it may be] according to grace, for the promise being sure to all the seed, not to that which [is] of the law only, but also to that which [is] of the faith of Abraham,

17 who is father of us all (according as it hath been written--`A father of many nations I have set thee,') before Him whom he did believe--God, who is quickening the dead, and is calling the things that be not as being.

18 Who, against hope in hope did believe, for his becoming father of many nations according to that spoken: `So shall thy seed be;'

19 and not having been weak in the faith, he did not consider his own body, already become dead, (being about a hundred years old,) and the deadness of Sarah's womb,

20 and at the promise of God did not stagger in unbelief, but was strengthened in faith, having given glory to God,

21 and having been fully persuaded that what He hath promised He is able also to do:

22 wherefore also it was reckoned to him to righteousness.

23 And it was not written on his account alone, that it was reckoned to him,

24 but also on ours, to whom it is about to be reckoned--to us believing on Him who did raise up Jesus our Lord out of the dead,

25 who was delivered up because of our offences, and was raised up because of our being declared righteous.

Romans 6

1 What, then, shall we say? shall we continue in the sin that the grace may abound?

2 let it not be! we who died to the sin--how shall we still live in it?

3 are ye ignorant that we, as many as were baptized to Christ Jesus, to his death were baptized?

4 we were buried together, then, with him through the baptism to the death, that even as Christ was raised up out of the dead through the glory of the Father, so also we in newness of life might walk.

5 For, if we have become planted together to the likeness of his death, [so] also we shall be of the rising again;

6 this knowing, that our old man was crucified with [him], that the body of the sin may be made useless, for our no longer serving the sin;

7 for he who hath died hath been set free from the sin.

8 And if we died with Christ, we believe that we also shall live with him,

9 knowing that Christ, having been raised up out of the dead, doth no more die, death over him hath no more lordship;

10 for in that he died, to the sin he died once, and in that he liveth, he liveth to God;

11 so also ye, reckon yourselves to be dead indeed to the sin, and living to God in Jesus Christ our Lord.

12 Let not then the sin reign in your mortal body, to obey it in its desires;

13 neither present ye your members instruments of unrighteousness to the sin, but present yourselves to God as living out of the dead, and your members instruments of righteousness to God;

14 for sin over you shall not have lordship, for ye are not under law, but under grace.

15 What then? shall we sin because we are not under law but under grace? let it not be!

16 have ye not known that to whom ye present yourselves servants for obedience, servants ye are to him to whom ye obey, whether of sin to death, or of obedience to righteousness?

17 and thanks to God, that ye were servants of the sin, and--were obedient from the heart to the form of teaching to which ye were delivered up;

18 and having been freed from the sin, ye became servants to the righteousness.

19 In the manner of men I speak, because of the weakness of your flesh, for even as ye did present your members servants to the uncleanness and to the lawlessness--to the lawlessness, so now present your members servants to the righteousness--tosanctification,

20 for when ye were servants of the sin, ye were free from the righteousness,

21 what fruit, therefore, were ye having then, in the things of which ye are now ashamed? for the end of those [is] death.

22 And now, having been freed from the sin, and having become servants to God, ye have your fruit--to sanctification, and the end life age-during;

23 for the wages of the sin [is] death, and the gift of God [is] life age-during in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 7

1 Are ye ignorant, brethren--for to those knowing law I speak--that the law hath lordship over the man as long as he liveth?

2 for the married woman to the living husband hath been bound by law, and if the husband may die, she hath been free from the law of the husband;

3 so, then, the husband being alive, an adulteress she shall be called if she may become another man's; and if the husband may die, she is free from the law, so as not to be an adulteress, having become another man's.

4 So that, my brethren, ye also were made dead to the law through the body of the Christ, for your becoming another's, who out of the dead was raised up, that we might bear fruit to God;

5 for when we were in the flesh, the passions of the sins, that [are] through the law, were working in our members, to bear fruit to the death;

6 and now we have ceased from the law, that being dead in which we were held, so that we may serve in newness of spirit, and not in oldness of letter.

7 What, then, shall we say? the law [is] sin? let it not be! but the sin I did not know except through law, for also the covetousness I had not known if the law had not said:

8 `Thou shalt not covet;' and the sin having received an opportunity, through the command, did work in me all covetousness--for apart from law sin is dead.

9 And I was alive apart from law once, and the command having come, the sin revived, and I died;

10 and the command that [is] for life, this was found by me for death;

11 for the sin, having received an opportunity, through the command, did deceive me, and through it did slay [me];

12 so that the law, indeed, [is] holy, and the command holy, and righteous, and good.

13 That which is good then, to me hath it become death? let it not be! but the sin, that it might appear sin, through the good, working death to me, that the sin might become exceeding sinful through the command,

14 for we have known that the law is spiritual, and I am fleshly, sold by the sin;

15 for that which I work, I do not acknowledge; for not what I will, this I practise, but what I hate, this I do.

16 And if what I do not will, this I do, I consent to the law that [it is] good,

17 and now it is no longer I that work it, but the sin dwelling in me,

18 for I have known that there doth not dwell in me, that is, in my flesh, good: for to will is present with me, and to work that which is right I do not find,

19 for the good that I will, I do not; but the evil that I do not will, this I practise.

20 And if what I do not will, this I do, it is no longer I that work it, but the sin that is dwelling in me.

21 I find, then, the law, that when I desire to do what is right, with me the evil is present,

22 for I delight in the law of God according to the inward man,

23 and I behold another law in my members, warring against the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of the sin that [is] in my members.

24 A wretched man I [am]! who shall deliver me out of the body of this death?

25 I thank God--through Jesus Christ our Lord; so then, I myself indeed with the mind do serve the law of God, and with the flesh, the law of sin.

Romans 8

1 There is, then, now no condemnation to those in Christ Jesus, who walk not according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit;

2 for the law of the Spirit of the life in Christ Jesus did set me free from the law of the sin and of the death;

3 for what the law was not able to do, in that it was weak through the flesh, God, His own Son having sent in the likeness of sinful flesh, and for sin, did condemn the sin in the flesh,

4 that the righteousness of the law may be fulfilled in us, who do not walk according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit.

5 For those who are according to the flesh, the things of the flesh do mind; and those according to the Spirit, the things of the Spirit;

6 for the mind of the flesh [is] death, and the mind of the Spirit--life and peace;

7 because the mind of the flesh [is] enmity to God, for to the law of God it doth not subject itself,

8 for neither is it able; and those who are in the flesh are not able to please God.

9 And ye are not in the flesh, but in the Spirit, if indeed the Spirit of God doth dwell in you; and if any one hath not the Spirit of Christ--this one is not His;

10 and if Christ [is] in you, the body, indeed, [is] dead because of sin, and the Spirit [is] life because of righteousness,

11 and if the Spirit of Him who did raise up Jesus out of the dead doth dwell in you, He who did raise up the Christ out of the dead shall quicken also your dying bodies, through His Spirit dwelling in you.

12 So, then, brethren, we are debtors, not to the flesh, to live according to the flesh;

13 for if according to the flesh ye do live, ye are about to die; and if, by the Spirit, the deeds of the body ye put to death, ye shall live;

14 for as many as are led by the Spirit of God, these are the sons of God;

15 for ye did not receive a spirit of bondage again for fear, but ye did receive a spirit of adoption in which we cry, `Abba--Father.'

16 The Spirit himself doth testify with our spirit, that we are children of God;

17 and if children, also heirs, heirs, indeed, of God, and heirs together of Christ--if, indeed, we suffer together, that we may also be glorified together.

18 For I reckon that the sufferings of the present time [are] not worthy [to be compared] with the glory about to be revealed in us;

19 for the earnest looking out of the creation doth expect the revelation of the sons of God;

20 for to vanity was the creation made subject--not of its will, but because of Him who did subject [it] --in hope,

21 that also the creation itself shall be set free from the servitude of the corruption to the liberty of the glory of the children of God;

22 for we have known that all the creation doth groan together, and doth travail in pain together till now.

23 And not only [so], but also we ourselves, having the first-fruit of the Spirit, we also ourselves in ourselves do groan, adoption expecting--the redemption of our body;

24 for in hope we were saved, and hope beheld is not hope; for what any one doth behold, why also doth he hope for [it]?

25 and if what we do not behold we hope for, through continuance we expect [it].

26 And, in like manner also, the Spirit doth help our weaknesses; for, what we may pray for, as it behoveth [us], we have not known, but the Spirit himself doth make intercession for us with groanings unutterable,

27 and He who is searching the hearts hath known what [is] the mind of the Spirit, because according to God he doth intercede for saints.

28 And we have known that to those loving God all things do work together for good, to those who are called according to purpose;

29 because whom He did foreknow, He also did fore-appoint, conformed to the image of His Son, that he might be first-born among many brethren;

30 and whom He did fore-appoint, these also He did call; and whom He did call, these also He declared righteous; and whom He declared righteous, these also He did glorify.

31 What, then, shall we say unto these things? if God [is] for us, who [is] against us?

32 He who indeed His own Son did not spare, but for us all did deliver him up, how shall He not also with him the all things grant to us?

33 Who shall lay a charge against the choice ones of God? God [is] He that is declaring righteous,

34 who [is] he that is condemning? Christ [is] He that died, yea, rather also, was raised up; who is also on the right hand of God--who also doth intercede for us.

35 Who shall separate us from the love of the Christ? tribulation, or distress, or persecution, or famine, or nakedness, or peril, or sword?

36 (according as it hath been written--`For Thy sake we are put to death all the day long, we were reckoned as sheep of slaughter,')

37 but in all these we more than conquer, through him who loved us;

38 for I am persuaded that neither death, nor life, nor messengers, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things present,

39 nor things about to be, nor height, nor depth, nor any other created thing, shall be able to separate us from the love of god, that [is] in Christ Jesus our Lord.

Romans 9

1 Truth I say in Christ, I lie not, my conscience bearing testimony with me in the Holy Spirit,

2 that I have great grief and unceasing pain in my heart--

3 for I was wishing, I myself, to be anathema from the Christ--for my brethren, my kindred, according to the flesh,

4 who are Israelites, whose [is] the adoption, and the glory, and the covenants, and the lawgiving, and the service, and the promises,

5 whose [are] the fathers, and of whom [is] the Christ, according to the flesh, who is over all, God blessed to the ages. Amen.

6 And it is not possible that the word of God hath failed; for not all who [are] of Israel are these Israel;

7 nor because they are seed of Abraham [are] all children, but--`in Isaac shall a seed be called to thee;'

8 that is, the children of the flesh--these [are] not children of God; but the children of the promise are reckoned for seed;

9 for the word of promise [is] this; `According to this time I will come, and there shall be to Sarah a son.'

10 And not only [so], but also Rebecca, having conceived by one--Isaac our father--

11 (for they being not yet born, neither having done anything good or evil, that the purpose of God, according to choice, might remain; not of works, but of Him who is calling,) it was said to her--

12 `The greater shall serve the less;'

13 according as it hath been written, `Jacob I did love, and Esau I did hate.'

14 What, then, shall we say? unrighteousness [is] with God? let it not be!

15 for to Moses He saith, `I will do kindness to whom I do kindness, and I will have compassion on whom I have compassion;'

16 so, then--not of him who is willing, nor of him who is running, but of God who is doing kindness:

17 for the Writing saith to Pharaoh--`For this very thing I did raise thee up, that I might shew in thee My power, and that My name might be declared in all the land;'

18 so, then, to whom He willeth, He doth kindness, and to whom He willeth, He doth harden.

19 Thou wilt say, then, to me, `Why yet doth He find fault? for His counsel who hath resisted?'

20 nay, but, O man, who art thou that art answering again to God? shall the thing formed say to Him who did form [it], Why me didst thou make thus?

21 hath not the potter authority over the clay, out of the same lump to make the one vessel to honour, and the one to dishonour?

22 And if God, willing to shew the wrath and to make known His power, did endure, in much long suffering, vessels of wrath fitted for destruction,

23 and that He might make known the riches of His glory on vessels of kindness, that He before prepared for glory, whom also He did call--us--

24 not only out of Jews, but also out of nations,

25 as also in Hosea He saith, `I will call what [is] not My people--My people; and her not beloved--Beloved,

26 and it shall be--in the place where it was said to them, Ye [are] not My people; there they shall be called sons of the living God.'

27 And Isaiah doth cry concerning Israel, `If the number of the sons of Israel may be as the sand of the sea, the remnant shall be saved;

28 for a matter He is finishing, and is cutting short in righteousness, because a matter cut short will the Lord do upon the land.

29 and according as Isaiah saith before, `Except the Lord of Sabaoth did leave to us a seed, as Sodom we had become, and as Gomorrah we had been made like.'

30 What, then, shall we say? that nations who are not pursuing righteousness did attain to righteousness, and righteousness that [is] of faith,

31 and Israel, pursuing a law of righteousness, at a law of righteousness did not arrive;

32 wherefore? because--not by faith, but as by works of law; for they did stumble at the stone of stumbling,

33 according as it hath been written, `Lo, I place in Sion a stone of stumbling and a rock of offence; and every one who is believing thereon shall not be ashamed.'

Romans 10

1 Brethren, the pleasure indeed of my heart, and my supplication that [is] to God for Israel, is--for salvation;

2 for I bear them testimony that they have a zeal of God, but not according to knowledge,

3 for not knowing the righteousness of God, and their own righteousness seeking to establish, to the righteousness of God they did not submit.

4 For Christ is an end of law for righteousness to every one who is believing,

5 for Moses doth describe the righteousness that [is] of the law, that, `The man who did them shall live in them,'

6 and the righteousness of faith doth thus speak: `Thou mayest not say in thine heart, Who shall go up to the heaven,' that is, Christ to bring down?

7 or, `Who shall go down to the abyss,' that is, Christ out of the dead to bring up.

8 But what doth it say? `Nigh thee is the saying--in thy mouth, and in thy heart:' that is, the saying of the faith, that we preach;

9 that if thou mayest confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and mayest believe in thy heart that God did raise him out of the dead, thou shalt be saved,

10 for with the heart doth [one] believe to righteousness, and with the mouth is confession made to salvation;

11 for the Writing saith, `Every one who is believing on him shall not be ashamed,'

12 for there is no difference between Jew and Greek, for the same Lord of all [is] rich to all those calling upon Him,

13 for every one--whoever shall call upon the name of the Lord, he shall be saved.'

14 How then shall they call upon [him] in whom they did not believe? and how shall they believe [on him] of whom they did not hear? and how shall they hear apart from one preaching?

15 and how shall they preach, if they may not be sent? according as it hath been written, `How beautiful the feet of those proclaiming good tidings of peace, of those proclaiming good tidings of the good things!'

16 But they were not all obedient to the good tidings, for Isaiah saith, `Lord, who did give credence to our report?'

17 so then the faith [is] by a report, and the report through a saying of God,

18 but I say, Did they not hear? yes, indeed--`to all the earth their voice went forth, and to the ends of the habitable world their sayings.'

19 But I say, Did not Israel know? first Moses saith, `I will provoke you to jealousy by [that which is] not a nation; by an unintelligent nation I will anger you,'

20 and Isaiah is very bold, and saith, `I was found by those not seeking Me; I became manifest to those not inquiring after Me;'

21 and unto Israel He saith, `All the day I did stretch out My hands unto a people unbelieving and gainsaying.'

Romans 11

1 I say, then, Did God cast away His people? let it not be! for I also am an Israelite, of the seed of Abraham, of the tribe of Benjamin:

2 God did not cast away His people whom He knew before; have ye not known--in Elijah--what the Writing saith? how he doth plead with God concerning Israel, saying,

3 `Lord, Thy prophets they did kill, and Thy altars they dug down, and I was left alone, and they seek my life;'

4 but what saith the divine answer to him? `I left to Myself seven thousand men, who did not bow a knee to Baal.'

5 So then also in the present time a remnant according to the choice of grace there hath been;

6 and if by grace, no more of works, otherwise the grace becometh no more grace; and if of works, it is no more grace, otherwise the work is no more work.

7 What then? What Israel doth seek after, this it did not obtain, and the chosen did obtain, and the rest were hardened,

8 according as it hath been written, `God gave to them a spirit of deep sleep, eyes not to see, and ears not to hear,' --unto this very day,

9 and David saith, `Let their table become for a snare, and for a trap, and for a stumbling-block, and for a recompense to them;

10 let their eyes be darkened--not to behold, and their back do Thou always bow down.'

11 I say, then, Did they stumble that they might fall? let it not be! but by their fall the salvation [is] to the nations, to arouse them to jealousy;

12 and if the fall of them [is] the riches of a world, and the diminution of them the riches of nations, how much more the fulness of them?

13 For to you I speak--to the nations--inasmuch as I am indeed an apostle of nations, my ministration I do glorify;

14 if by any means I shall arouse to jealousy mine own flesh, and shall save some of them,

15 for if the casting away of them [is] a reconciliation of the world, what the reception- -if not life out of the dead?

16 and if the first-fruit [is] holy, the lump also; and if the root [is] holy, the branches also.

17 And if certain of the branches were broken off, and thou, being a wild olive tree, wast graffed in among them, and a fellow-partaker of the root and of the fatness of the olive tree didst become--

18 do not boast against the branches; and if thou dost boast, thou dost not bear the root, but the root thee!

19 Thou wilt say, then, `The branches were broken off, that I might be graffed in;' right!

20 by unbelief they were broken off, and thou hast stood by faith; be not high-minded, but be fearing;

21 for if God the natural branches did not spare--lest perhaps He also shall not spare thee.

22 Lo, then, goodness and severity of God--upon those indeed who fell, severity; and upon thee, goodness, if thou mayest remain in the goodness, otherwise, thou also shalt be cut off.

23 And those also, if they may not remain in unbelief, shall be graffed in, for God is able again to graff them in;

24 for if thou, out of the olive tree, wild by nature, wast cut out, and, contrary to nature, wast graffed into a good olive tree, how much rather shall they, who [are] according to nature, be graffed into their own olive tree?

25 For I do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, of this secret--that ye may not be wise in your own conceits--that hardness in part to Israel hath happened till the fulness of the nations may come in;

26 and so all Israel shall be saved, according as it hath been written, `There shall come forth out of Sion he who is delivering, and he shall turn away impiety from Jacob,

27 and this to them [is] the covenant from Me, when I may take away their sins.'

28 As regards, indeed, the good tidings, [they are] enemies on your account; and as regards the choice--beloved on account of the fathers;

29 for unrepented of [are] the gifts and the calling of God;

30 for as ye also once did not believe in God, and now did find kindness by the unbelief of these:

31 so also these now did not believe, that in your kindness they also may find kindness;

32 for God did shut up together the whole to unbelief, that to the whole He might do kindness.

33 O depth of riches, and wisdom and knowledge of God! how unsearchable His judgments, and untraceable His ways!

34 for who did know the mind of the Lord? or who did become His counsellor?

35 or who did first give to Him, and it shall be given back to him again?

36 because of Him, and through Him, and to Him [are] the all things; to Him [is] the glory--to the ages. Amen.

Romans 14

1 And him who is weak in the faith receive ye--not to determinations of reasonings;

2 one doth believe that he may eat all things--and he who is weak doth eat herbs;

3 let not him who is eating despise him who is not eating: and let not him who is not eating judge him who is eating, for God did receive him.

4 Thou--who art thou that art judging another's domestic? to his own master he doth stand or fall; and he shall be made to stand, for God is able to make him stand.

5 One doth judge one day above another, and another doth judge every day [alike]; let each in his own mind be fully assured.

6 He who is regarding the day, to the Lord he doth regard [it], and he who is not regarding the day, to the Lord he doth not regard [it]. He who is eating, to the Lord he doth eat, for he doth give thanks to God; and he who is not eating, to the Lord he doth not eat, and doth give thanks to God.

7 For none of us to himself doth live, and none to himself doth die;

8 for both, if we may live, to the Lord we live; if also we may die, to the Lord we die; both then if we may live, also if we may die, we are the Lord's;

9 for because of this Christ both died and rose again, and lived again, that both of dead and of living he may be Lord.

10 And thou, why dost thou judge thy brother? or again, thou, why dost thou set at nought thy brother? for we shall all stand at the tribunal of the Christ;

11 for it hath been written, `I live! saith the Lord--to Me bow shall every knee, and every tongue shall confess to God;'

12 so, then, each of us concerning himself shall give reckoning to God;

13 no longer, therefore, may we judge one another, but this judge ye rather, not to put a stumbling-stone before the brother, or an offence.

14 I have known, and am persuaded, in the Lord Jesus, that nothing [is] unclean of itself, except to him who is reckoning anything to be unclean--to that one [it is] unclean;

15 and if through victuals thy brother is grieved, no more dost thou walk according to love; do not with thy victuals destroy that one for whom Christ died.

16 Let not, then, your good be evil spoken of,

17 for the reign of God is not eating and drinking, but righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Spirit;

18 for he who in these things is serving the Christ, [is] acceptable to God and approved of men.

19 So, then, the things of peace may we pursue, and the things of building up one another;

20 for the sake of victuals cast not down the work of God; all things, indeed, [are] pure, but evil [is] to the man who is eating through stumbling.

21 Right [it is] not to eat flesh, nor to drink wine, nor to [do anything] in which thy brother doth stumble, or is made to fall, or is weak.

22 Thou hast faith! to thyself have [it] before God; happy is he who is not judging himself in what he doth approve,

23 and he who is making a difference, if he may eat, hath been condemned, because [it is] not of faith; and all that [is] not of faith is sin.

Romans 16

1 And I commend you to Phebe our sister--being a ministrant of the assembly that [is] in Cenchrea--

2 that ye may receive her in the Lord, as doth become saints, and may assist her in whatever matter she may have need of you--for she also became a leader of many, and of myself.

3 Salute Priscilla and Aquilas, my fellow-workmen in Christ Jesus--

4 who for my life their own neck did lay down, to whom not only I give thanks, but also all the assemblies of the nations--

5 and the assembly at their house; salute Epaenetus, my beloved, who is first-fruit of Achaia to Christ.

6 Salute Mary, who did labour much for us;

7 salute Andronicus and Junias, my kindred, and my fellow-captives, who are of note among the apostles, who also have been in Christ before me.

8 Salute Amplias, my beloved in the Lord;

9 salute Arbanus, our fellow-workman in Christ, and Stachys, my beloved;

10 salute Apelles, the approved in Christ; salute those of the [household] of Aristobulus;

11 salute Herodion, my kinsman; salute those of the [household] of Narcissus, who are in the Lord;

12 salute Tryphaena, and Tryphosa, who are labouring in the Lord; salute Persis, the beloved, who did labour much in the Lord.

13 Salute Rufus, the choice one in the Lord, and his mother and mine,

14 salute Asyncritus, Phlegon, Hermas, Patrobas, Hermes, and the brethren with them;

15 salute Philologus, and Julias, Nereus, and his sister, and Olympas, and all the saints with them;

16 salute one another in a holy kiss; the assemblies of Christ do salute you.

17 And I call upon you, brethren, to mark those who the divisions and the stumblingblocks, contrary to the teaching that ye did learn, are causing, and turn ye away from them;

18 for such our Lord Jesus Christ do not serve, but their own belly; and through the good word and fair speech they deceive the hearts of the harmless,

19 for your obedience did reach to all; I rejoice, therefore, as regards you, and I wish you to be wise, indeed, as to the good, and harmless as to the evil;

20 and the God of the peace shall bruise the Adversary under your feet quickly; the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with you. Amen!

21 Salute you do Timotheus, my fellow-workman, and Lucius, and Jason, and Sosipater, my kindred;

22 I Tertius salute you (who wrote the letter) in the Lord;

23 salute you doth Gaius, my host, and of the whole assembly; salute you doth Erastus, the steward of the city, and Quartus the brother,

24 the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with you all. Amen.

25 And to Him who is able to establish you, according to my good news, and the preaching of Jesus Christ, according to the revelation of the secret, in the times of the ages having been kept silent,

26 and now having been made manifest, also, through prophetic writings, according to a command of the age-during God, having been made known to all the nations for obedience of faith--

27 to the only wise God, through Jesus Christ, to him [be] glory to the ages. Amen.

1 Corinthians 4

1 Let a man so reckon us as officers of Christ, and stewards of the secrets of God,

2 and as to the rest, it is required in the stewards that one may be found faithful,

3 and to me it is for a very little thing that by you I may be judged, or by man's day, but not even myself do I judge,

4 for of nothing to myself have I been conscious, but not in this have I been declared right--and he who is discerning me is the Lord:

5 so, then, nothing before the time judge ye, till the Lord may come, who will both bring to light the hidden things of the darkness, and will manifest the counsels of the hearts, and then the praise shall come to each from God.

6 And these things, brethren, I did transfer to myself and to Apollos because of you, that in us ye may learn not to think above that which hath been written, that ye may not be puffed up one for one against the other,

7 for who doth make thee to differ? and what hast thou, that thou didst not receive? and if thou didst also receive, why dost thou glory as not having received?

8 Already ye are having been filled, already ye were rich, apart from us ye did reign, and I would also ye did reign, that we also with you may reign together,

9 for I think that God did set forth us the apostles last--as appointed to death, because a spectacle we became to the world, and messengers, and men;

10 we [are] fools because of Christ, and ye wise in Christ; we [are] ailing, and ye strong; ye glorious, and we dishonoured;

11 unto the present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and wander about,

12 and labour, working with [our] own hands; being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we suffer;

13 being spoken evil of, we entreat; as filth of the world we did become--of all things an offscouring--till now.

14 Not [as] putting you to shame do I write these things, but as my beloved children I do admonish,

15 for if a myriad of child-conductors ye may have in Christ, yet not many fathers; for in Christ Jesus, through the good news, I--I did beget you;

16 I call upon you, therefore, become ye followers of me;

17 because of this I sent to you Timotheus, who is my child, beloved and faithful in the Lord, who shall remind you of my ways in Christ, according as everywhere in every assembly I teach.

18 And as if I were not coming unto you certain were puffed up;

19 but I will come quickly unto you, if the Lord may will, and I will know not the word of those puffed up, but the power;

20 for not in word is the reign of God, but in power?

21 what do ye wish? with a rod shall I come unto you, or in love, with a spirit also of meekness?

1 Corinthians 6

1 Dare any one of you, having a matter with the other, go to be judged before the unrighteous, and not before the saints?

2 have ye not known that the saints shall judge the world? and if by you the world is judged, are ye unworthy of the smaller judgments?

3 have ye not known that we shall judge messengers? why not then the things of life?

4 of the things of life, indeed, then, if ye may have judgment, those despised in the assembly--these cause ye to sit;

5 unto your shame I speak: so there is not among you one wise man, not even one, who shall be able to discern in the midst of his brethren!

6 but brother with brother doth go to be judged, and this before unbelievers!

7 Already, indeed, then, there is altogether a fault among you, that ye have judgments with one another; wherefore do ye not rather suffer injustice? wherefore be ye not rather defrauded?

8 but ye--ye do injustice, and ye defraud, and these--brethren!

9 have ye not known that the unrighteous the reign of God shall not inherit? be not led astray; neither whoremongers, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor sodomites,

10 nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, the reign of God shall inherit.

11 And certain of you were these! but ye were washed, but ye were sanctified, but ye were declared righteous, in the name of the Lord Jesus, and in the Spirit of our God.

12 All things are lawful to me, but all things are not profitable; all things are lawful to me, but I--I will not be under authority by any;

13 the meats [are] for the belly, and the belly for the meats. And God both this and these shall make useless; and the body [is] not for whoredom, but for the Lord, and the Lord for the body;

14 and God both the Lord did raise, and us will raise up through His power.

15 Have ye not known that your bodies are members of Christ? having taken, then, the members of the Christ, shall I make [them] members of an harlot? let it be not!

16 have ye not known that he who is joined to the harlot is one body? `for they shall be--saith He--the two for one flesh.'

17 And he who is joined to the Lord is one spirit;

18 flee the whoredom; every sin--whatever a man may commit--is without the body, and he who is committing whoredom, against his own body doth sin.

19 Have ye not known that your body is a sanctuary of the Holy Spirit in you, which ye have from God? and ye are not your own,

20 for ye were bought with a price; glorify, then, God in your body and in your spirit, which are God's.

1 Corinthians 7

1 And concerning the things of which ye wrote to me: good [it is] for a man not to touch a woman,

2 and because of the whoredom let each man have his own wife, and let each woman have her proper husband;

3 to the wife let the husband the due benevolence render, and in like manner also the wife to the husband;

4 the wife over her own body hath not authority, but the husband; and, in like manner also, the husband over his own body hath not authority, but the wife.

5 Defraud not one another, except by consent for a time, that ye may be free for fasting and prayer, and again may come together, that the Adversary may not tempt you because of your incontinence;

6 and this I say by way of concurrence--not of command,

7 for I wish all men to be even as I myself [am]; but each his own gift hath of God, one indeed thus, and one thus.

8 And I say to the unmarried and to the widows: it is good for them if they may remain even as I [am];

9 and if they have not continence--let them marry, for it is better to marry than to burn;

10 and to the married I announce--not I, but the Lord--let not a wife separate from a husband:

11 but and if she may separate, let her remain unmarried, or to the husband let her be reconciled, and let not a husband send away a wife.

12 And to the rest I speak--not the Lord--if any brother hath a wife unbelieving, and she is pleased to dwell with him, let him not send her away;

13 and a woman who hath a husband unbelieving, and he is pleased to dwell with her, let her not send him away;

14 for the unbelieving husband hath been sanctified in the wife, and the unbelieving wife hath been sanctified in the husband; otherwise your children are unclean, but now they are holy.

15 And, if the unbelieving doth separate himself--let him separate himself: the brother or the sister is not under servitude in such [cases], and in peace hath God called us;

16 for what, hast thou known, O wife, whether the husband thou shalt save? or what, hast thou known, O husband, whether the wife thou shalt save?

17 if not, as God did distribute to each, as the Lord hath called each--so let him walk; and thus in all the assemblies do I direct:

18 being circumcised--was any one called? let him not become uncircumcised; in uncircumcision was any one called? let him not be circumcised;

19 the circumcision is nothing, and the uncircumcision is nothing--but a keeping of the commands of God.

20 Each in the calling in which he was called--in this let him remain;

21 a servant--wast thou called? be not anxious; but if also thou art able to become free--use [it] rather;

22 for he who [is] in the Lord--having been called a servant--is the Lord's freedman: in like manner also he the freeman, having been called, is servant of Christ:

23 with a price ye were bought, become not servants of men;

24 each, in that in which he was called, brethren, in this let him remain with God.

25 And concerning the virgins, a command of the Lord I have not; and I give judgment as having obtained kindness from the Lord to be faithful:

26 I suppose, therefore, this to be good because of the present necessity, that [it is] good for a man that the matter be thus: --

27 Hast thou been bound to a wife? seek not to be loosed; hast thou been loosed from a wife? seek not a wife.

28 But and if thou mayest marry, thou didst not sin; and if the virgin may marry, she did not sin; and such shall have tribulation in the flesh: and I spare you.

29 And this I say, brethren, the time henceforth is having been shortened--that both those having wives may be as not having;

30 and those weeping, as not weeping; and those rejoicing, as not rejoicing; and those buying, as not possessing;

31 and those using this world, as not using [it] up; for passing away is the fashion of this world.

32 And I wish you to be without anxiety; the unmarried is anxious for the things of the Lord, how he shall please the Lord;

33 and the married is anxious for the things of the world, how he shall please the wife.

34 The wife and the virgin have been distinguished: the unmarried is anxious for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and in spirit, and the married is anxious for the things of the world, how she shall please the husband.

35 And this for your own profit I say: not that I may cast a noose upon you, but for the seemliness and devotedness to the Lord, undistractedly,

36 and if any one doth think [it] to be unseemly to his virgin, if she may be beyond the bloom of age, and it ought so to be, what he willeth let him do; he doth not sin--let him marry.

37 And he who hath stood stedfast in the heart--not having necessity--and hath authority over his own will, and this he hath determined in his heart--to keep his own virgin--doth well;

38 so that both he who is giving in marriage doth well, and he who is not giving in marriage doth better.

39 A wife hath been bound by law as long time as her husband may live, and if her husband may sleep, she is free to be married to whom she will--only in the Lord;

40 and she is happier if she may so remain--according to my judgment; and I think I also have the Spirit of God.

1 Corinthians 9

1 Am not I an apostle? am not I free? Jesus Christ our Lord have I not seen? my work are not ye in the Lord?

2 if to others I am not an apostle--yet doubtless to you I am; for the seal of my apostleship are ye in the Lord.

3 My defence to those who examine me in this;

4 have we not authority to eat and to drink?

5 have we not authority a sister--a wife--to lead about, as also the other apostles, and the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas?

6 or only I and Barnabas, have we not authority--not to work?

7 who doth serve as a soldier at his own charges at any time? who doth plant a vineyard, and of its fruit doth not eat? or who doth feed a flock, and of the milk of the flock doth not eat?

8 According to man do I speak these things? or doth not also the law say these things?

9 for in the law of Moses it hath been written, `thou shalt not muzzle an ox treading out corn;' for the oxen doth God care?

10 or because of us by all means doth He say [it]? yes, because of us it was written, because in hope ought the plower to plow, and he who is treading [ought] of his hope to partake in hope.

11 If we to you the spiritual things did sow--great [is it] if we your fleshly things do reap?

12 if others do partake of the authority over you--not we more? but we did not use this authority, but all things we bear, that we may give no hindrance to the good news of the Christ.

13 Have ye not known that those working about the things of the temple--of the temple do eat, and those waiting at the altar--with the altar are partakers?

14 so also did the Lord direct to those proclaiming the good news: of the good news to live.

15 And I have used none of these things; neither did I write these things that it may be so done in my case, for [it is] good for me rather to die, than that any one may make my glorying void;

16 for if I may proclaim good news, it is no glorying for me, for necessity is laid upon me, and woe is to me if I may not proclaim good news;

17 for if willing I do this, I have a reward; and if unwillingly--with a stewardship I have been entrusted!

18 What, then, is my reward? --that proclaiming good news, without charge I shall make the good news of the Christ, not to abuse my authority in the good news;

19 for being free from all men, to all men I made myself servant, that the more I might gain;

20 and I became to the Jews as a Jew, that Jews I might gain; to those under law as under law, that those under law I might gain;

21 to those without law, as without law--(not being without law to God, but within law to Christ) --that I might gain those without law;

22 I became to the infirm as infirm, that the infirm I might gain; to all men I have become all things, that by all means I may save some.

23 And this I do because of the good news, that a fellow-partaker of it I may become;

24 have ye not known that those running in a race--all indeed run, but one doth receive the prize? so run ye, that ye may obtain;

25 and every one who is striving, is in all things temperate; these, indeed, then, that a corruptible crown they may receive, but we an incorruptible;

26 I, therefore, thus run, not as uncertainly, thus I fight, as not beating air;

27 but I chastise my body, and bring [it] into servitude, lest by any means, having preached to others--I myself may become disapproved.

1 Corinthians 10

1 And I do not wish you to be ignorant, brethren, that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea,

2 and all to Moses were baptized in the cloud, and in the sea;

3 and all the same spiritual food did eat,

4 and all the same spiritual drink did drink, for they were drinking of a spiritual rock following them, and the rock was the Christ;

5 but in the most of them God was not well pleased, for they were strewn in the wilderness,

6 and those things became types of us, for our not passionately desiring evil things, as also these did desire.

7 Neither become ye idolaters, as certain of them, as it hath been written, `The people sat down to eat and to drink, and stood up to play;'

8 neither may we commit whoredom, as certain of them did commit whoredom, and there fell in one day twenty-three thousand;

9 neither may we tempt the Christ, as also certain of them did tempt, and by the serpents did perish;

10 neither murmur ye, as also some of them did murmur, and did perish by the destroyer.

11 And all these things as types did happen to those persons, and they were written for our admonition, to whom the end of the ages did come,

12 so that he who is thinking to stand--let him observe, lest he fall.

13 No temptation hath taken you--except human; and God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above what ye are able, but He will make, with the temptation, also the outlet, for your being able to bear [it].

14 Wherefore, my beloved, flee from the idolatry;

15 as to wise men I speak--judge ye what I say:

16 The cup of the blessing that we bless--is it not the fellowship of the blood of the Christ? the bread that we break--is it not the fellowship of the body of the Christ?

17 because one bread, one body, are we the many--for we all of the one bread do partake.

18 See Israel according to the flesh! are not those eating the sacrifices in the fellowship of the altar?

19 what then do I say? that an idol is anything? or that a sacrifice offered to an idol is anything? --

20 [no,] but that the things that the nations sacrifice--they sacrifice to demons and not to God; and I do not wish you to come into the fellowship of the demons.

21 Ye are not able the cup of the Lord to drink, and the cup of demons; ye are not able of the table of the Lord to partake, and of the table of demons;

22 do we arouse the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than He?

23 All things to me are lawful, but all things are not profitable; all things to me are lawful, but all things do not build up;

24 let no one seek his own--but each another's.

25 Whatever in the meat-market is sold eat ye, not inquiring, because of the conscience,

26 for the Lord's [is] the earth, and its fulness;

27 and if any one of the unbelieving do call you, and ye wish to go, all that is set before you eat, nothing inquiring, because of the conscience;

28 and if any one may say to you, `This is a thing sacrificed to an idol,' --do not eat, because of that one who shewed [it], and of the conscience, for the Lord's [is] the earth and its fulness:

29 and conscience, I say, not of thyself, but of the other, for why [is it] that my liberty is judged by another's conscience?

30 and if I thankfully do partake, why am I evil spoken of, for that for which I give thanks?

31 Whether, then, ye eat, or drink, or do anything, do all to the glory of God;

32 become offenceless, both to Jews and Greeks, and to the assembly of God;

33 as I also in all things do please all, not seeking my own profit, but that of many--that they may be saved.

1 Corinthians 11

1 Followers of me become ye, as I also [am] of Christ.

2 And I praise you, brethren, that in all things ye remember me, and according as I did deliver to you, the deliverances ye keep,

3 and I wish you to know that of every man the head is the Christ, and the head of a woman is the husband, and the head of Christ is God.

4 Every man praying or prophesying, having the head covered, doth dishonour his head,

5 and every woman praying or prophesying with the head uncovered, doth dishonour her own head, for it is one and the same thing with her being shaven,

6 for if a woman is not covered--then let her be shorn, and if [it is] a shame for a woman to be shorn or shaven--let her be covered;

7 for a man, indeed, ought not to cover the head, being the image and glory of God, and a woman is the glory of a man,

8 for a man is not of a woman, but a woman [is] of a man,

9 for a man also was not created because of the woman, but a woman because of the man;

10 because of this the woman ought to have [a token of] authority upon the head, because of the messengers;

11 but neither [is] a man apart from a woman, nor a woman apart from a man, in the Lord,

12 for as the woman [is] of the man, so also the man [is] through the woman, and the all things [are] of God.

13 In your own selves judge ye; is it seemly for a woman uncovered to pray to God?

14 doth not even nature itself teach you, that if a man indeed have long hair, a dishonour it is to him?

15 and a woman, if she have long hair, a glory it is to her, because the hair instead of a covering hath been given to her;

16 and if any one doth think to be contentious, we have no such custom, neither the assemblies of God.

17 And this declaring, I give no praise, because not for the better, but for the worse ye come together;

18 for first, indeed, ye coming together in an assembly, I hear of divisions being among you, and partly I believe [it],

19 for it behoveth sects also to be among you, that those approved may become manifest among you;

20 ye, then, coming together at the same place--it is not to eat the Lord's supper;

21 for each his own supper doth take before in the eating, and one is hungry, and another is drunk;

22 why, have ye not houses to eat and to drink in? or the assembly of God do ye despise, and shame those not having? what may I say to you? shall I praise you in this? I do not praise!

23 For I--I received from the Lord that which also I did deliver to you, that the Lord Jesus in the night in which he was delivered up, took bread,

24 and having given thanks, he brake, and said, `Take ye, eat ye, this is my body, that for you is being broken; this do ye--to the remembrance of me.'

25 In like manner also the cup after the supping, saying, `This cup is the new covenant in my blood; this do ye, as often as ye may drink [it] --to the remembrance of me;'

26 for as often as ye may eat this bread, and this cup may drink, the death of the Lord ye do shew forth--till he may come;

27 so that whoever may eat this bread or may drink the cup of the Lord unworthily, guilty he shall be of the body and blood of the Lord:

28 and let a man be proving himself, and so of the bread let him eat, and of the cup let him drink;

29 for he who is eating and drinking unworthily, judgment to himself he doth eat and drink--not discerning the body of the Lord.

30 Because of this, among you many [are] weak and sickly, and sleep do many;

31 for if ourselves we were discerning, we would not be being judged,

32 and being judged by the Lord, we are chastened, that with the world we may not be condemned;

33 so then, my brethren, coming together to eat, for one another wait ye;

34 and if any one is hungry, at home let him eat, that to judgment ye may not come together; and the rest, whenever I may come, I shall arrange.

1 Corinthians 12

1 And concerning the spiritual things, brethren, I do not wish you to be ignorant;

2 ye have known that ye were nations, unto the dumb idols--as ye were led-- being carried away;

3 wherefore, I give you to understand that no one, in the Spirit of God speaking, saith Jesus [is] anathema, and no one is able to say Jesus [is] Lord, except in the Holy Spirit.

4 And there are diversities of gifts, and the same Spirit;

5 and there are diversities of ministrations, and the same Lord;

6 and there are diversities of workings, and it is the same God--who is working the all in all.

7 And to each hath been given the manifestation of the Spirit for profit;

8 for to one through the Spirit hath been given a word of wisdom, and to another a word of knowledge, according to the same Spirit;

9 and to another faith in the same Spirit, and to another gifts of healings in the same Spirit;

10 and to another in-workings of mighty deeds; and to another prophecy; and to another discernings of spirits; and to another [divers] kinds of tongues; and to another interpretation of tongues:

11 and all these doth work the one and the same Spirit, dividing to each severally as he intendeth.

12 For, even as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of the one body, being many, are one body, so also [is] the Christ,

13 for also in one Spirit we all to one body were baptized, whether Jews or Greeks, whether servants or freemen, and all into one Spirit were made to drink,

14 for also the body is not one member, but many;

15 if the foot may say, `Because I am not a hand, I am not of the body;' it is not, because of this, not of the body;

16 and if the ear may say, `Because I am not an eye, I am not of the body;' it is not, because of this, not of the body?

17 If the whole body [were] an eye, where the hearing? if the whole hearing, where the smelling?

18 and now, God did set the members each one of them in the body, according as He willed,

19 and if all were one member, where the body?

20 and now, indeed, [are] many members, and one body;

21 and an eye is not able to say to the hand, `I have no need of thee;' nor again the head to the feet, `I have no need of you.'

22 But much more the members of the body which seem to be more infirm are necessary,

23 and those that we think to be less honourable of the body, around these we put more abundant honour, and our unseemly things have seemliness more abundant,

24 and our seemly things have no need; but God did temper the body together, to the lacking part having given more abundant honour,

25 that there may be no division in the body, but that the members may have the same anxiety for one another,

26 and whether one member doth suffer, suffer with [it] do all the members, or one member is glorified, rejoice with [it] do all the members;

27 and ye are the body of Christ, and members in particular.

28 And some, indeed, did God set in the assembly, first apostles, secondly prophets, thirdly teachers, afterwards powers, afterwards gifts of healings, helpings, governings, divers kinds of tongues;

29 [are] all apostles? [are] all prophets? [are] all teachers? [are] all powers?

30 have all gifts of healings? do all speak with tongues? do all interpret?

31 and desire earnestly the better gifts; and yet a far excelling way do I shew to you: